<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2021-09-25T17:34:56Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>My cell biology students would have fun with this</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/25/my-cell-biology-students-would-have-fun-with-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;Or maybe some would just be confused? After all, it comes from that reputable scientific authority, the Daily Mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;I am loving this explainer of DNA vs RNA from the Daily Mail. Just a couple of wildcards thrown in to keep you on your toes! &lt;a href="https://t.co/aD3N6cizZx"&gt;pic.twitter.com/aD3N6cizZx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Philip Leftwich (@PhilipLeftwich) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PhilipLeftwich/status/1441395083966918656?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 24, 2021&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To the red marks I&amp;#8217;d also add that mitochondria is plural, mitochondrion is singular, and a mitochondrian is, I think, a Dutch abstract painter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;#8217;t think I&amp;#8217;ll expose my students to this because I&amp;#8217;m concentrating on teaching them good science.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Or maybe some would just be confused? After all, it comes from that reputable scientific authority, the Daily Mail. I am loving this explainer of DNA vs RNA from the Daily Mail. Just a couple of wildcards thrown in to keep you on your toes! pic.twitter.com/aD3N6cizZx — Philip Leftwich (@PhilipLeftwich) September 24, 2021 To the […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64001</id>
    <published>2021-09-25T15:20:53Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-25T15:20:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I blame the obscure comic strip for Ogilvie’s travails!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/24/i-blame-the-obscure-comic-strip-for-ogilvies-travails/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Totally accurate summary of anti-vax research:</p>
<div id="attachment_63999" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch-500x679.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="679" class="size-large wp-image-63999" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch-500x679.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch-110x150.jpeg 110w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch-221x300.jpeg 221w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch-768x1044.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/youtuberesearch.jpeg 939w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.gocomics.com/tomthedancingbug/2021/09/24">Tom the Dancing Bug</a></p></div>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Totally accurate summary of anti-vax research:</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=63998</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T20:27:26Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T20:27:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Friday Cephalopod: Baby in a bubble</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/24/friday-cephalopod-baby-in-a-bubble/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Awww, so cute.</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/babyinabubble-500x333.png" alt="" width="500" height="333" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-63996" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/babyinabubble-500x333.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/babyinabubble-150x100.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/babyinabubble-300x200.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/babyinabubble.png 540w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Awww, so cute.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=63995</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T18:19:21Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T18:19:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Cephalopods"/>
    <category term="Organisms"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>That seems mean</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/24/that-seems-mean/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Mean, with a grain of truth.</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-63992" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid-300x225.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid-150x112.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid-768x575.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid-500x374.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/fixstupid.jpg 1242w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></p>
<p>Unfortunately, it relies on a flexible definition of “fix,” and it’s not a very satisfying solution.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean, with a grain of truth. Unfortunately, it relies on a flexible definition of “fix,” and it’s not a very satisfying solution.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=63991</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T14:26:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T14:26:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Psychic TikTok is a Cesspit of Sylvia Brownes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/55pGvkhCsg0/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! In the past few years, I’ve seen a resurgence in a “belief” in astrology, at least amongst my friends and social media follows. I say “belief,” with quotation marks, because honestly I’ve never been sure …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/55pGvkhCsg0" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131151</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T12:25:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T12:25:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I guess cowboys just hate Indians</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/24/i-guess-cowboys-just-hate-indians/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers-300x240.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="240" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-63989" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers-300x240.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers-150x120.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers-768x614.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers-500x400.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/lakotateenagers.jpg 794w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></p>
<p class="lead">There is this law called the Indian Child Welfare Act which, along with providing necessary protections, also helped kill the practice of tearing apart Indian families and putting their kids in boarding schools. Sounds like an obvious idea, right? It’s somewhat surprising that it was only enacted in 1978. Would you also be surprised to learn that some people are trying to overthrow that law?</p>
<p>It’s being <a href="https://www.wbur.org/onpoint/2021/09/14/custody-case-investigates-native-american-rebecca-nagle-this-land">challenged in child custody cases</a>, with people actually saying that no, it is wrong to try and keep children with their relatives or their tribe, and their reasoning is unbelievable.</p>
<blockquote><p>So a U.S. federal district judge did exactly that. He … a radical conservative judge in Texas. And he took the Indian Child Welfare Act and he checked it out the window and said that it was racial discrimination.</p></blockquote>
<p>That’s their argument: that a law to protect an oppressed minority is racist. That’s rich, coming from a radical conservative, the kind of person who wants to preserve the privilege that maintains a white majority rule. He doesn’t care about racism, except when brown people get uppity.</p>
<p>What’s worrisome is that the decision was appealed all the way to the 5th Circuit Court of Appeals, and they split.</p>
<blockquote><p>They strike down a few narrow parts of the law, but that 16 judge panel was evenly split on whether basically the foundation of the legal status of tribes is constitutional. And so that’s how close we are to a scary result in this case. And I think that we’ll have to see what the Supreme Court will do. But it’s terrifying to think that the Supreme Court is going to take it up and all federal Indian law is on the table.</p></blockquote>
<p>I wonder how many Trump appointees were involved. The Republicans have been doing their best to pack the courts. I wonder who could possibly want to strike down the ICWA, and it’s “private adoption attorneys, corporate lawyers and this universe of right-wing money and operatives”.</p>
<p>It always astonishes me, a professor at a college with a student body that is about 20% Indian, how much discrimination goes on in the communities around me — discrimination that is almost entirely invisible to me, and it’s disturbing when it rises up where an oblivious old white dude can see it.</p>
<p>Here’s another story, from Nebraska, in which <a href="https://flatwaterfreepress.org/a-school-sees-a-lice-check-lakota-people-sense-centuries-of-repression/">busybodies in a public school decided to cut Lakota kids’ hair in the name of searching for lice</a>. What gets me is all these white ranchers <em>defending</em> the school secretary who took it upon herself to hack at the kids’ hair (they didn’t have lice, by the way). She’s a <em>nice</em> lady, they say, she didn’t mean any harm, “She did it to help the children and keep the school safe”, etc. I don’t believe it. My particular culture doesn’t attach the kind of importance to long hair that the Lakota do, and if some school official had taken scissors to my kids’ hair, I would have marched to the school district office in a rage and demanded that they be fired. You don’t get to make those kinds of decisions for my children, they have more autonomy than that.</p>
<p>It’s an act that doesn’t have the historical resonance it does for the Lakota, so I can only imagine a fraction the anger it would generate.</p>
<blockquote><p>As the story circulated on social media, raw emotions surfaced. Grandparents shared stories of how their hair had been cut in boarding schools decades ago.</p>
<p>“Having the seventh, eighth, tenth generation having to go through it again … I mean, it’s just a big eye opener because it’s being re-lived,” LeRoy said. </p>
<p>On March 3, 1819, nearly 201 years to the day before the children’s hair was cut, the United States signed the Civilization Fund Act. That ushered in an era from 1860 to 1978 when boarding schools nationwide, including in Nebraska, separated Native children from their families, punished them for speaking their language, and often cut their long hair.</p>
<p>“… All the Indian there is in the race should be dead. Kill the Indian in him, and save the man,” Capt. Richard H. Pratt, who founded the Carlisle Indian Industrial School, famously said in 1892.</p>
<p>In 1884, Christian missionaries came to South Dakota’s Yankton Reservation and took eight-year-old Zitkála-Šá from her mother. </p>
<p>“I remember being dragged out, though I resisted by kicking and scratching wildly,” Zitkála-Šá wrote in 1900 of her hair cutting. “In spite of myself, I was carried downstairs and tied fast in a chair. I cried aloud, shaking my head all the while until I felt the cold blades of the scissors against my neck, and heard them gnaw off one of my thick braids. Then I lost my spirit…now I was only one of many little animals driven by a herder.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Are we really going to be fooled by a bunch of racists who cry that it’s racist to interfere with their racism?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is this law called the Indian Child Welfare Act which, along with providing necessary protections, also helped kill the practice of tearing apart Indian families and putting their kids in boarding schools. Sounds like an obvious idea, right? It’s somewhat surprising that it was only enacted in 1978. Would you also be surprised to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=63988</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T12:22:40Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T12:22:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: The Travel Writing Tribe</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5855/book-review-the-travel-writingtribe#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/51CrbWFssbL._SX317_BO1,204,203,200_.jpg" height="499" alt="51CrbWFssbL._SX317_BO1,204,203,200_" width="319" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In his comprehensive study of travel writing, Tim Hannigan explores the genre&amp;rsquo;s history and critical reception and tracks down well-known practitioners, from William Dalrymple to Dervla Murphy. He interviews academic Carl Thompson, publisher Barnaby Rogerson and a group of readers from the Globetrotters Club, and interrogates the lexicon of travel writing studies from &amp;ldquo;travellee&amp;rdquo; (the local people encountered by the writer) to &amp;ldquo;affective identification&amp;rdquo; (empathy with the subject). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hannigan grew up in Cornwall, trained as a chef, and now writes mainly about south-east Asia. Here, he tackles the criticism historically levelled at the travel writing genre: that it &amp;ldquo;was hopelessly entangled with the history of European colonialism&amp;rdquo; and that it &amp;ldquo;was an elite genre&amp;rdquo; with Oxbridge-educated writers presuming a shared knowledge of history and classics. He also explores the &amp;ldquo;rootedness&amp;rdquo; of certain travel writers &amp;ndash; like Robin Hanbury-Tenison and Patrick Barkham &amp;ndash; who have somewhere they always want to return to. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While considering &amp;ldquo;the troubled frontier between fact and fiction&amp;rdquo;, whether it is acceptable to fictionalise what is essentially a non-fiction genre, he travels to the Dorset&amp;ndash;Somerset border to meet Rory Maclean. In his debut, &lt;em&gt;Stalin&amp;rsquo;s Nose&lt;/em&gt; (1992), Maclean famously opens with a pig called Winston falling from a tree and killing the narrator&amp;rsquo;s uncle. As Maclean was quick to point out, he always &amp;ldquo;signalled&amp;rdquo; when he was about to become inventive: &amp;ldquo;Maclean never pretended to be recounting the hard facts.&amp;rdquo; Maclean broke the mould but claims that, as an outsider (born in Canada), he wasn&amp;rsquo;t aware of a tradition of travel writing: &amp;ldquo;I simply wrote the book that I wanted to.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For years, travel writing was dominated by white men of a certain class &amp;ndash; many of whom, as Hannigan discovers, were educated at Eton. But in our current age of globalisation and budget travel, this has changed with the emergence of writers like Monisha Rajesh, Samanth Subramanian and Sara Wheeler. Meanwhile, the growing popularity of nature writing appears &amp;ldquo;to have ousted travel writing as the dominant mode of creative nonfiction in Britain.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Particularly illuminating is Hannigan&amp;rsquo;s interview with Subramanian, an Indian journalist with a British passport and a degree from an Ivy League university. Subramanian, who lives in Dublin, emphasises travel writing&amp;rsquo;s journalistic function: &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;journalists . . . talk to people about their lives and about their problems and about their views on the world.&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; This approach ensures the travellee has a voice.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Finally, Hannigan makes a pilgrimage to the tiny 10th-century Byzantine chapel in Greece where Bruce Chatwin&amp;rsquo;s ashes are buried. Chatwin, loved by many, was lambasted for fictionalising &lt;em&gt;The Songlines&lt;/em&gt; (1987), his seminal book about central Australia, which effectively denied the Aborigines a voice. Chatwin later claimed it was a novel. Hannigan forgives Chatwin because of &amp;ldquo;the style of his prose; the way he could call up a place in its entirety with just a few, apparently inconsequential details . . . the sheer joy of being at large in the world with eye and brain engaged&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Travel Writing Tribe&lt;/em&gt; is meticulously researched and written with endearing humility. The bulk was finished before the pandemic, but Hannigan concludes by observing that &amp;ldquo;people will always want to read about journeys.&amp;rdquo; Becoming armchair travellers may well benefit the genre.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5855/book-review-the-travel-writingtribe#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-23T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-23T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Brief History of Vaccine Mandates (and How to Do it Right)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/Ra7AAsFBdiw/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Let’s talk about this hot new idea, “vaccine mandates.” Conservatives across the US are up in arms (and I mean that literally, because this is America, so of course the people scared of needles own …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/Ra7AAsFBdiw" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131149</id>
    <published>2021-09-22T19:59:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-22T19:59:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Anti-Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Learning from our ancestors w/ Alice Roberts</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5860/learning-from-our-ancestors-w-alice-roberts#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alice Roberts, one of the UK&amp;rsquo;s leading public scientists and President of Humanists UK, talks to our editor Samira Shackle about what we can learn from the burial sites of the earliest Britons, as explored in her new book &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt;. What does our prehistory &amp;ndash; cannibalism and all &amp;ndash; tell us about who we are? How does the way we mark death illuminate our perspective on life? And how are genetics and archaeology shaping each other today? Plus, Alice tells Samira how she came to be a humanist, and discusses the value of storytelling and science communication in our pandemic age, and beyond.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Podcast listeners can get a year's subscription to New Humanist magazine for just &amp;pound;13.50. Head to newhumanist.org.uk/subscribe and enter the code WITHREASON &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hosts&lt;/strong&gt;: Samira Shackle and Niki Seth-Smith&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Executive producer&lt;/strong&gt;: Alice Bloch&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; David Crackles&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music:&lt;/strong&gt; Danosongs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image: &lt;/strong&gt;Photo by Dave Stevens, artwork by Ed Dingli&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Transcript:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Samira Shackle:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hi and welcome to &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; with me Samira Shackle&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Niki Seth-Smith:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;and me Niki Seth-Smith.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;With Reason &lt;/em&gt;is where we meet people in fields like philosophy, science and culture whose work and ideas challenge dogma and lazy thinking. That's the place to consider questions of reason and unreason. belief and disbelief, critical thought and debate and today it's a place to think big about who we are and where we've come from.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And in this series, we're talking to people like the physicist Carlo Rovelli about the nature of reality and science writer Lucy Jones about wilderness and wellbeing. But today we're with the anatomist and biological anthropologist Alice Roberts, discussing our prehistory. Samira, I'll be listening in and back with you later for a bit of a chat. But it's over to you for now.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, so Alice Roberts is an academic and author and a broadcaster. I think lots of listeners will have already heard of her because I don't think it's any exaggeration to say she is one of Britain's most well-known contemporary scientists. She's been a regular fixture on TV and radio for the last two decades, starting with Time Team on Channel Four, back in 2001, where she was a bone specialist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alice first trained as a doctor before specialising in the crossover between human anatomy and archaeology and history. And she's published numerous books as well as presenting popular TV and radio shows about science. She's also a Professor of Public Engagement with Science at the University of Birmingham. And she has been vocal about her atheism. She's currently the president of Humanists UK. So her research combines biology and anatomy with archaeology and anthropology to shed new light on ancient history.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And that's something that she does in her new book &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt;, which zooms in on seven burial sites in Britain, to explore what new science can tell us about the bodies that are found there and the context in which they lived. Underpinning much of that new science are developments in, and collaboration between ,the fields of genetics and archaeology. So I started by asking her about how these two seemingly very different fields are shaping each other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alice Roberts:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's just a really exciting time at the moment. So genetics has been able to give us some information about the deep past and particularly about humans in the deep past for probably 20 years. And we're basically looking at the same techniques that are used to look at the DNA of living people. But now that's applied to people that have been dead for an extremely long time, in some cases, and due to advances in being able to extract DNA from very ancient bone, and then essentially, to be able to reconstruct the genome from that, but also actually advances in how fast you can sequence the genome, with just getting rich information coming through now. And we've also moved beyond &amp;ndash; just every 10 years ago, I made a series for the BBC called &lt;em&gt;The Incredible Human Journey&lt;/em&gt;, where we looked at Palaeolithic migrations that basically, it was the story of the origin of all species in Africa, and then the emergence of our species and the migrations - it's a tricky word migration, because we tend to think about it as journeys during someone's lifetime &amp;ndash; but over generations, you get these migrations, which took people to colonise the entire world. And you know, that all happened in the Palaeolithic, in the Old Stone Age. And the evidence for that comes from not only your traditional, I suppose, archaeological sources, but now we've got this genetic strand of evidence as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so back then, when I made that series, we were looking at the available genetic evidence, and a lot of it was in terms of small stretches of DNA, or particular focuses that people had looked at, I suppose. Then the next step was to use genome-wide analyses, which looked at particular points in the genome, where we knew that there were likely to be changes, likely to be mutations. But what geneticists are doing now is reading whole genomes, you know, sort of from cover to cover. And it's just extraordinary, it's really fast.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I'm involved with this fantastic new project at the Francis Crick Institute in London, which is the 1000 Ancient Genomes Project, which is focusing on British genomes from the deep past. And that will contribute enormous amounts to our understanding. So it's just getting really exciting. Some of the big questions that we haven't really been able to tackle before, or at least, you know, we've only been able to look at them in a very skewed way, have been questions like, you know: when the Neolithic happens &amp;ndash; which is the period in time when we see farming appearing and then spreading &amp;ndash; when that arrives in Britain, are we just looking at people picking up ideas, you know, have we got a few people coming over from the continent with seeds with livestock, and that idea, catching hold and spreading? Or are we looking at a big wave of migration? And I think we can reasonably robustly say &amp;ldquo;no, it's a big wave of migration&amp;rdquo;, because we've got the genetics, we can see that the genes, the DNA of people, once you get into the Neolithic is different from the people that were there in the preceding Mesolithic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And we're seeing that quite a bit. So we're seeing lots of waves of migration. I think it will work the other way as well. So I think there'll be periods where we think there's been a migration, and we look at the genetics and go, &amp;ldquo;Oh, doesn't seem to be many people coming over&amp;rdquo;. And a good example of that, at the moment, (although we've got a lot more data to come in on that) is the Anglo Saxon period, &lt;em&gt;you don't seem to be saying they were&lt;/em&gt; told by the history is that there was some massive invasion of Anglo Saxons and doesn't really seem to stack up genetically at the moment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s fascinating. But one thing and probably quite a basic question, I guess, is, you know, we've got this huge wealth of new information becoming available, as you've explained, but what's the kind of appeal to you, of studying prehistory, and getting that that kind of information about these events of the faraway past? Particularly in a time of such perpetual crisis, where we can struggle to keep up with even contemporary events, what can we learn from the ancient past?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, I think that's a really interesting question. I suppose, for me, it is very pertinent to the here and now, because what we see, you know, through great swathes of time, is the human experience. So, you know, we see people battling with disease outbreaks, we see, you know, what happens to society. So particularly thinking about events over the last 18 months, in Britain and globally, you know, this isn't the first time that humans have faced a terrible challenge in terms of a dreadful infection. And so we learn a lot by looking at how people responded to that in the past and how society changed. Actually, that&amp;rsquo;s really interesting, looking at, particularly, how society changed after the Black Death, for instance. So I think that there's always for me, contemporary resonance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And also, the other thing for me is that I feel very much that it's rather like that idea that you should travel and you should experience other cultures, because that makes you look at yourself in an objective way. And it makes you look at your own culture in an objective way. And it also makes you realise that you have this commonality with humans the world over, you know, that we're all very, very similar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Absolutely. And some of that, I guess, is about how it's communicated. And how these, you know, quite complicated scientific developments are put across to the public, which I guess is something that you think about, both in your books and your broadcasting. And I know you're, you're a Professor of Public Engagement with Science as well. One thing I wondered about, I think we hear a lot about the failings of the media, in reporting on science, you know, that this idea of crushing nuance or not fully understanding the peer review process, and so on. But I wondered what scientists can get wrong in communicating with the media. So what&amp;rsquo;s the kind of flipside of that?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Just to kind of pick up the earlier part of your question: a lot of what I do is looking for stories, and it feels quite archaeological. So when I'm writing about ancestors, I'm basically looking for the best stories. So I'm not, it's not fiction, I'm not creating, those stories already exist. And it's a question of finding them, and then bringing them together in a way that they form a larger saga, I suppose. And I really enjoy that. And I enjoy that in teaching as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think that, you know, every teaching activity that I plan and deliver with my students, I think about in a similar way, I'm telling them a story. And that's, that's how we imbibe information as humans. Anyway, you know, rather than just assembling a list of facts, telling a story, and it's not about packaging, it's actually much deeper than that. And I think that storytelling is something which is sometimes overlooked or considered to be superfluous and something around the edges of the science, rather than actually embedded within the science.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I would say a scientific hypothesis is a story about how the world works. So that's a more kind of philosophical take on it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, there's something I noticed in your book a lot, actually, is just the importance of narrative. And yeah, the way that that brings the science to life for a non-scientist. But as you say, also does seem quite integral to it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. I mean, that's something I've learned over my career. And I've particularly learnt it through getting involved in broadcast media. So some of the best kind of continuing professional development I've done has been in terms of teaching and university, has been doing public engagement in other ways. And particularly doing broadcast work and writing as well, of course, and it all then feeds back into my teaching.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But you've asked another question, which is about how scientists get information across to people and whether that's been done particularly well over the course of the pandemic. And I think it's very difficult because what we've seen over the last 18 months is that it's become incredibly political. And it's actually very difficult to tease apart the politics from the science and of course, every individual scientist &amp;ndash; scientists aren&amp;rsquo;t apolitical, but I think the important thing is that they know that that they know, in their professional life, they strive for objectivity. And I think that's, you know, what we really need in a time of pandemic is those scientists that, you know, bring that objectivity of their professional discipline to bear on the evidence that we can see in front of us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then when we're looking for solutions in a similar way, to do that as objectively as possible and to strip away ideology. And I feel in the UK that we've particularly been very ideology-driven. This &amp;ldquo;following the science thing is not true at all, we've been following an ideology, and trying to shoehorn the science into that. There's always kind of worries about what's going to happen to science in a time of crisis, that we're depending on it so much. And that if there is, if there's any kind of nuance, or uncertainty around various facts and figures, then, you know, the public might feel uneasy about that, or anxious about that. And I think that's, I don't think that's the reason to pretend that the evidence is either more robust or more certain than we know it to be. I think the absolute fundamental point is that we need to maintain trust, and that we need to, we need scientists who are engaging with the public in a very level way.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it's, you know, it's very, it's very difficult. I mean, there have been times in the pandemic, where we've got this great massive group of scientists advising the government, the Scientific Advisory Group for Emergencies, SAGE, and, you know, there'll be some times when I don't necessarily agree with the analysis, the kind of the solutions that perhaps they're suggesting, but I respect them immensely. But the awful thing that's happened is that they have become, I suppose the fall guys, you know. If there's an unpopular government policy, which draws on the science and the science as it's presented to the government by SAGE, then SAGE members become targeted for abuse online.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Jumping back to your book: So &lt;em&gt;Ancestors &lt;/em&gt;focuses on seven burials in British history. And I wondered why you chose to focus on burials, which obviously conveys information about much more than, than just death.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s my thing. So this is a podcast, so you can't see the shelves behind me, but they're basically full of anatomy, fossil record, evolution of the human I mean. I'm a biological anthropologist, which means I mostly study human bones. And that's my contact with the world of archaeology really. So I analyse human bones and work with archaeologists doing that. But what I love about burials is not just the bones and what they can tell us &amp;ndash; because they can tell us an enormous amount about somebody you know, I can tell how old somebody was, when they died, or what sex they were, usually I can look for pathology, I'm particularly interested in that because I was a doctor originally. So paleopathology, the study of disease in ancient human remains was always my kind of niche within this quite niche-sounding subject. So I'm really interested in the bones themselves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But then actually, you cannot fail to be interested in what's going on in that burial. And you get various cultures where we see so much within the burial of life, not just death. So for instance, I'm writing the follow up to &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt; at the moment in writing about the Anglo Saxon period where we get these amazing graves where people are buried, fully clothed. And they're also buried with lots of other objects which are obviously important to them and important as signals of their identity. It's quite macho: the men, if they can afford it are always buried with weapons. I don't think they were warriors, it's just that as a man, you had a spear and a shield. And women are buried with very gendered items as well, amazing beads, necklaces upon necklaces of beads. And there are other periods in history as well. So &lt;em&gt;Ancestors &lt;/em&gt;is focused on prehistory &amp;ndash; I'm looking at burials, for instance, from the Bronze Age, or the early Bronze Age, the Copper Age, and we've got burials like the Amesbury Archer, which is the most richly furnished copper age burial in Europe actually. And so we're just seeing an enormous amount. It's like a little time capsule of that culture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So we're not just getting the biology of the individual on their own from their bones, we're actually seeing a lot more about that individual and who they were in their community, and what their culture was about. And then burial itself, I think, is interesting, because we don't really see any other animals doing it. We know that other animals mourn. We know that chimpanzees mourn. Chimpanzee mothers who will carry the dead infant with them for days. Elephants will return to the corpse of a friend or relative, again and again. So there's definitely evidence of something that looks like mourning and an understanding of the loss of an individual. I don't think other animals, even chimpanzees, understand that they're going to die. So I think that's something that does mark us that is different, that we know that at some point, we're going to die. I think all of religion is about that, it&amp;rsquo;s about the kind of the terror of knowing that we're mortal. And trying to deal with that. And obviously, humanists have a different way of dealing with that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But yeah, trying to find out where burial starts, when burial starts happening. And there's some evidence of very early burial going back about 120,000 years ago for our species, modern humans. But we've also now got incontrovertible evidence that our sister species Neanderthals also buried their dead sometimes, and in some places. But when our species starts burying the dead, it's not universal. It's kind of sporadic. But we're seeing that kind of, I think we're seeing the thought process underlying that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And another thing I wonder about when you're talking about what differentiates us is this idea of collective memory. I guess that relates to what we were saying earlier about narrative and story. So there's something in your book about a hill in Ireland that was once known as the hill of incest. I wondered if you could tell me a bit about how genetic discoveries might be bearing out that slightly grim name.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's really difficult, isn't it? Because I think I mean, I've included that in there. And I do wonder if there's some kind of remembrance of that as a hill of sin? Because recent genetic evidence has shown that a man buried in Newgrange is the incestuous son of either a parent and a child, or two siblings. So you&amp;rsquo;ll never know if it's a parent and child or two siblings, we just know it was two first degree relatives.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So there's a possibility that that has then, you know, passed into legend, as it were, and then gone through time. But I think that the Neolithic tombs are more broadly interesting in that way, it has a lot to do with collective memory. And it's a lot to do with, you know, we're seeing quite a lot of these tombs containing relatives, for instance, not necessarily in one person &amp;ndash; as in this man who was a product of incest &amp;ndash; but we're seeing &amp;hellip;. Primrose Grange was a father and a daughter, there was a father and a son buried in two separate but fairly close tombs in Ireland as well. And then an instance of brothers buried in a tomb in Trumpington Meadows in Cambridgeshire. So this is fascinating, because we just haven't been able to get that information before genetics came along. We've wondered about what these Neolithic chambered tombs are, we've known for a long time that they&amp;rsquo;re communal burials, that there's a lot of human remains in some of them, and then wondered about what that means. The human remains are quite often fairly mixed up. So there's been one hypothesis that perhaps, once you die, you kind of enter this realm of the dead as a sort of communal entity, you'd lose your own individual identity, which would be subsumed into that communal identity, and it's somehow anonymizing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whereas actually, I think what we're saying here is, it's far from anonymous, at least in those tombs, where we've got this evidence of relatives buried in the same place. And perhaps what we are seeing is, is kind of family plots, you know, which we're obviously familiar with, later on, and up until quite recently. And it may be that these are essentially family tombs for the elite. Because we are entering a period of time where we're seeing a more kind of hierarchical structure of society. And they're making their mark in the landscape. It&amp;rsquo;s a fascinating time, because this Neolithic period is the first time we get people really stamping their identity on the landscape. And, you know, creating big monumental architecture in the landscape, from stones circles, to these amazing chamber tombs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so there's something there about collective memory, but also something about what it means for the living. I mean, tombs are all about the living really, they're not about the dead. And if you're a relative of somebody who's buried in that tomb, which is prominent in the landscape, then perhaps there's something about your land rights, and your right to live in that in that landscape and your own authority as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And there are some findings as well that you write about that hint about a past we might prefer to forget. Like cannibalism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Oh, yeah. So the cannibals of cheddar. Yeah. So we always associate cheddar with cheese. Back in the Mesolithic, they were eating each other. Now I'm always really really sceptical about evidence of cannibalism. Because archaeological human remains frequently get bashed up. You've got to be very, very careful about leaping to concrete conclusions about smashed bones. But Dr. Silvia Bello at the Natural History Museum has spent a huge amount of time poring over this collection of hundreds of fragments of bones from Gough&amp;rsquo;s Cave in Cheddar Gorge. And there's incontrovertible evidence of cannibalism there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So some of the long bones &amp;ndash; a say things like thigh bones &amp;ndash; are smashed when they're clearly green, when the bone is fresh. And, and fractures look very different when bone is fresh, and when bone has been in the ground for a long time, and then perhaps disturbed and gets broken. And there's also human tooth marks on the bones. So you know, that kind of adds up to being fairly kind of suspicious. And then also, there are skulls, which have been carved into cups. So the base of the skull has been taken away, you're just left with the dome of the skull, and you kind of turn it upside down. And some of these are chipped very carefully around the edges to even it out, to create a kind of cup.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think the first thing that we feel when we read about this, or even see the remains, as I've done, is a sense of quite intense disgust, actually. Which I think is reasonable, because we don't tend to go around eating each other nowadays. But again, we need to be objective: we need to think, right? Was it abhorrent to them? It obviously wasn't that abhorrent, because they're doing it. And you've got to think about all the reasons why somebody might have been eating someone else, you know. It could be nutritional, it could be that they're starving. I think the skull cups goes against that a bit. And there's also a bit of engraving on a radius too, so there's something more going on than just food.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And certainly Dr. Silvia Bello thinks that. So then you think about other reasons why people might eat each other, that we might eat an enemy in order to imbibe their power perhaps, or to really kind of mark the fact that you're victorious over them. There's lots and lots of reasons, through time where people might have eaten each other. And prehistory is always difficult in that respect. And it's prehistory, nobody's written anything down. And so we just have to look at the evidence and and think about what is the most likely explanation in each case. And I think that the most likely explanation for these for these remains is that it's not purely nutritional, there's some kind of ritual going on as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the ritual doesn't necessarily mean, you know, I've suggested an example there, where it might be done in deliberate disrespect, I suppose. Or as a way of marking superiority over another group or another person, but it could be &amp;hellip;. We do have to then really shake ourselves out of our current cultural ideas and go &amp;hellip; could it have been a respectful thing to do? Is it just what you do to Gran when she's died? You know, when I think it's respectful to cremate somebody and then grind them up into a fine powder and go and check that off a cliff, if we tell the Mesolithic people that, they might have thought that &lt;em&gt;we &lt;/em&gt;were obscene. So it is very weird to you know, you kind of turn it back on yourself and say &amp;ldquo;okay, yeah, some of the things we do are quite weird when you talk about it like that&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. I mean, I guess we probably won't be seeing a return to carving cups out of each other's skulls, or I hope not. But that's a really fascinating point about our current burial practices. I sort of wondered what you think that archaeologists of the future might be able to learn from studying our remains and the way that we commemorate the dead?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, we've done such an about turn over the 20th century into the 21st century, in Britain, and also in Europe more widely, not quite as not quite as profoundly, but in the States as well. If you go back to 1900, very, very few people were cremated in 1900 and one of them was Pitt Rivers. But it was a really kind of unusual thing to do. And most people looked at that with kind of horror, and certainly, Pitt River&amp;rsquo;s wife thought it was ridiculous that he was going to be cremated, and they had a lot of arguments about it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And now we just think, well, it's just, you know, it's the norm, and that's largely economic. So that's come about because of an economic necessity. And, you know, lack of space to bury people, there's always been a lack of space. So yeah, this kind of changed. I think archaeologists in the future will look at that and go, &amp;ldquo;Oh, there must have been a massive change in religion in 20th century Britain.&amp;rdquo; And of course, there wasn't. What there &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt;, was secularisation. So we've seen quite profound secularisation to the extent that now more than half of the country is not religious and say so on polls. But I don't think actually that the trend to cremate is much to do with that anyway. I think it is just quite economic. We're going to see another economic change very soon because, of course, all these people that are cremated, are cremated in big gas fired crematoria. So, that's not sustainable. So, you know, we need to tackle that quite quickly. And lots of people are often opting for things like eco burials, again, you know, going back to burial being the more ecological option. But then we come up with this issue of room again.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I think then you're looking at other ways. And I'll talk about some of the innovative ways that bodies are being disposed of, at the moment, and innovations which have come from America. So we've got things like resomation, when a body is essentially liquidised. And then that the liquid can be used as a fertiliser. And I also talk about that kind of the difference between memorialising somebody's life, and disposing of a body. And I do think we're going to see more kind of a move away from a focus on the body.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You're listening to &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; from the &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; magazine and the Rationalist Association. And I'm talking to anatomist, author and broadcaster Alice Roberts about ancient burials, bodies, and the business of science communication. And if science is your thing, why not head to our podcast archive where you can find Jo Marchant talking about the skies and the science of awe, and Kate Devlin discussing sex robots and feminism. Time for a quick word from &lt;em&gt;New humanist&lt;/em&gt; deputy editor Niki.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you're enjoying &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt;, remember that you can find reading lists and transcripts for all episodes on the &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; website. And while you're there, why not subscribe to the magazine using our discount for listeners, just head to &lt;em&gt;newhumanist.org.uk/subscribe&lt;/em&gt; and enter the offer code &lt;em&gt;WithReason&lt;/em&gt;. That means you'll get four beautifully designed additions sent to you through the year, as well as access to archive pieces going back through the decades, all for just &amp;pound;13.50. Back now to Samira and Alice Roberts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So Alice, we've been talking about burials, which is you say rituals often carried out in, or framed by, the presence or absence of religious belief. You're the president of Humanist UK. So I wondered if you could tell me about your own religious background? And what shapes your perspective on belief or non-belief?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, well, I was brought up in a quite devoutly religious family. So I got taken to church, pretty much every Sunday, and to Sunday school. And brought up with no kind of idea that there was really anything else on offer. And I went as far as getting confirmed. So I think I got confirmed when I was about 14.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then the following year, I said just &amp;ldquo;no I can't do this, I'm not, I'm not believing this.&amp;rdquo; So maybe it was the process of going through confirmation. But I think you do, you do examine your faith. And unfortunately, it took a little bit longer for the penny to drop for me. But it did, it was a process of questioning. And I think I was doing a lot of science at school as well. And so that kind of questioning and critical thinking extended to my personal beliefs and my thoughts about the world itself. And I realised that even if I were to take most of the Bible (so I was brought up as an Anglican in the Church of England), even if I was to take most of the Bible with a pinch of salt, there are kind of some fundamental things that you do have to believe in, one of these being the existence of God. If you don't believe in the existence of God, you're out of the club, really. So I suppose I became an atheist age 15.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It wasn't for a long time until I realised that actually what I was a humanist. And I think a lot of people are like that, it's a lot of conversations with people who have, you know, come to their approach to the world, sometimes having left religion as I did, sometimes never having been indoctrinated to begin with, so just quite naturally growing up thinking that the world is a natural place, that we don't have to invoke supernatural ideas or supernatural phenomena to explain things, that we're happy that there's some mystery and there are things that we don't know.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But that doesn't mean that we have to invent things to fill in these gaps. And we have this brilliant tool called science, which can help us to explore these gaps, but also actually to accept that science probably won't be able to tell us everything, and that we still don't need to invoke supernatural entities. And yeah, so I think for me, it was quite a long time after I became an atheist, that I realised that actually what described my approach to the world best was humanism, because of the way that we view the world as a natural place and our position in it is a natural phenomenon, that we are an evolved species just like any other. So that came through very strongly from me studying biology.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think there was something else. I did believe very strongly in the capability of humans to make the world a better place, and to cooperate with each other, and to use these kind of best aspects of what makes us human. So capabilities like empathy, kindness, together with logic and rationality, and that these things together were kind of the best you could be as a human and would help you make decisions about your own life, but also about society more generally, as well. And then you get well actually, that is humanism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Coming back to the idea of science and religious faith, which you said, you know, you're sort of getting more interested in, in science informing your atheism. Obviously, historically, as you say, I think that that experience of growing up in a religious family and not really questioning religion initially, that's probably something that was quite society-wide for long periods of our history. So I'm interested in science and religious influence, which is something that you write about in &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt;. So one story I was particularly struck by was about William Buckland, the 19th century antiquarian, who was also a priest. And you write that for him studying the Earth meant studying the work of God. And you describe how his early work actually started from the position that Noah's Ark and the flood that prompted it were historical fact. And so I wondered if you could, if you could tell me a bit about that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He is a fascinating character. I really enjoyed writing the chapter on the Red Lady of Paviland, which is one of the burials in the book that he excavated. But yeah, Buckland himself is just extraordinary. There&amp;rsquo;s a lot of evidence and a lot of source material. And he is interested in geology. He's interested in archaeology. He's a professor of geology at Oxford University, as well as being a cleric, obviously. And he didn't see any tension between those two things. For him science and religion were not in tension at all. Although he could see that there was a bit of a problem developing in the 19th centuries around that, you know, as science was starting to create this idea of how old the world was. And the story of evolution was starting to come out as well. He could see that there was going to be tension, that you certainly couldn't take the Bible literally anymore. But on the other hand, he was convinced that there were some things in the Bible that probably were true. And you know, were describing events in the deep past. And so he had this obsession with diluvian theory where he basically thought Noah's Flood was a historical reality, and was trying to find, trying to find evidence to show that actually, science was going to back up the Bible in that respect.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so it really shackled his thinking, because he couldn't see the evidence any other way. He found this skeleton of the Red Lady of Paviland &amp;ndash; who actually wasn't a woman either, he was a male skeleton. (That's another thing that Buckland couldn&amp;rsquo;t come to terms with, she looked like she was buried with what looked like jewellery. So that was, as far as he was concerned, that was a done deal. That's a closed case.) But he couldn't conceptualise that those human remains could have been as old as the elephant remains that he found in the same cave. Now these elephant remains were mammoth remains. He thought they were elephants that maybe got washed into the cave, during the Great Flood, and therefore must be much, much older than the human remains. He thought that humans were quite ancient, but only in the Middle East. So he didn't expect to see any humans at the same time as these very ancient elephants. So he says, in a letter to Lady Mary Cole, &amp;ldquo;we cannot admit the Red Lady to have been antediluvian.&amp;rdquo; In other words, to have existed before the Flood in Britain, because he didn't think there were any humans before the Flood in Britain.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So again, you know, ideology getting in the way of science, and to be fair to him, later on in life, having put forward all his evidence for what he thought was the Great Flood, and more and more evidence stacked up from geology, he backpedalled and he said, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, I was wrong. It's not a Flood at all. It is a series of ice ages.&amp;rdquo; Because the evidence had piled up to the point where actually you couldn't argue anymore that it was that. It looked like global inundation. And clearly what you had were ice ages. So it's interesting because hs mind was in shackles. His religion got in the way, but not completely. So in the end, I would have said he was more of a scientist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's interesting. Do you think that those two things are in opposition? Because obviously Buckland, as you explain, he was pursuing scientific discovery within a theological framework. So he was kind of starting from the place that science wouldn't challenge religious belief. So whether that was changing his view that the religious aspect was more metaphorical than literal, but it was still kind of within that framework. Do you think that religion and science are kind of fundamentally incompatible? Or are there ways in which that sort of Buckland attitude is maybe still around? For some scientists, I wonder?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's really difficult to say, I mean, I suppose if you look at it from a broadly societal level, you'd say, well, they're not incompatible, because there's plenty of scientists that are religious, there are I mean, you know, if you look at scientists as a whole, we are less religious than the rest of the population. But from an individual perspective, there are obviously lots and lots of scientists doing absolutely brilliant work, very eminent scientists who are religious. So it's not incompatible on that kind of individual level for them. And you know, somehow, they are able to return to look at their religion in one way, or look at their science in one way. And the two are not in tension with each other in their minds.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For me, it's just a very intensely personal thing. And for me, there was tension. And I was reading a lot. And you know, when I was a teenager, I was reading a lot of books about evolution, but also about these kind of philosophies to say Stephen Jay Gould, in particular, he came up with the idea of &amp;ldquo;non-overlapping magisteria&amp;rdquo;, where he said, actually, religion and science don't need to be in tension, because they they're doing different jobs, they're explaining different things. And there might be, you know, sometimes you will turn to religion for answers. And sometimes you're turning for science to answers. And they don't need to be in tension with each other. But in my own mind, they were. So it's interesting, isn't it? Because it's like, for me, it doesn't work. But obviously, it does work for some other people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. And actually, just sort of coming back to Buckland in a roundabout way. Of course, he was barking up the wrong tree trying to prove the historical truth of Noah's Ark. But something fascinating in your book is how some developments in ancient DNA do support some old stories, including from the Bible. So the one I'm thinking of is the case of bubonic plague and flee constipation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, now, that is absolutely fascinating. So I think if we look at the Bible as containing perhaps some, you know, historical nuggets within it, the I suppose we're saying, what Buckland was saying: &amp;ldquo;could it be that this is history?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;And could it be that the Genesis Flood myth is history?&amp;rdquo; And it's a reasonable question to ask, it's just that once you get the evidence piling up against it, you have to admit that it's not possible. But certainly with evidence of the bubonic plague, there are there are hints of this in the Bible. And, you know, there are stories where you where you think, well, it does sound like the plague. And we've now got the ability to sequence not only human DNA, but pathogen DNA. So any kind of diseases will, you know, there'll be bringing their own, bringing their own DNA with them. And when it comes to the plague, this has been really fascinating, because we can look at, for instance, passages in the Bible about the plague, we can look at later history as well. And look at the plague as described in the sixth century, for instance, the Justinian plague, and wonder whether that was the same pathogen that caused the Black Death much, much later in the Mediaeval period. But unless you've got a diagnostic technique, you don't know. And now we have a diagnostic technique. So now we know that the bubonic plague was around at the time it's being described in the Bible. So it seems very possible indeed, that this really was the plague. We know that the Justinian plague is the same, it&amp;rsquo;s Yersinia pestis, it's the same plague pathogen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And we've had recently, just a couple of years ago, a sequence from a cemetery in Essex, Spong Hill, showing that the Justinian plague reached Britain. So we didn't know that at all from the history. So it's really interesting, because it means that we can go back to the histories, again. We've got another diagnostic technique to help us. And sometimes we'll see that supporting what is described in the histories or actually nailing the pathogen for us. But sometimes as in this case of Spong Hill, there's no historical record of the plague reaching Eastern England, but we've got the DNA so we can say &amp;ldquo;Yes, it did&amp;rdquo;. So I think we're going to see that a lot with genetics, we're going to be able to explore historical stories. But we're also going to be able to really extend that historical story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Well that comes neatly back to what we were talking about at the outset, about narrative and science, doesn't it? So in each episode of &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt;, we dig around in the &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; archive for a piece that speaks to our guest's work. So today, I have been looking at a 2018 &lt;a href="/articles/5335/what-ancient-dna-says-about-us"&gt;piece by a science writer, Peter Forbes&lt;/a&gt;. And it's a profile of David Reich, a geneticist who has carried out pioneering research in the field of ancient DNA that, I think, touches on lots of what we've been talking about: human migration and identity and so on. So I wondered if you could tell me a bit about David Reich's research. I know you cited it at points in the book and its significance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Well David Reich is a real pioneer in ancient genetics. And he's really helped to bring genetics to the fore when it comes to exploring some of these questions, particularly about ancient migrations. I would urge anybody who is interested in this whole sphere of archaeology meets genetics to read David Reich&amp;rsquo;s brilliant book.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Great. And so you say he's a pioneer. And there's obviously, as we spoke about at the outset, these huge developments in this field. Where do you think is left to go for the collaboration between genetics and archaeology?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I think we're just starting. So I think what we're seeing at the moment within genetics, and particularly with genomics, we're seeing so many revelations coming through thick and fast. We will understand a lot more about people moving around in the past &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s one of the really big things. We're able to look at kinship. We're able to sex skeletons that I couldn't sex, for instance, say &amp;ndash; there'll be some skeletons &amp;hellip; there will always be skeletons where I go, &amp;ldquo;I don't know, I don't can't say for sure if this is male or female&amp;rdquo;, but genetics can. So there's lots of kind of details like that to be added.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But there's some really profound bigger picture stuff as well. It's quite a disruptive technology at the moment, because it's coming along and providing answers that we didn't even know were possible 10 years ago. But I think it will get to the point where it becomes an almost standard thing to do when you're analysing human remains, in the same way that we use radiocarbon dating to work out the date of any organic remains. I think that we'll be seeing genomes used much more frequently and much more widely.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And then one of the really exciting developments at the moment is that you don't even need a bone to get DNA out of. You can get DNA out of mud. So we're seeing amazing breakthroughs with sedaDNA, sedimentary ancient DNA, where just using soil samples, for instance, you can extract DNA from that. And you can see which organisms were around in a particular environment &amp;ndash; sort of dizzying, the amount of information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Before you go, what are you up to for the rest of the year?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I'm just off filming a new series of &lt;em&gt;Digging For Britain&lt;/em&gt;. So we had a fallow year last year, because there wasn't much archaeology happening. But I'm off travelling around the country visiting really exciting archaeological sites. And I'm halfway through filming that. So that should be on in probably November or December, on BBC Two. And I'm also going on tour. So I'm doing a small tour in November, where I'll be talking about &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt;, and all the details of that on my website.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Well, thank you, Alice. Thank you so much. Thank you for having me. Alice Roberts there, talking about her new book &lt;em&gt;Ancestors&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And with me now is Niki Smith, deputy editor of New Humanist magazine. So Niki, what's your take on what we've just heard from Alice?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So I was surprised at the level to which genetics was revolutionising what we know about history and prehistory. And I knew that developments were being made. But I was particularly struck by the fact that we might need to revise our ideas about the Anglo Saxon invasion. That seemed particularly interesting, because that informs so much about what we think about identity in this country and Englishness in particular.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yeah, absolutely. I think there's something really fascinating about these sort of legends that we grow up with, and the points of crossover between legend and history, and maybe not all is, as we think it is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NSS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yeah, you really got that sense of excitement from Alice of just applying this, you know, what she called a disruptive technology, to these really old ancient myths and these different forms of knowledge colliding. And I also found it interesting that she was talking about the act of burial and what we can learn about that being qs much to do with life, as it is to do with death, but also that it might say something very distinctive about our species, because I didn't realise that animals didn't bury their dead. I sort of had a notion of the elephant graveyard. And obviously, as Alice says, chimpanzees mourn. Elephants mourn. But they don't actually bury their dead.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;You have that whole idea about what makes us human, or what differentiates humans rather from other species. I think it's obviously a huge question and one of particular interest, perhaps to humanists, but also more broadly. And then I wonder also, if what we're talking about now, the kind of story and myth and legend, if that's another thing that might be differentiating. There's certainly a lot of that in what Alice was talking about.&lt;br /&gt;Absolutely. We're definitely storytelling animals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So that's all for today. We'll be back next week with more. And remember, you can find reading lists and transcripts for all episodes of &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; at newhumanist.org.uk. You can also find us on Twitter @NewHumanist. This podcast was presented by me, Samira Shackle with Niki Seth-Smith. Our sound engineer was David Crackles and our series producer is Alice Bloch. See you back here soon. Goodbye.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading list: &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alice Roberts, &amp;lsquo;Ancestors: A Prehistory of Britain in Seven Burials&amp;rsquo; (2021)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alice Roberts and Andrew Copson, &amp;lsquo;The Little Book of Humanism: Universal Lessons on Finding Purpose, Meaning and Joy&amp;rsquo; (2020)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;David Reich &amp;lsquo;Who We Are and How We Got Here: Ancient DNA and the New Science of the Human&amp;rsquo; (2018)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/articles/5335/what-ancient-dna-says-about-us"&gt;Peter Forbes &amp;lsquo;What Ancient DNA says about us&amp;rsquo;, New Humanist magazine (2018)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b014hl0d"&gt;&amp;lsquo;Digging for Britain&amp;rsquo; presented by Alice Roberts, BBC Four&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5860/learning-from-our-ancestors-w-alice-roberts#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-21T09:58:27Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-21T09:58:27Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Patron saint of doom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5854/patron-saint-of-doom#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/JFWF7M.jpg" height="645" alt="JFWF7M" width="525" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t know if you&amp;rsquo;ve noticed but everything, recently, has been very bad. Granted, the vaccine roll-out has given the pandemic a sort of &amp;ldquo;end-of-term&amp;rdquo; vibe &amp;ndash; more contagious variants notwithstanding &amp;ndash; as we anticipate the return of something like normality. But we have still lost more than a year of our lives to the pandemic. It is an episode we emerge from poorer and weaker, only able to continue, for the most part, as a result of our extraordinary ability to relegate death through illness to the back of our minds. And the pandemic, of course, is far from the worst disaster any of us, in our lifetimes, are likely to face. Perhaps, indeed, the coronavirus lockdowns were just a dry run for the sort of measures that will end up being permanently imposed on us &amp;ndash; as the planet, with increasingly rapidity, begins to boil and crack and drown us.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What philosophy could possibly be adequate to such an age of crisis and disaster? &lt;em&gt;On the Suffering of the World&lt;/em&gt;, a volume published by Repeater Books last December, might have something like the answer. Edited by the pessimist philosopher Eugene Thacker, the book collects eight of the later essays of Arthur Schopenhauer, the great grumpy old man of the history of thought; the philosophical patron saint of doom and gloom.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In his own most substantial contribution to thinking about how terrible everything is, &lt;em&gt;Infinite Resignation&lt;/em&gt; (also published by Repeater, in 2018), Thacker describes pessimism as &amp;ldquo;a strange philosophy . . . the most adequate, the least helpful&amp;rdquo;. The pessimist is the one determined to see reality always as it is, not how they would like it to be &amp;ndash; to constantly tell both themselves and others how things really are, shorn of any Pollyanna-ish enchantment. But when this happens &amp;ndash; when the disaster we exist within is seen, against all our hopes, for what it is &amp;ndash; we are left feeling hollow, powerless, resigned; in despair of an existence that, in truth, really doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem at all worth having. This is the sort of thinker that Schopenhauer was: someone willing to look the problem of our existence in the eye.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Schopenhauer is not an easy thinker to get a clear purchase on. Utterly contemptuous of the academic philosophy of his day, he largely eschewed its conventions, often pitching his work to editors with the promise that it was supposed to appeal more to generalists. The pitch of his invective has a certain visceral appeal, and his willingness to take his cues from &amp;ldquo;real-world&amp;rdquo; phenomena, like sex or noisy neighbours, ensures that his is a thought with its feet planted, at least in some way, on the ground. But in truth, Schopenhauer made few concessions to the general reader either: for most of his life, his work barely sold. His essays &amp;ndash; even his &amp;ldquo;popular&amp;rdquo; ones &amp;ndash; often have a rambling, repetitious feel, like being forced to listen to a crotchety old fart drone on and on about something in your general direction. They were typically published as a supplement to &lt;em&gt;The World as Will and Representation&lt;/em&gt;. Regarded as his &amp;ldquo;chief&amp;rdquo; work, &lt;em&gt;The World as Will and Representation&lt;/em&gt; is a sprawling, purportedly systematic monolith, which nowadays one inevitably feels obliged to surmount before attempting any of the rest of his writings, given that they are almost always still published together. One great advantage, then, of &lt;em&gt;On the Suffering of the World&lt;/em&gt; is that when you hold it in your hands, you feel relieved of this burden. Here, finally, is a version of Schopenhauer which feels condensed enough to approach. No longer does one have to sacrifice too much of one&amp;rsquo;s life to find out why it&amp;rsquo;s not worth living.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Thacker puts it, in his illuminating introduction to the volume, Schopenhauer is a thinker who spent his life elaborating just one &amp;ldquo;single thought&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a thought which Thacker identifies as: &amp;ldquo;I do not live, I am lived.&amp;rdquo; For Schopenhauer, the individual self of our perceptions is essentially an illusion, belonging to the world as &amp;ldquo;Representation&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; or, how we are obliged to picture things to ourselves. What really exists is &amp;ldquo;the Will&amp;rdquo;: an endless, blind, inhuman process of compulsion and desiring, of meaningless creation and destruction. Everything is bad; obviously, empirically bad, as Schopenhauer relates in &amp;ldquo;On the Vanity and Suffering of Life&amp;rdquo;, the first essay here and almost certainly the best introduction to his general outlook.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;We feel pain, but not painlessness; care, but not freedom from care; fear, but not safety and security. We feel the desire as soon as we feel hunger and thirst; but as soon as it has been satisfied, it is like the mouthful of food which has been taken, and which ceases to exist for our feelings the moment it is swallowed . . . How human beings deal with themselves is seen, for example, in slavery in America, the ultimate object of which is sugar and coffee. However, we need not go so far; to enter at the age of five a cotton-spinning or other factory. . . is to purchase dearly the pleasure of drawing breath. But this is the fate of millions, and many more millions have an analogous fate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it also can&amp;rsquo;t get any better: because the world is bad as a result of the Will which lives us &amp;ndash; and because it lives us, we have no autonomy in relation to our desires. We might hate that the world is like this, but we can&amp;rsquo;t meaningfully want it to be any better. At heart we are all stupid, selfish and hopelessly short-termist. Even the best of us will ultimately acquiesce somehow in exploitation; all of what we think are our decisions will ultimately end in failure and frustration. &amp;ldquo;As long as our will is the same,&amp;rdquo; as Schopenhauer puts it, &amp;ldquo;our world cannot be other than it is."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Schopenhauer's pessimism offers hope&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;This thought, of course, seems deeply relevant in the age of climate change, when everything we do, in all innocence, to prolong and to enjoy our lives seems bound to intensify the process which is tending towards the destruction of all things; when even the most concerted attempt to stand, saint-like, outside of this process seems likely to prove roughly as effective as an animal caught in a trap trying to escape by tearing at its fur. But for Schopenhauer, even death would be no way out &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;death is for the species what sleep is for the individual,&amp;rdquo; as he liked to put it. Upon our deaths, while we as individuals may be unburdened of the consciousness of our situation, some new individual quite like ourselves will be born again into the same hell, to undergo our fate instead.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;And so, reading this volume, I was surprised to find &amp;ndash; even within Schopenhauer&amp;rsquo;s unwaveringly pessimistic vision &amp;ndash; the basis for a real sort of hope. This might sound surprising. But in fact, if we take our cues from Thacker&amp;rsquo;s definition of pessimism, it makes perfect sense. Real hope must be distinguished from mere wishful thinking. It must provide us with a basis for practice, for actually doing something about things, or else all it will amount to is a reason to remain happily, passively, resigned to whatever fate has in store.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Any optimist worth their salt, therefore, must start out as the most deflated pessimist: they must strive to see our situation adequately, for how wretched it actually is. The challenge for hope, then, lies in finding the faith to try and do something about it &amp;ndash; to respond to the realisation by doing something other than being immediately hollowed out by despair. In a way, Schopenhauer really does give us the seeds for this sort of hope &amp;ndash; even if he has gone out of his way to hide them as deep down as possible in the dirt.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For Schopenhauer, we might not be able to change the Will, but we can do at least one thing other than acquiesce in it: we can strive to deny it. In showing this, he draws on Eastern philosophy and religion, especially Buddhism &amp;ndash; but he also cites examples from Christians such as the early Church fathers, or Francis of Assisi. Schopenhauer appears to envisage the process through which one might come to deny the Will along roughly similar lines to the story of the Buddha: through an awareness of the sufferings of the world, one might find oneself decentred from one&amp;rsquo;s selfish, temporal desires. Having thus come to realise that no good can arise from getting what we want, one is given to submerge one&amp;rsquo;s desires, to pursue inner peace &amp;ndash; although this is a state that Schopenhauer thought could only really be brought about for any one individual if the whole world were to be given peace as well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In Schopenhauer&amp;rsquo;s writings, admittedly, this wisdom is offered as a counsel of despair. Something can be hoped for, maybe &amp;ndash; but that something is, quite literally, nothing. But now, let&amp;rsquo;s think about what this &amp;ldquo;nothing&amp;rdquo; might look like in practice. Suppose the world were given peace. Must this in fact entail non-existence? If Schopenhauer thinks we should do anything, it is to strive, if even against the whole concept of striving itself, to create a world in which we are all decoupled from our basic selfishness; in which we have the strength to stand in solidarity with the sufferings of others; in which we have both the courage and the knowledge to meaningfully refuse to add to the world&amp;rsquo;s sum total of pain and exploitation. To live not for ourselves, in short, but for others. To not cling desperately and selfishly to our own lives, but to feel able to embrace the end joyfully, when ultimately faced with our time to go.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Perhaps such a world, full of people like this, would be impossible. Perhaps, given how we are mere puppets of the Will, such a world could never, finally, permanently, be brought about. At any rate it is a utopia that seems to be becoming more, rather than less, alien to us right now. If anything, the pandemic has increased our tendency to live as isolated little consumer-atoms, only able to satisfy our short-term lust for dopamine through the computer screen. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But even in the darkest depths of his pessimism &amp;ndash; and despite, I think, anything he understood himself to be doing &amp;ndash; Schopenhauer nevertheless manages to give us an idea of how we would need to be re-oriented towards our selves and our world, if we were ever going to try and change things for the better. It is as much for his secret hope as for his bombastic pessimism that Arthur Schopenhauer is a thinker for today. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5854/patron-saint-of-doom#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-21T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-21T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Teens Around the World are “Catching” Tourettes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/zJsHMsngzlg/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: I’ve long been fascinated by people who “fake” illnesses. It’s such a complicated mash-up of psychological disorders, real physical issues, medical neglect, marginalization — just a big mishmash of things I weirdly enjoy thinking …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/zJsHMsngzlg" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131144</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T15:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T15:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A good death</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5857/a-good-death#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/rad-ana-WgPC2oG_pYA-unsplash.jpg" height="945" alt="rad-ana-WgPC2oG_pYA-unsplash" width="1680" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On a sun-bleached afternoon in May, Rebecca Drury and Louise Sweeney, friends since their teenage years, strolled along a pebbled beach near Brighton, talking about death. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca, a blonde, stylish 53-year-old dance instructor, was dying. After fighting cancer on-and-off since 2016, she&amp;rsquo;d been told by oncologists in 2020 that her illness &amp;ndash; which despite chemo and immunotherapy had spread to her pleura and bones &amp;ndash; was incurable. Rebecca was not afraid of death itself. But she&amp;rsquo;d heard that palliative medicine cannot prevent painful deaths for some people. Already in immense pain, she was afraid of a bad death, and was making plans to avoid it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Louise, also 53, recalls visiting Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s flat that day: a plant-decorated sanctuary perched at the top of a Regency townhouse. Rebecca, a creative cook, had prepared a salad of avocado, couscous and beetroot. Out of the window, the sun scorched down on the sea. After lunch, Rebecca took Louise on a walk, to her favourite spot, quiet Ovingdean beach. On the way, they talked. It was now clear that Rebecca wasn&amp;rsquo;t well enough to fly to Dignitas in Switzerland, which allows people of sound judgement to apply for assisted suicide by drinking tonics of antiemetic and pentobarbital drugs. (Nearly 350 Brits have taken the trip, falling asleep within five minutes and then drifting away within half an hour.) Besides, Dignitas paperwork takes three or four months. Rebecca wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure she had that long.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Instead, Rebecca said she was meeting with an end-of-life doula, a trained healthcare companion who supports people during dying. The doula, Li Mills, would help to set her affairs in order, manage end-of-life care and sit with her as she died. The cancer had taken away Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s old life &amp;ndash; dancing, cycling, socialising, hosting &amp;ndash; and the pain was becoming unmanageable. &amp;ldquo;I wish that I had a heart attack tonight, because I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be in this pain all the time,&amp;rdquo; Rebecca said. Louise understood. She&amp;rsquo;d watched her sister die of cancer and knew how horrible life&amp;rsquo;s final chapters can be. &amp;ldquo;Well, you know I&amp;rsquo;ll be there to hold your hand too,&amp;rdquo; Louise said.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Conversations about death tear through dozens of families every month. Even if every dying person had access to the best palliative care, an average of 17 people a day would still die in severe pain in the UK, according to a 2019 study commissioned by campaign group Dignity In Dying and conducted by the Office of Health Economics. For some cancers, like those shredding through the lungs, end-of-life sedatives sometimes don&amp;rsquo;t work; it&amp;rsquo;s hard to fall asleep if you can&amp;rsquo;t breathe, leading to the horrific sensation of being awake during your own death.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What Rebecca and Louise did not talk about was the prospect of assisted dying at home in Brighton, surrounded by loved ones. When the UK parliament decriminalised suicide in the 1961, it created a criminal offence for &amp;ldquo;assisting, aiding or abetting&amp;rdquo; suicide punishable by up to 14 years in prison. Doctors administering a lethal dose of painkillers or people helping dying friends travel to Switzerland both fall under the Suicide Act&amp;rsquo;s crosshairs. For decades, assisted dying campaigners have pushed to change this law &amp;ndash; which they say would stop thousands of painful deaths a year, and finally grant people agency to choose how and when they die.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;For a long time, it appeared the tide would never turn. In 2007 the Daily Mail blasted a Liberal Democrat MP as &amp;ldquo;Dr Death&amp;rdquo; for supporting assisted suicide. As recently as 2015, MPs voted overwhelmingly to uphold the blanket ban. But after years of campaigning, and a pandemic that has forced everyone to confront their own mortality, momentum is building. After Covid, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re just more aware that people can die badly,&amp;rdquo; Sarah Wootton, chief executive of Dignity in Dying, told me. New bills are being debated by lawmakers in Westminster, Holyrood and Jersey. &amp;ldquo;Now, there&amp;rsquo;s a real sense that the campaign is winning the argument. We&amp;rsquo;re in the strongest strategic position that we&amp;rsquo;ve ever been in,&amp;rdquo; Wootton said.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When they returned from the beach, Rebecca insisted on gifting Louise a pair of silver Mexican earrings studded with turquoise and blue opal. &amp;ldquo;I want to give you something to remind you of me,&amp;rdquo; she said. Louise was reluctant at first, but accepted. They embraced. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s really nice that you&amp;rsquo;re giving it to me now, before you&amp;rsquo;re gone,&amp;rdquo; she told her.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca was raised in a theatrical family in Nottinghamshire, with a drama teacher mum and music teacher stepdad. In her early 20s she moved to Brighton for university, fell in love with the city&amp;rsquo;s creative streak and never left. She became famous for hosting cocktail parties. &amp;ldquo;Becca&amp;rsquo;s the linchpin of the social circle,&amp;rdquo; Janice Britz, an NHS worker who&amp;rsquo;s been close to her for 15 years, told me. Friends say she made each guest feel as if the whole night had been planned for them. &amp;ldquo;Rebecca makes you feel your best self,&amp;rdquo; Janice said. &amp;ldquo;She makes people glow.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Dignity in death&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;At age 48 she was active, teaching dance classes and cycling across Brighton to see friends. Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s 2016 stage-two lung cancer diagnosis screeched the brakes on her life. She immediately cut out meat, ate organic, reduced drinking and quit smoking. Within two months, she&amp;rsquo;d had an operation and was two-thirds of a lung down. Those close to her during this first phase recall a relentless optimism. When she visited the hospital, Janice remembered being asked by Rebecca, &amp;ldquo;How are you? What&amp;rsquo;s going on for you?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rebecca vowed to rebound and run 8k within the year. She did. Two years later, she got the all-clear. Life in her flat, nicknamed the Pink Palace, returned to normal again. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But cancer, as the physician and author Siddhartha Mukherjee wrote in his 2010 book &lt;em&gt;The Emperor of All Maladies: A Biography of Cancer&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;is an expansionist disease; it invades through tissues, sets up colonies in hostile landscapes, seeking &amp;lsquo;sanctuary&amp;rsquo; in one organ and then immigrating to another.&amp;rdquo; In 2018, Rebecca began to suffer a pain doctors couldn&amp;rsquo;t explain. After a series of painful tests, they spotted a tumour in Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s pleura, the cavity between the lungs and chest. Again, it was removed. Eight months later, however, with the pain still present, oncologists discovered the cancer had spread to her bones, entering through the ribs. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca was told in late 2019 her disease was incurable. She opted for chemo to beat it back. But she also started planning to end her life, in the hope of avoiding a bad death. With her energy dulled by heavy medication, Rebecca began researching Dignitas.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In 1998, Dignitas was launched in Zurich. The assisted suicide non-profit allows people to die in a domestic apartment, rather than a sterile hospital environment. Since its launch, it has aided 3,248 people&amp;rsquo;s deaths. During the application process, those who wish to take their own life meet twice with Dignitas consultants, plus independent doctors, for an evaluation to determine informed consent. The catch for British members is that the months-long process and necessity of travelling to Switzerland means people have to put a premature stop to their lives. But it is still popular with those who can afford it; someone from the UK travels to Switzerland to die on average every eight days. The typical cost is &amp;pound;10,000. So after her incurable diagnosis, Rebecca started saving.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca wanted dignity at the end. &amp;ldquo;I live life in agonising pain, and my pain is only going to get worse,&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;It just seems an obvious choice to me, if I could have a lovely little party &amp;ndash; that&amp;rsquo;s what I was famous for, throwing parties &amp;ndash; a nice little gathering of people around me the day before, and then someone to hold my hand.&amp;rdquo; Rebecca also began campaigning for a change to UK law with Dignity In Dying. She didn&amp;rsquo;t want other people to face her dilemma: a painful death, a potential botched home suicide, or ending life early (and friends facing prosecution) via Switzerland. &amp;ldquo;The UK&amp;rsquo;s law is inhumane,&amp;rdquo; she wrote to then health secretary Matt Hancock in June. &amp;ldquo;I want a beautiful death, on my own terms.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The 1961 Suicide Act created the legal paradox that assisting someone to do something legal was itself illegal. This is even if suicide is someone&amp;rsquo;s explicit wish and assistance is motivated by compassion. Some doctors and nurses talk of the &amp;ldquo;old days&amp;rdquo; when, if a terminally ill patient was suffering extreme pain, a doctor would prescribe or administer a high dose of painkillers to &amp;ldquo;make them more comfortable&amp;rdquo;, speeding up their death and letting them drift away painlessly. But things changed. After the conviction in 2000 of GP serial killer Harold Shipman for murdering patients via lethal doses of diamorphine, palliative care was radically altered. Doctors spoke of the &amp;ldquo;Shipman effect&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Medical professionals are now much more conservative with painkiller dosage. Some people die in immense pain, drawn out for days. &amp;ldquo;We treat dogs better,&amp;rdquo; one bereaved husband told me. His wife had cancer, and asphyxiated in August last year, four painful days after asking nurses to end her life. This is the death Rebecca feared the most.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In 2010, the Department of Public Prosecutions (DPP), then led by Keir Starmer, clarified guidance on who would be punished over trips to Switzerland. In a years-long lawsuit, Debbie Purdy, who had multiple sclerosis and planned to fly to Dignitas to die, demanded to know if her husband would face prison time for assisting her. Eventually forced by the court to clarify, the DPP said it was not likely to seek prosecutions as long as there was, among other things, a &amp;ldquo;voluntary, clear, settled and informed decision&amp;rdquo; to die and any assistance was &amp;ldquo;wholly motivated by compassion&amp;rdquo;. To campaigners, it felt like the edges of the jagged law had been sanded down. But the law was still in place. Now they wanted it replaced for good.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At the time, ministers saw nothing to be gained from decriminalising assisted dying. And with a trinity of opponents to provoke &amp;ndash; religious leaders, newspapers and the medical establishment &amp;ndash; it was a potential vote loser. Then in 2015, MPs got the chance to vote on assisted dying for the first time in 20 years. Labour backbencher Rob Marris&amp;rsquo;s assisted dying bill was pulled out the hat in the parliamentary private member&amp;rsquo;s bill ballot. It proposed stringent safeguards: not only two doctors were needed to approve a request but also the High Court, and only those with six months left to live were deemed eligible. (Humanists UK criticised the bill for being too narrow.)&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;MPs torpedoed the proposal 330-118. But since then energy has surged. Blanket bans seem to be waning globally. Nine US states, three Australian states and four European countries (most recently Spain) now have assisted dying laws. This May, Baroness Molly Meacher, a cross-bench peer and chair of Dignity In Dying, introduced a new bill to the House of Lords, modelled on the 2015 proposal. And this year The Sunday Times launched a campaign to legalise assisted dying. &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s extremely powerful,&amp;rdquo; Meacher told me, &amp;ldquo;partly because Conservative MPs read The Sunday Times, every single one of them.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Most significantly, the majority of UK medical professionals now support legalisation. Last October the British Medical Association published a poll of 150,000 doctors, finding 50 per cent personally supported a change in the law to enable assisted suicide, with 39 per cent personally opposed and 11 per cent undecided. Then, in September this year, the BMA dropped its opposition to assisted dying and adopted a neutral stance.&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;Opponents have lost their nuclear argument.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Limits to palliative care&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But opponents still remain, and they&amp;rsquo;re fighting hard. Many are people of faith who want to preserve the sanctity of life. In parliament they&amp;rsquo;re led by Danny Kruger, Conservative MP and chair of the all-party parliamentary group on Dying Well. (His office did not respond to an interview request.) The lobby to retain criminalisation centres around three arguments: first, government should properly fund disability benefit and palliative care, much of which is currently funded by charity. (Legalisation advocates say these goals are not mutually exclusive.) Secondly, they say people may feel like a burden on their carers and feel pressed to die early. Finally, they argue it is impossible to have adequate safeguards to protect people from malicious families. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;It can be quite a compelling idea, that greedy relatives want auntie Flo&amp;rsquo;s assets so they&amp;rsquo;re pushing her to go for an assisted death,&amp;rdquo; said Trevor Moore, chair of My Death, My Decision, which campaigns for a broader bill to include people suffering incurable pain. &amp;ldquo;Frankly, that&amp;rsquo;s specious.&amp;rdquo; There are much easier ways to grab assets that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t include a rigorous assisted dying procedure, Moore said. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In November 2020, when Hancock announced a fresh coronavirus lockdown, a strategic question at the dispatch box from the co-chair of the All-Party Parliamentary Group for Choice at the End of Life, Andrew Mitchell, forced him to clarify government guidance further. Amid travel restrictions, &amp;ldquo;It is legal to travel abroad for the purpose of assisted dying where it is allowed in that jurisdiction,&amp;rdquo; Hancock said. It was hailed as another step towards legalisation. The strategy, for Mitchell&amp;rsquo;s co-chair Karin Smyth, is to attack the existing law &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;you have to chink away at some of the side bits&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; while also battling for a new one. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Meacher bill will have its second reading this autumn. As a private member&amp;rsquo;s bill, its chances of passing are slim, but campaigners are hoping the government buckles to public pressure: according to a 2019 Yonder poll, a total of 84 per cent are now in favour of assisted dying.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On Friday 25 June, Janice visited Rebecca at the Pink Palace. Some other friends also dropped by to dye Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s hair pink. Then they drank tea and chatted. Rebecca was heavily medicated, but the pain was controllable and she was overjoyed to play the host. &amp;ldquo;Becca was just glowing. She was saying, &amp;lsquo;This is like it was before!&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo; Janice said. &amp;ldquo;And you could just see her. She&amp;rsquo;s still Becca &amp;ndash; we haven&amp;rsquo;t lost her yet.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Three days later, Rebecca entered a hospice. The plan was a short stay of two weeks to experiment with drugs that would placate her pain and allow her to function. But she was deteriorating fast. Two weeks later, Janice was phoned by Li Mills, the doula, saying Rebecca was in bad shape. Janice rushed to the hospice. The doctors said they suspected Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s cancer had penetrated her brain. She was near the end. Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s body was resisting sedation, plunging her into an endless agony. Janice gripped her hand for hours and hours. Rebecca could only rally a whisper, but Janice recalled her leaning in and saying, &amp;ldquo;I want to go, can you help me?&amp;rdquo; Janice checked in with the doctor about the situation with her medication. With a look of kindness and empathy, a nurse said, &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re upping her meds as much as we can.&amp;rdquo; Janice knew there was a line they could not cross. Rebecca was pushing up against it. After Janice left that evening, she pulsated with anger at the law which trapped Rebecca in this suffering. Rebecca wasn&amp;rsquo;t scared of exiting this world. &amp;ldquo;She was scared about the suffering,&amp;rdquo; Janice said. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m just holding her tortured face in my mind all the time.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;At last, the doctors found a balance of drugs that let Rebecca stay under and shelter from her aching body. She was tranquil, as if sleeping. Her room was flanked by pink roses, her favourite, that matched her pink hair. She stayed in this state for a few days, as if drawing one last deep breath before letting go. On the morning of 14 July, Rebecca died, her breathing ending almost imperceptibly.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rebecca Drury did not have the death she wanted. She exercised as much agency as she could; her doula was with her right until the end. But now, in her memory, Rebecca&amp;rsquo;s friends are fighting to change the law &amp;ndash; to stop others suffering a painful end.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The day before Rebecca died, I spoke to Louise over the phone. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m wearing her earrings today,&amp;rdquo; she said, &amp;ldquo;I really needed to feel her closer to me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5857/a-good-death#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T13:40:58Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T13:40:58Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Fallen Idols</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5852/book-review-fallen-idols#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/P297XD-w.jpg" height="987" alt="P297XD-w" width="1264" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fallen Idols: Twelve Statues That Made History&lt;/strong&gt; By Alex von Tunzelmann&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is possibly because statues are supposed to be permanent fixtures that they are so susceptible to being rethought or regretted: they&amp;rsquo;re the municipal equivalent of tattoos. &lt;em&gt;Fallen Idols&lt;/em&gt; is a response to 2020&amp;rsquo;s global iconoclastic mania. Of the dozen that Alex von Tunzelmann considers, including monuments to Lenin, Stalin, Rhodes and Robert E. Lee, two are among those pulled down amid last year&amp;rsquo;s Black Lives Matters protests &amp;ndash; the statue of Edward Colston dumped into Bristol Harbour in June, and the statue of George Washington in Portland, tipped over later that month, on Juneteenth. Colston was a slave-trader, yet a prolific philanthropist and builder of schools, hospitals and almshouses. Washington was a slave-owner, yet a revolutionary liberator, and founder of a mighty democracy. When we look at statues, for all their monolithic presence, we still get to decide what we&amp;rsquo;re looking at. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is why humankind has been pulling statues down (almost) as long as we have been putting them up. Von Tunzelmann&amp;rsquo;s introduction reminds that our totem-smashing instincts date back to at least ancient Egypt, where incoming pharaohs would demand the demolition of idols commemorating their predecessors. But she begins properly in New York in 1776, where Joseph Wilton&amp;rsquo;s statue of King George III was toppled &amp;ndash; and beheaded &amp;ndash; by an enraged rabble after just six years presiding over Bowling Green, in Lower Manhattan. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It was common in 2020 for anguished liberals to express discomfort with the anarchy of de-statueing, even as they agreed with the motives. This, von Tunzelmann explains, is not a new phenomenon either. One fretful observer who witnessed George III&amp;rsquo;s humiliation said that he &amp;ldquo;doubts not the persons who pulled down and mutilated the statue. . .were actuated by zeal in the public cause, yet it has so much the appearance of riot.&amp;rdquo; He carried on by advocating sternly that in future these things be left to proper authorities. His name was George Washington. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The difficulty will always be that no universally applicable ethical template can conclusively decide whether a given statue should stand or fall. That said, some of von Tunzelmann&amp;rsquo;s selections seem open-and-shut. Whatever one felt about the US-led invasion of Iraq in 2003, the glowering statue of tyrant Saddam Hussein in Baghdad assuredly had it coming. There seems no reason why the citizens of Kinshasa should want a statue of Belgian king Leopold II, who lorded over the horrors of the Congo Free State. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Even here, however, von Tunzelmann finds ambiguity and argument: Leopold&amp;rsquo;s statue was pulled down twice. The first time was in 1966, on the orders of loopy despot Mobutu Sese Soko, who may have believed that Kinshasa was only big enough for one rapacious maniac. After several decades mouldering &amp;ldquo;under a tree behind a shed, among other symbols of the colonial past&amp;rdquo;, Leopold was reinstalled in 2005 at the whim of Congolese culture minister Christophe Muzungu, taking to an extreme the notion, often floated in defence of controversial statues, that they are guarantors of our history, however murky it may be. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;When it was made clear to Muzungu by an unimpressed crowd that if he didn&amp;rsquo;t take Leopold back down, then they would, it was re-removed. As has been the case in von Tunzelmann&amp;rsquo;s previous books, including terrific histories of the Suez Crisis and the Partition of India, her research is enlivened by a talent for unearthing and relating the droll factoid: &amp;ldquo;Muzungu claimed, not all that credibly, that it had only been put up as a trial, to test the stability of the plinth.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Von Tunzelmann is surely correct when she argues that statuary is, in and of itself, a lousy way of commemorating or teaching history &amp;ndash; it is often, in her words, &amp;ldquo;didactic, haughty, and uninvolving&amp;rdquo;. But as this gently inquisitive and often very funny book amply demonstrates, the disputes over a given statue can teach us a great deal &amp;ndash; even if much of the culture war shrieking and quacking around statues, both for and against, does not usually indicate much willingness to learn.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5852/book-review-fallen-idols#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>US Politicians Want Less Regulations on Snake Oil “Medicine” During a Pandemic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/tLZbkZ_ahqs/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Look, I’m not one of those jerks who shames people because whatever cause they care about isn’t what I think is the absolute most important cause to care about right now. You can definitely care …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=tLZbkZ_ahqs:cN18F1DvJTs:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/tLZbkZ_ahqs" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131142</id>
    <published>2021-09-14T15:58:39Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-14T15:58:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>20 Years of 9/11 “Truther” Conspiracy Theories</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/l2OaVz1xYP0/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Well, it’s been 20 years since terrorists hijacked some commercial airliners and crashed them into things, and what a 20 years it’s been! I was 20 years old and living in Boston. I woke up …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=l2OaVz1xYP0:K6K2GzGz0VM:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/l2OaVz1xYP0" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131125</id>
    <published>2021-09-10T15:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-10T15:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rollercoaster of Faith that led to Atheism (twice)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/09/the-rollercoaster-of-faith-that-led-to-atheism-twice/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mine is not a terrible, bloodshed, or torturing example of the evil side of religion, but rather a story of how logic got me in and out of religious thinking. It is interesting, to say the least, so please stick to me until the end. I was born and raised a Roman Catholic, as most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Marc Kreidler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977256</id>
    <published>2021-09-07T13:47:24Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-07T13:47:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Converts Corner"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION SEPTEMBER 2021</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/09/open-discussion-september-2021/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for discussion on themes relevant to Reason and Science for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977239</id>
    <published>2021-09-01T10:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-01T10:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I was told that I was demon-possessed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/08/i-was-told-that-i-was-demon-possessed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since entering this world as a conscious autonomous human being I feel I have experienced a somewhat well-rounded experience of Christianity, suffering both at the hands of Christians as well as experiencing some kindness and love. I began my journey as a child under a thunderous pulpit preacher in Edinburgh where the women wore hats …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Marc Kreidler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977198</id>
    <published>2021-08-17T15:50:43Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-17T15:50:43Z</updated>
    <category term="Converts Corner"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Abracadabra!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/08/abracadabra/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! Words can have incredible power. If we didn’t think so, we wouldn’t produce magazines, podcasts, or this newsletter! But their power comes from how they transmit information, how they make us feel, and how they move us to act.  What words cannot do is cause things to …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977071</id>
    <published>2021-08-04T16:18:17Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-04T16:18:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Stuart Vyse on Superstitions: Good Luck with That</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/08/stuart-vyse-on-superstitions-good-luck-with-that/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Triskaidekaphobia, rabbits’ feet, horseshoes, throwing salt over your shoulder, and fear of black cats. Old and silly superstitions are remarkably common, with even some of the most skeptical among us feeling beholden to some ritual, trinket, or omen to determine our fortunes. On the latest Skeptical Inquirer Presents online event, psychologist Stuart Vyse explored the …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977095</id>
    <published>2021-08-04T16:05:45Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-04T16:05:45Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Magic Award</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our first award focused on performers who use magic tricks to improve the lives of others, including work with disadvantaged groups, hospital patients, and schools. The judges selected two great winners: Megan Swann (who presents a magic show that promotes environmental issues) and Breathe Magic (who support children with hemiplegia by helping them to learn tricks that improve physical and psychological wellbeing).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This year, the award will provide £2,000 to support a new and innovative project that promotes the art of magic. This might, for example, include developing a live or virtual performance, writing a magic-related book or essay, creating a podcast, devising a new form of illusion or presentation, or undertaking research into the history of magic. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Applicants need to be over 18 years old and currently residing in the UK, and nominations will close at 5pm (GMT) on 20th February 2021.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To enter, please head over to &lt;a href="https://goodthinkingsociety.org/projects/the-good-magic-awards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"&gt;The Good Thinking Society&lt;/a&gt; now! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards. Our first award focused… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Good Magic Award</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12851</id>
    <published>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/07/science-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>A few years ago I produced three videos containing ten magic-based science stunts. I thought that they might help educate and entertain children during lockdown, or indeed anyone with a curious disposition. Here they are…..</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yKxnnKLn9Hc?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rHoLqvzvDFc?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NkyEOrQiGMQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;start=1&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I produced three videos containing ten magic-based science stunts. I thought that they might help educate… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/07/science-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Science magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12825</id>
    <published>2021-01-07T14:20:22Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-07T14:20:22Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this episode of the podcast, Sam discusses the recent social protests and civil unrest, in light of what we know about racism and police violence in America.</p>
<p>This is a transcript of a <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/207-can-pull-back-brink/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">recorded podcast</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p>Welcome to the Making Sense podcast… This is Sam Harris.</p>
<p>OK…. Well, I’ve been trying to gather my thoughts for this podcast for more than a week—and have been unsure about whether to record it at all, frankly.</p>
<p>Conversation is the only tool we have for making progress, I firmly believe that. But many of the things we most need to talk about, seem impossible to talk about.</p>
<p>I think social media is a huge part of the problem. I’ve been saying for a few years now that, with social media, we’ve all been enrolled in a psychological experiment for which no one gave consent, and it’s not at all clear how it will turn out. And it’s still not clear how it will turn out, but it’s not looking good. It’s fairly disorienting out there. All information is becoming weaponized. All communication is becoming performative. And on the most important topics, it now seems to be fury and sanctimony and bad faith almost all the time.</p>
<p>We appear to be driving ourselves crazy. Actually, crazy. As in, incapable of coming into contact with reality, unable to distinguish fact from fiction—and then becoming totally destabilized by our own powers of imagination, and confirmation bias, and then lashing out at one other on that basis.</p>
<p>So I’d like to talk about the current moment and the current social unrest, and its possible political implications, and other cultural developments, and suggest what it might take to pull back from the brink here. I’m going to circle in on the topics of police violence and the problem of racism, because that really is at the center of this. There is so much to talk about here, and it’s so difficult to talk about. And there is so much we don’t know. And yet, most people are behaving as though every important question was answered a long time ago.</p>
<p>I’ve been watching our country seem to tear itself apart for weeks now, and perhaps lay the ground for much worse to come. And I’ve been resisting the temptation to say anything of substance—not because I don’t have anything to say, but because of my perception of the danger, frankly. And if that’s the way I feel, given the pains that I’ve taken to insulate myself from those concerns, I know that almost everyone with a public platform is terrified. Journalists, and editors, and executives, and celebrities are terrified that they might take one wrong step here, and never recover.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YdsmxzaHtSQ" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"/></p>
<p>And this is really unhealthy—not just for individuals, but for society. Because, again, all we have between us and the total breakdown of civilization is a series of successful conversations. If we can’t reason with one another, there is no path forward, other than violence. Conversation or violence.</p>
<p>So, I’d like to talk about some of the things that concern me about the current state of our communication. Unfortunately, many things are compounding our problems at the moment. We have a global pandemic which is still very much with us. And it remains to be seen how much our half-hearted lockdown, and our ineptitude in testing, and our uncoordinated reopening, and now our plunge into social protest and civil unrest will cause the Covid-19 caseload to spike. We will definitely see. As many have pointed out, the virus doesn’t care about economics or politics. It only cares that we keep breathing down each other’s necks. And we’ve certainly been doing enough of that.</p>
<p>Of course, almost no one can think about Covid-19 right now. But I’d just like to point out that many of the costs of this pandemic and the knock-on effects in the economy, and now this protest movement, many of these costs are hidden from us. In addition to killing more than 100,000 people in the US, the pandemic has been a massive opportunity cost. The ongoing implosion of the economy is imposing tangible costs, yes, but it is also a massive opportunity cost. And now this civil unrest is compounding those problems—whatever the merits of these protests may be or will be, the opportunity costs of this moment are staggering. In addition to all the tangible effects of what’s happening—the injury and death, the lost businesses, the burned buildings, the neighborhoods that won’t recover for years in many cities, the educations put on hold, and the breakdown in public trust of almost every institution—just think about all the good and important things we cannot do—cannot even <em>think</em> of doing now—and perhaps won’t contemplate doing for many years to come, because we’ll be struggling to get back to that distant paradise we once called “normal life.”</p>
<p>Of course, normal life for many millions of Americans was nothing like a paradise. The disparities in wealth and health and opportunity that we have gotten used to in this country, and that so much of our politics and ways of doing business seem to take for granted, are just unconscionable. There is no excuse for this kind of inequality in the richest country on earth. What we’re seeing now is a response to that. But it’s a confused and confusing response. Worse, it’s a response that is systematically silencing honest conversation. And this makes it dangerous.</p>
<p>This isn’t just politics and human suffering on display. It’s philosophy. It’s ideas about truth—about what it means to say that something is “true.” What we’re witnessing in our streets and online and in the impossible conversations we’re attempting to have in our private lives is a breakdown in epistemology. How does anyone figure out what’s going on in the world? What is real? If we can’t agree about what is real, or likely to be real, we will never agree about how we should live together. And the problem is, we’re stuck with one other.</p>
<p>So, what’s happening here?</p>
<p>Well, again, it’s hard to say. What is happening when <a href="https://youtu.be/viika57hTO4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a police officer or a mayor takes a knee</a> in front of a crowd of young people who have been berating him for being a cog in the machinery of systemic racism? Is this a profound moment of human bonding that transcends politics, or is it the precursor to the breakdown of society? Or is it both? It’s not entirely clear.</p>
<p>In the most concrete terms, we are experiencing widespread social unrest in response to what is widely believed to be an epidemic of lethal police violence directed at the black community by racist cops and racist policies. And this unrest has drawn a counter-response from law enforcement—much of which, ironically, is guaranteed to exacerbate the problem of police violence, both real and perceived. And many of the videos we’ve seen of the police cracking down on peaceful protesters are hideous. Some of this footage has been unbelievable. And this is one of many vicious circles that we must find some way to interrupt.</p>
<p>Again, there is so much to be confused about here. We’ve now seen endless video of police inflicting senseless violence on truly peaceful protesters, and yet we have also seen video of the police <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xrVp8vlQyU">standing idly by</a> while looters completely destroy businesses. What explains this? Is there a policy that led to this bizarre inversion of priorities? Are the police angry at the protesters for vilifying them, and simultaneously trying to teach society a lesson by letting crime and mayhem spread elsewhere in the city? Or is it just less risky to collide with peaceful protesters? Or is the whole spectacle itself a lie? How representative are these videos of what’s actually going on? Is there much less chaos actually occurring than is being advertised to us?</p>
<p>Again, it’s very hard to know.</p>
<p>What’s easy to know is that civil discourse has broken down. It seems to me that we’ve long been in a situation where the craziest voices on both ends of the political spectrum have been amplifying one another and threatening to produce something truly dangerous. And now I think they have. The amount of misinformation in the air—the degree to which even serious people seem to be ruled by false assumptions and non sequiturs—is just astonishing.</p>
<p>And it’s important to keep in mind that, with the presidential election coming in November, the stakes are really high. As most of you know, I consider four more years of Trump to be an existential threat to our democracy. And I believe that the last two weeks have been very good for him, politically, even when everything else seemed to go very badly for him. I know the polls don’t say this. A large majority of people disapprove of his handling this crisis so far. But I think we all know now to take polls with a grain of salt. There is the very real problem of preference falsification—especially in an environment of intense social pressure. People will often say what they think is socially acceptable, and then think, or say, or do something very different in private—like when they’re alone in a voting booth.</p>
<p>Trump has presided over the complete dismantling of American influence in the world and the destruction of our economy. I know the stock market has looked good, but the stock market has become totally uncoupled from the economy. According to the stock market, the future is just as bright now as it was in January of this year, before most of us had even heard of a novel coronavirus. That doesn’t make a lot of sense. And a lot can happen in the next few months. The last two weeks feel like a decade. And my concern is that if Trump now gets to be the law-and-order President, that may be his path to re-election, if such a path exists. Of course, this crisis has revealed, yet again, how unfit he is to be President. The man couldn’t strike a credible note of reconciliation if the fate of the country depended on it—and the fate of the country has depended on it. I also think it’s possible that these protests wouldn’t be happening, but for the fact that Trump is President. Whether or not the problem of racism has gotten worse in our society, having Trump as President surely makes it seem like it has. It has been such a repudiation of the Obama presidency that, for many people, it has made it seem that white supremacy is now ascendant. So, all the more reason to get rid of Trump in November.</p>
<p>But before this social unrest, our focus was on how incompetent Trump was in the face of the Covid-19 pandemic. And now he has been given a very different battle to fight. A battle against leftwing orthodoxy, which is growing more stifling by the minute, and civil unrest. If our social order frays sufficiently, restoring it will be the only thing that most people care about in November. Just think of what an act of domestic terrorism would do politically now. Things can change very, very quickly. And to all a concern for basic law and order “racist”, isn’t going to wash.</p>
<p>Trust in institutions has totally broken down. We’ve been under a very precarious quarantine for more than 3 months, which almost the entire medical profession has insisted is necessary. Doctors and public health officials have castigated people on the political Right for protesting this lockdown. People have been unable to be with their loved ones in their last hours of life. They’ve been unable to hold funerals for them. But now we have doctors and public officials by the thousands, signing <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/05/health/health-care-open-letter-protests-coronavirus-trnd/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open letters</a>, making public statements, saying it’s fine to stand shoulder to shoulder with others in the largest protests our nation has ever seen. The degree to which this has undermined confidence in public health messaging is hard to exaggerate. Whatever your politics, this has been just a mortifying piece of hypocrisy. Especially so, because the pandemic has been hitting the African American community hardest of all. How many people will die because of these protests? It’s a totally rational question to ask, but the question itself is taboo now.</p>
<p>So, it seems to me that almost everything appears upside down at the moment.</p>
<p>Before I get into details on police violence, first let me try to close the door to a few misunderstandings.</p>
<p>Let’s start with the proximate cause of all this: The killing of George Floyd by the Minneapolis police. I’ll have more to say about this in a minute, but nothing I say should detract from the following observation: That <a href="https://youtu.be/vksEJR9EPQ8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a> was absolutely sickening, and it revealed a degree of police negligence and incompetence and callousness that everyone was right to be horrified by. In particular, the actions of Derek Chauvin, the cop who kept his knee on Floyd’s neck for nearly 9 minutes, his actions were so reckless and so likely to cause harm that there’s no question he should be prosecuted. And he is being prosecuted. He’s been indicted for 2nd degree murder and manslaughter, and I suspect he will spend many, many years in prison. And, this is not to say “the system is working.” It certainly seems likely that without the cell phone video, and the public outrage, Chauvin might have gotten away with it—to say nothing of the other cops with him, who are also now being prosecuted. If this is true, we clearly need a better mechanism with which to police the police.</p>
<p>So, as I said, I’ll return to this topic, because I think most people are drawing the wrong conclusions from this video, and from videos like it, but let me just echo everyone’s outrage over what happened. This is precisely the kind of police behavior that everyone should find abhorrent.</p>
<p>On the general topic of racism in America, I want to make a few similarly clear, preemptive statements:</p>
<p>Racism is still a problem in American society. No question. And slavery—which was racism’s most evil expression—was this country’s founding sin. We should also add the near-total eradication of the Native Americans to that ledger of evil. Any morally sane person who learns the details of these historical injustices finds them shocking, whatever their race. And the legacy of these crimes—crimes that were perpetrated for centuries—remains a cause for serious moral concern today. I have no doubt about this. And nothing I’m about to say, should suggest otherwise.</p>
<p>And I don’t think it’s an accident that the two groups I just mentioned, African Americans and Native Americans, suffer the worst from inequality in America today. How could the history of racial discrimination in this country not have had lasting effects, given the nature of that history? And if anything good comes out of the current crisis, it will be that we manage to find a new commitment to reducing inequality in all its dimensions. The real debate to have is about how to do this, economically and politically. But the status quo that many of us take for granted to is a betrayal of our values, whether we realize it or not. If it’s not a betrayal or your values now, it will be a betrayal of your values when you become a better person. And if you don’t manage that, it will be a betrayal of your kid’s values when they’re old enough to understand the world they are living in. The difference between being very lucky in our society, and very unlucky, should not be as enormous as it is.</p>
<p>However, the question that interests me, given what has been true of the past and is now true of the present, is what should we do next? What should we do to build a healthier society?</p>
<p>What should we do next?  Tomorrow… next week…. Obviously, I don’t have the answers. But I am very worried that many of the things we’re doing now, and seem poised to do, will only make our problems worse. And I’m especially worried that it has become so difficult to talk about this. I’m just trying to have conversations. I’m just trying to figure these things out in real time, with other people. And there is no question that conversation itself has become dangerous.</p>
<p>Think about the politics of this. Endless imagery of people burning and looting independent businesses that were struggling to survive, and seeing the owners of these businesses beaten by mobs, cannot be good for the cause of social justice. Looting and burning businesses, and assaulting their owners, isn’t social justice, or even social protest. It’s crime. And having imagery of these crimes that highlight black involvement circulate endlessly on Fox News and on social media cannot be good for the black community. But it might yet be good for Trump.</p>
<p>And it could well kick open the door to a level of authoritarianism that many of us who have been very worried about Trump barely considered possible. It’s always seemed somewhat paranoid to me to wonder whether we’re living in Weimar Germany. I’ve had many conversations about this. I had <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/the-road-to-tyranny/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Timothy Snyder on the podcast</a>, who’s been worrying about the prospect of tyranny in the US for several years now. I’ve known, in the abstract, that democracies can destroy themselves. But the idea that it could happen here still seemed totally outlandish to me. It doesn’t anymore.</p>
<p>Of course, what we’ve been seeing in the streets isn’t just one thing. Some people are protesting for reasons that I fully defend. They’re outraged by specific instances of police violence, like the killing of George Floyd, and they’re worried about creeping authoritarianism—which we really should be worried about now. And they’re convinced that our politics is broken, because it is broken, and they are deeply concerned that our response to the pandemic and the implosion of our economy will do nothing to address the widening inequality in our society. And they recognize that we have a President who is an incompetent, divisive, conman and a crackpot at a time when we actually need wise leadership.</p>
<p>All of that is hard to put on a sign, but it’s all worth protesting.</p>
<p>However, it seems to me that most protesters are seeing this moment exclusively through the lens of identity politics—and racial politics in particular. And some of them are even celebrating the breakdown of law and order, or at least remaining nonjudgmental about it. And you could see, in the early days of this protest, news anchors take that line, on CNN, for instance. Talking about the history of social protest, “Sometimes it has to be violent, right? What, do you think all of these protests need to be nonviolent?” Those words came out of Chris Cuomo’s mouth, and Don Lemon’s mouth. Many people have been circulating a half quote from Martin Luther King Jr. about riots being “the language of the unheard.” They’re <a href="https://youtu.be/pjYZZC5i_AU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">leaving out the part</a> where he made it clear that he believed riots harmed the cause of the black community and helped the cause of racists.</p>
<p>There are now calls to defund and even to abolish the police. This may be psychologically understandable when you’ve spent half your day on Twitter watching videos of cops beating peaceful protesters. Those videos are infuriating. And I’ll have a lot more to say about police violence in a minute. But if you think a society without cops is a society you would want to live in, you have lost your mind. Giving a monopoly on violence to the state is just about the best thing we have ever done as a species. It ranks right up there with keeping our shit out of our food. Having a police force that can deter crime, and solve crimes when they occur, and deliver violent criminals to a functioning justice system, is the necessary precondition for almost anything else of value in society.</p>
<p>We need police reform, of course. There are serious questions to ask about the culture of policing—its hiring practices, training, the militarization of so many police forces, outside oversight, how police departments deal with corruption, the way the police unions keep bad cops on the job, and yes, the problem of racist cops. But the idea that any serious person thinks we can do without the police—or that less trained and less vetted cops will magically be better than more trained and more vetted ones—this just reveals that our conversation on these topics has run completely off the rails. Yes, we should give more resources to community services. We should have psychologists or social workers make first contact with the homeless or the mentally ill. Perhaps we’re giving cops jobs they shouldn’t be doing. All of that makes sense to rethink. But the idea that what we’re witnessing now is a matter of the cops being over-resourced—that we’ve given them too much training, that we’ve made the job too attractive—so that the people we’re recruiting are of too high a quality. That doesn’t make any sense.</p>
<p>What’s been alarming here is that we’re seeing prominent people—in government, in media, in Hollywood, in sports—speak and act as though the breakdown of civil society, and of society itself, is a form of progress and any desire for law enforcement is itself a form of racist oppression. At one point the woman who’s running the City Council in Minneapolis, which just decided to abolish the police force, was asked by a journalist, I believe on CNN, “What do I do if someone’s breaking into my house in the middle of the night? Who do I call?” And her first response to that question was, “You need to recognize what a statement of privilege that question is.” She’s since had to walk that back, because it’s one of the most galling and embarrassing things a public official has ever said, but this is how close the Democratic Party is to sounding completely insane. You cannot say that if someone is breaking into your house, and you’re terrified, and you want a police force that can respond, that fear is a symptom of “white privilege.” This is where Democratic politics goes to die.</p>
<p>Again, what is alarming about this is that this woke analysis of the breakdown of law and order will only encourage an increasingly authoritarian response, as well as the acceptance of that response by many millions of Americans.</p>
<p>If you step back, you will notice that there is a kind of ecstasy of ideological conformity in the air. And it’s destroying institutions. It’s destroying the very institutions we rely on to get our information—universities, the press. The New York Times in recent days, seems to be preparing for a self-immolation in recent days. No one wants to say or even think anything that makes anyone uncomfortable—certainly not anyone who has more wokeness points than they do. It’s just become too dangerous. There are people <a href="https://wwos.nine.com.au/news/nba-announcer-fired-over-controversial-all-lives-matter-tweet/a9a50198-4b52-4cb7-a800-e0ffacb3302d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">being fired</a> for tweeting “All Lives Matter.” #AllLivesMatter, in the current environment, is being read as a naked declaration of white supremacy. That is how weird this moment is. A soccer player on the LA Galaxy <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/sports/rowdies/2020/06/05/la-galaxy-releases-player-after-wifes-racist-and-violent-social-media-posts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">was fired</a> for something his wife tweeted…</p>
<p>Of course, there are real problems of inequality and despair at the bottom of these protests. People who have never found a secure or satisfying place in the world—or young people who fear they never will—people who have seen their economic prospects simply vanish, and people who have had painful encounters with racism and racist cops—people by the millions are now surrendering themselves to a kind of religious awakening. But like most religious awakenings, this movement is not showing itself eager to make honest contact with reality.</p>
<p>On top of that, we find extraordinarily privileged people, whatever the color of their skin—people who have been living wonderful lives in their gated communities or 5<sup>th</sup> avenue apartments—and who feel damn guilty about it—they are supporting this movement uncritically, for many reasons. Of course, they care about other people—I’m sure most of them have the same concerns about inequality that I do—but they are also supporting this movement because it promises a perfect expiation of their sins. If you have millions of dollars, and shoot botox into your face, and vacation on St. Bart’s, and you’re liberal—the easiest way to sleep at night is to be as woke as AOC and like every one of her tweets.</p>
<p>The problem isn’t just with the looting, and the arson, and the violence. There are problems with these peaceful protests themselves.</p>
<p>Of course, I’m not questioning anyone’s right to protest. Even our deranged president can pay lip service to that right—which he did as the DC police were violently dispersing a peaceful protest so that he could get his picture taken in front of that church, awkwardly holding a bible, as though he had never held a book in life.</p>
<p>The problem with the protests is that they are animated, to a remarkable degree, by confusion and misinformation. And I’ll explain why I think that’s the case. And, of course, this will be controversial. Needless to say, many people will consider the color of my skin to be disqualifying here. I could have invited any number of great, black intellectuals onto the podcast to make these points for me. But that struck me as a form of cowardice. Glenn Loury, John McWhorter, Thomas Chatterton Williams, Coleman Hughes, Kmele Foster, these guys might not agree with everything I’m about to say, but any one of them could walk the tightrope I’m now stepping out on far more credibly than I can.</p>
<p>But, you see, that’s part of the problem. The perception that the color of a person’s skin, or even his life experience, matters for this discussion is a pernicious illusion. For the discussion we really need to have, the color of a person’s skin, and even his life experience, simply does not matter. It cannot matter. We have to break this spell that the politics of identity has cast over everything.</p>
<p>Ok…</p>
<p>As I’ve already acknowledged, there is a legacy of racism in the United States that we’re still struggling to outgrow. That is obvious. There are real racists out there. And there are ways in which racism became institutionalized long ago. Many of you will remember that during the crack epidemic the penalties for crack and powder cocaine were quite different. And this led black drug offenders to be locked up for much longer than white ones. Now, whether the motivation for that policy was consciously racist or not, I don’t know, but it was effectively racist. Nothing I’m about to say entails a denial of these sorts of facts. There just seems to be no question that boys who grow up with their fathers in prison start life with a significant strike against them. So criminal justice reform is absolutely essential.</p>
<p>And I’m not denying that many black people, perhaps most, have interactions with cops, and others in positions of power, or even random strangers, that seem unambiguously racist. Sometimes this is because they are actually in the presence of racism, and perhaps sometimes it only seems that way. I’ve had unpleasant encounters with cops, and customs officers, and TSA screeners, and bureaucrats of every kind, and even with people working in stores or restaurants. People aren’t always nice or ethical. But being white, and living in a majority white society, I’ve never had to worry about whether any of these collisions were the result of racism. And I can well imagine that in some of these situations, had I been black, I would have come away feeling that I had encountered yet another racist in the wild. So I consider myself very lucky to have gone through life not having to think about any of that. Surely that’s one form of white privilege.</p>
<p>So, nothing I’m going to say denies that we should condemn racism—whether interpersonal or institutional—and we should condemn it wherever we find it. But as a society, we simply can’t afford to find and condemn racism where it doesn’t exist. And we should be increasingly aware of the costs of doing that. The more progress we make on issues of race, the less racism there will be to find, and the more likely we’ll find ourselves chasing after its ghost.</p>
<p>The truth is, we have made considerable progress on the problem of racism in America. This isn’t 1920, and it isn’t 1960. We had a two-term black president. We have black congressmen and women. We have black mayors and black chiefs of police. There are major cities, like Detroit and Atlanta, going on their fifth or sixth consecutive black mayor. Having more and more black people in positions of real power, in what is still a majority white society, is progress on the problem of racism. And the truth is, it might not even solve the problem we’re talking about. When Freddy Gray was killed in Baltimore, virtually everyone who could have been held accountable for his death was black. The problem of police misconduct and reform is complicated, as we’re about to see. But obviously, there is more work to do on the problem of racism. And, more important, there is much more work to do to remedy the inequalities in our society that are so correlated with race, and will still be correlated with race, even after the last racist has been driven from our shores.</p>
<p>The question of how much of today’s inequality is due to existing racism—whether racist people or racist policies—is a genuinely difficult question to answer. And to answer it, we need to distinguish the past from the present.</p>
<p>Take wealth inequality, for example: The median white family has a net worth of around $170,000—these data are a couple of years old, but they’re probably pretty close to what’s true now. The median black family has a net worth of around $17,000. So we have a <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/brookings-now/2019/06/18/a-conversation-about-the-racial-wealth-gap-and-how-to-address-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tenfold difference in median wealth</a>. (That’s the median, not the mean: Half of white families are below 170,000 and half above; half of black families are below 17,000 and half above. And we’re talking about wealth here, not income.)</p>
<p>This disparity in wealth persists even for people whose incomes are in the top 10 percent of the income distribution. For whites in the top 10 percent for income, the median net worth is $1.8 million; for blacks it’s around $350,000. There are probably many things that account for this disparity in wealth. It seems that black families that make it to the top of the income distribution fall out of it more easily than white families do. But it’s also undeniable that black families have less intergenerational wealth accumulated through inheritance.</p>
<p>How much of this is inequality due to the legacy of slavery? And how much of it is due to an ensuing century of racist policies? I’m prepared to believe quite a lot. And it strikes me as totally legitimate to think about paying reparations as a possible remedy here. Of course, one will then need to talk about reparations for the Native Americans. And then one wonders where this all ends. And what about blacks who aren’t descended from slaves, but who still suffered the consequences of racism in the US? In listening to people like <a href="https://youtu.be/FXt9Q5h1sCY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">John McWhorter</a> and Coleman Hughes discuss this topic, I’m inclined to think that reparations is probably unworkable as a policy. But the truth is that I’m genuinely unsure about this.</p>
<p>Whatever we decide about the specific burdens of the past, we have to ask, how much of current wealth inequality is due to existing racism and to existing policies that make it harder for black families to build wealth? And the only way to get answers to those questions is to have a dispassionate discussion about facts.</p>
<p>The problem with the social activism we are now seeing—what John McWhorter has called “the new religion of anti-Racism”—is that it finds racism nearly everywhere, even where it manifestly does not exist. And this is incredibly damaging to the cause of achieving real equality in our society. It’s almost impossible to exaggerate the evil and injustice of slavery and its aftermath. But it is possible to exaggerate how much racism currently exists at an Ivy League university, or in Silicon Valley, or at the Oscars. And those exaggerations are toxic—and, perversely, they may produce more real racism. It seems to me that false claims of victimhood can diminish the social stature of any group, even a group that has a long history of real victimization.</p>
<p>The imprecision here—the bad-faith arguments, the double standards, the goal-post shifting, the <a href="https://nyti.ms/2hrFzz1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">idiotic opinion pieces</a> in the New York Times, the defenestrations on social media, the general hysteria that the cult of wokeness has produced—I think this is all extremely harmful to civil society, and to effective liberal politics, and to the welfare of African Americans.</p>
<p>So, with that as preamble, let’s return to the tragic death of George Floyd.</p>
<p>As I said, I believe that any sane person who watches that video will feel that they have witnessed a totally unjustified killing. So, people of any race, are right to be horrified by what happened there. But now I want to ask a few questions, and I want us to try to consider them dispassionately. And I really want you to watch your mind while you do this. There are very likely to be few tripwires installed there, and I’m about to hit them. So just do your best to remain calm.</p>
<p>Does the killing of George Floyd prove that we have a problem of racism in the United States?</p>
<p>Does it even suggest that we have a problem of racism in the United States?</p>
<p>In other words, do we have reason to believe that, had Floyd been white, he wouldn’t have died in a similar way?</p>
<p>Do the dozen or so other videos that have emerged in recent years, of black men being killed by cops, do they prove, or even suggest, that there is an epidemic of lethal police violence directed especially at black men and that this violence is motivated by racism?</p>
<p>Most people seem to think that the answers to these questions are so obvious that to even pose them as I just did is obscene. The answer is YES, and it’s a yes that now needs to be shouted in the streets.</p>
<p>The problem, however, is that if you take even 5 minutes to look at the data on crime and police violence, the answer appears to be “no,” in every case, albeit with one important caveat. I’m not talking about how the police behaved in 1970 or even 1990. But in the last 25 years, violent crime has come down significantly in the US, and so has the police use of deadly force. And as you’re about to see, the police used more deadly force against white people—both in absolute numbers, and in terms of their contribution to crime and violence in our society. But the public perception is, of course, completely different.</p>
<p>In a city like Los Angeles, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2020-05-12/lapd-use-of-force-report" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2019 was a 30-year low</a> for police shootings. Think about that…. Do the people who were protesting in Los Angeles, peacefully and violently, do the people who were ransacking and burning businesses by the hundreds—in many cases, businesses that will not return to their neighborhoods—do the people who caused so much damage to the city, that certain neighborhoods, ironically the neighborhoods that are disproportionately black, will take years, probably decades to recover, do the celebrities who supported them, and even bailed them out of jail—do any of these people know that 2019 was the 30-year low for police shootings in Los Angeles?</p>
<p>Before I step out further over the abyss here, let me reiterate: Many of you are going to feel a visceral negative reaction to what I’m about to say. You’re not going to like the way it sounds. You’re especially not going to like the way it sounds coming from a white guy. This feeling of not liking, this feeling of outrage, this feeling of disgust—this feeling of “Sam, what the fuck is wrong with you, why are you even touching this topic?”—this feeling isn’t an argument. It isn’t, or shouldn’t be, the basis for your believing anything to be true or false about the world.</p>
<p>Your capacity to be offended isn’t something that I or anyone else needs to respect. Your capacity to be offended isn’t something that you should respect. In fact, it is something that you should be on your guard for. Perhaps more than any other property of your mind, this feeling can mislead you.</p>
<p>If you care about justice—and you absolutely should—you should care about facts and the ability to discuss them openly. Justice requires contact with reality. It simply isn’t the case—it cannot be the case—that the most pressing claims on our sense of justice need come from those who claim to be the most offended by conversation itself.</p>
<p>So, I’m going to speak the language of facts right now, in so far as we know them, all the while knowing that these facts run very much counter to most people’s assumptions. Many of the things you think you know about crime and violence in our society are almost certainly wrong. And that should matter to you.</p>
<p>So just take a moment and think this through with me.</p>
<p>How many people are killed each year in America by cops? If you don’t know, guess. See if you have any intuitions for these numbers. Because your intuitions are determining how you interpret horrific videos of the sort we saw coming out of Minneapolis.</p>
<p>The answer for many years running is <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/investigations/police-shootings-database/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">about 1000</a>. One thousand people are killed by cops in America each year. There are about 50 to 60 million encounters between civilians and cops each year, and <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2017/crime-in-the-u.s.-2017/tables/table-29" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">about 10 million arrests</a>. That’s down from a high of over 14 million arrests annually throughout the 1990’s. So, of the 10 million occasions where a person attracts the attention of the police, and the police decide to make an arrest, about 1000 of those people die as a result. (I’m sure a few people get killed even when no arrest was attempted, but that has to be a truly tiny number.) So, without knowing anything else about the situation, if the cops decide to arrest you, it would be reasonable to think that your chance of dying is around 1/10,000. Of course, in the United States, it’s higher than it is in other countries. So I’m not saying that this number is acceptable. But it is what it is for a reason, as we’re about to see.</p>
<p>Now, there are a few generic things I’d like to point here before we get further into the data. They should be uncontroversial.</p>
<p>First, it’s almost certainly the case that of these 1000 officer-caused deaths each year, some are entirely justified—it may even be true that most are entirely justified—and some are entirely unjustified, and some are much harder to judge. And that will be true next year. And the year after that.</p>
<p>Of the unjustified killings, there are vast differences between them. Many have nothing in common but for the fact that a cop killed someone unnecessarily. It might have been a terrible misunderstanding, or incompetence, or just bad luck, and in certain cases it could be a cop who decides to murder someone because he’s become enraged, or he’s just a psychopath. And it is certainly possible that racial bias accounts for some number of these unjustified killings.</p>
<p>Another point that should be uncontroversial—but may sound a little tone-deaf in the current environment, where we’ve inundated with videos of police violence in response to these protests. But this has to be acknowledged whenever we’re discussing this topic: Cops have a very hard job. In fact, in the current environment, they have an almost impossible job.</p>
<p>If you’re making 10 million arrests every year, some number of people will decide not to cooperate. There can be many reasons for this. A person could be mentally ill, or drunk, or on drugs. Of course, rather often the person is an actual criminal who doesn’t want to be arrested.</p>
<p>Among innocent people, and perhaps this getting more common these days, a person might feel that resisting arrest is the right thing to do, ethically or politically or as a matter of affirming his identity. After all, put yourself in his shoes, he did nothing wrong. Why are the cops arresting him? I don’t know if we have data on the numbers of people who resist arrest by race. But I can well imagine that if it’s common for African Americans to believe that the only reason they have been singled out for arrest is due to racism on the part of the police, that could lead to greater levels of non-compliance. Which seems very likely to lead to more unnecessary injury and death. This is certainly one reason why it is wise to have the racial composition of a police force mirror that of the community it’s policing. Unfortunately, there’s no evidence that this will reduce lethal violence from the side of the police. In fact, the evidence we have suggests that black and Hispanic cops are <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/116/32/15877.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">more likely</a> to shoot black and Hispanic suspects than white cops are. But it would surely change the perception of the community that racism is a likely explanation for police behavior, which itself might reduce conflict.</p>
<p>When a cop goes hands on a person in an attempt to control his movements or make an arrest, that person’s resistance poses a problem that most people don’t understand. If you haven’t studied this topic. If you don’t know what it physically takes to restrain and immobilize a non-compliant person who may be bigger and stronger than you are, and if you haven’t thought through the implications of having a gun on your belt while attempting to do that—a gun that can be grabbed and used against you, or against a member of the public—then your intuitions about what makes sense here, tactically and ethically, are very likely to be bad.</p>
<p>If you haven’t trained with firearms under stress. If you don’t know how suddenly situations can change. If you haven’t experienced how quickly another person can close the distance on you, and how little time you have to decide to draw your weapon. If you don’t know how hard it is to shoot a moving target, or even a stationary one, when your heart is beating out of your chest. You very likely have totally unreasonable ideas about what we can expect from cops in situations like these. [<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9NwWado4SVY&amp;bpctr=1592453276" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ygbOLb0O7Pw&amp;bpctr=1592455027" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_87GBOCVYTM" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>]</p>
<p>And there is another fact that looms over all this like the angel of Death, literally: Most cops do not get the training they need. They don’t get the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YQLOmfx8X_E&amp;feature=emb_title">hand-to-hand training</a> they need—they don’t have good skills to subdue people without harming them. All you need to do is watch YouTube videos of botched arrests to see this. The martial arts community stands in perpetual astonishment at <a href="https://youtu.be/F4VeHOkt_o8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the kinds of things cops do and fail to do</a> once they start fighting with suspects. Cops also don’t get the firearms training they need. Of course, there are elite units in many police departments, but most cops do not have the training they need to do the job they’re being asked to do.</p>
<p>It is also true, no doubt, that some cops are racist bullies. And there are corrupt police departments that cover for these guys, and cover up police misconduct generally, whether it was borne of racism or not.</p>
<p>But the truth is that even if we got rid of all bad cops, which we absolutely should do, and there were only good people left, and we got all these good people the best possible training, and we gave them the best culture in which to think about their role in society, and we gave them the best methods for de-escalating potentially violent situations—which we absolutely must do—and we scrubbed all the dumb laws from our books, so that when cops were required to enforce the law, they were only risking their lives and the lives of civilians for reasons that we deem necessary and just—so the war on drugs is obviously over—even under these conditions of perfect progress, we are still guaranteed to have some number of cases each year where a cop kills a civilian in a way that is totally unjustified, and therefore tragic. Every year, there will be some number of families who will be able to say that the cops killed their son or daughter, or father or mother, or brother or sister. And videos of these killings will occasionally surface, and they will be horrific. This seems guaranteed to happen.</p>
<p>So, while we need to make all these improvements, we still need to understand that there are very likely always to going to be videos of cops doing something inexplicable, or inexplicably stupid, that results in an innocent person’s death, or a not-so-innocent person’s death. And sometimes the cop will be white and the victim will be black. We have 10 million arrests each year. And we now live in a panopticon where practically everything is videotaped.</p>
<p>I’m about to get further into the details of what we know about police violence, but I want to just put it to you now: If we’re going to let the health of race relations in this country, or the relationship between the community and the police, depend on whether we ever see a terrible video of police misconduct again, the project of healing these wounds in our society is doomed.</p>
<p>About a week into these protests I heard Van Jones on CNN say, “If we see one more video of a cop brutalizing a black man, this country could go over the edge.” He said this, not as indication of how dangerously inflamed people have become. He seemed to be saying it as an ultimatum to the police. With 10 million arrests a year, arrests that have to take place in the most highly armed society in the developed world, I hope you understand how unreasonable that ultimatum is.</p>
<p>We have to put these videos into context. And we have to acknowledge how different they are from one another. Some of them are easy to interpret. But some are quite obviously being interpreted incorrectly by most people—especially by activists. And there are a range of cases—some have video associated with them and some don’t—that are now part of a litany of anti-racist outrage, and the names of the dead are intoned as though they were all evidence of the same injustice. And yet, they are not.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/XKQqgVlk0NQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Walter Scott</a> was stopped for a broken taillight and got out of his car and tried to flee. There might have been a brief struggle over the officer’s taser, that part of the video isn’t clear. But what is clear is that he was shot in the back multiple times as he was running away. That was insane. There was zero reason for the officer to feel that his life was under threat at the point he opened fire. And for that unjustified shooting, he was sentenced to 20 years in prison. I’m not sure that’s long enough. That seemed like straight-up murder.</p>
<p>The George Floyd video, while even more disturbing to watch, is harder to interpret. I don’t know anything about Derek Chauvin, the cop who knelt on his neck. It’s quite possible that he’s a terrible person who should have never been a cop. He seems to have a significant number of complaints against him—though, as far as I know, the details of those complaints haven’t been released. And he might be a racist on top of being a bad cop. Or he might be a guy who was totally in over his head and thought you could restrain someone indefinitely by keeping a knee on their neck indefinitely. I don’t know. I’m sure more facts will come out. But whoever he is, I find it very unlikely that he was intending to kill George Floyd. Think about it. He was surrounded by irate witnesses and being filmed. Unless he was aspiring to become the most notorious murderer in human history, it seems very unlikely that he was intending to commit murder in that moment. It’s possible, of course. But it doesn’t seem the likeliest explanation for his behavior.</p>
<p>What I believe we saw on that video was the result of a tragic level of negligence and poor training on the part of those cops. Or terrible recruitment—it’s possible that none of these guys should have ever been cops. I think for one of them, it was only his fourth day on the job. Just imagine that. Just imagine all things you don’t know as a new cop.  It could also be a function of bad luck in terms of Floyd’s underlying health. It’s been reported that he was complaining of being unable to breath before Chauvin pinned him with his knee. The knee on his neck might not have been the only thing that caused his death. It could have also been the weight of the other officer pinning him down.</p>
<p>This is almost certainly what happened in the cast of Eric Garner. Half the people on earth believe they witnessed a cop choke Eric Garner to death in that video. That does not appear to be what happened. When Eric Garner is saying “I can’t breathe” he’s not being choked. He’s being held down on the pavement by several officers. Being forced down on your stomach under the weight of several people can kill a person, especially someone with lung or heart disease. In the case of Eric Garner, it is absolutely clear that the cop who briefly attempted to choke him was no longer choking him. If you doubt that, watch the <a href="https://youtu.be/Nql1xRtWKOU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a> again.</p>
<p>And if you are recoiling now from my interpretation of these videos, you really should watch <a href="https://youtu.be/_c-E_i8Q5G0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the killing of Tony Timpa</a>. It’s also terribly disturbing, but it removes the variable of race and it removes any implication of intent to harm on the part of the cops about as clearly as you could ask. It really is worth watching as a corrective to our natural interpretation of these other videos.</p>
<p>Tony Timpa was a white man in Dallas, who was suffering some mental health emergency and cocaine intoxication. And he actually called 911 himself. What we see is the bodycam footage from the police, which shows that he was already in handcuffs when they arrived—a security guard had cuffed him. And then the cops take over, and they restrain Timpa on the ground, by rolling him onto a stomach and putting their weight on him, very much like in the case of Eric Garner. And they keep their weight on him—one cop has a knee on his upper back, which is definitely much less aggressive than a knee on the neck—but they crush the life out of him all the same, over the course of 13 minutes. He’s not being choked. The cops are not being rough. There’s no animus between them and Timpa. It was not a hostile arrest. They clearly believe that they’re responding to a mental health emergency. But they keep him down on his belly, under their weight, and they’re cracking jokes as he loses consciousness. Now, your knowledge that he’s going to be dead by the end of this video, make their jokes seem pretty callous. But this was about as benign an imposition of force by cops as you’re going to see. The crucial insight you will have watching this video, is that the officers not only had no intent to kill Tony Timpa, they don’t take his pleading seriously because they have no doubt that what they’re doing is perfectly safe—perfectly within protocol. They’ve probably done this hundreds of times before.</p>
<p>If you watch that video—and, again, fair warning, it is disturbing—but imagine how disturbing it would have been to our society if Tony Timpa had been black. If the only thing you changed about the video was the color of Timpa’s skin, then that video would have detonated like a nuclear bomb in our society, exactly as the George Floyd video did. In fact, in one way it is worse, or would have been perceived to be worse. I mean, just imagine white cops telling jokes as they crushed the life out of a black Tony Timpa… Given the nature of our conversation about violence, given the way we perceive videos of this kind, there is no way that people would have seen that as anything other than a lynching. And yet, it would not have been a lynching.</p>
<p>Now, I obviously have no idea what was in the minds of cops in Minneapolis. And perhaps we’ll learn at trial. Perhaps a tape of Chauvin using the N-word in another context will surface, bringing in a credible allegation of racism. It seems to me that Chauvin is going to have a very hard time making sense of his actions. But most people who saw that video believe they have seen, with their own eyes, beyond any possibility of doubt, a racist cop intentionally murder an innocent man. That’s not what the video necessarily shows.</p>
<p>As I said, these videos can be hard to interpret, even while seeming very easy to interpret. And these cases, whether we have associated video or not, are very different. Michael Brown is reported to have punched a cop in the face and attempted to get his gun. As far as I know, there’s no video of that encounter. But, if true, that is an entirely different situation. If you’re attacking a cop, trying to get his gun, that is a life and death struggle that almost by definition for the cop, and it most cases justifies the use of lethal force. And honestly, it seems that no one within a thousand miles of Black Lives Matter is willing to make these distinctions. An attitude of anti-racist moral outrage is not the best lens through which to interpret evidence of police misconduct.</p>
<p>I’ve seen many videos of people getting arrested. And I’ve seen the outraged public reaction to what appears to be inappropriate use of force by the cops. One overwhelming fact that comes through is that people, whatever the color of their skin, don’t understand how to behave around cops so as to keep themselves safe. People have to stop resisting arrest. This may seem obvious, but judging from most of these videos, and from the public reaction to them, this must be a totally arcane piece of information. When a cop wants to take you into custody, you don’t get to decide whether or not you should be arrested. When a cop wants to take you into custody, for whatever reason, it’s not a negotiation. And if you turn it into a wrestling match, you’re very likely to get injured or killed.</p>
<p>This is a point I once belabored in a <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/racism-and-violence-in-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast with Glenn Loury</a>, and it became essentially a public service announcement. And I’ve gone back and listened to those comments, and I want to repeat them here. This is something that everyone really needs to understand. And it’s something that Black Lives Matter should be teaching explicitly: If you put your hands on a cop—if you start wrestling with a cop, or grabbing him because he’s arresting your friend, or pushing him, or striking him, or using your hands in way that can possibly be interpreted as your reaching for a gun—you are likely to get shot in the United States, whatever the color of your skin.</p>
<p>As I said, when you’re with a cop, there is always a gun out in the open. And any physical struggle has to be perceived by him as a fight for the gun. A cop doesn’t know what you’re going to do if you overpower him, so he has to assume the worst. Most cops are not confident in their ability to physically control a person without shooting him—for good reason, because they’re not well trained to do that, and they’re continually confronting people who are bigger, or younger, or more athletic, or more aggressive than they are. Cops are not superheroes. They’re ordinary people with insufficient training, and once things turn physical they cannot afford to give a person who is now assaulting a police officer the benefit of the doubt.</p>
<p>This is something that most people seem totally confused about. If they see a video of somebody trying to punch a cop in the face and the person’s unarmed, many people think the cop should just punch back, and any use of deadly force would be totally disproportionate. But that’s not how violence works. It’s not the cop’s job to be the best bare-knuckled boxer on Earth so he doesn’t have to use his gun. A cop can’t risk getting repeatedly hit in the face and knocked out, because there’s always a gun in play. This is the cop’s perception of the world, and it’s a justifiable one, given the dynamics of human violence.</p>
<p>You might think cops shouldn’t carry guns. Why can’t we just be like England? That’s a point that can be debated. But it requires considerable thought in a country where there are over 300 million guns on the street. The United States is not England.</p>
<p>Again, really focus on what is happening when a cop is attempting to arrest a person. It’s not up to you to decide whether or not you should be arrested. Does it matter that you know you didn’t do anything wrong? No. And how could that fact be effectively communicated in the moment by your not following police commands? I’m going to ask that again: How could the fact that you’re innocent, that you’re not a threat to cop, that you’re not about to suddenly attack him or produce a weapon of your own, how could those things be effectively communicated at the moment he’s attempting to arrest you by your resisting arrest?</p>
<p>Unless you called the cops yourself, you never know what situation you’re in. If I’m walking down the street, I don’t know if the cop who is approaching me didn’t get a call that some guy who looks like Ben Stiller just committed an armed robbery. I know I didn’t do anything, but I don’t know what’s in the cop’s head. The time to find out what’s going on—the time to complain about racist cops, the time to yell at them and tell them they’re all going to get fired for their stupidity and misconduct—is after cooperating, at the police station, in the presence of a lawyer, preferably. But to not comply in the heat of the moment, when a guy with the gun is issuing commands—this raises your risk astronomically, and it’s something that most people, it seems, just do not intuitively understand, even when they’re not in the heat of the moment themselves, but just watching video of other people getting arrested.</p>
<p>Ok. End of public-service announcement.</p>
<p>The main problem with using individual cases, where black men and women have been killed by cops, to conclude that there is an epidemic of racist police violence in our society, is that you can find nearly identical cases of white suspects being killed by cops, and there are actually more of them.</p>
<p>In 2016, John McWhorter wrote a <a href="https://time.com/4404987/police-violence/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">piece</a> in Time Magazine about this.</p>
<p>Here’s a snippet of what he wrote:</p>
<p>“The heart of the indignation over these murders is a conviction that racist bias plays a decisive part in these encounters. That has seemed plausible to me, and I have recently challenged those who disagree to present a list of white people killed within the past few years under circumstances similar to those that so enrage us in cases such as what happened to Tamir Rice, John Crawford, Walter Scott, Sam Debose, and others.”</p>
<p>So, McWhorter issued that challenge, as he said, and he was presented with the cases [<a href="https://youtu.be/EPxNUKw0kV8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/VBUUx0jUKxc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/6KhRcIOuurI" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>]. But there’s no song about these people, admonishing us to say their names. And the list of white names is longer, and I don’t know any of them, other than Tony Timpa. I know the black names. In addition to the ones I just read from McWhorter’s article, I know the names of Eric Garner, and Michael Brown, and Alton Sterling, and Philando Castile, and now, of course, I know the name of George Floyd. And I’m aware of many of the details of these cases where black men and women have been killed by cops. I know the name of Breonna Taylor. I can’t name a single white person killed by cops in circumstances like these—other than Timpa—and I just read McWhorter’s article where he lists many of them.</p>
<p>So, this is also a distortion in the media. The media is not showing us videos of white people being killed by cops; activists are not demanding that they do this. I’m sure white supremacists talk about this stuff a lot, who knows? But in terms of the story we’re telling ourselves in the mainstream, we are not actually talking about the data on lethal police violence.</p>
<p>So back to the data: Again, cops kill around 1000 people every year in the United States. About 25 percent are black. About 50 percent are white. The data on police homicide are all over the place. The federal government does not have a single repository for data of this kind. But they have been pretty carefully tracked by outside sources, like the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/investigations/police-shootings-database/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Washington Post</a>, for the last 5 years. These ratios appear stable over time. Again, many of these killings are justifiable, we’re talking about career criminals who are often armed and, in many cases, trying to kill the cops. Those aren’t the cases we’re worried about. We’re worried about the unjustifiable homicides.</p>
<p>Now, some people will think that these numbers still represent an outrageous injustice. Afterall, African Americans are only 13 percent of the population. So, at most, they should be 13 percent of the victims of police violence, not 25 percent. Any departure from the baseline population must be due to racism.</p>
<p>Ok. Well, that sounds plausible, but consider a few more facts:</p>
<p>Blacks are 13 percent of the population, but they commit <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2015/crime-in-the-u.s.-2015/offenses-known-to-law-enforcement/expanded-homicide" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">at least 50 percent</a> of the murders and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-myth-of-systemic-police-racism-11591119883">other violent crimes</a>.</p>
<p>If you have 13 percent of the population responsible for 50 percent of the murders—and in some cities committing 2/3rds of all violent crime—what percent of police attention should it attract? I don’t know. But I’m pretty sure it’s not just 13 percent. Given that the overwhelming majority of their victims are black, I’m pretty sure that most black people wouldn’t set the dial at 13 percent either.</p>
<p>And here we arrive at the core of the problem. The story of crime in America is overwhelmingly the story of black-on-black crime. It is also, in part, a story of black-on-white crime. For more than a generation, crime in America really hasn’t been a story of much white-on-black crime. [Some listeners mistook my meaning here. I’m not denying that most violent crime is intraracial. So, it’s true that most white homicide victims are killed by white offenders. Per capita, however, the white crime rate is much lower than the black crime rate. And there is more black-on-white crime than white-on-black crime.—SH]</p>
<p>The murder rate has come down steadily since the early 1990’s, with only minor upticks. But, nationwide, blacks are still <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nvsr/nvsr68/nvsr68_09-508.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">6 times more likely</a> to get murdered than whites, and in some cities their risk is double that. And <a href="https://www.hks.harvard.edu/sites/default/files/centers/wiener/programs/pcj/files/PoliceandPublicDiscourseBlackonBlackViolence.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">around 95 percent</a> of the murders are committed by members of the African American community. [While reported in 2015, these data were more than a decade old. Looking at more recent data from the <a href="https://www.fbi.gov/services/cjis/ucr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FBI’s Uniform Crime Report</a>, the number appears to be closer to 90 percent.—SH]</p>
<p>The weekend these protests and riots were kicking off nationwide—when our entire country seemed to be tearing itself apart over a perceived epidemic of racist police violence against the black community, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/chicago-sees-18-homicides-deadliest-day-60-years/story?id=71150234" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">92 people were shot, and 27 killed</a>, in Chicago alone—one city. This is almost entirely a story of black men killing members of their own community. And this is far more representative of the kind of violence that the black community needs to worry about. And, ironically, it’s clear that one remedy for this violence is, or would be, effective policing.</p>
<p>These are simply the facts of crime in our society as we best understand them. And the police have to figure out how to respond to these facts, professionally and ethically. The question is, are they doing that? And, obviously, there’s considerable doubt that they’re doing that, professionally and ethically.</p>
<p>Roland Fryer, the Harvard economist who’s work I discussed on the podcast with Glenn Loury, studied police encounters involving black and white suspects and the use of force.</p>
<p>His <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w22399" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">paper</a> is titled, this from 2016, “An Empirical Analysis of Racial Differences in Police Use of Force.”</p>
<p>Fryer is black, and he went into this research with the expectation that the data would confirm that there’s an epidemic of lethal police violence directed at black men. But he didn’t find that. However, he did find support for the suspicion that black people suffer more nonlethal violence at the hands of cops than whites do.</p>
<p>So let’s look at this.</p>
<p>The study examined data from 10 major police departments, in Texas, Florida and California. Generally, Fryer found that there is 25 percent greater likelihood that the police would go hands on black suspects than white ones—cuffing them, or forcing them to ground, or using other non-lethal force.</p>
<p>Specifically, in New York City, in encounters where white and black citizens were matched for other characteristics, they found that:</p>
<p>Cops were…</p>
<ul>
<li>17 percent more likely to go hands on black suspects</li>
<li>18 percent more likely to push them into a wall</li>
<li>16 percent more likely to put them in handcuffs (in a situation in which they aren’t arrested)</li>
<li>18 percent more likely to push them to the ground</li>
<li>25 percent more likely to use pepper spray or a baton</li>
<li>19 percent more likely to draw their guns</li>
<li>24 percent more likely to point a gun at them.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is more or less the full continuum of violence short of using lethal force. And it seems, from the data we have, that blacks receive more of it than whites. What accounts for this disparity? Racism? Maybe. However, as I said, it’s inconvenient to note that other data suggest that black cops and Hispanic cops are more likely to shoot black and Hispanic suspects than white cops are. I’m not sure how an ambient level of racism explains that.</p>
<p>Are there other explanations? Well, again, could it be that blacks are less cooperative with the police. If so, that’s worth understanding. A culture of resisting arrest would be a very bad thing to cultivate, given that the only response to such resistance is for the police to increase their use of force.</p>
<p>Whatever is true here is something we should want to understand. And it’s all too easy to see how an increased number of encounters with cops, due to their policing in the highest crime neighborhoods, which are disproportionately black, and an increased number of traffic stops in those neighborhoods, and an increased propensity for cops to go hands-on these suspects, with or without an arrest, for whatever reason—it’s easy to see how all of this could be the basis for a perception of racism, whether or not racism is the underlying motivation.</p>
<p>It is totally humiliating to be arrested or manhandled by a cop. And, given the level of crime in the black community, a disproportionate number of innocent black men seem guaranteed to have this experience. It’s totally understandable that this would make them bitter and mistrustful of the police. This is another vicious circle that we must find some way to interrupt.</p>
<p>But Fryer also found that black suspects are around 25 percent less likely to be shot than white suspects are. And in the most egregious situations, where officers were not first attacked, but nevertheless fired their weapons at a suspect, they were more likely to do this when the suspect was white.</p>
<p>Again, the data are incomplete. This doesn’t not cover every city in the country. And a larger study tomorrow might paint a different picture. But, as far as I know, the best data we have suggest that for, whatever reason, whites are more likely to be killed by cops once an arrest is attempted. And a <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/116/32/15877.short" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">more recent study</a> in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences  by David Johnson and colleagues found similar results. And it is simply undeniable that more whites are killed by cops each year, both in absolute numbers and in proportion to their contributions to crime and violence in our society.</p>
<p>Can you hear how these facts should be grinding in that well-oiled machine of woke outrage? Our society is in serious trouble now. We are being crushed under the weight of a global pandemic and our response to it has been totally inept. On top of that, we’re being squeezed by the growing pressure of what might become a full-on economic depression. And the streets are now filled with people who imagine, on the basis of seeing some horrific videos, that there is an epidemic of racist cops murdering African Americans. Look at what this belief is doing to our politics. And these videos will keep coming. And the truth is they could probably be matched 2 for 1 with videos of white people being killed by cops. What percentage of people protesting understand that the disparity runs this way? In light of the belief that the disparity must run the other way, people are now quite happy to risk getting beaten and arrested by cops themselves, and to even loot and burn businesses. And most people and institutions are supporting this civil unrest from the sidelines, because they too imagine that cops are killing black people in extraordinary numbers. And all of this is calling forth an authoritarian response from Trump—and leading to more examples of police violence caught on video.</p>
<p>As I hope I’ve made clear, we need police reform—there’s no question about this. And some of the recent footage of the police attacking peaceful protests is outrageous. Nothing I just said should signify that I’m unaware of that. From what I’ve seen—and by the time I release this podcast, the character of all this might have changed—but, from what I’ve seen, the police were dangerously passive in the face of looting and real crime, at least in the beginning. In many cities, they just stood and watched society unravel. And then they were far too aggressive in the face of genuinely peaceful protests. This is a terrible combination. It is the worst combination. There’s no better way to increase cynicism and anger and fear, on all sides.</p>
<p>But racializing how we speak about the problem of police violence, where race isn’t actually the relevant variable—again, think of Tony Timpa— this has highly negative effects. First, it keeps us from talking about the real problems with police tactics. For instance, we had the recent case of Breonna Taylor who was killed in a so-called “no knock” raid of her home. As occasionally happens, in this carnival of moral error we call “the war on drugs,” the police had the wrong address, and they kicked in the wrong door. And they wound up killing a totally innocent woman. But this had nothing to do with race. The problem is not, as some commentators have alleged, that it’s not safe to be “sleeping while black.” The problem is that these no-knock raids are an obscenely dangerous way of enforcing despicably stupid laws. White people die under precisely these same circumstances, and very likely in greater numbers (I don’t have data specifically on no-knock raids, but we can assume that the ratio is probably conserved here).</p>
<p>Think about how crazy this policy is in a nation where gun ownership is so widespread. If someone kicks in your door in the middle of the night, and you’re a gun owner, of course you’re going to reach for your gun. That’s why you have a gun in the first place. The fact that people bearing down on you and your family out of the darkness might have yelled “police” (or might have not yelled “police”; it’s alleged in some of these cases that they don’t yell anything)—the fact that someone yells “police” isn’t necessarily convincing. Anyone can yell “police.” And, again, think of the psychology of this: If the police have the wrong house, and you know there is no reason on earth that real cops would take an interest in you, especially in the middle of the night, because you haven’t done anything (you’re not the guy running a meth lab)—and now you’re reaching for your gun in the dark—of course, someone is likely to get killed. This is not a racial issue. It’s a terrible policy.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the process of police reform isn’t straightforward—and it is made massively more complicated by what’s happening now. Yes, we will be urging police reform in a very big way now, that much seems clear. But Roland Fryer <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w27324" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">has also shown</a> that investigations of the cops, in a climate where viral videos and racial politics are operating, have dramatic effects, many of which are negative.</p>
<p>He studied the aftermath of the investigations into police misconduct that followed the killings Freddie Gray, Michael Brown, and Lequan McDonald, and found that, for reasons that seem pretty easy to intuit, proactive police contact with civilians decreases drastically, sometimes by as much 100 percent, once these investigations get started. This is now called “The Ferguson Effect.” The police still answer 911 calls, but they don’t investigate suspicious activity in the same way. They don’t want to wind up on YouTube. And when they alter their behavior like this, homicides go up. Fryer estimates that the effects of these few investigations translated into 1000 extra homicides, and almost 40,000 more felonies, over the next 24 months in the US. And, of course, most of the victims of those crimes were black. One shudders to imagine the size of the Ferguson effect we’re about to see nationwide… I’m sure the morale among cops has never been lower. I think it’s almost guaranteed that cops by the thousands will be leaving the force. And it will be much more difficult to recruit good people.</p>
<p>Who is going to want to be a cop now? Who could be idealist about occupying that role in society? It seems to me that the population of people who will become cops now will be more or less indistinguishable from the population of people who become prison guards. I’m pretty sure there’s a difference there, and I think we’re likely to see that difference expressed in the future. It’s a grim picture, unless we do something very creative here.</p>
<p>So there’s a real question about how we can reform police departments, and get rid of bad cops, without negatively impacting the performance of good cops? That’s a riddle we have to solve—or at least we have to understand what the trade-offs are here.</p>
<p>Why is all of this happening now? Police killings of civilians have gone way down. And they are rare events. They are 1/10,000 level events, if measured by arrests. 1/50-60,000 level events if measured by police encounters. And the number of unarmed people who are killed is smaller still. Around 50 last year, again, more were white than black. And not all unarmed victims are innocent. Some get killed in the act of attacking the cops.  [<a href="https://www.arlnow.com/2015/05/19/breaking-officer-involved-shooting-in-buckingham/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>, <a href="https://www.5newsonline.com/article/news/local/outreach/back-to-school/officer-involved-shooting-in-adair-county-oklahoma/527-e8cdc435-dcd0-429c-962f-b2c82c22068e" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>, <a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/crime/article36802032.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>]</p>
<p>Again, the data don’t tell a clean story, or the whole story. I see no reason to doubt that blacks get more attention from the cops—though, honestly, given the distribution of crime in our society, I don’t know what the alternative to that would be. And once the cops get involved, blacks are more likely to get roughed up, which is bad. But, again, it simply isn’t clear that racism is the cause. And contrary to everyone’s expectations, whites seem more likely to get killed by cops. Actually, one factor seems to be that whites are <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/116/32/15877.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">7 times more likely</a> to commit “suicide by cop” (and <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nvsr/nvsr68/nvsr68_09-508.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3 times more likely</a> to commit suicide generally). What’s going on there? Who knows?</p>
<p>There’s a lot we don’t understand about these data. But ask yourself, would our society seem less racist if the disparity ran the other way? Is less physical contact, but a greater likelihood of getting shot and killed a form of white privilege? Is a higher level of suicide by cop, and suicide generally, a form of white privilege? We have a problem here that, read either way, you can tell a starkly racist narrative.</p>
<p>We need ethical, professional policing, of course. But the places with the highest crime in our society need the most of it. Is there any doubt about that? In a city like Milwaukee, blacks are 12 times more likely to get murdered than whites [Not sure where I came by this number, probably a lecture or podcast. It appears the rate is closer to <a href="https://urbanmilwaukee.com/2015/01/12/gun-homicides-milwaukee-has-two-thirds-of-states-gun-killings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">20 times more likely</a> and <a href="https://www.bu.edu/sph/2018/07/13/residential-segregation-associated-with-black-white-disparity-in-firearm-homicide-rates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">22 times more likely</a> in Wisconsin as a whole—SH], again, they are being killed by other African Americans, nearly 100 percent of the time. I think the lowest figure I’ve seen is 93 percent of the time. [As noted above, more recent data suggest that it’s closer to 90 percent]. What should the police do about this? And what are they likely to do now that our entire country has been convulsed over one horrific case of police misconduct?</p>
<p>We need to lower the temperature on this conversation, and many other conversations, and understand what is actually happening in our society.</p>
<p>But instead of doing this, we now have a whole generation of social activists who seem eager to play a game of chicken with the forces of chaos. Everything I said about the problem of inequality and the need for reform stands. But I think that what we are witnessing in our streets, and on social media, and even in the mainstream press, is a version of mass hysteria. And the next horrific video of a black person being killed by cops won’t be evidence to the contrary. And there will be <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/17/us/rayshard-brooks-atlanta-shooting-wednesday/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">another video</a>. There are 10 million arrests every year. There will always be another video.</p>
<p>And the media has turned these videos into a form of political pornography. And this has deranged us. We’re now unable to speak or even think about facts. The media has been poisoned by bad incentives, in this regard, and social media doubly so.</p>
<p>In the mainstream of this protest movement, it’s very common to hear that the only problem with what is happening in our streets, apart from what the cops are doing, is that some criminal behavior at the margins—a little bit of looting, a little bit of violence—has distracted us from an otherwise necessary and inspiring response to an epidemic of racism. Most people in the media have taken exactly this line. People like Anderson Cooper on CNN or the editorial page of the New York Times or public figures like President Obama or Vice President Biden. The most prominent liberal voices believe that the protests themselves make perfect moral and political sense, and that movements like Black Lives Matter are guaranteed to be on the right side of history. How could anyone who is concerned about inequality and injustice in our society see things any other way? How could anyone who isn’t himself racist not support Black Lives Matter?</p>
<p>But, of course, there’s a difference between slogans and reality. There’s a difference between the branding of a movement and its actual aims. And this can be genuinely confusing. That’s why propaganda works. For instance, many people assume there’s nothing wrong with ANTIFA, because this group of total maniacs has branded itself as “anti-fascist.” What could be wrong with being anti-fascist? Are you pro fascism?</p>
<p>There’s a similar problem with Black Lives Matter—though, happily, unlike ANTIFA, Black Lives Matter actually seems committed to peaceful protest, which is hugely important. So the problem I’m discussing is more ideological, and it’s much bigger than Black Lives Matter—though BLM is its most visible symbol of this movement. The wider issue is that we are in the midst of a public hysteria and moral panic. And it has been made possible by a near total unwillingness, particularly on the Left, among people who value their careers and their livelihoods and their reputations, and fear being hounded into oblivion online—this is nearly everyone left-of-center politically. People are simply refusing to speak honestly about the problem of race and racism in America.</p>
<p>We are making ourselves sick. We are damaging our society. And by protesting the wrong thing, even the slightly wrong thing, and unleashing an explosion of cynical criminality in the process—looting that doesn’t even have the pretense of protest—the Left is empowering Trump, whatever the polls currently show. And if we are worried about Trump’s authoritarian ambitions, as I think we really should be, this is important to understand. He recently had what looked like paramilitary troops guarding the White House. I don’t know if we found out who those guys actually were, but that was genuinely alarming. But how are Democrats calls to “abolish the police” going to play to half the country that just watched so many cities get looted? We have to vote Trump out of office and restore the integrity of our institutions. And we have to make the political case for major reforms to deal with the problem of inequality—a problem which affects the black community most of all.</p>
<p>We need police reform; we need criminal justice reform; we need tax reform; we need health care reform; we need environmental reform—we need all of these things and more. And to be just, these policies will need to reduce the inequality in our society. If we did this, African Americans would benefit, perhaps more than any other group. But it’s not at all clear that progress along these dimensions primarily entails us finding and eradicating more racism in our society.</p>
<p>Just ask yourself, what would real progress on the problem of racism look like? What would utter progress look like?</p>
<p>Here’s what I think it would look like: More and more people (and ultimately all people) would care less and less (and ultimately not at all) about race. As I’ve said before in various places, skin color would become like hair color in its political and moral significance—which is to say that it would have none.</p>
<p>Now, maybe you don’t agree with that aspiration. Maybe you think that tribalism based on skin color can’t be outgrown or shouldn’t be outgrown. Well, if you think that, I’m afraid I don’t know what to say to you. It’s not that there’s nothing to say, it’s just there is so much we disagree about, morally and politically, that I don’t know where to begin. So that debate, if it can even be had, will have to be left for another time.</p>
<p>For the purposes of this conversation, I have to assume that you agree with me about the goal here, which is to say that you share the hope that there will come a time where the color of a person’s skin really doesn’t matter. What would that be like?</p>
<p>Well, how many blondes got into Harvard this year? Does anyone know? What percentage of the police in San Diego are brunette? Do we have enough red heads in senior management in our Fortune 500 companies? No one is asking these questions, and there is a reason for that. No one cares. And we are right not to care.</p>
<p>Imagine a world in which people cared about hair color to the degree that we currently care—or seem to care, or imagine that others care, or allege that they secretly care—about skin color. Imagine a world in which discrimination by hair color was a thing, and it took centuries to overcome, and it remains a persistent source of private pain and public grievance throughout society, even where it no longer exists. What an insane misuse of human energy that would be. What an absolute catastrophe.</p>
<p>The analogy isn’t perfect, for a variety of reasons, but it’s good enough for us to understand what life would be like if the spell of racism and anti-racism were truly broken. The future we want is not one in which we have all become passionate anti-racists. It’s not a future in which we are forever on our guard against the slightest insult—the bad joke, the awkward compliment, the tweet that didn’t age well. We want to get to a world in which skin color and other superficial characteristics of a person become morally and politically irrelevant. And if you don’t agree with that, what did you think Martin Luther King Jr was talking about?</p>
<p>And, finally, if you’re on the Left and don’t agree with this vision of a post-racial future, please observe that the people who agree with you, the people who believe that there is no overcoming race, and that racial identity is indissoluble, and that skin color really matters and will always matter—these people are white supremacists and neo-Nazis and other total assholes. And these are also people I can’t figure out how to talk to, much less persuade.</p>
<p>So the question for the rest of us—those of us who want to build a world populated by human beings, merely—the question is, how do we get there? How does racial difference become uninteresting? Can it become uninteresting by more and more people taking a greater interest in it? Can it become uninteresting by becoming a permanent political identity? Can it become uninteresting by our having thousands of institutions whose funding (and, therefore, very survival) depends on it remaining interesting until the end of the world?</p>
<p>Can it become less significant by being granted more and more significance? By becoming a fetish, a sacred object, ringed on all sides by taboos? Can race become less significant if you can lose your reputation and even your livelihood, at any moment, by saying one wrong word about it?</p>
<p>I think these questions answer themselves. To outgrow our obsession with racial difference, we have outgrow our obsession with race. And you don’t do that by maintaining your obsession with it.</p>
<p>Now, you might agree with me about the goal and about how a post-racial society would seem, but you might disagree about the path to get there—the question of what to do next. In fact, one podcast listener wrote to me recently to say that while he accepted my notion of a post-racial future, he thinks it’s just far too soon to talk about putting racial politics behind us. He asked me to imagine just how absurd it would have been to tell Martin Luther King Jr, at the dawn of the civil rights movement, that the path beyond racism requires that he become less and less obsessed with race.</p>
<p>That seems like a fair point, but Coleman Hughes has drawn my attention to a string of MLK quotes that seem to be just as transcendent of racial identity politics as I’m hoping to be here. You can <a href="https://twitter.com/coldxman/status/1087593991976243200?lang=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">see these quotations</a> on his Twitter feed. None of those statements by King would make sense coming out of Black Lives Matter at the moment.</p>
<p>In any case, as I said, I think we are living in a very different time than Martin Luther King was. And what I see all around me is evidence of the fact that we were paying an intolerable price for confusion about racism, and social justice generally—and the importance of identity, generally—and this is happening in an environment where the path to success and power for historically disadvantaged groups isn’t generally barred by white racists who won’t vote for them, or hire them, or celebrate their achievements, or buy their products, and it isn’t generally barred by laws and policies and norms that are unfair. There is surely still some of that. But there must be less of it now than there ever was.</p>
<p>The real burden on the black community is the continued legacy of inequality—with respect to wealth, and education, and health, and social order—levels of crime, in particular, and resulting levels of incarceration, and single-parent families—and it seems very unlikely that these disparities, whatever their origin in the past, can be solved by focusing on problem of lingering racism, especially where it doesn’t exist. And the current problem of police violence seems a perfect case in point.</p>
<p>And yet now we’re inundated with messages from every well-intentioned company and organization singing from the same book of hymns. Black Lives Matter is everywhere. Of course, black lives matter. But the messaging of this movement about the reality of police violence is wrong, and it’s creating a public hysteria.</p>
<p>I just got a message from the American Association for the Advancement of Science talking about fear of the other. The quote from the email: “Left unchecked, racism, sexism, homophobia, and fear of the other can enter any organization or community – and destroy the foundations upon which we must build our future.” Ok, fine. But is that really the concern in the scientific community right now, “unchecked racism, sexism, and homophobia.” Is that really what ails science in the year 2020? I don’t think so.</p>
<p>I’ll tell you the fear of the other that does seem warranted, everywhere, right now. It’s the other who has rendered him or herself incapable of dialogue. It’s the other who will not listen to reason, who has no interest in facts, who can’t join a conversation that converges on the truth, because he knows in advance what the truth must be. We should fear the other who thinks that dogmatism and cognitive bias aren’t something to be corrected for, because they’re the very foundations of his epistemology.  We should fear the other who can’t distinguish activism from journalism or politics from science. Or worse, can make these distinctions, but refuses to. And we’re all capable of becoming this person. If only for minutes or hours at a time. And this is a bug in our operating system, not a feature. We have to continually correct for it.</p>
<p>One of the most shocking things that many of us learned when the Covid-19 pandemic was first landing on our shores, and we were weighing the pros and cons of closing the schools, was that for tens of millions of American kids, going to school represents the only guarantee of a decent meal on any given day. I’m pretty confident that most of the kids we’re talking about here aren’t white. And whatever you think about the opportunities in this country and whatever individual success stories you can call to mind, there is no question that some of us start on third base, or second base. Everyone has a lot to deal with, of course. Life is hard. But not everyone is a single mom, or single grandparent, struggling to raise kids in the inner city, all the while trying to keep them from getting murdered. The disparities in our society are absolutely heartbreaking and unacceptable. And we need to have a rational discussion about their actual causes and solutions.</p>
<p>We have to pull back from the brink here. And all we have with which to do that is conversation. And the only thing that makes conversation possible is an openness to evidence and arguments—a willingness to update one’s view of the world when better reasons are given. And that is an ongoing process, not a place we ever finally arrive.</p>
<p>Ok… Well, perhaps that was more of an exhortation than I intended, but it certainly felt like I needed to say it. I hope it was useful. And the conversations will continue on this podcast.</p>
<p>Stay safe, everyone.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this episode of the podcast, Sam discusses the recent social protests and civil unrest, in light of what we know about racism and police violence in America. This is a transcript of a recorded podcast. * * * Welcome to the Making Sense podcast… This is Sam Harris. OK…. Well, I’ve been trying to … <a href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Porscha Pressler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=1571161</id>
    <published>2020-06-18T21:59:09Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-18T21:59:09Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Personal Note</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear Making Sense and Waking Up subscribers—</p>
<p>Those of you who have been listening to my podcast or following me on Twitter know that I’m quite worried about the emerging coronavirus pandemic. Barring some extraordinarily good luck, I believe that we have some very rough months ahead of us. Health concerns aside, it now seems inevitable that we will experience considerable economic uncertainty as a wave of illness disrupts normal life in a hundred countries simultaneously.</p>
<p>As you know, both the <a href="https://wakingup.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up app</a> and the <a href="https://samharris.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="https://samharris.org/">Making Sense podcast</a> are subscription services. However, it has always been my policy that money should never be the reason why someone can’t get access to them. As we collectively respond to this global emergency, please know that if you can no longer afford a subscription to Waking Up or Making Sense, you need only send an email to <a href="mailto:support@wakingup.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="mailto:support@wakingup.com">support@wakingup.com</a> or <a href="mailto:support@samharris.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="mailto:support@samharris.org">support@samharris.org</a>, and you’ll receive a free account when your subscription expires.</p>
<p>I’m incredibly fortunate to have found work that I love to do, along with a community of people willing to support it—and I feel especially good knowing that I can be of use to many of you at a time like this. I’m also very happy that both Waking Up and Making Sense are supported by a wonderful team of employees and contractors who can work from home indefinitely.</p>
<p>So please don’t forget: The work we are doing is for you, whether you can pay for it or not. And don’t hesitate to be in touch if you need help.</p>
<p>Wishing you all health and happiness,</p>
<p>Sam</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">A Personal Note</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear Making Sense and Waking Up subscribers— Those of you who have been listening to my podcast or following me on Twitter know that I’m quite worried about the emerging coronavirus pandemic. Barring some extraordinarily good luck, I believe that we have some very rough months ahead of us. Health concerns aside, it now seems … <a href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">A Personal Note</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Mary Morrison</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=1570286</id>
    <published>2020-03-14T19:26:17Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-14T19:26:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As many of you know, the Day of Reflection conference, scheduled for November 17 in NYC, has been cancelled, and some hundreds of ticket holders are now left seeking refunds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was forced to pull out of this event &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SamHarrisOrg/status/1043277230632132608"&gt;nearly two months ago&lt;/a&gt; and have said very little about it since. Now that Travis Pangburn has officially announced that he will be &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PangburnInspire/status/1062431248205864962"&gt;“folding” his touring company&lt;/a&gt;, Pangburn Philosophy, I can give a brief account of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I participated in 10 events organized by Pangburn Philosophy between September 2017 and July 2018. I didn’t always approve of the way those events were staged or marketed, but all of them appeared to be successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, after the cancellation of an August 2018 conference in Auckland, Pangburn seemed intent on running his business off a cliff. He owed a lot of money to several speakers at that point, in the form of unpaid fees and reimbursements. Most egregiously, he seemed less than fully committed to refunding ticket holders for the cancelled Auckland conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this point, I had two more dates on the calendar with Pangburn in 2018: a dialogue with Brian Greene in Toronto (September 5) and the Day of Reflection conference in New York (November 17). I kept my appointment in Toronto because I was contractually obligated to do so. I also didn’t want to do anything that would harm Pangburn’s ability to pay his mounting debts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After Toronto, however, it became clear that Pangburn could not be trusted to put his house in order. Facing a total lack of transparency, and realizing that Pangburn was using my ongoing association with him to book future speakers, I withdrew from the NYC conference on September 21 (as well as from a Vancouver conference scheduled for March 2019). Legally, I was able to do this because Pangburn was in breach of my speaking contract. Ethically, I had a far more compelling reason to back out: I couldn’t promote or participate in an event for which I believed other speakers were unlikely to get paid; nor could I continue to work with someone who still hadn’t given refunds to ticket holders for a conference that had been canceled more than a month before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After I withdrew from the NYC conference, my management team asked Pangburn to give us the email addresses of all ticket holders so that we could notify them that I was no longer involved with the event. Pangburn refused to provide this information. However, he assured us that he would notify everyone himself. (I do not know whether he ever did.) He then stopped responding to our emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the time I pulled out of the NYC conference, I assumed that the revenue from ticket sales was still safely in the box office and that Pangburn would be obliged to issue refunds should the conference fail. That’s how things normally work, especially at a reputable venue like Lincoln Center. It hadn’t occurred to me that New York ticketholders might suffer the same fate as those in Auckland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was left with a legal and ethical puzzle that I could not solve. Again, I had no way to communicate with ticket holders directly, and discussing the chaos surrounding Pangburn on my podcast never seemed like an option. Several friends and colleagues still had events on the calendar with him, and I didn’t want to do anything to derail them. In addition, many speakers who were aware of my reasons for pulling out of the NYC conference were still signed on and seemed intent on making it work. I couldn’t see anything to do that wouldn’t risk creating further harms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Pangburn still owes several speakers (including me) an extraordinary amount of money, we were willing to participate in the NYC conference for free as recently as a few days ago, if he would have handed it over to us and stepped away. I have been told that this offer was made, and he declined it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it appalling that so many people were needlessly harmed by the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy. I can assure you that every speaker associated with the NYC event will be much wiser when working with promoters in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/"&gt;A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; appeared first on &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org"&gt;Sam Harris&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>As many of you know, the Day of Reflection conference, scheduled for November 17 in NYC, has been cancelled, and some hundreds of ticket holders are now left seeking refunds. I was forced to pull out of this event nearly two months ago and have said very little about it since. Now that Travis Pangburn has … <a href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/">A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sam Harris</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=675963</id>
    <published>2018-11-16T15:36:59Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-16T15:36:59Z</updated>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><iframe loading="lazy" class="youtube-player" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h1oaSt60b0o?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=474318</id>
    <published>2018-09-04T20:00:04Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-04T20:00:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><iframe loading="lazy" class="youtube-player" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/m0-oC_49fq4?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=474326</id>
    <published>2018-09-04T19:30:31Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-04T19:30:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evidence to House of Commons Sci Tech Select Committee on Research Integrity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/12/evidence-to-house-of-commons-sci-tech-select-committee-on-research-integrity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry not to be in regular blogging mode at the moment. Here’s a video of our evidence session to parliament, where they are running an inquiry into research integrity. I think clinical trials are the best possible way to approach this issue. Lots of things in “research integrity” are hard to capture in hard logical […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3498</id>
    <published>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</updated>
    <category term="alltrials campaign"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do the world’s biggest drug companies compare, in their transparency commitments?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/how-do-the-worlds-biggest-drug-companies-compare-in-their-transparency-commitments/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hereâ€™s a paper, and associated website, that we launch today: we have assessed, and then ranked, all the biggest drug companies in the world, to compare their public commitments on trials transparency. Regular readers will be familiar with this ongoing battle. In medicine we use the results of clinical trials to make informed treatments about […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3485</id>
    <published>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meaningful Transparency Commitments: the WHO Joint Statement from Trial Funders</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/meaningful-transparency-commitments-the-who-joint-statement-from-trial-funders/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By now I hope you all know about the ongoing global scandal of clinical trial results being left unpublished, and of course our AllTrials campaign. Doctors, researchers, and patients cannot make truly informed choices about which treatments work best if they don’t have access to all the trial results. Earlier this year, I helped out […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3481</id>
    <published>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/02/how-many-epidemiologists-does-it-take-to-change-a-lightbulb/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robin Ince just asked if I know any epidemiologist lightbulb jokes. I wrote this for him. How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb? Weâ€™ve found 12,000 switches hidden around the house. Some of them turn this lightbulb on, some of them donâ€™t; some of them only work sometimes; and some of them […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3472</id>
    <published>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“Transparency, Beyond Publication Bias”. A video of my super-speedy talk at IJE.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2016/10/transparency-beyond-publication-bias-a-video-of-my-super-speedy-talk-at-ije/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">People oftenÂ talk about “trials transparency” as if this means “all trials must be published in an academic journal”. In reality, true transparency goes much further than this. We need Clinical Study Reports, and individual patient data, of course. But we also need the consent forms, so we can see what patients were told. We need […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3463</id>
    <published>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
