<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2021-12-22T15:35:42Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Hey, how about some local good news for a change?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/22/hey-how-about-some-local-good-news-for-a-change/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Incremental progress exists, and I should acknowledge that now and then.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.co.stevens.mn.us/CivicAlerts.aspx?AID=69">Morris is implementing organics pick-up</a>! The county is collecting food waste from local grocery stores and restaurants for composting. It’s a drop in the bucket, but a good step.</li>
<li>This is impressive: Alexandria (a city about 45 minutes north of me) is <a href="https://www.minnpost.com/greater-minnesota/2021/12/what-one-greater-minnesota-citys-experience-says-about-the-states-efforts-to-integrate-mental-health-and-police-work/">partnering the police with mental health professionals</a> to put the right people in charge of handling citizens having mental health crises. Imagine: someone having a breakdown and the city response is not to send an unqualified thug with a gun charging in to do battle.</li>
</ul>
<p>We’re taking baby steps in the right direction, let’s keep it up.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Incremental progress exists, and I should acknowledge that now and then. Morris is implementing organics pick-up! The county is collecting food waste from local grocery stores and restaurants for composting. It’s a drop in the bucket, but a good step. This is impressive: Alexandria (a city about 45 minutes north of me) is partnering the […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64982</id>
    <published>2021-12-22T15:12:51Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-22T15:12:51Z</updated>
    <category term="Local"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Would you put your brain in a robot body?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/22/would-you-put-your-brain-in-a-robot-body/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;This little cartoon captures the American zeitgeist perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NKVkMEhtkI8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This little cartoon captures the American zeitgeist perfectly.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64980</id>
    <published>2021-12-22T14:12:30Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-22T14:12:30Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How are we supposed to teach in the Plague Years?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/22/how-are-we-supposed-to-teach-in-the-plague-years/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid-150x100.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="100" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-62859" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid-150x100.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid-300x201.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid-768x514.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid-500x334.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/05/covid.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></p>
<p class="lead">Yesterday, I got all my grades turned in, meaning Fall semester is all done…oh, wait, I had to write a bunch of student recommendations and get those sent off. OK, that done, <em>now</em> the semester is behind me, I’m care-free and can go dancing in the streets, or <em>whatever I want</em> for a little while. So what do I do? I opened up my calendar and started planning my schedule for next semester, sketching in lab protocols and exam dates, assembling the information that’ll go into my syllabus. I had some ideas for revising the content/pedagogy of the course, and I wanted to map them out.</p>
<p>It was kind of pointless.</p>
<p>Universities elsewhere (not the University of Minnesota, which will drag its heels to the last moment) are noticing this Omicron variant, and how quickly it may potentially spread, and are scrambling to adjust their schedules, just in case. <a href="https://www.sacbee.com/news/coronavirus/article256767607.html">Four California universities are switching to online only instruction</a> for the first few weeks of the spring term; the <a href="https://www.washington.edu/coronavirus/2021/12/21/most-classes-will-meet-online-the-first-week-of-winter-quarter-message-to-uw-students-and-personnel/">University of Washington is going online only for the first week</a>. This is bad news. If you’ve paid any attention at all to university management for the last few years, you’d know that they are always reluctant to adjust to reality, and are never pro-active. If this is what the UW and UC are doing, the situation has to be far worse than anyone is telling.</p>
<p>UM is doing nothing new. Not even a whisper of concern. You’d think, given the fact that our <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/minnesota-gov-tim-walz-announces-174207436.html?fr=yhssrp_catchall">governor and his family just tested positive for COVID-19</a>, that maybe there’d be an alarm bell ringing faintly in some neglected corner of the administration building. For that matter, you’d think Governor Walz might wake up and realize that his lackadaisical, half-assed approach of doing the bare minimum to contain the pandemic wasn’t working, but I don’t expect that to happen, either.</p>
<p>I realized then that next term might be more challenging than I expected, especially since I’m now <em>required</em> to teach all of my classes in-person. Brilliant. Maybe that will change, but I think the faculty and students are now sacrificial lambs laid out on the altar of an optimistic sense of normalcy. It’s all on the shoulders of the faculty to figure out how to flexibly cope with the changing situation.</p>
<p>I made a decision as I was drafting my syllabus. I am required by my employers to be there in Sci 1020, the genetics classroom, but I don’t have to demand that students be there. I’m making attendance optional. I’ll record all my lectures and post them online. Exams will all be take-home. I’ll hold office hours on campus (you better be vaccinated &amp; wearing a mask if you show up in person) and held simultaneously on Zoom.</p>
<p>The lab is a problem. Actually doing the data collection and analysis of independently acquired data is kind of the core purpose of doing a lab, and it’s going to require using on-campus facilities. I have a plan for that, too. The first week of lab will be online: it’s all preparation in basic probability and statistics to get ready for the actual work, and I have exercises in coin-flipping and die-rolling they can do at home. That one is manageable.</p>
<p>Subsequent labs are all about working with flies, and most people would rather not breed thousands of fruit flies in their kitchen. Once again, I am required to teach in-person, so I’ll go in, record myself doing the procedures and showing the students who show up how to do them, and make that available online. Then I’m throwing the lab schedule out the window: the genetics lab will be open from 9am onwards, students will come in when they’ve got available time to do the work on our incubators and microscopes, and I’ll be on call to help out from 9-whenever. That should help spread out attendance. If the university shuts down (I hope the severity of the pandemic isn’t so great that that is necessary), I’ll do the experiments alone, supplemented with class data from previous years, so the students will at least have numbers and phenotypic data to analyze.</p>
<p>It’s going to be a lot of extra work, but I’ll do it. The university administration better be prepared, too: so help me Dog if any of my students die of COVID-19 because of the mandated university environment, I’ll be preparing my letter of resignation and will take my retirement right now, thank you very much. I am so damn tired of irresponsible, incompetent responses to the pandemic, not just from my university, but from every level of government.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yesterday, I got all my grades turned in, meaning Fall semester is all done…oh, wait, I had to write a bunch of student recommendations and get those sent off. OK, that done, now the semester is behind me, I’m care-free and can go dancing in the streets, or whatever I want for a little while. […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64978</id>
    <published>2021-12-22T13:53:41Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-22T13:53:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My illusory award of two days of vacation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/22/my-illusory-award-of-two-days-of-vacation/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Last week, I mentioned this odd <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/17/wtf-um/">“gesture of appreciation”</a> my university was making to thank us for all our hard work and sacrifices during these pandemic years. We could take two days off in the coming semester. I was baffled…no, I can’t. I’m in a salaried position with daily responsibilities to my students and colleagues — unless you’re telling me that I can send the students home, this is a meaningless, useless gift.</p>
<p>I said as much to one of our administrators, and whoa, I got a straight answer from them. They admitted that “the days off are not as meaningful a gift of time for faculty as for others.” They’re a good thing for staff with regular 9-5 working days, I agree — of course, I suspect that they’ll get eaten up with sick days, or days spent caring for kids who’ve been sent home for school. Then I was told I “can take a day off formally, in the system when you are not teaching”, which is great, except that teaching is something I have to do every day, and is my primary job responsibility. So basically this is a promise of a little extra free time that I’m not allowed to take, but hey, the administration at the Twin Cities campus gets to feel good about doing a little something which is actually nothing.</p>
<p>I suspect some out of touch bright MBA in the marble halls of the central administration wracked their brains really hard to come up with a sop to the workers that would look really good on paper to outsiders, yet wouldn’t cost the university a penny.</p>
<p>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last week, I mentioned this odd “gesture of appreciation” my university was making to thank us for all our hard work and sacrifices during these pandemic years. We could take two days off in the coming semester. I was baffled…no, I can’t. I’m in a salaried position with daily responsibilities to my students and colleagues […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64976</id>
    <published>2021-12-22T12:53:23Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-22T12:53:23Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I could be worse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/12/21/i-could-be-worse/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I know many of my readers shudder in dread whenever I mention “sp*d*rs”, but just imagine if <i>Arthropleura</i> hadn’t died off a few hundred million years ago — I’d be growing them in my lab right now and posting photos of my cuties for you to see. This is in the news now because they just found a <a href="https://phys.org/news/2021-12-millipedes-big-cars-roamed-northern.html">third fossil</a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1-500x331.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="331" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64973" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1-500x331.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1-150x99.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1-300x199.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1-768x509.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/millipedes-as-big-as-c-1.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></p>
<p>Sadly, not only have only a few of these humongous millipedes been found, but they’re all fragmentary. All we have are chunks — chunks that are several feet long — of the beast. Nobody has yet found a fossilized <i>Arthropleura</i> head. Just imagine all the eyes, and the nasty great mandibles, and the hungry expression on their face, if you can figure out the various bits of what passes for a face in a giant millipede. I’d show you, if I had a picture!</p>
<p>As long as your imagination is cranking away, here’s a visual aid.</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura-500x406.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="406" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64974" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura-500x406.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura-150x122.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura-300x243.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura-768x623.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/12/arthropleura.jpeg 954w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></p>
<p>I think his cousin is living in my bathroom shower right now.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I know many of my readers shudder in dread whenever I mention “sp*d*rs”, but just imagine if Arthropleura hadn’t died off a few hundred million years ago — I’d be growing them in my lab right now and posting photos of my cuties for you to see. This is in the news now because they […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64972</id>
    <published>2021-12-21T19:09:49Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-21T19:09:49Z</updated>
    <category term="Fossils"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The quiet subversiveness of A Christmas Carol</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5906/the-quiet-subversiveness-of-a-christmas-carol#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="'Marley's Ghost. Ebenezer Scrooge visited by a ghost.' (Flickr / Creative Commons)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2021-12-20-at-17.39.40.jpg" height="753" alt="Screenshot-2021-12-20-at-17.39.40" width="1031" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a young child, my brother and I would be packed into the family car each year at Christmas and driven to Rochester, in north Kent. There, my father had an annual engagement that, to be quite frank, embarrassed the hell out of us both. In the boot of the car was a small suitcase, and inside that a tailcoat, watchchain and other faded garments. We&amp;rsquo;d arrive soon after sundown at Gad&amp;rsquo;s Hill Place, the final home of Charles Dickens, and within the hour, dad would be up on stage in the school hall in Victorian costume, gripping a lectern, his body pitched forward as he read to the audience his own rendering of &lt;em&gt;A Christmas Carol&lt;/em&gt;. We, meanwhile, slid ever deeper into our seats. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The voices of the many characters - gnarled and guttural for Scrooge, weak and whiny for Tiny Tim - I remember well. He executed them brilliantly. I also remember the odd gushing fan who&amp;rsquo;d greet him like a rock star once the reading finished. What I wasn&amp;rsquo;t of course aware of was the significance of the text itself. To me, it was just a Christmas story. The characters were richer than those of your average tale, and the story had a better developed moral arc than most. But it was just another Christmas story.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Only later did the subversive quality of &lt;em&gt;A Christmas Carol&lt;/em&gt;, published in December 1843, come into view. Like several of Dickens&amp;rsquo; other works, the book electrified much of Victorian Britain. But it did so for reasons that have been largely forgotten. The origins of &lt;em&gt;A Christmas Carol&lt;/em&gt; had nothing to do with Christmas; it arose from an idea Dickens had earlier in 1843 to issue a political pamphlet, &amp;ldquo;An Appeal to the People of England on behalf of the Poor Man&amp;rsquo;s Child&amp;rdquo;, to protest against the exploitation of children sent to work in mines and factories. He was also exercised by the condition of children attending London&amp;rsquo;s Ragged Schools - free institutions for the poor that had been established by charities. Should children be given so much religious instruction in circumstances where the basic needs of food, drink and clothing seemed so much more urgent to address? &amp;ldquo;To impress them, even with the idea of God, when their own condition is so desolate, becomes a monstrous task,&amp;rdquo; he wrote in a published letter.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dickens shelved his first idea of the &amp;ldquo;Appeal&amp;rdquo;, and decided instead to reshape it into a short story and then to link that story with Christmas. The &amp;ldquo;Poor Man&amp;rsquo;s Child&amp;rdquo; became Tiny Tim; Victorian society&amp;rsquo;s spirit of callous laissez-faire was embodied in the grasping misanthrope Ebenezer Scrooge. It was an extraordinary success: 6000 copies sold in one day.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;Blessings on your kind heart,&amp;rdquo; the Scottish literary critic Francis Jeffery wrote to Dickens soon after reading the short book. &amp;ldquo;You may be sure you have done more good by this little publication, fostered more kindly feelings, and prompted more positive acts of beneficence, than can be traced to all the pulpits and confessionals in Christendom since 1842.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A secularist Victorian bible&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Christmas Carol&lt;/em&gt; was greeted at the time, informally at least, as something of a secularist bible - or, as Paul Davis writes, &amp;ldquo;the first gospel in the &amp;lsquo;secular scripture&amp;rsquo; of Victorian fiction&amp;rdquo;. Dickens located the story in a smog-filled London at a time when cities, according to the American critic J. Hillis Miller, were &amp;ldquo;the literal representation of the progressive humanization of the world&amp;hellip; The way in which many men have experienced most directly what it means to live without God in the world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That distancing from Christian worship is reflected in the book. Despite occasional mentions of &amp;ldquo;Our Founder&amp;rdquo;, as well as the fact that Dickens was a practising Christian himself, &lt;em&gt;A Christmas Carol&lt;/em&gt; steers clear of theological evangelising. The redemption story of Scrooge is a deeply humanistic one, and as such, the book appealed to both churchgoers and agnostics. It therefore stood out at a time when obsession with Christianity was pervasive in the literary world. By the time of Dickens&amp;rsquo; death, half of all monthly periodicals and books were religiously oriented, despite the fact that religion was waning in British society more generally as a result of the rise of evolutionary science and the historical criticism of the Bible that would come a decade or two later.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am sure I have always thought of Christmas time, when it has come round &amp;ndash; apart from the veneration due to its sacred name and origin, if anything belonging to it can be apart from that &amp;ndash; as a good time: a kind, forgiving, charitable, pleasant time,&amp;rdquo; Scrooge&amp;rsquo;s nephew says early on, shunting the religious origin of Christmas into a passing parenthesis and instead emphasising the humanist value and meaning of the festivity. &amp;ldquo;The only time I know of, in the long calendar of the year, when men and women seem by one consent to open their shut-up hearts, freely, and to think of people below them as if they really were fellow-passengers to the grave, and not another race of creatures bound on other journeys.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t understand, as a child, that in this Christmas tale, Dickens had nailed together the structural edifice of a broad church, one that took ownership of charity away from the pious and made it a public moral duty. His belief was that responsibility for the unfortunate should be democratised - it was everyone&amp;rsquo;s to share. It&amp;rsquo;s a nice thing to remember my father using Christmas to bellow this same message from the lamplit stage.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5906/the-quiet-subversiveness-of-a-christmas-carol#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-12-20T17:51:40Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-20T17:51:40Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Reign of Terror</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5894/book-review-reign-of-terror#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Former president Donald Trump disembarking from Air Force One (Alamy Stock Photo)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2GF12N6.jpg" height="467" alt="2GF12N6" width="700" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is a strange and disturbing thing to notice that after 20 years, we do not have a neat and evocative phrase that can truthfully summarise what the United States has done to the world, and to itself, since 11 September 2001. The commonplace descriptor, used by the press and politicians, has been &amp;ldquo;The War on Terror&amp;rdquo;. Yet this is vague and euphemistic, as it is impossible to wage war on an emotion and even more difficult to declare victory in such a conflict. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Flushed with fervour, George Bush Jr initially wanted to describe his wartime actions as a &amp;ldquo;crusade&amp;rdquo;, but quickly backtracked, to the annoyance of his base. With the title of his 2011 book, the British foreign correspondent Jason Burke collected the various bombings, occupations and insurgencies under the banner of &lt;em&gt;The 9/11 Wars&lt;/em&gt;, while &amp;ldquo;The Forever War&amp;rdquo; became popular as a means to convey the interminable emotional reality of what America&amp;rsquo;s renewed imperium represents. Yet both of these can only encapsulate what happened on foreign soil, and not what occurred within the borders of the world&amp;rsquo;s superpower.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The national security journalist Spencer Ackerman has a different suggestion: &amp;ldquo;If the United States is ever to recover from the destruction it unleashed not only on the world but on itself, and primarily on its most vulnerable, it must first understand the post-9/11 era as nothing other than a reign of terror.&amp;rdquo; This term reconfigures &amp;ldquo;terror&amp;rdquo; as something that was being inflicted as much as it was being &amp;ldquo;fought&amp;rdquo;. Moreover, it captures the kind of power developed by the Bush administration and inherited by its successors: a sacred consensus contemptful of any challenge.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A terse and vigorous primer on the last two decades, Ackerman&amp;rsquo;s new book maps the political and cultural trajectory of the Reign of Terror from September 2001 and Bush&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;shock and awe&amp;rdquo;, through Obama&amp;rsquo;s attempt to craft a &amp;ldquo;sustainable&amp;rdquo; war, up until the chaotic end of Trump&amp;rsquo;s presidency. The actions taken in the months and years after 9/11, he writes, &amp;ldquo;echoed the jihadism it sought to destroy: brutal, messianic, aggrieved, censorious, eschatological.&amp;rdquo; One might also add totalising, given that every institution of the state, all wings of the armed forces, the entire political and media class, sport, literature, music, television serials, cafeteria food, cut-price trinkets, bumper stickers, the judiciary and the education system were suborned to the vagaries of a conflict designed to be endless.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The all-seeing power of the NSA&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Indeed, in the founding charters of the Reign of Terror &amp;ndash; specifically the Patriot Act, defining the legal tools available to the state, and the Authorisation for the Use of Military Force, granting the president unlimited warmaking powers &amp;ndash; no clear enemy was ever defined. &amp;ldquo;Precision was not something temporarily lost in the wake of [9/11],&amp;rdquo; Ackerman notes, &amp;ldquo;but was a fundamental obstacle to the emerging enterprise.&amp;rdquo; With these weapons in hand, the will to dominate was alluring, and for many of its victims, inescapable. Tucker Carlson, the rightwing shock-jock, ventriloquised many when he suggested that Iraqis, who had the singular bad taste to demand the freedom of their country, ought to &amp;ldquo;just shut the fuck up and obey&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Between brief forays into the places which felt the weight of American might (Iraq, Afghanistan, Pakistan, Somalia, Libya, Mali and many others), Ackerman details the architecture of an internal regime of repression, roundups and the most penetrating digital panopticon ever built. Run by the NSA, the security state possessed (and still possesses) the capacity to collect any amount of information from anyone, anytime: &amp;ldquo;the first mathematically exponential violation of constitutional rights in American history,&amp;rdquo; as Ackerman puts it. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This surveillance behemoth was wedded to a regimented bureaucracy of assassinations and abductions, and a shadow regime of deniable &amp;ldquo;black sites&amp;rdquo; with their own trained-up torturers. &amp;ldquo;Being Muslim in public,&amp;rdquo; Ackerman writes, &amp;ldquo;was treated as a disreputable political act,&amp;rdquo; courtesy of the FBI and their vast network of informants, wiretaps, dragnets and legal threats. A programme of looting shifted $6 trillion to men in uniform and their auxiliary of mercenary &amp;ldquo;contractors&amp;rdquo;. And where did all of those tanks and armoured trucks, helicopters and grenade launchers later resurface? On American streets, often enough, to discipline protestors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;9/11 and the birth of the Trump administration&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Throughout &lt;em&gt;Reign of Terror&lt;/em&gt;, Ackerman makes a point of mentioning the figures who made their names in the 2000s and would later become superstars of the rolling controversies of the Trump years: Robert Mueller, James Comey, Bill Barr, Jeff Sessions, Jim Mattis and so on. This is because the last third of Ackerman&amp;rsquo;s book makes the case that, by galvanising the Republican right and creating an unimpeachable administration of violence bolstered by liberal complicity, the Reign of Terror &amp;ldquo;produced&amp;rdquo; Trump&amp;rsquo;s presidency. &amp;ldquo;A war that never defined its enemy became an opportunity for the so-called MAGA coalition of white Americans to merge their grievances in an atmosphere of righteous emergency. That impulse unlocked a panoply of authoritarian possibilities.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;True, but not true enough. Missing from this analysis is the deep and morbid social crisis created by the Great Recession of 2007/08, which is under-examined in the book. Those &amp;ldquo;grievances&amp;rdquo; (real or imagined) were as much a product of the 9/11 era as they were the result of a class of Americans, badly hit by the economic crisis, feeling themselves to be increasingly precarious and alienated. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nevertheless, Ackerman shrewdly observes that at critical moments when the Reign of Terror might have been calmed down or cut back, the Democratic Party and many of its supporters moved in the opposite direction, rushing to entrench the security state. When fears grew that Trump might enact a coup or anoint himself a dictator, when the worrying about the structural stability of American democracy reached its peak, who did they appeal to for redemption? The generals, the police, the intelligence &amp;ldquo;community&amp;rdquo;: in short, the Reign of Terror&amp;rsquo;s administrators who had done so much to threaten that democracy in the first instance. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There has been no reckoning, in other words. The machinery of the Terror was passed from Trump to Joe Biden fundamentally intact. We continue to live within the grip of what Ackerman stoutly calls &amp;ldquo;a perpetual-motion engine of death&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter edition 2021. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5894/book-review-reign-of-terror#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-12-20T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-20T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why LEGO Sets are Fun AND a Smart Investment!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2021/12/why-lego-sets-are-fun-and-a-smart-investment/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Merry Christmas, everyone! As I’m sure you’ve all noticed, this is the season of love, togetherness, and most importantly, the birth of our Lord and savior, Jesus Christ. Just kidding, it’s “toys.” Toys are …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=nzIYpo0P1Lw:8HhvpzfWmF8:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131254</id>
    <published>2021-12-16T21:03:07Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-16T21:03:07Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Omicron: Is “Less Lethal but More Contagious” Good?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2021/12/omicron-is-less-lethal-but-more-contagious-good/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: You know what I haven’t talked about lately? COVID-19. I mean, I’ve talked about the stuff surrounding it but I haven’t really talked about SARS-CoV-2 itself a lot. To be fair, the basic facts …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Fbjzv9TzyGw:8Nulpl9bzpk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131245</id>
    <published>2021-12-16T16:39:12Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-16T16:39:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The curious mind of a dog</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5899/the-curious-mind-of-a-dog#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2021-12-16-at-10.47.26.jpg" height="862" alt="Screenshot-2021-12-16-at-10.47.26" width="1393" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As soon as Christina and Jake Hunger brought their new puppy home, they were utterly smitten. Stella was a tiny eight-week-old Catahoula-Blue Heeler cross, with rich, chocolate-coloured fur, bat ears and a white bib. Stella was a highly engaging little dog, almost frantic with delight every time they entered the room, wagging her tail so hard it set her whole body a-wiggle.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Puppies are hard work. There was toilet training, nap times, playtime and lead training. At night, Stella often whimpered until Jake went downstairs to sleep by her bed. But Stella was a quick learner too. Some commands, like &amp;ldquo;Come&amp;rdquo;, were easy. They just bent down and patted their knees and Stella would dash right over.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Christina, who works as a speech-language pathologist, was struck by just how precocious her pet was. Sure, Stella was a puppy, but she was also displaying many of the pre-linguistic skills Christina looked for in her nonverbal clients: she maintained eye contact, whined for attention, dropped toys by their feet when she wanted to play, and used gestures to make requests, like pawing at her empty water bowl. Christina started noting down these milestones as she noticed them: already, at two months, Stella was exhibiting over half of the skills a nine-month-old baby might be expected to demonstrate shortly before they begin to say their first words.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the same. Christina knew that. Stella wouldn&amp;rsquo;t keep passing milestones that would, within months, bring her miraculously into the realm of the verbal the way most infant humans are. Still, it was enough to give her pause.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In her job, Christina works with children with developmental issues, finding ways in which they might communicate their wants through non-normative means. This field, known as &amp;ldquo;augmented and alternative communication&amp;rdquo;, or AAC, encompasses many tools and techniques, including sign language and facial expressions, as well as speech-generating devices of the kind used by Stephen Hawking. In AAC, there is no &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; way to communicate, no end goal for clients to aim towards; success is successful communication of intent between two parties, however that&amp;rsquo;s achieved. Often she uses iPad apps, allowing her clients to press buttons that enunciate words or phrases on their behalf &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;More&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Stop&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Hungry&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;All done&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Human devices for canine friends&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;What she likes most about her job is that her clients often surprise both her and their parents with their hidden abilities. Suddenly, children who had seemed oblivious to much of what was going on around them would seize their device and communicate in unexpected bursts, stringing together words they had never before used or even seemed to understand. Sometimes children who seemed to have plateaued would make huge advances once their device was reprogrammed to offer a better range of vocabulary. In this way, Christina had learned never to underestimate how closely someone else might be listening, even if they seemed inattentive or used unusual body language, their verbal speech non-existent.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Christina wondered whether Stella could learn to communicate using similar tools. Could a dog use AAC? She didn&amp;rsquo;t see why not. One evening she found a pack of four &amp;ldquo;recordable answer buzzers&amp;rdquo; online &amp;ndash; easy-press buttons intended for use during parlour games, but perfect for Stella. They were palm-sized and easily compressible by a paw or a muzzle. When triggered, each button would sound a short audio clip. Christina programmed the first button to announce &amp;ldquo;Outside&amp;rdquo;. It would be Stella&amp;rsquo;s first word.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It took a while for the penny to drop, but after three weeks of Christina and Jake pressing the button with their toe and enunciating the word before opening the door, Stella began to pay it a great deal of attention. Sometimes she would bark at the button, as if willing it to activate itself, or tensely sit by it, waiting for them to press it. Christina recognised this behaviour from the children at work: sometimes a child on the cusp of understanding would take her finger in theirs and use it to press the button on their behalf. It was a good sign: this usually happened very shortly before the child first used the device for themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sure enough, a few nights later, Jake woke Christina. It had happened. They rushed downstairs. Stella did it again. Outside. Outside. She seemed delighted with herself, and when they opened the door in response she ran in ecstatic loops around the garden. Jake and Christina were elated.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Since that first button push, Stella has gone on to learn around 50 words: nouns, verbs, adjectives. Christina introduced them slowly and thoughtfully, based largely on her own intuition and her experience of working with children. She also tried to offer Stella what speech-language pathologists call &amp;ldquo;core words&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; that is, the words she would use most often. Then, as with the &amp;ldquo;Outside&amp;rdquo; button, she and Jake would faithfully model the new words every time a suitable situation arose. They&amp;rsquo;d press &amp;ldquo;Water&amp;rdquo; right before they refilled her bowl. Or &amp;ldquo;Play&amp;rdquo; before, during and after a game with a toy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Stella&amp;rsquo;s favourites, of course, were &amp;ldquo;Walk&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Beach&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Park&amp;rdquo;. But she also had &amp;ldquo;Help&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Love you&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Bye&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Bed&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Cat&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Eat&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Play&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Want&amp;rdquo;. Stella was curious and would press buttons to see what happened next. Christina and Jake would enact what the button suggested, and after dozens or hundreds of reinforcements, Stella learned what to expect. Christina wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure that Stella understood the words to mean exactly what we use them to mean, but the connotations were similar. &amp;ldquo;Love you&amp;rdquo; became associated with cuddles, soft voices, sympathetic attention. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Christina was working purely to satisfy her own curiosity. But Stella&amp;rsquo;s progress was quick and caught her by surprise. In early interactions, button usage orbited around requests: &amp;ldquo;Outside&amp;rdquo; to go to the toilet, &amp;ldquo;Help&amp;rdquo; to request assistance with a lost toy. As time went on, Stella began to use the buttons in interesting ways. While watching Christina watering houseplants, she pressed &amp;ldquo;Water&amp;rdquo;; when emotionally charged, she tapped buttons repeatedly. She then began to combine words. &amp;ldquo;Eat no&amp;rdquo; one evening when they got home past her usual dinner time. Later on, &amp;ldquo;Come outside&amp;rdquo;. Further down the line, &amp;ldquo;Stella want play&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The limits of a dog&amp;rsquo;s comprehension&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Christina isn&amp;rsquo;t the first person to explore the limits of a pet dog&amp;rsquo;s language comprehension. Behavioural psychologist Dr John Pilley once taught the collie Chaser the names of 1,000 toys, and later demonstrated that she understood basic grammar. But Christina&amp;rsquo;s AAC board meant she could study not only Stella&amp;rsquo;s comprehension but her capacity for generating language, for two-way communication. The experiment has been successful far beyond what she ever imagined. Throughout, she has documented Stella&amp;rsquo;s progress online, via her popular Instagram account, @hunger4words, where she has amassed close to 800,000 followers, many of them pet owners keen to try Christina&amp;rsquo;s methods for themselves.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Among them is Alexis Devine, an artist based in Tacoma, Washington, who in 2019 bought a bouncy, bed-headed Sheepadoodle (an Old English Sheepdog crossed with a Poodle) called Bunny. She used an AAC system and also began with a simple &amp;ldquo;outside&amp;rdquo; button by the front door. Alexis copied Christina&amp;rsquo;s methods. Over a six-month period she modelled new button usage before combining them into a large wooden &amp;ldquo;keyboard&amp;rdquo; on the floor. Soon she was contacted by Leo Trottier, a cognitive scientist and computer programmer who offered her the use of a prototype canine AAC device, which grouped buttons by type &amp;ndash; activities, objects, places, descriptions &amp;ndash; in a modification of the Fitzgerald Key, a system developed in the early 20th century to help deaf children structure sentences. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Since then, Bunny&amp;rsquo;s progress has been even faster than Stella&amp;rsquo;s. Videos posted by Alexis, who has seven million followers on TikTok (@whataboutbunny), show more than 90 buttons arranged on neat hexagonal tiles. In one viral clip, Bunny looks in the mirror and appears to experience an existential crisis. &amp;ldquo;Who this?&amp;rdquo; she asks. &amp;ldquo;Bunny&amp;rdquo;, Alexis replies. Bunny then walks away and stares through the window before returning to press &amp;ldquo;Help&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Amusing as the videos are, the researchers need harder data to work from. The history of cross-species communication study has been plagued with controversy. In one famous early example, a horse called Clever Hans appeared to perform calculations on request, tapping his hoof on the ground to answer questions like, &amp;ldquo;What is three plus four?&amp;rdquo; Hans would perform when asked both by his owner and by strangers, but it became apparent that he was responding not to the rules of mathematics, but to his questioners&amp;rsquo; body language: when he reached the right answer, they would relax, and he would know to stop tapping.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The science of talking animals&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Clever Hans&amp;rsquo; owner was not a fraudster &amp;ndash; he was utterly convinced of his horse&amp;rsquo;s genius &amp;ndash; and Hans also took in a number of contemporary scientists. What the case demonstrates is just how difficult it can be to disentangle animal comprehension from their responses to subtle cues. &amp;ldquo;The issues of overinterpretation (ie the human interprets the animal signals as more meaningful than they actually are) and cueing (the animal reproducing sequences acquired through extensive learning or simply responding to cues by the human rather than flexibly producing communicative sequences) have long been discussed as some of the main issues of several other animal language studies,&amp;rdquo; explains Federico Rossano, a cognitive scientist at the University of California, San Diego. He has been studying Bunny&amp;rsquo;s progress as part of the &amp;ldquo;They Can Talk&amp;rdquo; research project, which aims to apply &amp;ldquo;a rigorous scientific approach to determine whether, and if so, how and how much non-humans are able to express themselves in language-like ways.&amp;rdquo; Bunny is only one of 3,000 pets taking part in &amp;ldquo;They Can Talk&amp;rdquo;, in which Rossano, Trottier and others have been analysing the dogs&amp;rsquo; keypad logs and the context in which the buttons are used. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The key requirement for them to be classed as language users, in Rossano&amp;rsquo;s opinion, is that the dogs must be able to combine and recombine the various words in different contexts &amp;ndash; that is, not simply asking &amp;ldquo;Where dad?&amp;rdquo;, as Bunny has done when Alexis&amp;rsquo; partner goes to work, but also asking &amp;ldquo;Where mum?&amp;rdquo; when Alexis leaves, and so on. &amp;ldquo;If she repeats or slightly modifies sequences when she does not get a response and clearly orients towards the human while producing the button presses, it would appear more likely that she is trying to communicate something.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rossano and his team have installed five cameras in Alexis&amp;rsquo; house to allow a constant livestream to be beamed to Rossano&amp;rsquo;s lab. &amp;ldquo;Having the cameras on Bunny&amp;rsquo;s board takes some of the pressure off of me feeling like I have to personally record everything,&amp;rdquo; explains Alexis. It also removes any suspicion that she might be selectively editing their interactions. So far, Rossano says, the data is quite convincing. The &amp;ldquo;They Can Talk&amp;rdquo; team is preparing to present their findings to the scientific community. It&amp;rsquo;s important, he says, to &amp;ldquo;retain a healthy scientific scepticism&amp;rdquo;. Nevertheless, &amp;ldquo;the evidence points pretty clearly towards them [the pets in the study] communicating with the humans while using these devices&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alexis too is keen to underline that she does not know exactly how much Bunny understands of their interaction. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve been open about the importance of scepticism, and the difficulty of avoiding implicit bias from the beginning, and thankfully I personally am not tasked with proving or disproving anything. Our journey is about curiosity, connection and exploring the depths of communication with a non-human animal, and I think that&amp;rsquo;s pretty important regardless of the eventual scientific findings.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Shaping a dog's mind and body&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dog owners are not unbiased parties when it comes to assessing their own pet&amp;rsquo;s mental abilities. This much is obvious. I&amp;rsquo;m a dog owner, and I can tell you this for free. When dog owners speak to one another, we often expound at length upon our pets&amp;rsquo; habits and personalities, their likes and dislikes, even their opinions or dreams. Some of these impressions may well be true. It&amp;rsquo;s also possible, even likely, that we are wrong more often than not.&lt;br /&gt;We project a great deal onto our wordless companions, and pride ourselves in playing a protective, even parental, role in their lives. They offer us clues as to their feelings, moods and wants, but we can never truly know what they are thinking. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s for the best: &amp;ldquo;no small amount of dogs&amp;rsquo; winsomeness is the empathy that we can attribute to them as they silently contemplate us,&amp;rdquo; wrote the cognitive scientist Alexandra Horowitz, director of the Dog Cognition Lab at Barnard College, in &lt;em&gt;Inside of a Dog&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nevertheless, the relationship between dog and human is unusually close thanks to an estimated 11,000 years of domestication. We feed them, care for them and breed them selectively for friendliness and other useful traits. We have shaped almost every attribute of their bodies and minds. They live in our homes and play important roles in many industries. In various ways, dogs have shaped us too.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If any animal was likely to excel at communication with humans, it would be the dog. Yet until now, there has been surprisingly little study of them. Past animal communication researchers have instead opted for gorillas, chimpanzees, bonobos and even dolphins. But monkeys and apes, for all their human-like characteristics, are notoriously erratic, even aggressive. Dolphins, being water-based, bring myriad logistical problems. Dogs, meanwhile, are domestic companions, unusually easy to train, responsive to human commands and body language, and are often &amp;ndash; but not invariably &amp;ndash; keen to please. For these reasons, the Soviet space programme, unlike Nasa&amp;rsquo;s, opted to use dogs in early rocket launches after circus trainers warned them that monkeys were too temperamental to be useful. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Their attentiveness and intelligence is part of what makes dogs so appealing, but our love for them is also part of the reason why it&amp;rsquo;s so difficult to lay aside scepticism. &amp;ldquo;It is not the animals who desire to speak and cannot, I suspect; it is that we desire them to talk and cannot effect it,&amp;rdquo; writes Horowitz. In past interviews, Horowitz has called for research to focus on dogs&amp;rsquo; natural modes of communication and behaviour, rather on their capacity to learn or respond to ours. Nevertheless, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult not to get excited by Bunny and Stella&amp;rsquo;s conversational prowess, and the small glimmers they offer us as to how canine minds might work.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We may never know if the dogs are using and comprehending human language to mean exactly the same as we do. But if nothing else, it gives us a great deal of insight into our relationship with them as a species, their concerns and their personalities. As for my own dog, I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet tried to teach her to speak. I very much want to learn her innermost desires, but I suspect she has little interest in communicating with me on my own terms. If she did, I imagine it might closely resemble the one-track conversation of scrappy Bastian, a rescued terrier in New York City (@bastianandbrews), who will scratch the relevant buttons repeatedly until their covers fly off. &amp;ldquo;Hungry hungry hungry hungry,&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;food food food food treat treat treat treat food food food.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Still, who can blame him? I think I can relate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5899/the-curious-mind-of-a-dog#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-12-16T10:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-16T10:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Myth Management</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/12/myth-management/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The scientific method is, without a doubt, the best means of arriving at the truth ever devised. We flawed humans can and do make mistakes in its execution, but the rigorous application of science is what allows us to make discoveries and, perhaps most importantly, verify the …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977833</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T17:21:24Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T17:21:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Education"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hitting the Books with TIES</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/12/hitting-the-books-with-ties/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since 2015, the Teacher Institute for Evolutionary Science (TIES), a program of the Richard Dawkins Foundation, has been giving teachers the tools they need to effectively teach evolution and answer its critics. After producing hundreds of workshops, dozens of webinars, and troves of free resources and guided lessons, the people who power TIES have learned …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977828</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T17:07:04Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T17:07:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Education"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Unabated Unaffiliation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/12/unabated-unaffiliation/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A decade ago, about one out of every five American adults were religiously unaffiliated, according to Pew Research, and that was a big deal. Today in 2021, that number has leapt to three-in-ten. A brand new survey from Pew shows the “rise of the Nones” shows no sign of abating, jumping to 29 percent of …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977823</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T17:00:40Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T17:00:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="News Article"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The One-Man War on Christmas</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/12/the-one-man-war-on-christmas/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 1993, Tom Flynn published the groundbreaking and controversial book The Trouble with Christmas, arguing that it was long past time for the abandonment of this Christian holiday, particularly for nonbelievers. It also brought to life Tom’s perennial alter-ego, the Anti-Claus.  Tom died suddenly this past August, and the latest issue of the magazine he …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977818</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T16:55:57Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T16:55:57Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Jesus Debate</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/12/the-jesus-debate/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Christians believe that Jesus was the son of God and that he walked the Earth as a human being a couple millennia ago. Atheists obviously don’t believe in God, let alone that he produced offspring. But there is less of a consensus around whether the historical Jesus—a mere mortal member of Homo sapiens—ever existed. On …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977811</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T16:52:45Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T16:52:45Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Break the Cycle of Poverty: Give Poor People Money</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2021/12/break-the-cycle-of-poverty-give-poor-people-money/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Tis the season of giving, and thus it’s a great time to evaluate the many ways we give to others who are in desperate need. For instance, a few years ago I made a video …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=265WwAvH9g4:dOhEzgqapg8:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131243</id>
    <published>2021-12-15T15:38:55Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-15T15:38:55Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can GOOP help get you DTF for Christmas?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2021/12/can-goop-help-get-you-dtf-for-christmas/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The world is going to hell in a handbasket and it’s looking like we’re riding another massive COVID wave into 2022, so why not take a break from it all? Read something fun? Like this short stroll down memory lane and look at whether GOOP has something for the sex drive that constant existential dread …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ob2PyiXEUMc:diodMEEy3bs:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Bjørnar</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131221</id>
    <published>2021-12-14T16:30:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-14T16:30:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Study: Why Zoom Meetings are Worse for Women</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2021/12/study-why-zoom-meetings-are-worse-for-women/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Remember when the whole pandemic thing really got going in early 2020, and most of us at least kind of tried to quarantine? And then we missed our friends, and a company was like “Hey, …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=u6SwJ4NuNpg:3l8bVa9mlJg:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131226</id>
    <published>2021-12-13T18:18:40Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-13T18:18:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In the US, 'civil religion' ensures church and state remain tied at the hip</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5904/in-the-us-civil-religion-ensures-church-and-state-remain-tied-at-the-hip#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="US coins were inscribed with 'In God We Trust' following the US Civil War (image taken from QuoteInspector.com)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/money-qi57-md.jpg" height="480" alt="money-qi57-md" width="720" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The First Amendment to the US Constitution prevents the government from making laws designed to regulate the establishment of any religion, or that would prohibit the free exercise of religion. Yet the US remains a decidedly "Christian" nation. Nearly all US Presidents have &lt;a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/fact-tank/2021/01/20/biden-only-second-catholic-president-but-nearly-all-have-been-christians-2/"&gt;professed&lt;/a&gt; to follow some form of the Christian faith. Only Presidents Lincoln and Jefferson have claimed no religious affiliation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Historically, the sitting president's personal faith has been reflected in the overall populace. The Public Religion Research Institute &lt;a href="https://www.prri.org/research/2020-census-of-american-religion/"&gt;notes&lt;/a&gt; that 70 per cent of Americans identify as Christian, and 5 per cent identify with non-Christian religions. Nearly a quarter are religiously unaffiliated. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Given the preponderance of US citizens who claim to be Christians, how is this ideal of the separation of church and state enacted within the public square? Rob Boston, Director of Communications at &lt;a href="https://www.au.org/"&gt;Americans United&lt;/a&gt;, a nonpartisan educational and advocacy organization dedicated to advancing the separation of religion and government, explains that while the United States operates under the separation of church and state, &amp;ldquo;there has always been something of a carve out for what scholars call &amp;lsquo;civil religion&amp;rsquo; &amp;ndash; that is, the tendency of government and political leaders to use religion (usually in a generic sense) to buttress perceived national goals.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Perhaps the most explicit recent example of this came during the Trump administration. Throughout his time in office, Trump &lt;a href="https://thehumanist.com/commentary/let-us-say-its-time-to-end-the-national-prayer-breakfast"&gt;displayed&lt;/a&gt; a politicised version of Christianity that contained a toxic mixture of conservative white evangelicalism, prosperity gospel preaching, and Christian nationalism. His policies were not reflective of the will of the majority of Americans but instead tended to reflect his Christian nationalist policy goals. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Upon initial glance, the Biden administration may present itself as less outwardly "religious" than Trump&amp;rsquo;s. For instance, as &lt;a href="https://religiondispatches.org/2021-national-prayer-breakfast-a-kinder-gentler-form-of-christian-capitalism/"&gt;reported&lt;/a&gt; at Religion Dispatches, during the 2021 National Prayer Breakfast, President Joe Biden offered a bipartisan message of national unity and faith in light of the January 6 Capitol insurrection, with even Fox News &lt;a href="https://www.foxnews.com/politics/biden-addresses-national-prayer-breakfast"&gt;highlighting&lt;/a&gt; Biden&amp;rsquo;s call to end &amp;ldquo;political extremism.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yet Biden&amp;rsquo;s endorsement by progressive faith leaders, as well as events like the virtual &lt;a href="https://www.americamagazine.org/politics-society/2020/09/04/biden-campaign-launches-catholic-voter-outreach-initiative"&gt;Catholics for Biden&lt;/a&gt; voter outreach campaign and the rise of organizations like Evangelicals for Biden and The New Moral Majority point to the continued infusion of faith and politics within the US administration. It may manifest in a somewhat kinder, gentler expression, yet the ongoing problematic practice of &amp;ldquo;civil religion", in which an administration&amp;rsquo;s national policy agenda is influenced by its religious orientation, remains in place. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Politicians, prayer and "God talk"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;For decades, American civil religion has been seen most visibly through the National Prayer Breakfast, an annual gathering of US politicians, pastors and industry leaders. Despite the fact that it is sponsored by a secretive private Christian group titled The Family (aka The Fellowship Foundation), invitations are issued on congressional letterhead and the press secure their access via the White House. Ever since President Dwight D. Eisenhower delivered the inaugural address in 1953, every US president has addressed this gathering. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;During the Eisenhower era from 1953 to 1961, Christianity became identified as the country's overall civil religion. &amp;ldquo;Under God&amp;rdquo; became part of the Pledge of Allegiance, and &amp;ldquo;In God We Trust&amp;rdquo; was added to the US paper currency (and to US coins after the Civil War). Politicians regularly employ &amp;ldquo;God talk&amp;rdquo; in speeches, call on Americans to pray during times of crisis or uncertainty, and offer prayers before meetings of local, state, and federal governments. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Supreme Court of the United States has issued rulings in favour of church and state separation, including &lt;a href="https://www.uscourts.gov/educational-resources/educational-activities/facts-and-case-summary-engel-v-vitale"&gt;banning prayer in public schools&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://mtsu.edu/first-amendment/article/37/bob-jones-university-v-united-states"&gt;permitting&lt;/a&gt; the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) to deny tax-exempt status to institutions whose policies are &amp;ldquo;contrary to established public policy,&amp;rdquo; even if those policies are based on religious beliefs. However, as Rob Boston has noted, US Courts have also ruled that certain forms of &amp;ldquo;civil religion" are legal. This can be seen in court rulings granting individuals exemptions based on religious beliefs to, for example, the government-mandated Covid-19 &lt;a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/health-law-and-business/courts-clash-over-religious-exemptions-for-vaccine-mandates"&gt;vaccine&lt;/a&gt;. "Given the current conservative cast of the Supreme Court, that is not likely to change anytime soon," Boston says. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Christian pastors and leading faith-based institutions can, according to Boston, endorse candidates for public office in their private capacities. However, they are not legally allowed to use the resources of their houses of worship or faith-based nonprofit to support or oppose a political candidate, nor are they permitted to issue statements of support or opposition from the pulpit. All the same, the IRS has not, in a number of years, penalised those churches who use their pulpit for political purposes. The last &lt;a href="https://nonprofitquarterly.org/senator-grassley-and-the-televangelists/"&gt;attempt&lt;/a&gt; by Congress in 2007 to force ministries to provide greater fiscal accountability failed to garner traction. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While political candidates and elected officials can and should hear from faith communities about their concerns and views on social issues, public officials should be careful to include diverse faith and secular voices in discussions on public policy. Boston cites as one example former President Trump's creation of an Evangelical Advisory Board that was not inclusive of the full spectrum of faith and nonreligious communities in America. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Despite now being out of the presidency, Trump's public support among white evangelicals continues to rise in part due to his ongoing support of faith-based &lt;a href="https://divinity.uchicago.edu/sightings/articles/why-white-evangelicals-stuck-trump"&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; that matter to evangelical leaders, such as abortion and religious freedom. White evangelicals in the pews also remain attracted to Republican positions on the economy, national security, and immigration. According to the &lt;a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/politics/2021/06/30/behind-bidens-2020-victory/"&gt;Pew Research Center&lt;/a&gt;, 77 per cent of this demographic supported Trump in 2016, a number that increased to 84 per cent in 2020.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The rise of the irreligious US voting bloc&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;While these debates continue to rage, the religious composition of the US continues to grow more pluralistic. &amp;ldquo;Nones&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; people who profess no religious affiliation - &lt;a href="https://thehumanist.com/commentary/debunking-rise-democratic-christian-voters"&gt;represent&lt;/a&gt; 24 per cent of US voters. As the Pew Research Center has noted, Biden's win can be attributed in part to the fact that more atheists and agnostics voted for him in 2020 than they did Hillary Clinton in 2016. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Most politicians remain entrenched in their old patterns, and despite a 2019 &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2019/04/13/us/no-religion-largest-group-first-time-usa-trnd/index.html"&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; finding that there are as many nonreligious Americans as there are Catholics or evangelicals, they continue to engage in efforts to reach the faithful in the pews. To date, neither the Democrats or Republicans have launched any significant initiatives to target the growing voting block that professes no religious affiliation. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The US electorate is changing. It&amp;rsquo;s time the political establishment took note and responded to the will of the people and not their faith-based funding streams.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5904/in-the-us-civil-religion-ensures-church-and-state-remain-tied-at-the-hip#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-12-13T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-13T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The art of the blag</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5892/the-art-of-the-blag#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Rowson.jpg" height="608" alt="Illustration by Martin Rowson" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was Janet Dobson who first suggested that I was degree material. I was 23 at the time and working as a linkman outside the Odeon cinema in Leicester Square. Although the job had its perks &amp;ndash; a rather fetching brown and gold uniform and regular tips from cinemagoers who needed help parking their cars &amp;ndash; it was not an occupation that offered great hope of advancement. And, as Janet pointed out, an ability to stand upright outside a building for five hours at a time hardly qualified me for any other position.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;You should try for Birkbeck College,&amp;rdquo; urged Janet. &amp;ldquo;They take people without the usual qualifications on their evening degree courses.&amp;rdquo; As I undid the gold buttons of my uniform that night, I did so with a new resolve.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The application form seemed straightforward enough until I reached the final paragraph: &amp;ldquo;State your principal hobbies.&amp;rdquo; What hobbies? Hobbies meant collecting. And had I ever collected anything? Stamps? Not really. Butterflies? No. Early Victorian etchings? Certainly not. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But what about bus tickets? When I was about 11, a classmate, Ken Rogers, told me a secret. Apparently if you collected a bus ticket on which all the numbers added up to 21 &amp;ndash; say 4, 8, 7, 2 &amp;ndash; then you could show this ticket to any girl and she would immediately grant you special favours. In Ken&amp;rsquo;s measured words, &amp;ldquo;She&amp;rsquo;ll be up for it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Even if Ken had been right, I could hardly expect that my Birkbeck invigilators would regard my clumsy numerical attempts to seduce third-form schoolgirls as somehow equivalent to a lifetime collecting butterflies or Commonwealth stamps.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Neither, in all conscience, could I cite my junior school collection of birds&amp;rsquo; eggs. That had now become a hobby that dare not speak its name. For although we had a tacit agreement that we would only take one egg from any of the nests that we raided, it was difficult to evade the charge that our concerted efforts were doing much to further the imminent extinction of the Pied Flycatcher. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I did remember one other activity that might just pass muster as a hobby. From the age of nine I&amp;rsquo;d assiduously racked up a complete set of Catholic indulgences. Back then a whole range of devotional activities came with a promise of relief from eternal damnation. So if you regularly attended Holy Mass on the first Friday of nine consecutive months, you were assured by serious theologians that you would evade everlasting Hell. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Once again, however, this seemed to fall short. It was difficult to imagine a vice-chancellor, or even a registrar, admitting an applicant on the grounds that his hobby would eventually ensure eternal life in the blessed company of saints and archangels.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was Janet who came to the rescue. She asked her graduate friends how they had filled in their applications. Yes, they&amp;rsquo;d all been required to state a hobby and many had opted for brass rubbing. There was a good reason. Whereas other hobbies required some basic knowledge &amp;ndash; an ability, say, to translate the foreign words on postage stamps or to know the fine distinction between a Red Admiral and a Clouded Skipper butterfly &amp;ndash; brass rubbing required nothing more than a sheet of tracing paper and the tomb of some long-forgotten saint in the local parish church. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;Brass rubbing?&amp;rdquo; queried the Birkbeck registrar. I was ready for him. &amp;ldquo;Oh yes,&amp;rdquo; I said. &amp;ldquo;You only need a sheet of tracing paper and the tomb of some long-forgotten saint in your local parish church.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Well, Mr Taylor,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;You have not exactly impressed the panel with the news that you wish to study psychology because you are interested in other people. But, on balance, we are happy to offer you a place on the grounds that you should enjoy a great deal of fellowship with your other first-year undergraduates. None of them may have any expertise in the psychological processes of learning, memory or motivation. But to a man and a woman they are all brass rubbers. You never know, perhaps they will let you share their tracing paper!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter 2021 edition. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5892/the-art-of-the-blag#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-12-13T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-12-13T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" alt="71K22hD8AqL" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750 750w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1500 1500w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Magic Award</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our first award focused on performers who use magic tricks to improve the lives of others, including work with disadvantaged groups, hospital patients, and schools. The judges selected two great winners: Megan Swann (who presents a magic show that promotes environmental issues) and Breathe Magic (who support children with hemiplegia by helping them to learn tricks that improve physical and psychological wellbeing).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This year, the award will provide £2,000 to support a new and innovative project that promotes the art of magic. This might, for example, include developing a live or virtual performance, writing a magic-related book or essay, creating a podcast, devising a new form of illusion or presentation, or undertaking research into the history of magic. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Applicants need to be over 18 years old and currently residing in the UK, and nominations will close at 5pm (GMT) on 20th February 2021.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To enter, please head over to &lt;a href="https://goodthinkingsociety.org/projects/the-good-magic-awards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"&gt;The Good Thinking Society&lt;/a&gt; now! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards. Our first award focused… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Good Magic Award</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12851</id>
    <published>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evidence to House of Commons Sci Tech Select Committee on Research Integrity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/12/evidence-to-house-of-commons-sci-tech-select-committee-on-research-integrity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry not to be in regular blogging mode at the moment. Here’s a video of our evidence session to parliament, where they are running an inquiry into research integrity. I think clinical trials are the best possible way to approach this issue. Lots of things in “research integrity” are hard to capture in hard logical […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3498</id>
    <published>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</updated>
    <category term="alltrials campaign"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do the world’s biggest drug companies compare, in their transparency commitments?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/how-do-the-worlds-biggest-drug-companies-compare-in-their-transparency-commitments/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hereâ€™s a paper, and associated website, that we launch today: we have assessed, and then ranked, all the biggest drug companies in the world, to compare their public commitments on trials transparency. Regular readers will be familiar with this ongoing battle. In medicine we use the results of clinical trials to make informed treatments about […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3485</id>
    <published>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meaningful Transparency Commitments: the WHO Joint Statement from Trial Funders</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/meaningful-transparency-commitments-the-who-joint-statement-from-trial-funders/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By now I hope you all know about the ongoing global scandal of clinical trial results being left unpublished, and of course our AllTrials campaign. Doctors, researchers, and patients cannot make truly informed choices about which treatments work best if they don’t have access to all the trial results. Earlier this year, I helped out […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3481</id>
    <published>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/02/how-many-epidemiologists-does-it-take-to-change-a-lightbulb/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robin Ince just asked if I know any epidemiologist lightbulb jokes. I wrote this for him. How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb? Weâ€™ve found 12,000 switches hidden around the house. Some of them turn this lightbulb on, some of them donâ€™t; some of them only work sometimes; and some of them […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3472</id>
    <published>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“Transparency, Beyond Publication Bias”. A video of my super-speedy talk at IJE.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2016/10/transparency-beyond-publication-bias-a-video-of-my-super-speedy-talk-at-ije/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">People oftenÂ talk about “trials transparency” as if this means “all trials must be published in an academic journal”. In reality, true transparency goes much further than this. We need Clinical Study Reports, and individual patient data, of course. But we also need the consent forms, so we can see what patients were told. We need […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3463</id>
    <published>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
