<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-06-04T14:32:03Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Textbook Giveaway #3!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/03/textbook-giveaway-3/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3-500x436.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="436" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66770" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3-500x436.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3-150x131.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3-300x262.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3-768x670.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/giveaway3.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I’ve told you the way this works a few times now. Just leave a comment telling me which book you want and why, and I’ll choose someone to receive a free book. These are generally not easy to read popular books — these are reference texts, kind of on the dense and heavy side, but full of information.<br/>
Your choices this time are:<br/>
<i>Fundamentals of Human Physiology</i>, by Stuart Ira Fox. Yeah, I’m not ashamed to admit it, I’ve taught A&amp;P. I hope I never have to again, so I can bear to part with this one. I’ve still got several others.<br/>
<i>An Introduction to Biological Evolution</i>, by Kenneth Kardong. This is a fairly slender paperbound text, a little on the light side for what I want when teaching evolution. It’s not bad, though.<br/>
<i>Neuroscience</i>, by Purves and others. Also pretty good, if not the massive magisterial monster text of Kandel. This one I think is already earmarked for someone who asked for a neuro text in Giveaway #2. (Trust me, you don’t want Kandel unless you need to press a witch to death.)<br/>
There are many more on my shelves. If you don’t get it this time, check again next month for a different selection.</p>
<p>This is as announced on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/67309566">my Patreon page</a>, but you don’t need to sign up to win a book.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’ve told you the way this works a few times now. Just leave a comment telling me which book you want and why, and I’ll choose someone to receive a free book. These are generally not easy to read popular books — these are reference texts, kind of on the dense and heavy side, but […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66769</id>
    <published>2022-06-03T19:20:30Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-03T19:20:30Z</updated>
    <category term="Books"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I f’in hate evolutionary psychology</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/03/i-fin-hate-evolutionary-psychology/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;Sorry, I saw this evo psych study and had to vent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;found this evo psych paper which asks the pressing question: do guys living under a neoliberal capitalist realism hellscape like big boobs? &lt;a href="https://t.co/v9d28u02Zn"&gt;pic.twitter.com/v9d28u02Zn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; evo psych googling (@evopsychgoogle) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/evopsychgoogle/status/1532725705771220992?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 3, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the protocol: subjects were primed with powerpoint slides of modern economic devastation with an explicit slide with text saying the 21st century is a &amp;#8220;harsh and unpredictable world&amp;#8221;. The controls, near as I can tell, saw the same slides without the text. Then they flashed a slide of topless women&amp;#8217;s torsos with breasts of varying shapes and sizes, and asked the subjects to rate the women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me just say that if you&amp;#8217;re doing any kind of psych study that ends with a request to rate women&amp;#8217;s breasts, you&amp;#8217;re doing something wrong. I can&amp;#8217;t even begin to unpack all the assumptions you&amp;#8217;ve pre-loaded into the work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then the results are underwhelming: a bunch of bar graphs that show very little variation in the responses, with a few showing statistically significant but totally unimpressive differences. &lt;q&gt;Overall, men rated women with larger breasts as more attractive, fertile, healthier, reproductively successful, and likely to befriend&lt;/q&gt;. The n was 144, all drawn from college students at a midwestern American university, so of course we can infer universal principles of human evolution from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s the kind of graph you can make as an evo psych goofball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/breastcupsize.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/breastcupsize.png" alt="" width="329" height="520" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-66767" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/breastcupsize.png 329w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/breastcupsize-95x150.png 95w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/breastcupsize-190x300.png 190w" sizes="(max-width: 329px) 100vw, 329px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dazzling information. If you hate yourself as much as I do, you can &lt;a href="https://link.springer.com/content/pdf/10.1007/s40806-020-00262-w.pdf"&gt;read the paper&lt;/a&gt;, too. It&amp;#8217;s awful. So many statistics to strain to extract something significant from noisy data already compromised by cultural indoctrination.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry, I saw this evo psych study and had to vent. found this evo psych paper which asks the pressing question: do guys living under a neoliberal capitalist realism hellscape like big boobs? pic.twitter.com/v9d28u02Zn — evo psych googling (@evopsychgoogle) June 3, 2022 Here’s the protocol: subjects were primed with powerpoint slides of modern economic devastation […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66766</id>
    <published>2022-06-03T14:41:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-03T14:41:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How did one sentence become the Sacred, Inviolable Word of the Constitution?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/03/how-did-one-sentence-become-the-sacred-inviolable-word-of-the-constitution/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;You know the sentence: “A well regu­lated mili­tia, being neces­sary for the secur­ity of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.” It&amp;#8217;s Holy Writ. It may not be questioned, or at least, the interpretation that means anyone can own a weapon of mass murder, may not be questioned. One may wonder how that came to be, especially given the more limiting interpretation that prevailed over most of American history. Here&amp;#8217;s a &lt;a href="https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/research-reports/how-nra-rewrote-second-amendment"&gt;good summary of the twists and turns that led to our current armed state&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“A fraud on the Amer­ican public.” That’s how former Chief Justice Warren Burger described the idea that the Second Amend­ment gives an unfettered indi­vidual right to a gun. When he spoke these words to PBS in 1990, the rock-ribbed conser­vat­ive appoin­ted by Richard Nixon was express­ing the long­time consensus of histor­i­ans and judges across the polit­ical spec­trum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-five years later, Burger’s view seems as quaint as a powdered wig. Not only is an indi­vidual right to a fire­arm widely accep­ted, but increas­ingly states are also passing laws to legal­ize carry­ing weapons on streets, in parks, in bars—even in churches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many are startled to learn that the U.S. Supreme Court didn’t rule that the Second Amend­ment guar­an­tees an indi­vidu­al’s right to own a gun until 2008, when District of Columbia v. Heller struck down the capit­al’s law effect­ively banning hand­guns in the home. In fact, every other time the court had ruled previ­ously, it had ruled other­wise. Why such a head-snap­ping turn­around? Don’t look for answers in dusty law books or the arcane reaches of theory.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know, it has the words &amp;#8220;well regulated militia&amp;#8221; right there in the sentence, and it turns out the phrase &amp;#8220;bear arms&amp;#8221; had a very specific meaning to the Sacred Founding Fathers: it didn&amp;#8217;t mean to just carry a musket in case you saw a squirrel to shoot, it had the implication of being armed in warfare. That&amp;#8217;s all been lost, thanks to the activities of one effective organization, the goddamned NRA. The NRA has only a partial quote on the wall of their building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today at the NRA’s headquar­ters in Fair­fax, Virginia, over­sized letters on the facade no longer refer to “marks­man­ship” and “safety.” Instead, the Second Amend­ment is emblazoned on a wall of the build­ing’s lobby. Visit­ors might not notice that the text is incom­plete. It reads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“.. the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first half—the part about the well regu­lated mili­tia—has been edited out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting. Also revealing is this interview with attendees at the NRA conference this past week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QL9hILfREL8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gun-waving fanatics will defend to the death the Holy Second Amendment, but they don&amp;#8217;t even know what it says, despite being only one sentence long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then to learn that the whole modern justification for ubiquitous guns is built on lies, half-truths, and quote mining…jesus, what an embarrassing foundation of pseudo-scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Thomas Jeffer­son offers numer­ous oppor­tun­it­ies for pro-gun advoc­ates. “Histor­ical research demon­strates the Founders out-‘NRAing’ even the NRA,” proclaimed one prolific scholar. “‘One loves to possess arms’ wrote Thomas Jeffer­son, the premier intel­lec­tual of his day, to George Wash­ing­ton on June 19, 1796.” What a find! Oops: Jeffer­son was not talk­ing about guns. He was writ­ing to Wash­ing­ton asking for copies of some old letters, to have handy so he could issue a rebut­tal in case he got attacked for a decision he made as secret­ary of state. The NRA website still includes the quote. You can go online to buy a T-shirt emblazoned with Jeffer­son’s mangled words.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought creationists were the most shameless of liars, but gun-fondlers are giving them a run for the money. Although I also suspect there&amp;#8217;s a huge overlap between gun-fondlers and bible-thumpers.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You know the sentence: “A well regu­lated mili­tia, being neces­sary for the secur­ity of a free state, the right of the people to keep and bear arms, shall not be infringed.” It’s Holy Writ. It may not be questioned, or at least, the interpretation that means anyone can own a weapon of mass murder, may […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66764</id>
    <published>2022-06-03T13:55:48Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-03T13:55:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Gun Fondlers"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What is going on in Ohio?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/03/what-is-going-on-in-ohio/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;The state seems to be a magnet for bad political ideas, and is striving to become the Yankee Texas. Recently, it was the &lt;a href="https://my.lwv.org/sites/default/files/leagues/wysiwyg/%5Bcurrent-user%3Aog-user-node%3A1%3Atitle%5D/ohios_gerrymanding_problem.pdf"&gt;extreme gerrymandering that no one wants to fix&lt;/a&gt; (hey, maybe political parties shouldn&amp;#8217;t be in charge of defining districts?), and now…this new law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Finally got Sub HB 151, which includes Ohio&amp;#39;s &amp;quot;Save Women&amp;#39;s Sports Act.&amp;quot; This passed close to midnight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Section C has the verification process if accused of being trans.&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8211; External and internal genitalia evaluation&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8211; Testosterone level check&lt;br /&gt;&amp;#8211; Genetic makeup test&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WEWS?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@WEWS&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/ZhtGOcx4DY"&gt;pic.twitter.com/ZhtGOcx4DY&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Morgan Trau (News Reporter) (@MorganTrau) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/MorganTrau/status/1532417493658177536?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;June 2, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/OhioBill.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/OhioBill.png" alt="" width="468" height="217" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-66762" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/OhioBill.png 468w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/OhioBill-150x70.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/OhioBill-300x139.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;re unhappy that you lost a contest in high school, just accuse your opponent of being transgender, and demand a thorough investigation. Ohio Republicans will help by demanding that their pants be pulled down to inspect their genitals, followed by an invasive internal inspection, then a blood draw to have their testosterone levels measured, and a cheek swab to check out their chromosomes. FREEDOM! They&amp;#8217;re the party that is going to get the intrusive legislation of Big Government off your backs by legislating that your school can insist on ad hoc genital, hormone, and chromosome inspections, all in the name of protecting women&amp;#8217;s sports.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yeah, that&amp;#8217;s exactly what women athletes have been demanding, that others can request gynecological exams at will.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The state seems to be a magnet for bad political ideas, and is striving to become the Yankee Texas. Recently, it was the extreme gerrymandering that no one wants to fix (hey, maybe political parties shouldn’t be in charge of defining districts?), and now…this new law. Finally got Sub HB 151, which includes Ohio's "Save […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66761</id>
    <published>2022-06-03T13:26:11Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-03T13:26:11Z</updated>
    <category term="Feminism, Gender, and Equality"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“University” is not a word that should be associated with “scam”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/03/university-is-not-a-word-that-should-be-associated-with-scam/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I think it’s part of the Right’s efforts to undermine education — steal the word “university” and attach it to rank garbage. Think PragerU. Think Trump University. Think <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/11/17/i-had-to-get-this-video-out-fast/">University of Austin</a>. All trash. Now how about this: a <a href="https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2019/05/26/woolf-the-university-on-the-blockchain-or-not/">blockchain university, Woolf U</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>In a lengthy August 2018 interview with Disruption Hub, Woolf’s founder Joshua Broggi — a philosopher of religion at Wolfson College, Oxford — tells how he was first inspired to blockchain by a student who wanted to pay his university fees in cryptocurrency.</p>
<p>Broggi thinks “blockchain” could solve all manner of issues in higher education, even the problem with adjunct teaching, the gig economy of academia — “when I look around my faculty, they spend a significant portion of their time acquiring their next temporary position, and that’s really a wasteful use of these extremely talented peoples’ time” — even though Woolf’s plan is also a gig economy. His answer to this detail is that the Woolf model will assure a steady supply of students for the independently-contracting academics to teach.</p>
<p>As of October 2018, Broggi was still confident in the blockchain approach — “We literally could not do what we are doing without a blockchain,” he told ABC News — though actual blockchain academic Michèle Finck told ABC she considered the project fundamentally “misunderstands what a university education is about,” and would be a GDPR disaster.</p>
<p>Broggi also stated at this time that tuition would be $5,000 per year — down from the $19,200 he had estimated in March 2018.</p></blockquote>
<p>Perhaps it’s my limited imagination, but I fail to see how blockchain helps anything here. Broggi seems to be getting fired up about a tool (a bad tool) for managing payments to administrators, which is a bizarre focus for a university, but a pretty good one for a scam, where the money rolling in is all that matters. I’m trying to remember the 1980s when spreadsheets were all the rage…did anyone propose a Spreadsheet University, where everyone was excited about using VisiCalc to track budgets and grades? This is not to imply that blockchain has all the utility of a spreadsheet — it doesn’t — or that spreadsheets aren’t extremely useful for managing grades (I use them all the time), but that no one would look at a tool like that and say, “Hmmm. I am inspired to wrap a whole university in that, it’s far more important than trivialities like a curriculum.”</p>
<p>Poor Broggi. He seems to have lately realized that you shouldn’t name your scam “Scam University”, and “blockchain” has become synonymous with “scam”, so he’s had to delete the word “blockchain” from his promotional materials.</p>
<blockquote><p>The word “blockchain” seems to have vanished from Woolf’s site some time between September 2018 and January 2019 — and the page title changed from “Building The First Blockchain University” to “Building a Borderless University.” The main headline is now “Not your typical online university,” and the front page speaks of video tutorials with a “real professor” and two or three students.</p></blockquote>
<p>That leaves me wondering what makes Woolf University different from other fly-by-night student-loan-exploiting fake university out there. The answer is…nothing.</p>
<hr/>
<p>Oh hey, speaking of fake universities, let’s check in with the University of Austin. June 2022 is a big month for them, because this is when they have their very first course offering, “<a href="https://www.uaustin.org/forbidden-courses">The Forbidden Courses</a>“. They’ve had to scale back a bit, unsurprisingly. The courses will not be held in Austin — they’ve rented some lovely spaces in Dallas for the whole thing. The “course” is all of 4 days long, and there are two course sessions…you could apply for both if you wanted.  It is not accredited.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>No, our program is not a credit-bearing or degreed program. Students may not earn continuing education credits, credit hours, or a diploma for participation in this program. Each course will occur over ten hours in one week.</p></blockquote>
<p>The “course” itself is an incoherent schmear. They’ve gathered together a set of ideologues and told them, apparently, to talk about whatever they feel like. There is no clear theme, no synthesis, just third-rate conservative rock stars asked to talk at the students.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>WEEK ONE</p>
<p>Niall Ferguson on free vs. unfree societies in the 20th century<br/>
Ayaan Hirsi Ali on free speech, religion, and women’s rights<br/>
Dorian Abbot on approaches to climate change<br/>
Rob Henderson on the psychology of social status</p>
<p>WEEK TWO</p>
<p>Kathleen Stock on varieties of feminism<br/>
Jacob Howland on ideology<br/>
Deirdre McCloskey on capitalism: catastrophe or triumph?<br/>
Thomas Chatterton Williams on black male writing from Richard Wright to Ta-Nehisi Coates</p></blockquote>
<p>There are also “workshops”. It is not clear what they are workshopping.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>WORKSHOP LEADERS<br/>
Arthur Brooks, Professor of the Practice of Public Leadership, Harvard University<br/>
Nadine Strossen, Professor of Law, New York Law School; former President of the ACLU<br/>
David Mamet, award-winning playwright and author; Pulitzer Prize winner<br/>
Peter Boghossian, Philosopher and Author<br/>
Bari Weiss, journalist and best-selling author<br/>
Carlos Carvalho, Professor of Statistics, UT-Austin<br/>
Joshua Katz, Classicist, Princeton University<br/>
Lea Carpenter, novelist and screenwriter<br/>
Edward Luttwak, military strategist and author<br/>
Joe Lonsdale, CEO of 8VC, Co-Founder of Palantir<br/>
Balaji Srinivasan, Angel Investor and Tech Founder<br/>
Maleka Momand, Co-Founder &amp; CEO, Esper<br/>
Katherine Boyle, General Partner at Andreessen Horowitz<br/>
Robert Steffens, Co President, Marvel Entertainment<br/>
Geoff Lewis, Founder &amp; Managing Partner, Bedrock<br/>
Amber Allen, Founder and CEO, Double A Labs<br/>
Jack Abraham, Founder, Managing Partner &amp; CEO at Atomic<br/>
Michael Solana, Vice President, Founders Fund</p></blockquote>
<p>So you show up for one of these forbidden courses, and there’s a mob of like 20 professors waiting to divvy up the 10 hours of instruction, and each one has their own peculiar hobby horse they’re riding, and they anticipate a group of 30-40 students, and then what?</p>
<p>I looked at that mess and figured their student body was going to be tinier than they expect, except they did one thing exactly right. They are <em>paying</em> bodies to attend.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>Due to the support of a generous grant from our donors, there is no cost to attend the program. Hotels, some meals, and activities are covered by UATX. A $300 stipend will be given to participants to defray costs from travel, some meals, and other incidental expenses. Any additional costs will be the responsibility of participants.</p></blockquote>
<p>Whoa. I wish we could just pay our students to attend my university, and take care of their housing and meals at no cost. This is what you get when millionaires and billionaires back your efforts to destroy public education. I wonder what contribution Elon Musk made?</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/scamisbad.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/scamisbad-500x333.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="333" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66759" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/scamisbad.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/scamisbad-150x100.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/scamisbad-300x200.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I think it’s part of the Right’s efforts to undermine education — steal the word “university” and attach it to rank garbage. Think PragerU. Think Trump University. Think University of Austin. All trash. Now how about this: a blockchain university, Woolf U. In a lengthy August 2018 interview with Disruption Hub, Woolf’s founder Joshua Broggi […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66758</id>
    <published>2022-06-03T12:38:57Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-03T12:38:57Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Illumination in Hay-on-Wye</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5989/illumination-in-hay-on-wye#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="HowTheLightGetsIn is in Hay-on-Wye from 2-5 June." src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2016_River_Wye_0006.jpg" height="786" alt="HowTheLightGetsIn" width="1181" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not every day that you go to a philosophy talk and look down to find that the audience members in front of you aren&amp;rsquo;t wearing any shoes. This little moment goes some way to capture the atmosphere of HowTheLightGetsIn, a festival billed as a &amp;ldquo;playground for the soul&amp;rdquo; that this year features leading thinkers from across the fields of philosophy, science, culture and politics, with music and comedy thrown in the mix. Running alongside the well-established Hay Festival of Literature and Arts since 2018, HTLGI has more than outgrown initial assumptions that it might be some kind of &amp;ldquo;Hay fringe&amp;rdquo;, with big hitters like Richard Dawkins and Nobel prize-winning physicist Richard Penrose starring alongside an impressive diversity of thinkers, and plenty of music and comedy from afro-futurist beats to philosophers and comedians joining forces in midnight sessions of intellectual jousting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The talk with the bare feet saw Slavoj Zizek and Yuval Harari discuss the idea of &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; and interrogate why we associate the natural with the good. Zizek, the Hegelian provocateur, and Harari, historian and author of the best-selling &lt;em&gt;Sapiens: a Brief History of Humankind&lt;/em&gt;, don&amp;rsquo;t make an immediately intuitive pair, but after a mutual agreement between the two to do away entirely with the natural / unnatural binary itself (in Harari&amp;rsquo;s words &amp;ldquo;everything that is possible is also natural&amp;rdquo;), there followed a wonderfully wide-ranging debate touching on the deep ecology movement, the definition of the good, and the frightening possibilities of gene editing creating a new species of &amp;ldquo;human 2.0&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inter-disciplinary is definitely the watchword at HTGLI. A debate on the "World In Jeopardy" was quite rightly dominated by the Russia-Ukraine war, with former member of the British Secret Intelligence Service Nigel Inkster debating with Labour MP Tulip Siddiq and the conservative cultural critic and psychiatrist Theodore Dalrymple. &amp;ldquo;Dreams and Jeopardy&amp;rdquo; is the theme of this year&amp;rsquo;s festival and it feels right to step back for a moment from the news cycle to pose the big questions around the war: Is the west in decline? Do we need another global hegemon, now that the United States appears to have eschewed its role as &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rsquo;s policeman&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href="/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture"&gt;I talked to Hilary Lawson&lt;/a&gt;, the founder, before the festival, he spoke about the importance of politicians engaging with these fundamental questions. In practice however, as it turns out, it may not always run smoothly. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t attend myself, the buzz around the food and drink tents today, the first day of the festival, was somewhat dominated by the afternoon session with Matt Hancock, whose talk on his &amp;ldquo;life and philosophy&amp;rdquo; prompted more than one critic of his conduct as health secretary during the pandemic to heckle from the audience - one loudly calling him a &amp;ldquo;hypocrite&amp;rdquo; after he alluded to the crucial virtue of &amp;ldquo;sacrifice&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, if the motive is bringing philosophy alive, visceral responses should be expected. And the festival certainly lives up to its brief of encouraging lively debate, inside and outside the sessions themselves. The lack of any real VIP areas means that speakers and artists are drifting around with the guests. At lunch, simply by virtue of sitting near to the South Indian dosa stall, I found myself discussing the life of the prophet and Islamic history with Zizek and Myriam Francois, a journalist and research associate at the Centre of Islamic Studies. Lawson had promised me a festival in which people &amp;ldquo;genuinely do mix &amp;hellip;. You might be standing next to the world's leading scientist in a particular area, or a major politician. It also means that those people are really engaged. And we involve music and comedy and those sorts of things, because it softens all of that status stuff. I mean, we all have to deal with the fact that, you know, life is a really puzzling thing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is indeed, and particularly at this fraught point of history, with climate crisis and major shifts in geopolitics recurring as themes throughout the day. Reflecting on these big questions can often be a lonely, silent past-time. But now, I&amp;rsquo;m about to go re-join the noise and lights, to dance it out with Groove Armada&amp;rsquo;s Tom Findlay, then maybe a late-night ride on the Ferris Wheel. That&amp;rsquo;s what this festival provides: four days of intellectual stimulation, yes, but also some much-needed distance from the churn of news and the stress of daily life, inviting you to listen, learn, and see the wood for the trees for once. (And it helps that from this spot on the Welsh border, there are a lot of beautiful woods to see.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Humanist magazine is Philosophy Partner of HowTheLightGetsIn festival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5989/illumination-in-hay-on-wye#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-06-02T23:34:07Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-02T23:34:07Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Feminists Were Wrong About Domestic Violence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/06/feminists-were-wrong-about-domestic-violence/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Okay, I know what you’re thinking, but the title of this video has nothing to do directly with the recently concluded Johnny Depp and Amber Heard trial. I’m done talking about that for now. …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131514</id>
    <published>2022-06-02T20:45:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-02T20:45:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JUNE 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/06/open-discussion-june-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978354</id>
    <published>2022-06-01T08:37:47Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-01T08:37:47Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No, Monkeypox Didn’t Come From a Human Getting Frisky with a Monkey</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/no-monkeypox-didnt-come-from-a-human-getting-frisky-with-a-monkey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! A few weeks ago I made a video about how “the Great Replacement Theory” hawked by white supremacists has persisted in part thanks to Nazis at the Pioneer Fund, who have been promoting eugenics since …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131512</id>
    <published>2022-05-31T14:14:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-31T14:14:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>You’re Wrong about Johnny Depp and Amber Heard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/youre-wrong-about-johnny-depp-and-amber-heard/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! I’ve spent several years now studiously avoiding learning anything about the ongoing battle between Johnny Depp and Amber Heard, but as an avid user of social media I find that it has finally become completely …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131508</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T18:05:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T18:05:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>With "Station Eleven", apocalyptic fiction has come of age</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5974/with-station-eleven-apocalyptic-fiction-has-come-of-age#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="A still from &amp;quot;Station Eleven&amp;quot;" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/StationEleven.jpeg" height="1067" alt="A still from 'Station Eleven'" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;In March 2020, it felt like those of us who were lucky enough to be able to lock down in our homes and watch a lot of television were quickly sorted into two opposing camps. There were those who sought out a total escape from the daily accumulation of death tolls. Absurdist documentaries like Netflix&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; and endless dating reality shows were this group&amp;rsquo;s binging material. But alongside them co-existed the people who wanted to immerse themselves in fictional versions of their current situation, rather than look away. Pandemic-based films like &lt;em&gt;Contagion&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;28 Days Later&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Outbreak&lt;/em&gt; and others provided this hit of schadenfreude, filling our screens with safely contained versions of &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; even as a real-life virus raged through our communities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;These, and indeed many other conventional disaster movies, follow a simple narrative template. The viewer is introduced to the central characters before The Event that will utterly change their lives, either in early scenes or via flashbacks to life before. Initially, the warning signs of the cataclysm are ignored by many, until it is too late to prevent the inevitable. Transmission of the virus surges exponentially, millions die, and our remaining heroes are left to make the best of the life that remains to them in the post-apocalyptic landscape. Invariably, human life finds a way to endure, albeit in much altered and reduced circumstances. To put it another way: it is extremely rare for a mainstream pandemic thriller to end with the camera panning over an empty planet heaped with corpses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;"Station Eleven" and breaking new ground&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;There is something gratifying about the rhythms of this basic story. It takes a terrifying, incomprehensible unknown and slots it into a familiar structure with a beginning, middle and end. But having now lived through two years and counting of a major viral pandemic, we know that such an event is anything but neat and compartmentalised. Imaginary pandemics will forever hit differently for us, now we have first-hand experience of the chaos such a situation can create in the lives of even the luckiest survivor. With this knowledge has come an appetite for a different kind of on-screen pandemic &amp;ndash; something that reflects the true complexities of life with a deadly virus and resists the easy categorisation of everyone as either &amp;ldquo;victim&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;survivor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The best example of this new wave of fictional pandemics was, surprisingly, imagined long before the SARS‑CoV‑2 virus was first identified. Emily St John Mandel&amp;rsquo;s novel &lt;em&gt;Station Eleven &lt;/em&gt;was published in 2014 and follows a group of travelling players touring the Great Lakes region of North America 20 years after a virulent strain of swine flu has wiped out most of the population. Although critically acclaimed from the start, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until 2020 that the book went stratospheric, selling hundreds of thousands of copies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;A film adaptation had been in the works since 2015, but in late 2019 this was revealed to have been transformed into a television series for the HBO Max streaming service. By the time the show aired in 2021, the world had been altered irrevocably by events that bore an uncanny similarity to those of the plot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Yet &lt;em&gt;Station Eleven&lt;/em&gt; is worth watching regardless of its coincidental mirroring of reality. Mandel&amp;rsquo;s story, unlike some of the big-budget pandemic thrillers that scratched that early itch for manageable terror, is small in scale. It focuses tightly on the creative and emotional lives of her main characters. As is the case with real people, their past relationships and traumas inform their present-day behaviour far more than the big-picture facts about a flu virus. The virus intrudes only insofar as it is relevant to their daily existence. There are no forced flashbacks showing what the US president was doing the moment that the virus hit, or dramatic scenes where epidemiologists summarise the worldwide prognosis.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The show is emotional and dark in places, but it is also, audaciously, uplifting. Hinting that people who have suffered through horrible things can also sometimes enjoy the life they still have feels daring, almost taboo, but at our current moment it is deeply satisfying."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;"Sweet Tooth" and "Creamery": a new breed of story?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sweet Tooth,&lt;/em&gt; a 2021 adaptation of a comic book of the same name, uses whimsy and fantasy to achieve a similarly broad emotional range. In this scenario, society has ten years prior experienced &amp;ldquo;the Great Crumble&amp;rdquo;, because of a pandemic known only as &amp;ldquo;the Sick&amp;rdquo;. As a result, most of the world&amp;rsquo;s humans were killed and human-animal hybrid babies emerged. Gus, a half-deer half-child, has been left alone in the woods after the death of his father. He thus sets out on his own at the age of ten to find his absent mother.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The show is visually gorgeous, setting this cute antlered child in a series of sweeping forest landscapes. The beauty all around him contrasts with Gus&amp;rsquo;s ambient fear. He is being hunted by a band of humans known as &amp;ldquo;the Last Men&amp;rdquo;, who fear that these hybrid children were the cause, rather than the result, of the pandemic. The Sick not only killed people, it also destroyed the survivors&amp;rsquo; ability to interact without suspicion. As a portrayal of a pandemic&amp;rsquo;s ripple effect, it is potent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Seriousness is another boundary that creators of post-Covid pandemics are beginning to push. Contagion and death are not traditionally fertile grounds for comedy, but choosing to laugh at horrible things can sometimes tease out greater nuance than a purely po-faced treatment. This is definitely the case in &lt;em&gt;Creamerie&lt;/em&gt;, a late 2021 comedy-horror show from New Zealand that follows a trio of women running a dairy farm eight years after a viral pandemic has wiped out most of the world&amp;rsquo;s men. Although free of the patriarchal dynamics that govern other post-apocalyptic fertility-orientated stories such as &lt;em&gt;The Handmaid&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/em&gt;, the working women of &lt;em&gt;Creamerie&lt;/em&gt; still find themselves oppressed by a fascist authority. But this one is run by authoritarian women and uses &amp;ldquo;wellness&amp;rdquo; practices to achieve its ends. Part black comedy, part satire, part crime caper, it can feel unsettling at first to laugh at the show&amp;rsquo;s jabs at wellness mantras alongside flashbacks to the gory pyres of male corpses. But when the women discover a man who has survived the extermination and decide to help him evade capture by the sperm-obsessed wellness authorities, the emotional stakes are raised.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Bobby, played by a former &lt;em&gt;Neighbours&lt;/em&gt; star, needs their generosity and courage to survive, even if he is physically stronger than the women in authority. The mixture of camaraderie, jadedness and hope exhibited by the central characters is recognisable. In amongst the dirty jokes and Gwyneth Paltrow-esque platitudes &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s an &amp;lsquo;us&amp;rsquo; in every uterus!&amp;rdquo; they chant at one point &amp;ndash; is a familiar tale about power and who gets to wield it in difficult times.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;All three of these post-Covid pandemic portrayals are set years after the initial outbreak. One of the overriding lessons of the last two years has been that pandemics don&amp;rsquo;t end as neatly as the classic disaster film might have once led us to believe. Rather than being short and sharp, this is a calamity that unfolds slowly, intertwining with our existing lives, rather than blotting them out in one convenient detonation. It&amp;rsquo;s no wonder that we now prefer pandemic dramas that engage with the myriad ways in which these creeping tendrils of fear can change us and how we live &amp;ndash; for the worse, of course, but also for the better.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5974/with-station-eleven-apocalyptic-fiction-has-come-of-age#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T10:39:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T10:39:19Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Impossible freedom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5973/impossible-freedom#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/freedom.jpg" height="359" alt="'Freedom' by Raymond Tallis" width="239" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;"All theory is against free will; all experience for it.&amp;rdquo; So said Dr Johnson, in his famous formulation. Which, then, should we follow: theory or experience? Is it our responsibility to follow the inexorable logic of theories wherever they might lead, even if they deny us the reality of our freedom? Or do we take as our guide the practical knowledge that for anything we do to be meaningfully ours at all, it must have been chosen freely? Both options are open to the philosopher, and both suggest not only different pre-theoretical commitments, but different conceptions of what philosophy might help us do with our freedom.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The theoretical arguments against free will are familiar. The natural world is governed by exceptionless and immutable laws. Everything we do is an effect of causes outside of our control, so even when we think we are choosing between alternative futures, there is in truth no way we could have done otherwise, and therefore no meaningful sense in which we are free. All said, we are nothing but a conduit for natural forces: we never act, things only happen to us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This possibility terrified Immanuel Kant. Like many before and since, Kant saw a deterministic universe as a kind of desert, bereft of anything that could make human life meaningful. Without free will there is no morality, no taking responsibility for our own life or the lives of others. The task of philosophy is to show a way out of this uninhabitable desert, to show how free will is possible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This was not the only response to determinism. Spinoza asks us to consider a stone falling from the sky. Were we to ask the stone, Spinoza suggests, it would claim that it moves of its own accord, and could just as well decide to change direction if it pleased. Human freedom, he argues, like that of the stone, consists solely in our being conscious of our desires yet ignorant of their causes. Stubbornly clinging to our intuitions of freedom even where they contradict rational thought is a kind of betrayal, an abdication of philosophical responsibility. The purpose of philosophy is not to find space for freedom &amp;ndash; there is none &amp;ndash; but rather to conceive what a meaningful human life might look like given its absence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;Free will and science: a reconciliation?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The very title of Raymond Tallis&amp;rsquo;s new book tells us where he stands. &lt;em&gt;Freedom: An Impossible Reality&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; impossible according to theory, and yet affirmed by our every action. For Tallis, the experience of freedom is non-negotiable: we cannot but experience ourselves as choosing and deciding, intervening in the world in ways that make a difference to it. Beginning from the reality of this experience, Tallis argues that where our theories appear to contradict free will, it is a sign we have misinterpreted them. Scientific theories, far from providing arguments against free will, are powerful evidence for its existence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Tallis is a philosopher, but he also spent much of his career as a clinical neuroscientist. Early on in the book, he takes on the concept of &amp;ldquo;neurodeterminism&amp;rdquo;, according to which it is not us but the neurochemistry of our brains that really calls the shots in human agency. Everything we do, according to this theory, is pre-determined by the firings of neurons in our brain, as is supposedly demonstrated by the famous experiments of Benjamin Libet, in which certain neurons are seen to fire in advance of the self-reported taking of a &amp;ldquo;decision&amp;rdquo; (whatever that is supposed to mean, neuroscientifically speaking). Tallis presents a convincing argument that such interpretations tend to turn good science into bad philosophy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;The most original part of Tallis&amp;rsquo;s argument is his account of causation. Determinism relies on the idea of causal necessity: the earthquake in the ocean bed causes a chain of events that necessarily leads to the tsunami crashing on the coast. But, Tallis argues, causal necessity is not at all inherent in nature. David Hume famously claimed that the &amp;ldquo;necessary connection&amp;rdquo; between cause and effect is formed in the mind, and Tallis pushes the argument further, arguing not only that the necessary connection between cause and effect is forged in the mind, but that what we call &amp;ldquo;causes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; are themselves mind-dependent, picked out from a fundamentally undifferentiated nature for pragmatic purposes. If causes and effects are not building blocks of reality, but useful tools that are simply assigned that status for explanatory purposes, it makes little sense to think of ourselves as constrained by them. Causation is not something outside us that limits our freedom, but an expression of the free and creative choices we make in constructing scientific theories.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This brings us to Tallis&amp;rsquo;s controversial claim of the &amp;ldquo;unnaturalness of natural science&amp;rdquo;: the claim that the very practice of experimental science demonstrates our freedom, because it shows that in an important sense, we stand outside of nature. Nature, left to its own devices, has certain habits; there are patterns and regularities to its behaviour. But for these &amp;ldquo;habits of nature&amp;rdquo; to become &amp;ldquo;laws of science&amp;rdquo;, there must be conscious subjects to discover and elaborate these laws &amp;ndash; there must be something which &amp;ldquo;stands outside&amp;rdquo; nature, holding a mirror up to it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The importance of "intentionality"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;What allows us to stand outside the laws of nature, Tallis argues, is &amp;ldquo;intentionality&amp;rdquo;, the relation between a mind and a world by virtue of which thoughts can be &lt;em&gt;about &lt;/em&gt;anything at all. He argues that this is a property unique to human subjects: earthquakes &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;, but they are not &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; anything. The thoughts of seismologists, on the other hand, are quite frequently about earthquakes. It is this aboutness that &amp;ldquo;opens up a distance&amp;rdquo;, what Tallis calls the &amp;ldquo;virtual distance created by intentionality&amp;rdquo;. This distance allows the scientist to observe the world, to carve events into &amp;ldquo;causes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; for his own purposes, and to open up a space of possibility outside of that which actually exists. Crucially, the intentionality that allows for action and for the scientific gaze cannot itself be explained scientifically: &amp;ldquo;telereception explains how the light gets in, but not how a gaze looks out.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;If this sounds less razor-sharp than the earlier critiques, it is. Tallis does not suffer from the inhibition of academic philosophers, or share the restraint of their conclusions. This makes for an invigorating treatise, especially in the critical sections, and it is perhaps natural that Tallis is more convincing arguing against determinism than for free will. If free will just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, then Tallis&amp;rsquo;s task is to rid those overly enamoured of scientific materialism of the strange delusions that lead them to deny manifest reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;But which is the delusion? Denying the experience of freedom affirmed by our every action, or insisting, like Spinoza&amp;rsquo;s stone, that in spite of everything we know, we are free, for no other reason than we feel we must be? One final response suggests itself: a shrug of the shoulders. Being &lt;em&gt;truly, really, metaphysically&lt;/em&gt; free might mean very little to me. Whether or not I am truly free, I still have to get out of bed in the morning. I still make plans for the future, hope for their success and risk disappointment if they fail. Does any of this depend on my being radically free? Would any of it be compromised if I was but a conduit for natural forces? If not, if I were to go about my life the same way in either case, then the distinction between free will and determinism, in which so much of our humanity appears to be at stake, can come to seem a difference that makes no difference at all.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5973/impossible-freedom#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T10:04:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T10:04:56Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Henrietta Lacks and the fight for genetic justice</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5972/henrietta-lacks-and-the-fight-for-genetic-justice#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="The family of Henrietta Lacks at the launch of her statue in Bristol, 2021" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2GX5HP9.jpg" height="1066" alt="The family of Henrietta Lacks at the launch of her statue in Bristol" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;When Johns Hopkins Hospital held a press conference in 1951 announcing its discovery of the HeLa cell line, the body of Henrietta Lacks was still lying in the hospital&amp;rsquo;s morgue. She had died of cervical cancer at the age of 31, leaving behind a husband and five children. Johns Hopkins took time to excitedly inform the world of a great medical advancement: these were the first human cells able to grow outside a body for more than 36 hours, opening up new paths for research. But they never told her grieving family.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;It was only in 1975 that the family discovered the fate of the cells, which had been harvested from tumours in Henrietta&amp;rsquo;s womb. Scientists hoping to map Henrietta&amp;rsquo;s DNA called her husband in order to request permission to collect genetic samples from him and other relatives. Before that phone call, no efforts had been made to seek consent or inform the family. They tried to find out more, but the details were scarce. &amp;ldquo;She was systematically erased by Johns Hopkins, scientists, researchers and doctors &amp;ndash; often incorrectly referred to as &amp;lsquo;Helen Lane&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;Henry Lawson&amp;rsquo;,&amp;rdquo; Alfred Lacks Carter, Henrietta&amp;rsquo;s grandson, said.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The cells, which are remarkably durable and prolific, thriving in lab conditions, have since been reproduced billions of times. The HeLa cell line has facilitated crucial research on viruses such as polio, zika, HIV, herpes and measles. Recently, it played an important role in the development of Covid-19 vaccines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;On 4 October, exactly 70 years since the day Henrietta died, the Lacks family estate filed a lawsuit against biotech giant Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc, one of the many companies making use of the HeLa cell line. Represented by civil rights attorney Benjamin Crump, who has fought for the rights of police brutality victims including Trayvon Martin and George Floyd, and Christopher Seeger, who led the $1 billion National Football League concussion settlement, the suit accuses the company of selling HeLa cells without consent in a &amp;ldquo;racially unjust medical system&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;For the family, the lawsuit is part of a long fight to have Henrietta&amp;rsquo;s mistreatment recognised. &lt;em&gt;The Immortal Life of Henrietta Lacks&lt;/em&gt; (2017), an HBO film starring Oprah Winfrey, based on Rebecca Skoolt&amp;rsquo;s 2010 book of the same title, initially helped draw mainstream attention to the Lacks story and the impact of HeLa cells. Seeger and Crump were drawn to the case partly due to its historical significance. They now plan to investigate at least 100 other pharmaceutical companies for their use of the cells.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;The continued exploitation of Mrs. Lacks&amp;rsquo; genetic material is one of the greatest examples of corporate theft in history,&amp;rdquo; Seeger said. &amp;ldquo;Her story represents the unfortunately common exploitation of Black people by the medical industry throughout US history. When I learned about this case, I wanted to be a part of correcting that wrong, even if only for one family.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The doctrine of unjust enrichment&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Over 50 million metric tonnes of HeLa cells have been distributed around the world to date, while the cells have been involved in nearly 75,000 studies. Widely considered the industry standard tool for studying human biology, they have contributed to the development of drugs for HIV/Aids and Parkinson&amp;rsquo;s disease, as well as breakthroughs in reproductive health and research on chromosomal conditions, gene-mapping and precision medicine. As Carter, Henrietta&amp;rsquo;s grandson, has said: &amp;ldquo;Billions of dollars [are] being made without our consent.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Should the Lacks family be compensated &amp;ndash; and if so, how? This past October, Crump told Amy Goodman of &lt;em&gt;Democracy Now! &lt;/em&gt;that the lawsuit is based &amp;ldquo;on the principle of not just simple justice, not just social justice,&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;genetic justice &amp;ndash; the belief that justice should flow from one generation to the next.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Genetic justice recognises how past violations of disenfranchised communities have shaped science and medical education around the world. But will it hold up in a court of law? Experts in bioethics or law may simply counter that while informed consent matters, &amp;ldquo;genetic justice&amp;rdquo; is not a recognised legal theory. However, it is related to the doctrine of Unjust Enrichment, which occurs when one person is enriched at the expense of another in circumstances that the law sees as unjust.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Crump believes that the doctrine of Unjust Enrichment applies to this case. As he put it in the interview, &amp;ldquo;You should not be allowed to continue to benefit at the peril of the victim, which is Henrietta Lacks.&amp;rdquo; Seeger, meanwhile, has claimed that &amp;ldquo;research organisations and pharmaceutical companies are making a conscious choice to embrace the legacy of racial injustice embedded in the US research and medical systems.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;It is difficult, however, to provide concrete evidence of racial injustice. Its role in Henrietta Lack&amp;rsquo;s mistreatment is a point of legal dispute in the case. Back in the 1950s, there were no clear ethical standards for any patient, regardless of race, when it came to medical research. It was &lt;br /&gt;common practice for biospecimens to be taken or analysed by doctors and researchers without their consent. Meanwhile, official health data related to race from the period is thin on the ground. However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to look at the big picture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Medical ethics and the question of profit&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Henrietta Lacks was born in 1920 in Virginia, at a time when the Jim Crow laws enforced racial segregation in most areas of life. Her mother died when Lacks was aged four, and she was sent to live with her grandfather in a log cabin on a tobacco farm that once housed slaves. Her cancer diagnosis came in early 1951, following her marriage to Daniel &amp;ldquo;Day&amp;rdquo; Lacks and the birth of her five children. She was sent to Baltimore for treatment but her options were limited. Most hospitals refused to take Black patients. Only teaching hospitals, like Johns Hopkins, had segregated wards.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Lacks died on such a ward. In the eight months before her death, doctors had been taking biopsies of her rapidly reproducing cancerous cells. Dr George Gey, a cell biologist and prominent cancer researcher at Johns Hopkins, created the HeLa cell line and sent it to a special facility at the Tuskegee Institute without patient knowledge or family consent, in order to manufacture more HeLa cells and distribute them worldwide.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;My great-grandmother experienced medical racism,&amp;rdquo; said Victoria Baptiste, &amp;ldquo;and my family faced discrimination.&amp;rdquo; This pattern, she says, has continued. &amp;ldquo;Today, we [the family] speak out against normalised malpractice and structural gaslighting to demand that historical injustices are acknowledged and addressed as the first step to building trust in research, science and medicine.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Johns Hopkins Hospital, however, denies targeting Black patients. &amp;ldquo;It was common practice at Johns Hopkins to collect tissue samples from cervical cancer patients, regardless of race or socio-economic status,&amp;rdquo; it has stated on a special legacy site, devoted to clarifying their stance on the case. The hospital has admitted that it should have done more in the past to inform the Lacks family. However, it has emphasised that it has only ever &amp;ldquo;offered&amp;rdquo; HeLa cells for scientific research, not sold them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;But while the hospital may not have profited, its extraction of the cells has meant that others have. There are approximately 11,000 registered patents around the world using HeLa cells, owned by multiple companies. One of these is Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. In the case brought by the Lacks family, the company has been accused of profiting directly from the mass production of Lacks&amp;rsquo; cell tissue. It has also marketed at least 12 products, sold to labs across the globe, that contain the HeLa cell line.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This use of the cells, the lawsuit states, &amp;ldquo;can only be understood as a choice to embrace a legacy of racial injustice embedded in the US research and medical systems.&amp;rdquo; The Lacks family want the company to release &amp;ldquo;the full amount of its net profits obtained by commercialising the HeLa cell line&amp;rdquo;. They also want Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. to stop using HeLa cells without permission and to create a trust for the Henrietta Lacks Estate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In December, the company filed a Motion to Dismiss, stating: &amp;ldquo;Thermo Fisher is left in the untenable position of defending itself for the downstream effects of 70-year-old acts in which Thermo Fisher had no part, which took place in a different time, under different norms than today, with no known physician or family witnesses still living.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;They added: &amp;ldquo;A plaintiff cannot wait decades to bring a claim while the scientific community &amp;ndash; including companies that serve it like Thermo Fisher &amp;ndash; makes use of a resource that has been freely and publicly available for the better part of a century.&amp;rdquo; This would, it states, place &amp;ldquo;every researcher (not just Thermo Fisher) who uses HeLa cells . . . under a cloud of potential liability&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;What might unnerve those companies still using the HeLa line is the precedent set by another case nearly four decades ago.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;John Moore and patient consent&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;John Moore was an entrepreneur who learned that he had cancer &amp;ndash; a rare form known as hairy cell leukaemia &amp;ndash; in 1976. Like Lacks, his diagnosis came at the age of 31. Born in Seattle, Moore had an eclectic career which included stints working in Alaska as a survey engineer and alcohol counsellor, establishing a college in Guadalajara, Mexico, becoming a beverage distributor and even a worm farmer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The condition Moore was diagnosed with caused his spleen to fill with defective lymphocytes (a type of white blood cell) and doctors grew fearful that his spleen might burst. He underwent treatment at UCLA&amp;rsquo;s Medical Center, where his spleen was removed. Later, one Dr David Golde, a cancer researcher at the medical centre, realised that the spleen contained unique blood cells of a kind that stimulated white blood cell development. This find was remarkable: white blood cells are needed to fight infection. From the extracted cells, Golde created a replicating cell, which the university then patented under the name &amp;ldquo;Mo&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;John Moore survived the treatment. But when he learned of the patent, he filed a lawsuit against the University of California and Dr Golde, who had not obtained consent to replicate the cells. Moore felt he had been duped. Between 1976-83 he was asked to make frequent trips to Los Angeles from Seattle, believing he was doing so for treatment. In reality, Golde was taking more specimens for the &amp;ldquo;Mo&amp;rdquo; cell line, and by the mid-1980s, he had established contracts with Sandoz Pharmaceuticals and Genetics Institute, Inc. to turn it into a commercial product.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Moore sued for lack of informed consent, fraud and deceit. His legal team argued that he had a right to a portion of the profits made from the &amp;ldquo;Mo&amp;rdquo; line. The case was initially dismissed, before the California Court of Appeal ruled in favour in 1988, stating that a patient&amp;rsquo;s blood and tissue was personal property, meaning that they could take a share in resulting profits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In 1990, however, the Supreme Court of California reversed the decision. They considered cells to be similar to donated or discarded organs, and believed that laboratories with large amounts of bio materials could not always be expected to know if everything was obtained ethically. At the time, the &amp;ldquo;Mo&amp;rdquo; cell line was valued at $3 billion. Today, it is worth more than $6 billion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In 1991, Moore took his case to the US Supreme Court, but he was denied again on similar grounds. However, he did negotiate a settlement with UCLA, which covered all of his legal fees, based on the fact that he was an uninformed patient and research subject. The Supreme Court also acknowledged his mistreatment, stating that &amp;ldquo;a physician who is seeking a patient&amp;rsquo;s consent for a medical procedure must . . . disclose personal interest unrelated to the patient&amp;rsquo;s health, whether research or economic, that may affect his medical judgment.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Moore was a white man who had access to medical treatment without prejudice. He was also alive when his cells were being harvested. Yet, while medical standards and the law had progressed significantly in the decades between, there is still a connection between him and Henrietta Lacks. Both were desperate for treatment, and sought care for rare forms of cancer at teaching hospitals. Both were not informed about the basic fact that their bodies were being harvested, creating cell lines which are now worth billions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Although Moore ultimately lost the case, legal scholars have noted the precedent set by it. &amp;ldquo;He was able to show how his doctors violated their ethical duties to him, which is very serious,&amp;rdquo; says Jorge L. Contreras, an expert in science and technology law at the American Bar Association and a member of the advisory board of the American Antitrust Institute. &amp;ldquo;Even so, the court didn&amp;rsquo;t go as far as he wanted . . . The theory is that (in the hospital) as part of your treatment, you discard cells all the time . . . when you give that vial of blood to the hospital, you can&amp;rsquo;t give it back. It&amp;rsquo;s gone. You give up ownership when you give it to the hospital.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Moore lost when it came to ownership over his cells, but he won when it came to the question of whether doctors breached their ethical duties towards him.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p6"&gt;A threat to future scientific enquiry?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;W&lt;/span&gt;hat will happen if the Lacks family win? Thermo Fisher Scientific Inc. has an estimated annual revenue of $40 billion. In December 2021, it acquired PPD, a renowned global research organization, for $17.4 billion. PPD provides clinical research services to biopharma and biotech companies, all of which require, or have required, HeLa cells to expand their own growth and innovation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The Lacks family are clear that the lawsuit should not be understood as a threat to the future of scientific enquiry. &amp;ldquo;The Lacks family does not want to stop innovation or research. Instead, we want to end injustice,&amp;rdquo; said Alfred Lacks Carter. &amp;ldquo;We want what is rightfully ours &amp;ndash; the Henrietta Lacks Estate having a say in how her cells and genetic materials are used, to be compensated, and to ensure equitable access to the innovations made possible by the HeLa cells.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The research community is already paying attention. The Henrietta Lacks Foundation, established by Skoolt in 2010 using proceeds from her book, has received large donations from institutions including the UK biotech firm Abcam and the University of California (San Diego) and a six-figure sum from the Howard Hughes Medical Institute in 2020. The foundation has thus far awarded 90 grants to over 30 members of Henrietta Lacks&amp;rsquo; immediate family.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;While the foundation is separate from the case against Thermo Fisher, the donations show that medical institutions are showing an interest in the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Meanwhile, Seeger has confirmed that more claims against other companies are likely to be filed soon. &amp;ldquo;What happened to [Henrietta] cannot be changed,&amp;rdquo; he said, &amp;ldquo;but by returning to her family what is rightfully theirs and acknowledging the Lacks family&amp;rsquo;s contribution to scientific advancement, these companies can demonstrate that Black lives are valued and respected.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5972/henrietta-lacks-and-the-fight-for-genetic-justice#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T10:03:48Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T10:03:48Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Science of How to Stop Mass Shootings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/the-science-of-how-to-stop-mass-shootings/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: On Tuesday, May 24 2022, an 18-year old South Texas man shot his grandmother, drove to an elementary school, barricaded himself in a classroom, and murdered 19 small children and 2 adults before he …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131506</id>
    <published>2022-05-25T19:56:10Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-25T19:56:10Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>"Deep Deception" and policing without consent</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5970/deep-deception-and-policing-without-consent#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/deception.jpeg" height="636" alt="Deep deception" width="415" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;There was a blue notice on the desk. It said: &amp;ldquo;All police officers wearing plain clothes and all civil staff are required to display identification whilst in this building.&amp;rdquo; I guessed it was a salvaged official sign from a police building somewhere. But its presence on the welcome desk at this conference hall in central London was a symbol of defiance by a group of women and their supporters making a stand against inhumane state surveillance. Their slogan is &amp;ldquo;Police spies out of our lives&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The event was the book launch for &lt;em&gt;Deep Deception&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s authored by five women, Helen Steel (the only one to use her real name), Belinda, Alison, Lisa and Naomi &amp;ndash; all of whom gradually found out the men they thought were their partners were in fact undercover police officers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been more than 20 years since these left-wing activists discovered and exposed how undercover police officers had been infiltrating their groups and having sexual relationships with many women for years. Though the practice goes back to 1968, these women were being spied on from the 1990s to the 2010s. Their boyfriends suddenly disappeared, sometimes leaving a note, often after having or possibly staging breakdowns, leaving their distraught partners worried for their wellbeing. In some cases they had fathered children and abandoned them too.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Yet only now can we appreciate how much we don&amp;rsquo;t yet know about the scale of these operations, as the police have continued to withhold the names and numbers involved.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep Deception&lt;/em&gt;, told in chronological order, reads like a kind of overlapping thriller, as each woman is trapped by a man following a system of training that had clearly developed over years. They often had a van, so they could take you home and meet your friends. They often got themselves quite senior within the organisation, giving them access to membership lists. In some cases they were involved in the planning and carrying out of crimes. Then there were the clues that only in hindsight read like red flags: on first seeing their place, the women noticed their new boyfriends had very few possessions. The officers usually moved in with them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Media coverage has too often been only interested in the salacious details of the sexual relationships. As Lisa observed, it was like the fascination with serial killers. What motivates them? Before &lt;em&gt;Deep Deception&lt;/em&gt;, Helen, Alison and their solicitor Harriet Wistrich had met the creative team planning a BBC drama inspired by the spycops story, but were deeply unimpressed by what emerged: Peter Moffat&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Undercover &lt;/em&gt;(2016), starring Adrian Lester and Sophie Okonedo, ended up being a love story about a black undercover officer who was still married to the radical lawyer he&amp;rsquo;d targeted.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Alison spoke out at the time: &amp;ldquo;To give the impression that the undercover relationships that inspired this drama were based on reciprocal love &amp;ndash; where no other woman is being cheated on and lied to &amp;ndash; is to misrepresent the deceitful individuals involved, and to misunderstand the power dynamics and sexual politics that underpinned them.&amp;rdquo; In fact, by 1996, officers working in the SDS unit &amp;ndash; the Special Demonstration Squad &amp;ndash; were required to be married before deployment, to ensure they had an external life to return to. The undercover cops called the women activists they slept with &amp;ldquo;wearies&amp;rdquo;, as in wearisome. In February 2022, a report by the Independent Office for Police Conduct into the misogynist and sexist culture at Charing Cross police station in central London found that male officers used the same term to describe female officers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;As a journalist, reading &lt;em&gt;Deep Deception&lt;/em&gt; was like having a veil lifted from my eyes. So many of the stories I&amp;rsquo;d covered over my career turned out to have had a covert police operation involved in manipulating and entrapping activists: the McLibel case, for example, where a leaflet opposing McDonalds was later found to have been co-written by an undercover police officer, or the mass arrests of green activists at Ratcliffe-on-Soar power station before their protest had even begun.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;As Lisa said at the book launch, there is real sadness for the lost decade or more when climate change activism was derailed by these operations, given the warnings now being issued by the UN&amp;rsquo;s IPCC. The ongoing public inquiry into covert policing is only expected to complete taking evidence in 2025. These women are determined not to let this scandal disappear under the weight of time. There is still a reckoning due, with those officers yet to retire, and a wider awakening for a nation that has been too complacent about the very British idea of policing by consent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5970/deep-deception-and-policing-without-consent#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-23T09:44:16Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-23T09:44:16Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are MATH TEXTBOOKS Teaching Kids Critical Race Theory?????</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/are-math-textbooks-teaching-kids-critical-race-theory/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Well, I made it to May of 2022 before I finally gave up and decided to talk about “critical race theory,” or CRT, the latest straw-filled bogeyman being attacked by whatever alt-right morons haven’t …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=O5LOwl_hf8c:jlaxPk1mwoE:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131487</id>
    <published>2022-05-19T14:23:31Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-19T14:23:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Twitter: Reinstate Atheist Republic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/twitter-reinstate-atheist-republic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier this year, Twitter suspended the account of Atheist Republic (@AtheistRepublic) for unspecified violations after complaints from the Indian government. In the letter below, Robyn Blumner, president and CEO of the Center for Inquiry, and Richard Dawkins, CFO board member and founder of the Richard Dawkins Foundation for Reason &amp; Science, write to request that …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978338</id>
    <published>2022-05-12T15:44:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-12T15:44:56Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dawkins on the Overturning of Roe: “They Think It’s Murder”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/dawkins-on-the-overturning-of-roe-they-think-its-murder/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an essay exclusive to Free Inquiry, Richard Dawkins responds to the likely overturning of Roe v. Wade by the U.S. Supreme Court, and the roots of anti-abortion fanaticism found in Catholic dogma. Why are they so fanatical about this one issue, eclipsing, as it does, all others? It is because they really think abortion …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978334</id>
    <published>2022-05-12T14:56:14Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-12T14:56:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/open-discussion-may-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978329</id>
    <published>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/04/open-discussion-april-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978276</id>
    <published>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
