<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-06-12T13:35:47Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Reminder: podish sortacast this afternoon</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/11/reminder-podish-sortacast-this-afternoon/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;Yep, this is happening:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/a0JRTAPsBJU" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll be listening in, but won&amp;#8217;t be on it. I don&amp;#8217;t think grimaces and moans would be a helpful contribution (although maybe it would be representative of America), and I have to concentrate on not moving in a way that doesn&amp;#8217;t antagonize the disc between L3 and L4, which is very angry with me right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ever try &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; thinking about your spine? Usually it&amp;#8217;s easy, except when it&amp;#8217;s yelling at you all the time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yep, this is happening: I’ll be listening in, but won’t be on it. I don’t think grimaces and moans would be a helpful contribution (although maybe it would be representative of America), and I have to concentrate on not moving in a way that doesn’t antagonize the disc between L3 and L4, which is very […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66838</id>
    <published>2022-06-11T14:59:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-11T14:59:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>This was supposed to be a vanity exercise</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/10/this-was-supposed-to-be-a-vanity-exercise/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I asked one of those <a href="https://creator.nightcafe.studio/">AI art generators</a> to draw a portrait of me. It is stunningly accurate.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ-500x500.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="500" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66836" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ-500x500.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ-150x150.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ-300x300.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/dall-e-PZ.jpg 512w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Somehow it caught my essence flawlessly.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I asked one of those AI art generators to draw a portrait of me. It is stunningly accurate. Somehow it caught my essence flawlessly.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66835</id>
    <published>2022-06-10T15:27:38Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-10T15:27:38Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Friday Cephalopod: Most punk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/10/friday-cephalopod-most-punk/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Definitely should have a featured role in a Bladerunner movie.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper-500x281.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="281" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66833" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper-500x281.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper-150x84.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/Galiteuthis_wallpaper-768x432.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Definitely should have a featured role in a Bladerunner movie.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66832</id>
    <published>2022-06-10T15:11:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-10T15:11:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Cephalopods"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two more Skepticon speakers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/10/two-more-skepticon-speakers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/skepticon14.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/skepticon14-150x150.png" alt="" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-66830" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/skepticon14-150x150.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/skepticon14.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">New announcement: also in the lineup are <a href="https://skepticon.org/skepticon-14-speaker-debbie-goddard/">Debbie Goddard</a> and <a href="https://skepticon.org/skepticon-14-speaker-greta-christina/">Greta Christina</a>!</p>
<p>That means the main stage roster is: PZ Myers, Eli Heina Dadabhoy, Jey McCreight, Debbie Goddard, and Greta Christina. There will also be a game night on Friday, the traditional SkeptiProm on Saturday, and workshops on Sunday. Come on down to St Louis!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New announcement: also in the lineup are Debbie Goddard and Greta Christina! That means the main stage roster is: PZ Myers, Eli Heina Dadabhoy, Jey McCreight, Debbie Goddard, and Greta Christina. There will also be a game night on Friday, the traditional SkeptiProm on Saturday, and workshops on Sunday. Come on down to St Louis!</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66829</id>
    <published>2022-06-10T14:56:11Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-10T14:56:11Z</updated>
    <category term="Conferences"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Traitors, traitors, traitors</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/06/10/traitors-traitors-traitors/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I did not watch the Jan. 6 Committee hearings last night, but my wife did. I’m suffering from a serious lack of capacity to sit in horror watching pretty much anything, and today I’m waiting on medical information. Yesterday I got an X-ray to check out the state of my spine, and now that they know I’ve got one (it’s leaked out that I’m a registered Democrat, so the existence of a spine had to be tested first), I’m awaiting a probable MRI and an informed treatment plan.</p>
<p>I’ve seen a bit of the hearings on video, and caught up with <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/06/09/capitol-attack-house-hearing/">summaries in the newspapers</a>. At least I’ve confirmed that Liz Cheney has a spine, I guess my party had to import a Republican to get one.</p>
<p>I like the tenor so far: this was a violent insurrection by traitors to the country, and the person responsible was the man at the top, Donald J. Trump. They’re definitely implying that the end result of these hearings is going to be justice for the wicked, and they’re doing a fine job of laying the groundwork of the magnitude of the crime, but I’ve been an American for so long that I’ve become cynical, so I’m anticipating a failure of nerve and a complete collapse of the case, followed by a feeble handslap and prizes and applause for the assholes who collaborated, but are now playing the role of pious witnesses (I see you, Bill Barr and Jared and Ivanka Trump, you ought to be in a holding cell right now.)</p>
<p>I’m just saying, I don’t expect the Democrats or the media to maintain a strong position. Liz Cheney might, though.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal-500x374.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="374" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66827" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal-500x374.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal-150x112.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/06/betrayal.jpeg 625w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Tell me I’m wrong. I wish I had more faith in our political system.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I did not watch the Jan. 6 Committee hearings last night, but my wife did. I’m suffering from a serious lack of capacity to sit in horror watching pretty much anything, and today I’m waiting on medical information. Yesterday I got an X-ray to check out the state of my spine, and now that they […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66826</id>
    <published>2022-06-10T13:27:12Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-10T13:27:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to dance with the dead</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5976/how-to-dance-with-the-dead#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img title="Carnival of the dead, Mexico" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/skulls1.jpeg" height="1026" alt="Carnival of the dead" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;All the Living and the Dead (Raven Books) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;by Hayley Campbell&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This Party&amp;rsquo;s Dead (Unbound) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;by Erica Buist &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Our awareness of our own mortality, and attempts to keep death at bay, are arguably the reason we do anything at all. The fear of ceasing to exist has fuelled entire religions and often tediously complicated visions of the afterlife. So is death the biggest subject of them all? The authors of two new books on the theme &amp;ndash; Hayley Campbell and Erica Buist &amp;ndash; would probably say so. &amp;ldquo;We all find ways, regardless of our beliefs, to believe in our own immortality,&amp;rdquo; writes Buist. &amp;ldquo;Some of us, ahem, write books.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Both authors are based in the UK, and it can seem like the British are particularly dreadful at confronting death head-on. It is not that dying is taboo: we are in fact surrounded by it. &amp;ldquo;Death is everywhere, but it&amp;rsquo;s veiled, or it&amp;rsquo;s fiction,&amp;rdquo; writes Campbell in &lt;em&gt;All the Living and the Dead&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;Just like in video games, the bodies disappear.&amp;rdquo; Buist makes a similar point, in &lt;em&gt;This Party&amp;rsquo;s Dead&lt;/em&gt;, that our entertainment empires are built on piles of corpses. &amp;ldquo;And yet,&amp;rdquo; she writes, &amp;ldquo;when it comes to our own, we blanch.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;These books are interested in why we fear death, and how best to confront our preoccupation with it. Campbell tackles these questions in a journalistic manner, by talking to people in the death trade and seeking out &amp;ldquo;unromantic, unpoetic, unsanitised visions of death&amp;rdquo;. Buist&amp;rsquo;s is a more personal journey, starting with a definite trigger: discovering the body of her soon-to-be father-in-law, eight days after his death at a relatively young age. This traumatic moment leads her on a journey around the globe, to seven festivals or &amp;ldquo;parties&amp;rdquo; where they celebrate the dead.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Despite their different approaches, the books share some common refrains. One is around silence. &amp;ldquo;Nobody wants to say the wrong thing, so nobody says anything,&amp;rdquo; as Campbell puts it. As we hear through her interviewees, this squeamishness can be counterproductive, to say the least. She writes at various points about it being better for a loved one to see a dead body &amp;ndash; closure is important, even if it is of a gruesome kind. Buist draws the same conclusion: in Nepal, Indonesia and Sicily, people are hands-on with the dead, even, in Madagascar, digging them back up every seven years to party with them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Both authors are also interested in the gendered aspect of death. &amp;ldquo;Men weren&amp;rsquo;t interested in deathcare until they thought they could make money from it,&amp;rdquo; says one of Buist&amp;rsquo;s interviewees. Campbell writes that before the business of death became commercialised, &amp;ldquo;The bookends of life were considered to be the realm of women.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Now the death industry is a significant part of the global economy, and one that Campbell explores with an interest that is infectious. You can almost see her, notebook and dictaphone in hand, taking in the smells and the often horrific sights as she talks to an embalmer, a grave digger or a maker of death masks. (She can apparently watch bodies being hacked apart with few qualms.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Buist&amp;rsquo;s writing, meanwhile, is more novelistic and self-conscious. Her characters can sometimes come across as conduits for heart-warming messages that are a little too neat for comfort:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;ve got it all, and we&amp;rsquo;ve just got to face it, never deny it, and never fear death. Dance with the dead. Dance with death, and it&amp;rsquo;ll teach you the right steps.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;That said, it&amp;rsquo;s a book full of parties, so it would be unfair to criticise it for being too upbeat. And there are lessons to be learned here, especially for the British, about how we could change our attitude to death for the better. In Sicily, for example, the dead leave presents for the living, like &lt;br /&gt;Father Christmas. This kind of celebration seems more fun, as well as more sensible. As Buist writes, &amp;ldquo;I imagined growing up associating the dead with a treasure hunt, a sugar hit and a gift, instead of an awkward silence, averted gazes and the obligatory muttering of &amp;lsquo;very sad&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;But there are, to put it bluntly, simply more interesting insights and arresting details in &lt;em&gt;All the Living and the Dead&lt;/em&gt;. Campbell meets people with horribly fascinating jobs: a crime scene cleaner who wipes up after a brain has sprayed up a wall; anatomical pathology technologists who have to sew dead babies&amp;rsquo; heads back together; someone from a disaster response service that anticipates mass fatalities so that your company doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to. Her similes &amp;ndash; describing, for example, a complex tumour as wrapping its way down a person&amp;rsquo;s spine &amp;ldquo;like the red stripe on a barber&amp;rsquo;s pole&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; beg to be underlined. She has nightmares after seeing a dead baby fall helplessly underwater while being washed, yet resists the urge to become sentimental. &amp;ldquo;I try to suppress every built-in urge to stop him drowning,&amp;rdquo; she writes, &amp;ldquo;telling myself he is dead, realising that he is dead, that nothing I do here would matter or change the outcome of his being dead.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Campbell&amp;rsquo;s book is also just recent enough to feature an afterword that acknowledges the coronavirus pandemic &amp;ndash; an event so far-reaching that it has warped all of our experiences of mortality, as war would have done in the 20th century. After being witness to so much death, Campbell pictured each person as a body in a bag, not a statistic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the Living and the Dead&lt;/em&gt; triumphs in its mission statement: the reflections from the death workers are very unromantic indeed. Campbell draws conclusions, but these are not cliches. &amp;ldquo;By shielding ourselves from what happens past the moment of death,&amp;rdquo; she writes, &amp;ldquo;we deny ourselves a deeper understanding of who we truly are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This Party&amp;rsquo;s Dead&lt;/em&gt; also achieves its aim, in the sense that it seems to have partly been an attempt to find comfort for the author &amp;ndash; and may, along the way, provide the same to us as readers. After trekking to several continents, Buist concludes, &amp;ldquo;Festivals for the dead aren&amp;rsquo;t for the dead, really. They&amp;rsquo;re for us.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Despite the billions of words others have scribbled down about death, both Buist&amp;rsquo;s and Campbell&amp;rsquo;s books add something significant to the literature. Death can galvanise a writer to raise their game. As the ultimate subject, its wordcount is rivalled perhaps only by love. It will continue to be the most immense inspiration, as long as we are unable to escape its clutches. The upside here is that we&amp;rsquo;ll be treated to a lot more fabulous books.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5976/how-to-dance-with-the-dead#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-06-08T09:50:58Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-08T09:50:58Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In a word: "Process"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5975/in-a-word-process#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/process.jpeg" height="345" alt="Process" width="500" /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;process (verb)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;1530s, &amp;ldquo;begin legal action against&amp;rdquo; from French processer &amp;ldquo;to prosecute&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;In April, a &lt;em&gt;UN New&lt;/em&gt;s story said: &amp;ldquo;A deal reportedly made by the United Kingdom to send some migrants for processing and relocation to the Central African nation of Rwanda, are at odds with States&amp;rsquo; responsibility to take care of those in need of protection.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;processing&amp;rdquo; cropped up in quite a few news stories on this subject. It is reminiscent of other forms of processing which give us such things as processed cheese and processed meat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;The Oxford English Dictionary tells us that the first use of &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; to mean putting people through a legal process started in Scotland at the end of the 15th century. In 1532, for example, someone would be &amp;ldquo;processit&amp;rdquo; for not paying tax. Processing food crops up first in the US (1878) when glucose was added to honey. Six years later we hear of ozone being added to meat to make it processed. Our supermarkets have been full of processed food ever since.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;The specific use of &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; to mean subjecting a person to registration seems to begin in the 1920s, again in the US. The &lt;em&gt;New York Times &lt;/em&gt;reported in 1925 that policemen were &amp;ldquo;processed&amp;rdquo; before being given uniforms. By 1935 (still in the US), we find applicants being put through medical examinations and &amp;ldquo;transported to army camps to be &amp;lsquo;processed&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;We get a sense that people began to find the word discomforting; the &lt;em&gt;Times Literary Supplement &lt;/em&gt;noted in 1959 that some great books of French culture about &amp;ldquo;wild boys&amp;rdquo; like Maupassant or Gauguin were being processed, &amp;ldquo;attractively jacketed, to emerge as items suitable for ticking off on library lists&amp;rdquo;. Even more explicitly uneasy is one D. Ginsberg saying in 2000 that he &amp;ldquo;checked into the main office and was processed like a piece of salmon caught in a net&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;So it is in 2022, we wait and see if Rwanda will indeed set up &amp;ldquo;processing centres&amp;rdquo; for people who tried to come to the UK. Lord Alf Dubs, a former &amp;ldquo;kindertransport&amp;rdquo; child, is determined that the &amp;ldquo;process&amp;rdquo; won&amp;rsquo;t happen. He, more than anyone, knows how human beings were processed during the horrors of the mid-20th century.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p7"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5975/in-a-word-process#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-06-08T09:43:32Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-08T09:43:32Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What Does it Mean to Lead?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/06/what-does-it-mean-to-lead/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There’s really only one person in the world that I hope will read this. Earlier today, a dear friend asked, “What makes a leader?” I have to be honest, I have no idea. But, I know the qualities of the leaders I have respected. They stand up when others don’t. Even at great personal peril. …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=iLXyhrzbl60:0YwrEiaNxDA:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131532</id>
    <published>2022-06-07T19:03:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-07T19:03:56Z</updated>
    <category term="Activism"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Illumination in Hay-on-Wye</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5989/illumination-in-hay-on-wye#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="HowTheLightGetsIn is in Hay-on-Wye from 2-5 June." src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2016_River_Wye_0006.jpg" height="786" alt="HowTheLightGetsIn" width="1181" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not every day that you go to a philosophy talk and look down to find that the audience members in front of you aren&amp;rsquo;t wearing any shoes. This little moment goes some way to capture the atmosphere of HowTheLightGetsIn, a festival billed as a &amp;ldquo;playground for the soul&amp;rdquo; that this year features leading thinkers from across the fields of philosophy, science, culture and politics, with music and comedy thrown in the mix. Running alongside the well-established Hay Festival of Literature and Arts since 2018, HTLGI has more than outgrown initial assumptions that it might be some kind of &amp;ldquo;Hay fringe&amp;rdquo;, with big hitters like Richard Dawkins and Nobel prize-winning physicist Richard Penrose starring alongside an impressive diversity of thinkers, and plenty of music and comedy from afro-futurist beats to philosophers and comedians joining forces in midnight sessions of intellectual jousting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The talk with the bare feet saw Slavoj Zizek and Yuval Harari discuss the idea of &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; and interrogate why we associate the natural with the good. Zizek, the Hegelian provocateur, and Harari, historian and author of the best-selling &lt;em&gt;Sapiens: a Brief History of Humankind&lt;/em&gt;, don&amp;rsquo;t make an immediately intuitive pair, but after a mutual agreement between the two to do away entirely with the natural / unnatural binary itself (in Harari&amp;rsquo;s words &amp;ldquo;everything that is possible is also natural&amp;rdquo;), there followed a wonderfully wide-ranging debate touching on the deep ecology movement, the definition of the good, and the frightening possibilities of gene editing creating a new species of &amp;ldquo;human 2.0&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Inter-disciplinary is definitely the watchword at HTGLI. A debate on the "World In Jeopardy" was quite rightly dominated by the Russia-Ukraine war, with former member of the British Secret Intelligence Service Nigel Inkster debating with Labour MP Tulip Siddiq and the conservative cultural critic and psychiatrist Theodore Dalrymple. &amp;ldquo;Dreams and Jeopardy&amp;rdquo; is the theme of this year&amp;rsquo;s festival and it feels right to step back for a moment from the news cycle to pose the big questions around the war: Is the west in decline? Do we need another global hegemon, now that the United States appears to have eschewed its role as &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rsquo;s policeman&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When &lt;a href="/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture"&gt;I talked to Hilary Lawson&lt;/a&gt;, the founder, before the festival, he spoke about the importance of politicians engaging with these fundamental questions. In practice however, as it turns out, it may not always run smoothly. Although I didn&amp;rsquo;t attend myself, the buzz around the food and drink tents today, the first day of the festival, was somewhat dominated by the afternoon session with Matt Hancock, whose talk on his &amp;ldquo;life and philosophy&amp;rdquo; prompted more than one critic of his conduct as health secretary during the pandemic to heckle from the audience - one loudly calling him a &amp;ldquo;hypocrite&amp;rdquo; after he alluded to the crucial virtue of &amp;ldquo;sacrifice&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, if the motive is bringing philosophy alive, visceral responses should be expected. And the festival certainly lives up to its brief of encouraging lively debate, inside and outside the sessions themselves. The lack of any real VIP areas means that speakers and artists are drifting around with the guests. At lunch, simply by virtue of sitting near to the South Indian dosa stall, I found myself discussing the life of the prophet and Islamic history with Zizek and Myriam Francois, a journalist and research associate at the Centre of Islamic Studies. Lawson had promised me a festival in which people &amp;ldquo;genuinely do mix &amp;hellip;. You might be standing next to the world's leading scientist in a particular area, or a major politician. It also means that those people are really engaged. And we involve music and comedy and those sorts of things, because it softens all of that status stuff. I mean, we all have to deal with the fact that, you know, life is a really puzzling thing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is indeed, and particularly at this fraught point of history, with climate crisis and major shifts in geopolitics recurring as themes throughout the day. Reflecting on these big questions can often be a lonely, silent past-time. But now, I&amp;rsquo;m about to go re-join the noise and lights, to dance it out with Groove Armada&amp;rsquo;s Tom Findlay, then maybe a late-night ride on the Ferris Wheel. That&amp;rsquo;s what this festival provides: four days of intellectual stimulation, yes, but also some much-needed distance from the churn of news and the stress of daily life, inviting you to listen, learn, and see the wood for the trees for once. (And it helps that from this spot on the Welsh border, there are a lot of beautiful woods to see.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Humanist magazine is Philosophy Partner of HowTheLightGetsIn festival.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5989/illumination-in-hay-on-wye#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-06-02T23:34:07Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-02T23:34:07Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Feminists Were Wrong About Domestic Violence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/06/feminists-were-wrong-about-domestic-violence/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Okay, I know what you’re thinking, but the title of this video has nothing to do directly with the recently concluded Johnny Depp and Amber Heard trial. I’m done talking about that for now. …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uUwGuAg1aBA:la5wu0bivOo:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131514</id>
    <published>2022-06-02T20:45:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-02T20:45:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JUNE 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/06/open-discussion-june-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978354</id>
    <published>2022-06-01T08:37:47Z</published>
    <updated>2022-06-01T08:37:47Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No, Monkeypox Didn’t Come From a Human Getting Frisky with a Monkey</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/no-monkeypox-didnt-come-from-a-human-getting-frisky-with-a-monkey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! A few weeks ago I made a video about how “the Great Replacement Theory” hawked by white supremacists has persisted in part thanks to Nazis at the Pioneer Fund, who have been promoting eugenics since …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=hQggtBAtgFY:1EjNWv34NMc:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131512</id>
    <published>2022-05-31T14:14:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-31T14:14:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>You’re Wrong about Johnny Depp and Amber Heard</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/youre-wrong-about-johnny-depp-and-amber-heard/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! I’ve spent several years now studiously avoiding learning anything about the ongoing battle between Johnny Depp and Amber Heard, but as an avid user of social media I find that it has finally become completely …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=vqU-tPA5cMg:OqakBcV7DB0:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131508</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T18:05:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T18:05:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>With "Station Eleven", apocalyptic fiction has come of age</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5974/with-station-eleven-apocalyptic-fiction-has-come-of-age#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="A still from &amp;quot;Station Eleven&amp;quot;" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/StationEleven.jpeg" height="1067" alt="A still from 'Station Eleven'" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;In March 2020, it felt like those of us who were lucky enough to be able to lock down in our homes and watch a lot of television were quickly sorted into two opposing camps. There were those who sought out a total escape from the daily accumulation of death tolls. Absurdist documentaries like Netflix&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Tiger King&lt;/em&gt; and endless dating reality shows were this group&amp;rsquo;s binging material. But alongside them co-existed the people who wanted to immerse themselves in fictional versions of their current situation, rather than look away. Pandemic-based films like &lt;em&gt;Contagion&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;28 Days Later&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Outbreak&lt;/em&gt; and others provided this hit of schadenfreude, filling our screens with safely contained versions of &amp;ldquo;what if&amp;rdquo; even as a real-life virus raged through our communities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;These, and indeed many other conventional disaster movies, follow a simple narrative template. The viewer is introduced to the central characters before The Event that will utterly change their lives, either in early scenes or via flashbacks to life before. Initially, the warning signs of the cataclysm are ignored by many, until it is too late to prevent the inevitable. Transmission of the virus surges exponentially, millions die, and our remaining heroes are left to make the best of the life that remains to them in the post-apocalyptic landscape. Invariably, human life finds a way to endure, albeit in much altered and reduced circumstances. To put it another way: it is extremely rare for a mainstream pandemic thriller to end with the camera panning over an empty planet heaped with corpses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;"Station Eleven" and breaking new ground&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;There is something gratifying about the rhythms of this basic story. It takes a terrifying, incomprehensible unknown and slots it into a familiar structure with a beginning, middle and end. But having now lived through two years and counting of a major viral pandemic, we know that such an event is anything but neat and compartmentalised. Imaginary pandemics will forever hit differently for us, now we have first-hand experience of the chaos such a situation can create in the lives of even the luckiest survivor. With this knowledge has come an appetite for a different kind of on-screen pandemic &amp;ndash; something that reflects the true complexities of life with a deadly virus and resists the easy categorisation of everyone as either &amp;ldquo;victim&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;survivor&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The best example of this new wave of fictional pandemics was, surprisingly, imagined long before the SARS‑CoV‑2 virus was first identified. Emily St John Mandel&amp;rsquo;s novel &lt;em&gt;Station Eleven &lt;/em&gt;was published in 2014 and follows a group of travelling players touring the Great Lakes region of North America 20 years after a virulent strain of swine flu has wiped out most of the population. Although critically acclaimed from the start, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t until 2020 that the book went stratospheric, selling hundreds of thousands of copies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;A film adaptation had been in the works since 2015, but in late 2019 this was revealed to have been transformed into a television series for the HBO Max streaming service. By the time the show aired in 2021, the world had been altered irrevocably by events that bore an uncanny similarity to those of the plot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Yet &lt;em&gt;Station Eleven&lt;/em&gt; is worth watching regardless of its coincidental mirroring of reality. Mandel&amp;rsquo;s story, unlike some of the big-budget pandemic thrillers that scratched that early itch for manageable terror, is small in scale. It focuses tightly on the creative and emotional lives of her main characters. As is the case with real people, their past relationships and traumas inform their present-day behaviour far more than the big-picture facts about a flu virus. The virus intrudes only insofar as it is relevant to their daily existence. There are no forced flashbacks showing what the US president was doing the moment that the virus hit, or dramatic scenes where epidemiologists summarise the worldwide prognosis.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The show is emotional and dark in places, but it is also, audaciously, uplifting. Hinting that people who have suffered through horrible things can also sometimes enjoy the life they still have feels daring, almost taboo, but at our current moment it is deeply satisfying."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;"Sweet Tooth" and "Creamery": a new breed of story?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sweet Tooth,&lt;/em&gt; a 2021 adaptation of a comic book of the same name, uses whimsy and fantasy to achieve a similarly broad emotional range. In this scenario, society has ten years prior experienced &amp;ldquo;the Great Crumble&amp;rdquo;, because of a pandemic known only as &amp;ldquo;the Sick&amp;rdquo;. As a result, most of the world&amp;rsquo;s humans were killed and human-animal hybrid babies emerged. Gus, a half-deer half-child, has been left alone in the woods after the death of his father. He thus sets out on his own at the age of ten to find his absent mother.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The show is visually gorgeous, setting this cute antlered child in a series of sweeping forest landscapes. The beauty all around him contrasts with Gus&amp;rsquo;s ambient fear. He is being hunted by a band of humans known as &amp;ldquo;the Last Men&amp;rdquo;, who fear that these hybrid children were the cause, rather than the result, of the pandemic. The Sick not only killed people, it also destroyed the survivors&amp;rsquo; ability to interact without suspicion. As a portrayal of a pandemic&amp;rsquo;s ripple effect, it is potent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Seriousness is another boundary that creators of post-Covid pandemics are beginning to push. Contagion and death are not traditionally fertile grounds for comedy, but choosing to laugh at horrible things can sometimes tease out greater nuance than a purely po-faced treatment. This is definitely the case in &lt;em&gt;Creamerie&lt;/em&gt;, a late 2021 comedy-horror show from New Zealand that follows a trio of women running a dairy farm eight years after a viral pandemic has wiped out most of the world&amp;rsquo;s men. Although free of the patriarchal dynamics that govern other post-apocalyptic fertility-orientated stories such as &lt;em&gt;The Handmaid&amp;rsquo;s Tale&lt;/em&gt;, the working women of &lt;em&gt;Creamerie&lt;/em&gt; still find themselves oppressed by a fascist authority. But this one is run by authoritarian women and uses &amp;ldquo;wellness&amp;rdquo; practices to achieve its ends. Part black comedy, part satire, part crime caper, it can feel unsettling at first to laugh at the show&amp;rsquo;s jabs at wellness mantras alongside flashbacks to the gory pyres of male corpses. But when the women discover a man who has survived the extermination and decide to help him evade capture by the sperm-obsessed wellness authorities, the emotional stakes are raised.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Bobby, played by a former &lt;em&gt;Neighbours&lt;/em&gt; star, needs their generosity and courage to survive, even if he is physically stronger than the women in authority. The mixture of camaraderie, jadedness and hope exhibited by the central characters is recognisable. In amongst the dirty jokes and Gwyneth Paltrow-esque platitudes &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s an &amp;lsquo;us&amp;rsquo; in every uterus!&amp;rdquo; they chant at one point &amp;ndash; is a familiar tale about power and who gets to wield it in difficult times.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;All three of these post-Covid pandemic portrayals are set years after the initial outbreak. One of the overriding lessons of the last two years has been that pandemics don&amp;rsquo;t end as neatly as the classic disaster film might have once led us to believe. Rather than being short and sharp, this is a calamity that unfolds slowly, intertwining with our existing lives, rather than blotting them out in one convenient detonation. It&amp;rsquo;s no wonder that we now prefer pandemic dramas that engage with the myriad ways in which these creeping tendrils of fear can change us and how we live &amp;ndash; for the worse, of course, but also for the better.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5974/with-station-eleven-apocalyptic-fiction-has-come-of-age#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T10:39:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T10:39:19Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Impossible freedom</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5973/impossible-freedom#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/freedom.jpg" height="359" alt="'Freedom' by Raymond Tallis" width="239" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;"All theory is against free will; all experience for it.&amp;rdquo; So said Dr Johnson, in his famous formulation. Which, then, should we follow: theory or experience? Is it our responsibility to follow the inexorable logic of theories wherever they might lead, even if they deny us the reality of our freedom? Or do we take as our guide the practical knowledge that for anything we do to be meaningfully ours at all, it must have been chosen freely? Both options are open to the philosopher, and both suggest not only different pre-theoretical commitments, but different conceptions of what philosophy might help us do with our freedom.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The theoretical arguments against free will are familiar. The natural world is governed by exceptionless and immutable laws. Everything we do is an effect of causes outside of our control, so even when we think we are choosing between alternative futures, there is in truth no way we could have done otherwise, and therefore no meaningful sense in which we are free. All said, we are nothing but a conduit for natural forces: we never act, things only happen to us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This possibility terrified Immanuel Kant. Like many before and since, Kant saw a deterministic universe as a kind of desert, bereft of anything that could make human life meaningful. Without free will there is no morality, no taking responsibility for our own life or the lives of others. The task of philosophy is to show a way out of this uninhabitable desert, to show how free will is possible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This was not the only response to determinism. Spinoza asks us to consider a stone falling from the sky. Were we to ask the stone, Spinoza suggests, it would claim that it moves of its own accord, and could just as well decide to change direction if it pleased. Human freedom, he argues, like that of the stone, consists solely in our being conscious of our desires yet ignorant of their causes. Stubbornly clinging to our intuitions of freedom even where they contradict rational thought is a kind of betrayal, an abdication of philosophical responsibility. The purpose of philosophy is not to find space for freedom &amp;ndash; there is none &amp;ndash; but rather to conceive what a meaningful human life might look like given its absence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;Free will and science: a reconciliation?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The very title of Raymond Tallis&amp;rsquo;s new book tells us where he stands. &lt;em&gt;Freedom: An Impossible Reality&lt;/em&gt; &amp;ndash; impossible according to theory, and yet affirmed by our every action. For Tallis, the experience of freedom is non-negotiable: we cannot but experience ourselves as choosing and deciding, intervening in the world in ways that make a difference to it. Beginning from the reality of this experience, Tallis argues that where our theories appear to contradict free will, it is a sign we have misinterpreted them. Scientific theories, far from providing arguments against free will, are powerful evidence for its existence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Tallis is a philosopher, but he also spent much of his career as a clinical neuroscientist. Early on in the book, he takes on the concept of &amp;ldquo;neurodeterminism&amp;rdquo;, according to which it is not us but the neurochemistry of our brains that really calls the shots in human agency. Everything we do, according to this theory, is pre-determined by the firings of neurons in our brain, as is supposedly demonstrated by the famous experiments of Benjamin Libet, in which certain neurons are seen to fire in advance of the self-reported taking of a &amp;ldquo;decision&amp;rdquo; (whatever that is supposed to mean, neuroscientifically speaking). Tallis presents a convincing argument that such interpretations tend to turn good science into bad philosophy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;The most original part of Tallis&amp;rsquo;s argument is his account of causation. Determinism relies on the idea of causal necessity: the earthquake in the ocean bed causes a chain of events that necessarily leads to the tsunami crashing on the coast. But, Tallis argues, causal necessity is not at all inherent in nature. David Hume famously claimed that the &amp;ldquo;necessary connection&amp;rdquo; between cause and effect is formed in the mind, and Tallis pushes the argument further, arguing not only that the necessary connection between cause and effect is forged in the mind, but that what we call &amp;ldquo;causes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; are themselves mind-dependent, picked out from a fundamentally undifferentiated nature for pragmatic purposes. If causes and effects are not building blocks of reality, but useful tools that are simply assigned that status for explanatory purposes, it makes little sense to think of ourselves as constrained by them. Causation is not something outside us that limits our freedom, but an expression of the free and creative choices we make in constructing scientific theories.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This brings us to Tallis&amp;rsquo;s controversial claim of the &amp;ldquo;unnaturalness of natural science&amp;rdquo;: the claim that the very practice of experimental science demonstrates our freedom, because it shows that in an important sense, we stand outside of nature. Nature, left to its own devices, has certain habits; there are patterns and regularities to its behaviour. But for these &amp;ldquo;habits of nature&amp;rdquo; to become &amp;ldquo;laws of science&amp;rdquo;, there must be conscious subjects to discover and elaborate these laws &amp;ndash; there must be something which &amp;ldquo;stands outside&amp;rdquo; nature, holding a mirror up to it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The importance of "intentionality"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;What allows us to stand outside the laws of nature, Tallis argues, is &amp;ldquo;intentionality&amp;rdquo;, the relation between a mind and a world by virtue of which thoughts can be &lt;em&gt;about &lt;/em&gt;anything at all. He argues that this is a property unique to human subjects: earthquakes &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;, but they are not &lt;em&gt;about&lt;/em&gt; anything. The thoughts of seismologists, on the other hand, are quite frequently about earthquakes. It is this aboutness that &amp;ldquo;opens up a distance&amp;rdquo;, what Tallis calls the &amp;ldquo;virtual distance created by intentionality&amp;rdquo;. This distance allows the scientist to observe the world, to carve events into &amp;ldquo;causes&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; for his own purposes, and to open up a space of possibility outside of that which actually exists. Crucially, the intentionality that allows for action and for the scientific gaze cannot itself be explained scientifically: &amp;ldquo;telereception explains how the light gets in, but not how a gaze looks out.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;If this sounds less razor-sharp than the earlier critiques, it is. Tallis does not suffer from the inhibition of academic philosophers, or share the restraint of their conclusions. This makes for an invigorating treatise, especially in the critical sections, and it is perhaps natural that Tallis is more convincing arguing against determinism than for free will. If free will just &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;, then Tallis&amp;rsquo;s task is to rid those overly enamoured of scientific materialism of the strange delusions that lead them to deny manifest reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;But which is the delusion? Denying the experience of freedom affirmed by our every action, or insisting, like Spinoza&amp;rsquo;s stone, that in spite of everything we know, we are free, for no other reason than we feel we must be? One final response suggests itself: a shrug of the shoulders. Being &lt;em&gt;truly, really, metaphysically&lt;/em&gt; free might mean very little to me. Whether or not I am truly free, I still have to get out of bed in the morning. I still make plans for the future, hope for their success and risk disappointment if they fail. Does any of this depend on my being radically free? Would any of it be compromised if I was but a conduit for natural forces? If not, if I were to go about my life the same way in either case, then the distinction between free will and determinism, in which so much of our humanity appears to be at stake, can come to seem a difference that makes no difference at all.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5973/impossible-freedom#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-26T10:04:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-26T10:04:56Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Science of How to Stop Mass Shootings</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/the-science-of-how-to-stop-mass-shootings/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: On Tuesday, May 24 2022, an 18-year old South Texas man shot his grandmother, drove to an elementary school, barricaded himself in a classroom, and murdered 19 small children and 2 adults before he …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uB502D_VwZ8:J8m4N9G8Ewk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131506</id>
    <published>2022-05-25T19:56:10Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-25T19:56:10Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Twitter: Reinstate Atheist Republic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/twitter-reinstate-atheist-republic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier this year, Twitter suspended the account of Atheist Republic (@AtheistRepublic) for unspecified violations after complaints from the Indian government. In the letter below, Robyn Blumner, president and CEO of the Center for Inquiry, and Richard Dawkins, CFO board member and founder of the Richard Dawkins Foundation for Reason &amp; Science, write to request that …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978338</id>
    <published>2022-05-12T15:44:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-12T15:44:56Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dawkins on the Overturning of Roe: “They Think It’s Murder”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/dawkins-on-the-overturning-of-roe-they-think-its-murder/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an essay exclusive to Free Inquiry, Richard Dawkins responds to the likely overturning of Roe v. Wade by the U.S. Supreme Court, and the roots of anti-abortion fanaticism found in Catholic dogma. Why are they so fanatical about this one issue, eclipsing, as it does, all others? It is because they really think abortion …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978334</id>
    <published>2022-05-12T14:56:14Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-12T14:56:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/open-discussion-may-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978329</id>
    <published>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/04/open-discussion-april-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978276</id>
    <published>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
