<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2021-10-03T06:36:00Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Don’t debate creationists, mmm-kay?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/10/02/dont-debate-creationists-mmm-kay/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hw1xH0ne2aI" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64068</id>
    <published>2021-10-02T17:42:48Z</published>
    <updated>2021-10-02T17:42:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Clean him out, shut him down</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/10/01/clean-him-out-shut-him-down/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones-150x113.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="113" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-64065" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones-150x113.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones-300x225.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones-768x576.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones-500x375.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/alexjones.jpg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></p>
<p class="lead">Alex Jones has, by default, <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2021/10/01/us/alex-jones-loses-sandy-hook-cases/index.html">lost two lawsuits</a> that accuse him of being responsible for the abuse the parents of children murdered in the Sandy Hook shooting received. You may recall that he claimed none of the children were killed, that their parents were “crisis actors” trying to profit off the story, and that the whole tragedy was a “false flag” operation to kill the second amendment (which I hope does get killed someday).</p>
<blockquote><p>Alex Jones, the conspiracy theorist who hosts the right-wing commentary website Infowars, was found legally responsible in two lawsuits for damages caused by his claims surrounding the 2012 Sandy Hook school mass shooting, according to court documents released Thursday.</p>
<p>Judge Maya Guerra Gamble issued default judgments on Monday against Jones and his outlet for not complying with court orders to provide information for the lawsuits brought against him by the parents of two children killed in the shooting.<br/>
The rulings, which were first reported by the Huffington Post, effectively mean that Jones lost the cases by default. A jury will convene to ascertain how much he will owe the plaintiffs, the report said.</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh, boy, I eagerly await news of the penalties. I hope they’re substantial enough to shut down Infowars for good.</p>
<p>ESAD, evil fraud.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alex Jones has, by default, lost two lawsuits that accuse him of being responsible for the abuse the parents of children murdered in the Sandy Hook shooting received. You may recall that he claimed none of the children were killed, that their parents were “crisis actors” trying to profit off the story, and that the […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64064</id>
    <published>2021-10-01T17:17:45Z</published>
    <updated>2021-10-01T17:17:45Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Friday Cephalopod: Freeday Octopus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/10/01/friday-cephalopod-freeday-octopus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/illianaaquarium-200x300.png" alt="" width="200" height="300" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-64061" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/illianaaquarium-200x300.png 200w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/illianaaquarium-100x150.png 100w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/illianaaquarium.png 395w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px"/></p>
<p class="lead">A few months ago, my granddaughter Iliana got to visit the Seattle Aquarium, along with many other Pacific Northwest landmarks. Here she is communing with the Giant Pacific Octopus that was there.</p>
<p>Good news! The aquarium has <a href="https://westseattleblog.com/2021/09/west-seattle-scene-licorice-the-octopus-goes-free/">set the octopus free</a>! Transporting him in a garbage can seems a little undignified, but the important thing is that now he can wander in Puget Sound, looking for mates and, we hope, siring many progeny.</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/licoricefreed-500x375.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="375" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64062" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/licoricefreed-500x375.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/licoricefreed-150x113.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/licoricefreed-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/10/licoricefreed.jpeg 652w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few months ago, my granddaughter Iliana got to visit the Seattle Aquarium, along with many other Pacific Northwest landmarks. Here she is communing with the Giant Pacific Octopus that was there. Good news! The aquarium has set the octopus free! Transporting him in a garbage can seems a little undignified, but the important thing […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64060</id>
    <published>2021-10-01T13:03:36Z</published>
    <updated>2021-10-01T13:03:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Cephalopods"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION OCTOBER 2021</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/10/open-discussion-october-2021/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for discussion on themes relevant to Reason and Science for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977317</id>
    <published>2021-10-01T08:18:48Z</published>
    <updated>2021-10-01T08:18:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What are you wearing?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/30/what-are-you-wearing/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Y’all know it is <a href="https://www.orangeshirtday.org/">Orange Shirt Day</a>, right?</p>
<p><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday-500x667.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="667" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64058" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday-500x667.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday-113x150.jpg 113w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday-225x300.jpg 225w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/orangeshirtday.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></p>
<p>It doesn’t change much, but at the very least I can make a statement that I’m aware of the injustice in how we Europeans treated the native people of this land. Get your orange shirt on!</p>
<p>By the way, I discovered several years ago that I had nothing that was orange in my closet — it’s a less common color for everyday apparel. You may have to go shopping for it.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Y’all know it is Orange Shirt Day, right? It doesn’t change much, but at the very least I can make a statement that I’m aware of the injustice in how we Europeans treated the native people of this land. Get your orange shirt on! By the way, I discovered several years ago that I had […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64057</id>
    <published>2021-09-30T16:20:28Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-30T16:20:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>…cut off their tails with a CRISPR knife…</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2021/09/30/cut-off-their-tails-with-a-crispr-knife/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Brachyury&lt;/i&gt; (Greek for &amp;#8220;short tail&amp;#8221;) is an important protein in animal development &amp;#8212; it&amp;#8217;s found in &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; chordates and is expressed along the midline, and sets up the anterior-posterior axis. It seems to play an essential role in defining tissues along the length of the animal, and many mutations have been found in the gene &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; for it that cause defects in the spinal cord. In addition to the short tail phenotype it&amp;#8217;s named for, different variants affect other regions as well. For instance, you probably know that almost all mammals have precisely 7 cervical vertebrae, but there is a mutation in &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; that reduces that number to 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, basically, if you want to profoundly muck up the developing vertebrae and spinal cord, mutating &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; is a way to do it, as long as you don&amp;#8217;t mind inducing neural tube defects, like say, spina bifida. It&amp;#8217;s a dangerously significant gene to tinker with, and most of the outcomes would not be good. But note &amp;#8212; humans and other hominoids have an inherited, ubiquitous spinal cord defect. We don&amp;#8217;t have tails, unlike other mammals. Could we be carrying a mutation in our &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; gene? Could that be what caused all us apes to lose our tails? Maybe we should look and compare our &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; to that of other animals. Huh, what do you know…we do have &lt;a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.09.14.460388v1.full.pdf"&gt;a curiously broken &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids-500x205.png" alt="" width="500" height="205" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64052" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids-500x205.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids-150x61.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids-300x123.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids-768x315.png 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/taillesshominoids.png 908w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little background first. Eukaryotic genes are broken up into segments called exons alternating with other segments called introns. To make a functional gene product, like &lt;i&gt;Brachyury&lt;/i&gt;, the cell has enzymes that cut out the introns from the RNA and splice together the exons. The intronic RNA is then generally allowed to be broken down and recycled. So &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; has 7 exons, E1, E2, E3, E4, E5, E6, and E7, with intervening introns which must be snipped out and the exons spliced together to make a final, complete RNA, E1-E2-E3-E4-E5-E6-E7, which will be translated to make the &lt;i&gt;Brachyury&lt;/i&gt; protein.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another complication: there are these short bits of selfish DNA called Alus which are scattered throughout the genome. We have over a million Alu elements sprinkled throughout, and usually they do nothing, although if an Alu gets inserted into an exon of a gene, it can disrupt the function of that gene. The good news: there is no Alu stuck in the exons of &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt;. There are a couple of them in the introns of &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt;, but remember, the introns get chopped out and thrown away, so they shouldn&amp;#8217;t matter. Except that in this case, they do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In us hominoids, there is one Alu, AluSx1, in intron 5. There is another Alu, AluY, in intron 6. They happen to complement each other in reverse, so in the &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; RNA, before the introns are edited out, the RNA folds over to make a loop that allows the two Alus to bind to each other. This messes up the editing, because the cell then snips out the introns &lt;em&gt;and the loop&lt;/em&gt;, throwing away exon 6. Uh-oh. That means that instead of producing the full length &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt;, we make a shortened version lacking exon 6, called &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/AluSx1-AluY-500x309.png" alt="" width="500" height="309" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64053" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/AluSx1-AluY-500x309.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/AluSx1-AluY-150x93.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/AluSx1-AluY-300x186.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/AluSx1-AluY.png 734w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This observation was tested with a couple of nifty experiments. First question: is it really the Alus that are causing this error in splicing? Yes. Doing a little gene editing and knocking out either Alu in human embryonic stem cells causes them to generate full length &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; transcripts. These are just single cells in a dish, and while you might be curious to know if deleting those specific Alus in a human &lt;em&gt;embryo&lt;/em&gt; would lead to it developing a tail, that would be unethical. In a sense, you&amp;#8217;d be generating a neural tube defect, never a desired outcome, and we don&amp;#8217;t know what other compensatory or cooperative genes to our, for us, normal &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt; exist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But hey, good news, we don&amp;#8217;t have the same ethical restrictions when working with mouse embryos! Let&amp;#8217;s dive into the mouse genome and insert Alus, just like ours, into the introns of the mouse &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; gene! And so it was done, producing mice that made &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt;, and lo, they had little stumpy tails, or no tails at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/mouseTBXT-500x379.png" alt="" width="500" height="379" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64054" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/mouseTBXT-500x379.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/mouseTBXT-150x114.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/mouseTBXT-300x227.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/mouseTBXT.png 765w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few complications. Mice that were homozygous for &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt; died embryonically with substantial neural tube defects. Heterozygotes for &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt; survived, and exhibited the tailless phenotype with variable penetrance, that is some mice were lacking the whole shebang, missing sacral vertebrae (sv) and all caudal vertebrae (cv), and others lost variable numbers of caudal vertebrae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s lovely work, but I still have to disagree a little bit with their interpretation. Their model of hominoid evolution puts the tail-loss mutation right at the base of the progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model-500x174.png" alt="" width="500" height="174" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-64055" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model-500x174.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model-150x52.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model-300x105.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model-768x268.png 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2021/09/tail-loss-model.png 792w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s too simple. The lethality of the homozygous mutant in mice, while we homozygous mutants are fine, tells me that there are a lot of other genes that work together with &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; to make a viable embryo &amp;#8212; that we have a suite of supporting genes that can compensate for the lethal effects of &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt;. This model assumes that all those supporting roles evolved &lt;em&gt;after&lt;/em&gt; the &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt; mutation occurred. There is no reason to think that. Why not consider that our ancestral hominoid had a few exaptations that made it slightly more fault-tolerant in axis formation? Put those additional mutations ahead of the AluY insertion. Then have additional mutations afterwards. Our ancestors were not mice, so there&amp;#8217;s no reason to think they&amp;#8217;d have had the same response (that is, the lethality) to &lt;i&gt;TBXT-&amp;Delta;exon6&lt;/i&gt; as do modern mice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, now I&amp;#8217;m really interested in those additional mutations. &lt;i&gt;TBXT&lt;/i&gt; isn&amp;#8217;t the whole story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xia, b, Zhang W, Wudzinska A, Huang E, Brosh R, Pour M, Miller A, Dasen JS, Maurano MT, Kim SY, Boeke JD, Yanai I (2021) &lt;a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.09.14.460388v1.full.pdf"&gt;The genetic basis of tail-loss evolution in humans and apes&lt;/a&gt;. https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.09.14.460388v1&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brachyury (Greek for “short tail”) is an important protein in animal development — it’s found in all chordates and is expressed along the midline, and sets up the anterior-posterior axis. It seems to play an essential role in defining tissues along the length of the animal, and many mutations have been found in the gene […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=64051</id>
    <published>2021-09-30T12:42:06Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-30T12:42:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Evolution"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Chronicles of decline</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5863/chronicles-of-decline#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/checklist_composition_handwriting_list_memo_note_notebook_page-1553027.jpg" height="450" alt="checklist_composition_handwriting_list_memo_note_notebook_page-1553027" width="800" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While some of my more creative colleagues have used their lockdown time to pen indulgent autobiographies, increase the size of their biceps, or finally master the intricacies of Derridean deconstructionism, I&amp;rsquo;ve passed a productive nine months developing a personal deterioration index. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What prompted this initiative was the melancholy realisation that several of my nearest and dearest were developing a range of unacknowledged signs of ageing. Consider my former academic colleague Ralph Stigsby. He&amp;rsquo;s now drifting inexorably into late middle age. Nothing at all the matter with that. It is happening to most of us. But Ralph, whose early work on the French symbolist poets was described in the Times Literary Supplement as &amp;ldquo;unexpectedly lucid&amp;rdquo;, has singularly failed to bring any such perceptual clarity to his own physical condition.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Now, I was only too happy when Ralph announced his intention to come round and watch the Euro 2020 matches on my television. I reckoned that the presence of such a celebrated academic on the domestic sofa might go some way to temper my wife&amp;rsquo;s constant contention that there was surely something more to life than watching 22 grown men kicking a ball backwards and forwards. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But even before the first match had reached half time, I found my attention wandering. For even as Raheem Stirling set off on another dazzling run or Harry Kane let loose a blistering shot, I was distracted by my sofa companion&amp;rsquo;s complaints about the inadequacy of the television picture and the incoherence of the commentary. At first I attempted to accommodate my companion&amp;rsquo;s problem by subtly shifting the sofa nearer to the screen and unobtrusively yanking up the sound level. It was only when Ralph missed yet another critical moment in the Germany game because of his need for a further trip to the bathroom that I made my personal resolution. Rather than ignoring any of my own developing physical deficiencies, rather than blaming them upon faults in material reality, I would draw up a definitive list: a deterioration index.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I began with my sight. Now, although cataract surgery means that I no longer need to nudge the sofa closer to the television or noisily complain about the size of the print in contemporary novels, I have noted on the very first page of my index that from time to time the world around me unexpectedly starts to rotate. An armchair which customarily sits firmly alongside my sofa can quite suddenly take to the air and deposit itself alongside the bookshelf on the other side of the room. This optical displacement remedies itself in several seconds, but in my index the phenomenon is marked down as firm evidence of deteriorating sight, rather than being falsely attributed to the recurrence of an ancient acid trip or the intervention of a hostile poltergeist.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I have been equally circumspect about my hearing. My index has absolutely no truck with the idea that young people now only speak in murmurs or with the notion that the age of my iPhone has interfered with its volume control. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These deteriorations only occupy a small part of the index. On other pages I note that my occasional stumbles on the way to my local Waitrose can no longer be attributed to the local council&amp;rsquo;s inability to fix cracks in the paving stones, and that there are really no grounds for maintaining that Marks &amp;amp; Spencer have been subtly reducing the size of trouser waistbands. My deterioration index announces the real truth in capital letters: &amp;ldquo;GETTING FATTER&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It has not all been plain sailing. Until recently, for example, I had come to the conclusion that my newfound inability to readily retrieve a packet of biscuits from the very top shelf of the kitchen cabinet could only be attributed to the slipperiness, the ungraspability, of the new plastic packaging. However, a recent medical examination has led to a much more considered entry in my index. After feeling my pulse and pressing my stomach in a few places, my doctor invited me to stand up straight on the scales in the corner of the surgery. &amp;ldquo;Very good. Very good,&amp;rdquo; he muttered (he did mutter) as he lowered the wooden measuring bar onto my scalp. &amp;ldquo;But there is just one thing. It happens to everyone. Nothing to worry about. It&amp;rsquo;s an ageing process.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That &amp;ldquo;one thing&amp;rdquo; is now dutifully recorded in my deterioration index. Under Biscuit Tin Retrieval, there is the sad but terse truth: &amp;ldquo;GETTING SHORTER&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5863/chronicles-of-decline#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-30T08:51:32Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-30T08:51:32Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Q&amp;A: Kyle Harper</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5859/qa-kyle-harper#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Kyle-Harper-Portrait-Outside-1.jpg" height="595" alt="Kyle-Harper-Portrait-Outside-1" width="800" /&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dr Kyle Harper is a historian of the ancient world whose work has spanned economic, environmental and social history. He holds the post of Professor of Classics and Letters and Provost Emeritus at The University of Oklahoma, and has published four books on the history of slavery, sexual morality, climate, disease and empire. His latest, "Plagues Upon the Earth: Disease and the Course of Human History", is published in October 2021 by Princeton University Press. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You write that humankind&amp;rsquo;s ability to control infectious diseases is a relatively new thing. What intensity of fears might have stalked those who came before us? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was every handshake or doorknob potentially lethal?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s certainly new, in the grand scheme of human history. It&amp;rsquo;s easy for us to forget that down to around 1900, even in the most economically developed societies, infectious diseases were collectively the leading cause of death. Throughout our past, diseases like malaria and tuberculosis, typhus and typhoid, smallpox and measles and plague, and a lot of other diseases caused by microbial pathogens were the biggest burden on human health. Of course people feared sickness and were surrounded by threats in a way that is I think hard for us to understand. But recall that they also did not have our concept of germs &amp;ndash; of microscopic agents of infection. They thought of disease as a kind of imbalance in the body, perhaps caused by poor diet or bad air or a weak constitution. I don&amp;rsquo;t think we should imagine most people in the past as &amp;ldquo;germophobes&amp;rdquo; in the contemporary sense!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You make the point that our mastery of disease and other illnesses is geographically uneven. Viruses know no borders, but quality of treatment, in a sense, does. Has this worsened or improved? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is important to think about health inequality historically and to consider both &lt;em&gt;within society differences&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;between societies differences&lt;/em&gt;. Between-society inequalities in health are a product of both geographic and human factors, and the interplay of these over very long time-periods. In the modern period, say from 1500 onward, the gap between the most and least healthy countries grows. In the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century, the gaps really widen, both because of rapid improvements in countries that industrialized first, but also because the disease environments in much of the world became much more challenging then too. The increase in global trade and in imperialism may actually have lowered life expectancies in many places. I argue that the global gaps in life expectancy may have peaked around 1900. Since then, there has actually been convergence, thanks to the global spread of science and biomedicine and public health, decolonization, and economic development. But, obviously, there are still large inequities today, driven in part by the burden of infectious disease. It is too easy to take for granted basic things like clean drinking water (one of the most important foundations of good health) that remains unevenly distributed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Several factors have spurred an evolution in diseases that affect humans, including population growth and the development of agriculture. The latter allowed humans to become more sedentary. What happened then?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s actually an old trope that the transition from hunting and gathering to farming was a calamity for human health. In the 1970s Marshall Sahlins started calling hunter-gatherer societies the original affluent societies, and in the 1980s Jared Diamond called farming humanity&amp;rsquo;s greatest mistake. It&amp;rsquo;s true that farming was bad for human health in lots of ways, but we are starting to learn a lot about how changes in human societies shaped the ecology and evolution of our pathogens. I would argue that we have underestimated some of the effects of sedentism on disease environments. Among the many ecological implications of settling down from a mobile lifestyle to a settled one is that our ancestors started living in close proximity to their waste, and the waste of their domesticated animals. There&amp;rsquo;s really nothing in nature quite like the aggregation of feces in human settlements. And the evolutionary reaction to this is that we get a lot &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;a lot &lt;/em&gt;&amp;ndash; of pathogens that exploit the fecal-oral route of transmission. The burden of diarrheal disease and dysentery throughout human history is enormous, and it&amp;rsquo;s a consequence of the environments that we create.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A later evolution changed human ecology once again: the rise of early cities. What did the Alexandrias and Constantinoples of the world do to our vulnerability to diseases?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The rise of big cities &amp;ndash; which really takes off to new levels in the Iron Age &amp;ndash; was an important transition in the history of disease. To a microparasite, the human body is a host. The more of them there are, and the more densely packed they are, the easier it is to exploit them. So the rise of dense aggregations of human bodies is the ecological background to the rise of a number of directly-transmissible pathogens &amp;ndash; ones that transmit from host to host, often via the respiratory route. Measles is a perfect example. It becomes a human pathogen just as humans figure out how to build big cities. The measles virus is a freak of nature. It is completely specialized in infecting humans. It confers very strong and enduring immune resistance in survivors. It is extremely contagious and moves through susceptible populations quickly. In short, it has an evolutionary strategy that only works because of us &amp;ndash; because we built big cities. Measles goes rapidly extinct whenever it is introduced into small, susceptible populations. Measles exists because of human social development. And now we have pretty remarkable consilient evidence for this from different fields. A new genetic study suggests that the measles virus adapted to human populations around 2500 years ago. That&amp;rsquo;s just the moment when human societies start building cities big enough to keep measles circulating for a long time.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Population change as a result of mass death from plague is one obvious example of how disease has shaped human social evolution. What are some of the less obvious examples?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The relationship goes both ways. Structures of power shape human health, while infectious diseases also shape power dynamics. Again, this is true both within and between societies. The whole history of colonialism, slavery, and imperialism was shaped by these two-way relationships, fundamentally. And disease has also had a strong impact on things like fertility and human capital. For instance, in really high-mortality environments, women have to marry earlier and have more children. There is a very strong association and I think causal relationship. And we now have a fairly firm understanding that the association between health and wealth goes both ways: yes, economic growth enables better health, but good health is also very conducive to economic productivity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technology has advanced humankind in myriad ways. But it&amp;rsquo;s also, in many ways, been catastrophic for our health. Tell us how.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the paradox of progress. We can see the connections between the history of technology and the history of disease by trying to see both from an ecological perspective. The technologies that make human societies more populous and more prosperous also make us easier and more appealing targets. Think of a technology like the railroad. The use of mineral energy to fuel transportation was revolutionary. It was also a boon for our germs. The railroad - and the steamship - facilitated the transmission of infectious disease in the 19&lt;sup&gt;th&lt;/sup&gt; century. The evident example is cholera, of course, which dispersed globally over rail and by steamboat. But influenza dispersed further and faster in the age of rail. And even diseases like malaria seem to have taken advantage of thicker networks of communication. Toward the end of the 19th century, by then in the steamboat age, bubonic plague made a bid to become a major global scourge again. Aggressive preventative measures kept it from flaring into disaster in most of the developed world, but the impact in east and south Asia was severe. In our own time, jet travel has similarly changed the connectivity of human populations and thus our pathogens. The dialectic of technological progress, pathogen evolution, and human adaptation is a fundamental theme of human history.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;As we push technological innovations further, will we become more susceptible to disease?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Any technology that exposes us to more potential new diseases - by, for instance, intruding on new ecosystems - or that facilitates easier transmission of diseases or makes us more numerous, will create the evolutionary incentives for diseases to take advantage of us. Of course there are no guarantees &amp;ndash; evolution is weird and unpredictable. And, of course, our tools continue to advance too. I think when we look back on the Covid-19 pandemic we will realize that it helped to stimulate a lot of amazing research and development. Hopefully the discoveries and technologies that we are making now will help us be more resilient in the future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve spent much of your career as a historian looking backwards, so to speak. But this issue compels us to look forward. How do you see our interaction with disease evolving over the coming century?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;Of course I want to plead that I am a historian, not a futurist. But the past can help us see longer trends. We should have been more prepared for Covid-19. We were repeatedly and continuously warned by experts in microbial evolution, zoonotic disease, public health, and so on. And we were warned by historians, too. One of my favourite books is William McNeill&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Plagues and Peoples&lt;/em&gt;, which ends&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;on a note of warning that infectious diseases have always been, and will always be, a factor for human societies. The reason why is evolution. Evolution is relentless, crafty, and weird. If there are more and more humans, microbes have the means, motives, and opportunity to adapt to exploit us. The modern period is not one of linear triumph for humanity. Thanks to empirical science and rational statecraft, we have gained a huge amount of control over infectious disease. But nature does not stand still. I think the big question is whether COVID-19 is the arrival of a new phase where we struggle to respond to microbial threats. And I would add that social adaptations are as important as technical solutions. Three extremely safe and effective vaccines were developed against Covid-19 in less than a year. The scientific response to the crisis has been tremendously strong. The social responses have been all over the place, with some communities and societies responding very well, others very poorly. We know new infectious diseases will arrive. We know our technical solutions will continue to advance. I worry more about our political capacities in the next few decades.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5859/qa-kyle-harper#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-30T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-30T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hard labour</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5861/hard-labour#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/YW038225L_Stages-in-pregnancy-as-represented-by-the-growth-of-the-womb-from-normal-state-through-to-3-6-and-9-months.jpg" height="395" alt="YW038225L_Stages-in-pregnancy-as-represented-by-the-growth-of-the-womb-from-normal-state-through-to-3-6-and-9-months" width="593" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The creation stories that have informed Western culture are full of miraculous births, with gods and mortals emerging from heads, shells and spare ribs. Looking to the future, medical advancements in the realm of artificial wombs have meanwhile raised questions as to whether, by the end of the 21st century, humans will in fact be &amp;ldquo;born&amp;rdquo; at all. For now, however, women still find themselves bound firmly to the earthly birth process &amp;ndash; one that can be fraught with trauma or injury for mother and infant. Furthermore, the medical cultures and institutions that govern this process have historically undermined women&amp;rsquo;s agency, and evidence suggests that they continue to do so today.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The innovations of medical intervention have greatly reduced maternal mortality across developed nations. In Finland, for example, they are as little as 5.6 per 100,000 live births, while rates across lower-income countries average at almost 500. The World Health Organisation (WHO) estimates that nearly 95 per cent of maternal deaths occur in low-resource settings and that most are preventable.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Given these advances and reductions in maternal mortality, modern medicine is often presented as the antidote to the risks of childbirth, taking control of the process to ensure a safer birth. These interventions range from caesarean sections &amp;ndash; the surgical procedure whereby a baby is delivered through an incision in the mother&amp;rsquo;s abdomen &amp;ndash; to the use of synthetic hormones to induce birth, epidurals for pain relief, and physical instruments such as forceps to physically pull the baby out. The fact that almost one third of female obstetricians in the UK (and almost half in the US) have expressed a preference for delivering their own babies via C-section may be enough to seed doubts about vaginal births among many women.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But at the same time, medical professionals and rights campaigners in wealthier nations are increasingly highlighting the obstetric violence &amp;ndash; neglect, physical abuse or lack of respect &amp;ndash; that too often accompanies medicalised interventions in birth. In this light, some maternity experts argue in favour of &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; birth, holding that we need to go back to basics, and retreat from medicalisation to rely on our human faculties and instincts.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The debate around birthing choices and the future trajectory of childbirth is a fraught and often polarising one, which can quickly veer away from evidence and into moralising and judgment. Many women find themselves at the mercy of the ideological or financial priorities of medical professionals and pressured into one form of birth or another, without the space to make their own informed decisions about their bodies&lt;span class="s1"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; In this context, what does progress in the realm of birth really look like?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Obstetric violence&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;When Anna Michalaki returned home from the birth of her first child in an Athens hospital in 2010, she was traumatised. &amp;ldquo;It was extremely stressful,&amp;rdquo; she says of her 34-hour labour. &amp;ldquo;I was afraid &amp;ndash; I was treated with no respect by the staff and given no choice about what was done to me.&amp;rdquo; It was only later that Anna, now a midwife, was able to name what she had suffered at the hands of the hospital system: obstetric violence. In 2018, she founded the Obstetric Violence Observatory in Greece to campaign to have this form of harm recognised under law.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Anna&amp;rsquo;s experience mirrors that of many women in a country with one of the most medicalised obstetric care systems in the world. The WHO recommends that caesareans should only be performed in cases of medical necessity. As it explains, this is surgery, and as such it can cause significant complications, disability or even death &amp;ndash; particularly in settings that lack resources to ensure its safe execution. The WHO recommends a caesarean rate of around 10-15 per cent. The average among EU member states is 25 per cent. Reported rates in Greece, however, are well above half, with the real figure likely much higher. Anna says that some public hospitals she spoke to boasted of more than 90 per cent C-section births. Following a 2016 review by the WHO, Greece pledged to reduce its excessive reliance on the procedure.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There can be financial incentives for doctors to perform C-sections, from limiting their overtime to payment perks for the surgery. This pattern has been observed in other high C-section countries such as Brazil, where there is a major spike in operations around Carnival, as doctors are loath to forgo the festivities while waiting around for a birth. These factors have been compounded in the aftermath of austerity in Greece. &amp;ldquo;Doctors don&amp;rsquo;t have good enough conditions to care about women&amp;rsquo;s health,&amp;rdquo; Anna says. &amp;ldquo;Now the typical view is that the most important thing is that the baby is alive &amp;ndash; they don&amp;rsquo;t care about anything beyond that.&amp;rdquo; This pragmatism is coupled with what many have described as a chauvinistic and technocratic medical culture that is geared towards intervention at the expense of women&amp;rsquo;s choice and, often, their well-being. &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;You cannot question the doctor &amp;ndash; they become something like a god,&amp;rdquo; explains Anna. &amp;ldquo;They are preparing you for surgery through the whole birth process, even if you don&amp;rsquo;t know it. The messaging protocol is that you are sick &amp;ndash; that your anatomy is wrong, so their method is to keep everything under control.&amp;rdquo; Such an approach means over-emphasising the risks to mother and baby of vaginal birth, while undermining women&amp;rsquo;s own capacity for informed decision-making. Anna says that misinformation has created the widespread belief among mothers and their families that C-sections are a cleaner, safer mode of delivery. &amp;ldquo;Most women don&amp;rsquo;t know what a C-section is &amp;ndash; they think it is an alternative to birth, not an emergency procedure. There is a cultural fear of pain and the woman often believes a C-section is better because her baby will not be stressed and she will not damaged. But if a woman is not properly informed, she cannot give informed consent.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;One 17-year-old migrant mother who had a C-section birth in Greece&amp;rsquo;s largest public maternity hospital told me that she felt coerced into the surgery. &amp;ldquo;Before the birth, I was watching YouTube videos about C-sections and I knew that I really did not want one,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;But I don&amp;rsquo;t know what happened in the hospital &amp;ndash; it was like I was not myself &amp;ndash; I had no choice. The staff lied and told me I was seven centimetres dilated when I was actually ten and then I signed a paper agreeing to the C-section, though I was telling myself, &amp;lsquo;No, no, no.&amp;rsquo; I felt so disappointed afterwards &amp;ndash; I wish I could have been stronger.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Similar observations about a medical culture that teaches women to distrust their own bodies have been made across developed countries. As one British midwife observed in a UK medical journal in relation to the notion of &amp;ldquo;choice&amp;rdquo; around surgical deliveries, &amp;ldquo;[women] are convinced that vaginal birth will distort and mutilate their bodies and leave them gaping and incontinent, or they are simply frightened about what doctors will do to them, and believe that caesarean section offers the safest birth for the baby . . . They see vaginal birth as ugly, agonising &amp;ndash; a form of torture &amp;ndash; and enlist a surgeon to avoid this.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;'Birth is seen as a problem'&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;This is not to say that new technology hasn&amp;rsquo;t improved outcomes. Giving birth is no longer the threat to life and health it once was, due to medical advancements. However, even beyond the potential for injustice or abuse in the deployment of such medical technology, some suggest that medicalisation has in fact diminished women&amp;rsquo;s natural abilities for childbirth.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Michel Odent has been a pioneer of natural birth since he founded the London-based Primal Health Research Centre in the 1980s. The French obstetrician argues that medical culture has conditioned us to regard birth as a problem, rather than a natural process. &amp;ldquo;The first question that is asked in medicine is, why is human birth so difficult?&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;But instead, we should start from another question &amp;ndash; why occasionally in the 21st century are there women who give birth easily and quickly without pharmacological assistance? That is &amp;ndash; why can women give birth so easily? And if we start from this, we can better understand the basic needs.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;One of the most fundamental needs, Odent argues, is for a woman in labour to retreat from cognitive functions &amp;ndash; and to be protected in doing so. &amp;ldquo;Giving birth is not a product of rational thinking &amp;ndash; even today there are still women who can understand the solution that nature found, cutting herself off from her world, forgetting what she learned in books, forgetting her plans, behaving in a way that might be considered unacceptable in a civilised world &amp;ndash; to scream and to swear, to find herself in postures that are mammalian or primitive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Yet the defining features of modern births &amp;ndash; be it the presence of other people in the ward, unnatural lighting, machine monitoring or informational overload &amp;ndash; all inhibit a woman&amp;rsquo;s inability to abandon cortical control and follow a more involuntary process. &amp;ldquo;In the 20th century, the history of childbirth was mostly influenced by technological advances &amp;ndash; we had the plastic revolution, the electronic revolution, advances in surgical techniques and anaesthetics. These have been absorbed all over the world,&amp;rdquo; says Odent. &amp;ldquo;But today, we have to de-programme the conditioning.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;From his early status as a leading voice on natural birth, encouraging the use of birthing pools and skin-to-skin contact after birth, Odent has become a more controversial figure following the publication of books such as &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Childbirth&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;and the&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;Future of Homo Sapiens&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/span&gt;and &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;The Birth of Homo, the Marine Chimpanzee&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. These works argue that modern medicine is &amp;ldquo;neutralising&amp;rdquo; the laws of natural selection by allowing babies to be born that might not otherwise have survived. While acknowledging the &amp;ldquo;miracle&amp;rdquo; of modern medicine, Odent argues that its advent has meant that most women no longer need to use important physiological functions in order to have a baby &amp;ndash; and indeed, that blind adherence to the medical trajectory may itself pose a grave threat to the future of human childbirth.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Foremost among his concerns is the role of oxytocin &amp;ndash; the so-called &amp;ldquo;love hormone&amp;rdquo; which is released during childbirth &amp;ndash; whose levels have been decreasing over the past half-century due to the use of synthetic oxytocin to induce or speed up labour, C-sections and the actively managed third stage of labour. A reduction in birth-rates and shortened duration of breast-feeding in OECD countries also mean that the oxytocin system is underused among women and may as a result, he proposes, be weakening in humans overall: a development with far-reaching consequences beyond birth itself. &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Odent notes that the first stage of labour is today much longer than it was in the mid-20th century. &amp;ldquo;We can anticipate that the capacity to give birth will become weaker in the future, taking into account what we are learning from epigenetics which shows that our physiological functions are underused . . . this is serious.&amp;rdquo; These are provocative claims. But Odent does not discount the use of C-sections, maintaining that they are often preferable to a traumatic vaginal birth. The decision, as he acknowledges, is often an extremely complex one.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Damaging deliveries&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;A 38-year-old mother of two, Melissa still doesn&amp;rsquo;t know which birth caused her injuries. Both of the screenwriter&amp;rsquo;s sons were 4kg or more, both were born in London NHS hospitals and both times &amp;ndash; once after a delivery involving an episiotomy and forceps and once after second-degree tearing &amp;ndash; she was stitched up by the midwife in the room and sent home the following day. More than two years on, she suffers faecal incontinence as a result of what was later determined to be, among other injuries, a fourth-degree tear and prolapse. She is unable to have penetrative sex and has been instructed not to engage in vigorous physical activity in case it worsens her condition.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;These injuries have had a profound impact on my life &amp;ndash; I was left very depressed, suicidal and diagnosed with PTSD,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;I kept reliving the births, the decisions made that led to these injuries, my own ignorance of the risks, my naivety in trusting others. I&amp;rsquo;ve been left feeling disgusting, broken, ashamed, dirty, sexless.&amp;rdquo; Melissa manages her symptoms &amp;ndash; which she has been told will worsen with age &amp;ndash; through various forms of therapy while she deliberates over the prospect of major and risky reconstructive surgery. Managing the social damage can be equally difficult. &amp;ldquo;I know women whose relationships broke down after their injury who have never sought another romantic partner, too ashamed of their symptoms,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;I know other women who&amp;rsquo;ve had to quit their job because the incontinence wasn&amp;rsquo;t possible to manage in their work environment, and those that don&amp;rsquo;t leave their homes because they&amp;rsquo;re afraid of having an incontinence episode in public.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t an outcome Melissa ever imagined when she first became pregnant. She attended all her maternity classes and midwife appointments, where &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;in contrast to Anna&amp;rsquo;s experiences in Greece&lt;span class="s1"&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;she was told about the dangers of interventions such as epidurals and C-sections and where natural births were emphasised as the preferred outcome for both mother and baby.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;There was a lot of focus on how we didn&amp;rsquo;t want C-sections because they could leave you bed-bound for a week and the recovery was terrible and it would interfere with breastfeeding and bonding with the baby,&amp;rdquo; she explains. &amp;ldquo;I was very scared of needing a C-section because I believed the information I was given. I was never given any information about the risk of vaginal childbirth, forceps delivery or what my choices were. I had complete trust in the healthcare professionals that everything would be fine.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It was only through Googling her symptoms after the births that she learned about the prevalence of incontinence, prolapsed pelvic floor organs, chronic pain and sexual dysfunction from childbirth. The average woman in the UK faces at least a 10 per cent risk of some form of post-partum incontinence &amp;ndash; a rate which increases in births assisted with medical intervention, for example, forceps or episiotomies. Research from one UK study suggests that at least 9,000 women are left with life-long faecal incontinence from birth injuries every year.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In 2020, a major UK independent review of the use of specific medical interventions, the &lt;span class="s1"&gt;First Do No Harm &lt;/span&gt;report, concluded that women had been widely dismissed and disbelieved by medical practitioners when seeking help for their injuries &amp;ndash; what some clinicians disregarded as &amp;ldquo;women&amp;rsquo;s issues&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;Women are exposed to injury, and at the mercy of a dysfunctional healthcare system that tells them that their injury is the cost of being a woman,&amp;rdquo; says Melissa, noting that seeking diagnosis and treatment has cost her around &amp;pound;3,000 &amp;ndash; a price that would be unaffordable to most women. &amp;ldquo;We tolerate the status quo in relation to birth injuries precisely because it happens to women. Caesarean section is considered the rich women&amp;rsquo;s alternative, for those who are &amp;lsquo;too posh to push&amp;rsquo;. That is a dangerous, misguided and vile assumption that undermines all women&amp;rsquo;s rights to body autonomy.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Women are typically denied the necessary information to give informed consent to the risks of vaginal delivery, as Melissa sees it. &amp;ldquo;Obstetricians and midwives still adhere to a &amp;lsquo;natural is best&amp;rsquo; ideology, prioritising vaginal delivery over other options,&amp;rdquo; she says, noting the outcome of the independent 2020 Ockendon Review of NHS maternity services, which found that hundreds of women felt the pressure to have a &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo; birth where a C-section might have been safer. &amp;ldquo;But what gives the ideology its lasting power is the economic reality &amp;ndash; vaginal birth is the cheapest way to deliver babies. There is immense pressure for NHS Trusts to keep caesarean section rates down. Serious birth injuries are not rare, but the outcome of a system that cheapens women&amp;rsquo;s trauma because it&amp;rsquo;s cheap.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Alongside greater information about the risks of childbirth, greater respect for women&amp;rsquo;s autonomy and improved aftercare, Melissa would like to see reforms implemented to restrict the use of instruments like forceps, as has been done in countries such as Denmark.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;We need to be honest with women about the risks of childbirth. All childbirth delivery involves risk &amp;ndash; [C-section] and vaginal birth. But it is women, and not an ideology about what is morally preferable or the financial imperative, who should decide how to manage those risks,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;Instead, we are treated as children, poor dears who shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be frightened with nasty stories that apparently only happen to a very small percentage of women. But birth injuries aren&amp;rsquo;t rare.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The experiences of women in Greece pressured into C-sections, and women in the UK pushed towards a vaginal delivery, exist on a continuum. Rarer than damaging birth outcomes across the OECD, it seems, is any real engagement by the medical profession with expectant mothers as people with the capacity to decide what happens to their bodies and babies. Be it through interventionism, coercion or negligent omissions, women&amp;rsquo;s birthing experiences in the 21st century continue to be shaped by the ideologies, biases or financial imperatives of the dominant medical culture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;What can we do? Accurate, transparent and impartial advice from doctors and midwives is crucial; women cannot be expected to make such decisions unaided or uninformed. It seems the future here must be about pluralism, information, choice and equality. Babies were never dropped by storks, and the artificial womb is still a vision of the future. While women&amp;rsquo;s bodies are at risk in the birthing process, it is women who must be at the centre of decision-making.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5861/hard-labour#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-29T14:52:36Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-29T14:52:36Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are Poor People Happier in Religious Societies?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/Sl1kuHmlPv8/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Is it better to be poor in a rich country or in a poor country? It’s a deceptively complicated question! An overall poor country may have less income inequality, meaning you might be poor, …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Sl1kuHmlPv8:MXaopmAHxBw:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/Sl1kuHmlPv8" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131158</id>
    <published>2021-09-29T14:45:04Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-29T14:45:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why our minds need the wild w/Lucy Jones</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5864/why-our-minds-need-the-wild-wlucy-jones#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For centuries, we&amp;rsquo;ve had an intuitive sense that connecting with &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; is good for our wellbeing. But what&amp;rsquo;s the hard evidence? What exactly is &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; anyway? Should we be wary of it being prescribed as a catch-all cure for complex problems? And what impact does nature writing itself actually have? Science writer Lucy Jones talks to Alice Bloch about her prize-winning book &amp;lsquo;Losing Eden&amp;rsquo;, which surveys the mass of research &amp;ndash; from the work of Carl Jung to cutting-edge neurology, medical and social science &amp;ndash; on why our minds need the wild.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you want access to more fresh thinking, why not subscribe to New Humanist magazine? Head to newhumanist.org.uk/subscribe and enter the code WITHREASON to get a whole year's subscription for just &amp;pound;13.50&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hosts:&lt;/strong&gt; Alice Bloch and Samira Shackle&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exec Producer:&lt;/strong&gt; Alice Bloch&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sound Engineer:&lt;/strong&gt; David Crackles&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Music: &lt;/strong&gt;Danosongs&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Image: &lt;/strong&gt;Gemma Brunton (photo), Ed Dingli (artwork)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Transcript:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alice Bloch:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hi there. Welcome to &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt;, the podcast from &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; magazine. I'm Alice Bloch,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Samira Shackle:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;and I'm Samira Shackle,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;and &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; is where we meet people working in fields like culture, science and philosophy. People who draw on evidence and rigorous thinking to challenge dogma and lazy ideas and to offer something new. It's the place to think about reason and unreason, criticism and debate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In this series, we're talking to people like the physicist Carlo Rovelli about the nature of reality, behavioural and data scientist Pragya Agarwal about motherhood and choice. And last week I had a fascinating conversation with anatomist Alice Roberts all about our shared prehistory. But today, we're with science writer, Lucy Jones. Alice, I'm gonna listen in and catch up with you afterwards for a bit of a chat. So I'll leave it to you to tell us more about Lucy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Okay, so Lucy may well be a science writer, but you'll probably find her work more in the nature section of your local bookshop. That's the section that&amp;rsquo;s increasingly packed out with books vying for your attention on rewilding and recovery, escapism, the science behind the way in which plants and trees communicate with each other. That is something I'm keen to ask Lucy about when we speak about the impact of all of that stuff. And her book &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden: Why Our Minds Need The Wild&lt;/em&gt; is about the connection between mental health and the rest of nature that surrounds us, or doesn't actually, as I&amp;rsquo;ts rapidly dying and disappearing. The book is packed with ideas that seemed relevant even before COVID-19. But that actually couldn&amp;rsquo;t have been more salient now that our mental health crisis has been really exposed and exacerbated by the pandemic. And also obviously, because the UK is hosting the UN Climate Change Conference in Glasgow this year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But though &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden&lt;/em&gt; does grapple with policy and evidence, it's also a really personal work, not in the kind of &amp;ldquo;man gets in a bivvy bag, man heads off to the wilderness, on his own without his family, etc, etc,&amp;rdquo; kind of vein, instead Lucy is writing from experience, in part, of addiction and recovery. So I started by asking her all about that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lucy Jones:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I found myself at the age of about 27, having addiction issues with alcohol and drugs, which were linked to anxiety and depression. And I knew that psychotherapy and medication was helping and could help me and support groups as well in my recovery, but I still needed something to kind of try and lift my mood in the day, get me out of bed and soothe some of the pretty painful and difficult emotions that were coming up. As I entered sobriety, I knew that running could release endorphins, you know, lots of us know that. So I tried to go running and to the nearest natural area to my house in northeast London, which was Walthamstow Marshes. And I found that instead of running, I would kind of slow down and stop, looking at things and watching the Coots and visiting the Heron, and listening out for a water vole and, and it became kind of an addiction, similar to the substances that I'd grown to rely on. And this was about 10 years ago.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And it was kind of before the nature and health discourse was really crescendoing. And although I had some vague notion that spending time in nature maybe could make you feel good in some way, I was really blown away by how powerful it was, for me personally, alongside psychiatry and psychotherapy, and so on. And it became something I came to rely on. And I was interested in, when I went to this space, and I came back and it was the only thing that seemed to kind of calm my nerves and give me some respite from critical thinking and so on, from my critical thoughts, and I wanted to know what was happening. So what was happening to my brain chemistry, my nervous system, how and why was spending time in nature making me feel better? So that was the perspective I began with, the kind of genesis was a curiosity about, why does spending time in nature help our minds?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And you spoke there about the nature and health discourse and how that's kind of crescendoed. We do use that word &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo;, but also a phrase that you use is &amp;ldquo;the rest of nature&amp;rdquo;. And I know the writer Richard Mabey, for example, has been and was recently again, critical of the way in which we kind of speak of &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; as if it's distinct from us. And I wonder where this idea of our supposed separation from nature, the idea that we're somehow superior to it or distinct from it, came from?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So nature has so many different meanings as a word. The original etymology of the word is from the Latin for &amp;ldquo;birth&amp;rdquo;. And then another kind of original meaning is nature as the essence or something that is essential to something. In a way, it's kind of one of the most problematic words, because we use it kind of unthinkingly to describe the outdoor world or the living world. But it's very hard to pin down or kind of really define what we mean when we say nature.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think the kind of cementing of nature as meaning what we use it to mean today, you know, green space, rivers, woodlands, seas, etc, we can chart back to the post-industrial times and the influence of the Romantics and the Transcendentalists, where we saw kind of a reaction against industrialization, and people going into nature in a different way. The idea of wilderness became not something to be afraid of, or to abhor, but something that we, we need it in our kind of urbanising worlds. And I think we've got to the point now, where when we think of nature, it's often something kind of chocolate boxy or twee or something out there &amp;ndash; so influenced are we still by the Romantics, and so on. And we forget that we're nature and we forget that it&amp;rsquo;s also the cold that you might be able to hear in my voice, the viruses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. Even pandemics you could say,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Exactly. And when you become aware of it, you kind of see it everywhere, the sense of human exceptionalism and supremacy. This morning I saw a sign that said, &amp;ldquo;wildflower trial area&amp;rdquo;, you know, just wow. Parcelling things out, nature, into these tiny margins.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, yeah, it's become rather sad, hasn&amp;rsquo;t it? Yeah, I was thinking about this idea about how, in a way, if we see ourselves as separate from nature, that means that it can be kind of packaged up and commodified and sold back to us really in some fashion. I was thinking, before talking to you, about an exercise class I went to the other day, where there was birdsong outside the window, and one of the women attending said, &amp;ldquo;oh, wow, there's so many birds, that sounds like one of those CDs of bird song&amp;rdquo;. Which kind of just strikes me as rather sad. But yeah, both of those examples, I guess, are indicative of how far and how separate we&amp;rsquo;ve become.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In writing &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden&lt;/em&gt; you kind of set out to look at hard evidence and peer reviewed studies showing how engaging with the rest of nature can improve our well-being. So you looked at everything from you know, research on the positive effects of being exposed to bacteria in soil, right up to kind of big studies, I think, a 2008 study in &lt;em&gt;The Lancet&lt;/em&gt;, concluding that greener neighbourhoods could mitigate the negative effects of income deprivation on health. And so I'm wondering, you know, amongst all of these pieces of evidence that you cite, is there a particular piece of research that really speaks loudest of all to you, and the one that you really feel should be on the desks of policymakers right now to say &amp;ldquo;hey, there's this connection between being exposed to the rest of nature and our well-being and mental health and we need to act on this.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I definitely thought that there would be kind of one silver bullet piece of evidence, something which was incredibly compelling to stand above all the other studies, but what really kind of blew my mind was the volume of studies that there are and the fact there is this kind of enormous evidence base of high quality, as you say, robust peer reviewed science. So it's kind of that vastness of the evidence base, but I think if I had to choose one area, I think, I would say the stress recovery evidence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So in our modern world, stress is very much on the increase. Stress-related disease and illness is increasing. Stress is very well, it's a word to describe a lot of our modern problems. The word was only coined in the 1920s, I think, by Walter Cannon. And the evidence shows that when we go into a natural space, the effect on our nervous systems &amp;ndash; our parasympathetic nervous system is more likely to be activated in a natural area, which is the side of the nervous system associated with &amp;ldquo;rest and digest&amp;rdquo; and feelings of calm and contentment. And when our bodies are in that state, we can invest towards our immune system. I feel kind of calmer and more relaxed, compared to the opposite: the sympathetic nervous system, which is when we're feeling kind of high levels of cortisol, adrenalized, fight or flight, a state that I'm sure many of us are quite familiar with. And that's more likely to be raised in urban environments.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And when we move into a natural space, when we spend time in forests, or woods or, or by water, we recover from stress quickly and more completely. So I think I became very convinced that this was a central pathway and mechanism, which meant that by kind of taking that away from people or not allowing adequate access to the natural world, it's actually a public health disgrace.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And you talk about kind of going into natural spaces there, but then there's also the idea of kind of looking at them as being good for us also. And I think one thing you talk about is attention restoration theory.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, this is a really influential and quite intriguing theory that was developed by the Kaplan's Stephen and Rachel Kaplan, who are environmental psychologists from North America. And they develop this theory in the &amp;lsquo;80s, building on the work of William James, the psychologist who introduced this idea of directed attention, and that when we kind of focus and we concentrate on one thing for a long time, we get cognitive fatigue, which can lead to kind of stress and irritability. So they posited that when we spend time in natural spaces, or as you say, when we even watch nature on a screen, or look at our house plants, and so on, we can engage in something that they called effortless attention, which is kind of&amp;hellip; imagine looking at a plant moving gently in the breeze or kind of rain falling on water, or so on, we're kind of paying attention, but it's not in a really tiring way, like crossing a busy road or, you know, listening to someone, or the stress of work or so on. So, attention restoration theory has a number of different kind of ingredients to it. One of which is &amp;ldquo;soft fascination&amp;rdquo;, which I think is just a really nice concept phrase. And the studies in this area suggest that even taking a micro break at work, taking kind of 10 minutes out on a lunch break. And one study looked at green roofs outside an office and people who looked out onto green roofs or just kind of took a break from their desks, reported feeling kind of less cognitively fatigue &amp;ndash; and more productive, more relaxed afterwards.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's interesting, that idea of productivity. That's something I wanted to ask about, because I guess I'm slightly wary of this line of thinking that says that exposure to the rest of nature can boost our productivity. I wonder really, whether there's much point in say, putting a tree outside of the window, for someone who works for an oil company. Or sort of a pot plant on the desk of someone who works in fast fashion, or at the Googleplex or whatever, right? I guess there's the risk that you know, nature can be kind of co-opted, actually, to kind of make us all better workers and feed into the growth agenda, etc, which actually might in the long run not have a very good outcome for the environment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I agree with everything you've said. I barely mentioned productivity actually in the book, because I'm not really that interested in it. And I mean, exactly what you said is how I feel too. It's kind of the ultimate &amp;ldquo;nature and health&amp;rdquo; kind of area of study for the &amp;ldquo;capitalist scene&amp;rdquo; as Donna Haraway calls it, isn't it? So, you do see offices and corporations and companies plopping a tree in a corridor to kind of try and improve people's productivity or, kind of nodding to this idea that we expect people to work 14 hour days at their desks and we give them a plant and they'll be fine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Give him a succulent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, we have to be really wary of that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, throw some &amp;ldquo;nature&amp;rdquo; at everything and everything will be okay. I think there's also an example in your book of I mean, it's a lovely example in lots of ways, but of people in solitary confinement in prisons in the US, and the experience of that, the suffering of that being mitigated by a project whereby I think they were shown videos of greenery and wildlife? Is that correct?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. So it was Nalini Nadkarni, his work in Snake River Correctional Institution in Oregon. And yeah, she developed this blue room, she called it, where she projected nature documentaries, and part of the study group were invited to come and watch, listen to birdsong and watch them. And the other half of them were given their normal exercise which was kind of half an hour in a yard with no contact with nature.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The results were really interesting and they did show that the people who watched the nature documentaries reported higher levels of well-being and were more relaxed and there were less altercations. And even the staff as well reported kind of positive therapeutic benefits from it. But saying that, there are interesting studies about techno nature and how listening to birdsong even under anaesthetic can reduce the stress biomarker, cortisol for example, and, looking at nature through a screen can can be therapeutic. However, another thing I'm quite wary of: the end result is, it's never as good as the real thing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, so it's better than nothing, but it's never as good as the real thing. And that example of prisons there was from the US but you've looked at examples from around the world, where we have different relationships with nature, and the effect of that on mental health. And I wonder whether in the UK &amp;hellip;. actually, do we have a particularly troubled bond with the natural world? Or rather what would be the specific nature of our relationship to it here in the UK?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So I mean, I was thinking when I was younger, there was a real dismissal of &amp;ldquo;tree huggers&amp;rdquo;. For example, you can&amp;rsquo;t sort of touch a tree without being teased for being a tree hugger. You know, compare that to Japan where you write about forest bathing and actually I noticed on the forestry England website they now have a little page on kind of how to do forest bathing. So things seem to be changing, but talk to me a bit about the cross cultural differences there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;it's such an interesting question. Yeah, I remember that growing up in the 90s it just wasn't very cool to be into nature, and like Swampy, who is actually like a legend. Yeah. And still going!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So this is the activist?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. But you know, he was seen as like a complete joke and then Prince Charles was like massively dissed for talking to his plants and yeah, it was, it's kind of corny. I think that is changing and I think we can see there's lots of interesting young people and kind of youth movements trying to engage younger people and kids more with nature. It's not seen as such an eccentric and cringe thing to do.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But what's underneath that? I mean the UK is one of the most nature-depleted countries in the world. So we pride ourselves in being this from nature-loving nation, but actually our biodiversity levels are really shocking. And obviously we have this grotesque colonial history and our industrial footprint on the world is very significant. So I wonder if there is a kind of, (I'm just kind of talking off the top of my head right now) but a kind of denial of nature or maybe a guilt. Maybe there's a kind of sense of guilt in us that we have destroyed so much. I mean, I'm half Scottish, half English, but we've destroyed so many natural areas across the world, you know, for both humans and nonhumans, that maybe there is a sense of kind of bullish denialism and you can see that in the way we even today are not taking our legal obligations for nature recovery more seriously.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So we're talking, right now, in June. And councils across the country are mowing and cutting hedgerows and verges &amp;ndash; but the wild flowers are at their most important for other animals and yet they're being kind of scalped across the country. We don't seem to to get it yet, compared with other countries that you mentioned, like Japan. Forest bathing has been prescribed in in Japan and South Korea.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We should say it's where you go out into the forest, ideally in the morning, if I'm not wrong, and kind of literally breathe it in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes, for a couple of hours and use all the senses to kind of engage. People diss forest bathing and I think that might be because it can be packaged up as this kind of wellness cure, which is, you know, kind of problematic. But in Japan &amp;ndash; based on the really excellent work of Dr. King Lee &amp;ndash; it's been proven by doctors and they protect forest parks and forest areas for the health of people and citizens and so on. And like you say, you can see that starting to kind of come over here a little bit more. I saw, I think yesterday, that some walks have been named well-being walks in various woodlands. I feel slightly wary of it. I mean, I understand where it's coming from, but it's almost, it's the same kind of parcelling off or putting nature in the margins.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Absolutely. So go off and experience a bit of something called nature, and then finish that task and go home again, you're no longer in nature. Yeah, why?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Biodiversity continues to crash out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AR:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So you mentioned earlier guilt, and our relationship to nature. And I think you met an eco-psychologist who spoke to you about how, actually, the thing that's partly causing our climate and environmental crisis, our overconsumption, has in a way become our &lt;em&gt;response &lt;/em&gt;to that crisis. So we kind of consume, it creates a crisis, we feel really guilty, and we despair, and then we actually go off and consume more. And I think she compares that to the patterns actually found with addiction. I found that really fascinating. I wondered if you could talk around that a little bit for me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. So this was Mary-Jane Rust, who has been writing about this relationship between the natural world and the psyche for quite a long time. And she's also a women's health therapist and a Jungian analyst and works with people with eating disorders. And yes, as you say, she likens it to addiction, it was one of the most illuminating conversations I think I had, because nature is very absent in psychoanalysis, very absent in Freud, and did an early year training to be a therapist, and you don't hear anything about the environment, our environment, and how that impacts on our minds.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I agree with Mary-Jane Rust. And I think and I can see it in my own life, that consuming and buying things can cause this kind of pattern of guilt, but also a dopamine hit, and so on. And we're all in this system. And these structures, which are so hard to kind of break out of, and I suppose I think that guilt in this sense is it's very paralysing, and while we all have individual responsibilities to do what we can to tread lightly on the earth, there's only so much we can do. And we really need top down system change and kind of political will.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I mean, you mentioned that psychoanalysis hasn't had much to say about the environment. But you also talk about Carl Jung, and about how he took issue with Christianity as partly culpable for our severance from the natural world. I wasn't aware of that. So why, why was that? What does he have to say on this?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So Jung, said, wrote, that we've kind of forgotten that we're primates, and we've forgotten about animals. And he uses an image of a house and says that we live on the kind of top floor, the loft extension: the 19th century is kind of the second floor, the Mediaeval days are like the ground floor, and the kind of Earth underneath is the 99 per cent of our evolutionary history outside.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And although we kind of have forgotten that, it's still alive in our consciousness. And he, he lays the blame of us kind of forgetting that and estranging ourselves from nature at the feet of 2000 years of Christianity. And he doesn't really go into much detail. But I suppose my interpretation of him saying that would be, and having grown up in an evangelical conservative house, and family, that Christianity teaches that man is made in the image of God. So we're not animals, we are different, and therefore we're Supreme. And I think that the idea of Dominion in Genesis has been used to trash, to completely destroy the planet, hasn't it, instead of the stewardship angle. And he also wrote that the West is kind of in shock after the Second World War, and we're still in that kind of psychological shock state, which I thought was quite interesting because I think they're interesting links between our relationship with nature and denial of death. And there's lots of studies about that, actually, which suggests that when we're in nature we sometimes we might think about our mortality more, think about death more, which could be why it&amp;rsquo;s off putting in some ways some people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But if I'm not wrong, there's also some research into how actually being in nature can make make us more humble. Maybe more generally aware of our own mortality. I guess it's like cliched, giving us a bit of perspective. It's something &lt;a href="/articles/5774/the-cosmos-us-w-jo-marchant"&gt;we spoke to Jo Marchant about&lt;/a&gt; in our previous series of &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; about the science of awe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think you mentioned this a bit when you talk about river swimming. So you're no longer of Christian faith, that was in youth, but you say that now, river swimming is kind of your &amp;ldquo;church&amp;rdquo;. And I was really fascinated by that. And I wonder whether that's your moment of feeling at one with things and kind of in proportion to the rest of nature?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, it definitely, it definitely is. If you've been brought up in a kind of really quite intense religious cult almost, it's quite hard to shake off that search for transcendence. And I suppose I find it in the rivers near my house, which are very cold, and they're beautiful. And there's water-mint, which smells lovely, and kingfishers. And there's something about being in the water and kind of having my hands in the mud and immersing myself in another element where I, the self, dissolves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You're listening to &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; from &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; magazine and the Rationalist Association. I'm Alice Bloch, and I'm talking to Lucy Jones today about nature and why our minds need the wild. If that's something you'd like to explore more, you can head to &lt;a href="/podcast"&gt;our archive&lt;/a&gt; where you can find us talking to the science writer, Jo Marchant about the science of awe, or Minna Salami about the arrogance of damaging euro patriarchal knowledge. And Michael Rosen, the poet and broadcaster, reflecting rather beautifully on writing and recovery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And if you want to hear more from us at &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt;, press pause right now and click Subscribe on whatever app you're using. It's quick, it's free. And it helps us to make more episodes for you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Back now to my conversation with Lucy. Okay, so far today, Lucy, we've talked about why exposure to the rest of nature matters for our mental health and well-being, we've talked about Carl Jung and his perspective on our severance from the natural world. But let's move on a bit to what can be done. And I guess what the individual's responsibility may be here. So you write not only about your experience of addiction and recovery, but you also write from the position of being a mother, and you express concern about the depleted world that future generations might face. But you also say, actually, that you wanted to have another child. So your daughter could kind of have someone to weather it all with. Some would say, you know, if you care about the future of the planet, you shouldn't have children at all. I wonder what your perspective is on this. And I should say, you know, something I grappled with also, I had a baby last year, he's nearly one. And that&amp;rsquo;s something I think about often too, I think all parents or parents must. But I wonder what your view on it is, especially as someone who's gone out there and written about this in the public domain. Has anything been said to you?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I'm very conscious of it. And I do think about it all the time. And it's a bit of a cop out answer, but I think the honest answer would be that I just couldn't quiet the biological longing that I had. I just couldn't. And I know that probably sounds, I don't know, I'm kind of embarrassed to say that. That is the truth. I think there's a lot of problems with the over-population argument. I mean, I'm sure I'm a hypocrite in many, many different ways. But we try and consume as little as possible and live a low carbon lifestyle. And I suppose, you know, none of us individually are going to be able to stop the climate crisis or the biodiversity crisis. But the one thing I can do now I &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have children is to bring them up to love the world, you know, human and non-human, and to experience the wonder in all of our natural world. So they may care for it. But yeah, it's a really, really tough, really tough subject, something that I'm still grappling with. I think I'm probably in denial quite a lot about the future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, it makes me think about that whole thing we spoke about earlier of, you know, kind of overconsumption leads to crisis leads to overconsumption. And I was wondering whether almost having children can be a response to that. It&amp;rsquo;s kind of, &amp;ldquo;Oh, God, the future is going to be awful, best to have children&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; as a comfort, or to weather it? I don't know. As you say, it's not something that can be resolved now. But it's something people continue to write about.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But speaking of impact, and change, your work is full of loads of evidence-based claims about the link between nature and mental health. But I'm wondering actually what evidence we have of the impact of nature writing itself. So my local bookshop window is packed with books about, you know, rewilding your life. I think there's some book with the title &amp;ldquo;12 birds to save your life&amp;rdquo;. There's stuff about, you know, talking to trees, talking to each other, etc, etc. I think when I see these kind of really stacked up, I have to say that sometimes I'm a little bit sceptical about the net impact of these books because there's been a huge rush of them recently, it seems, in publishing. I wonder what your perspective on this is. Maybe it's an unfair question to ask someone who's written one of these books, but also whether we have any evidence of the impact of nature writing &amp;ndash; for want of a better term. Whether it actually leads to activism and change, or whether these books become just something nice for the shelf to be spotted when you have people around for dinner?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, sure. It's a really interesting subject. I don't know of any evidence. I would be interested to know. I think my perspective is the one thing that really worries me about the kind of &amp;ldquo;nature cure&amp;rdquo; narrative is that people think that they will go for a walk in the woods, and that they will be cured. And obviously it doesn't work like that at all. Mental health is complex, and heck, nature is complex. And I think that could probably be really kind of alienating for a lot of people or upsetting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I make it quite clear in &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden&lt;/em&gt; that I've had periods of clinical depression, where I would go into my local cemetery, and I felt nothing. And did it make me feel better at all? I mean, eventually, you know, as I recovered from this postnatal depression, it helped, but, you know, it's not a cure, and I understand why in our kind of cultural worlds, we either tell stories about nature as this kind of saviour, or this kind of sacred, palliative, or there are natural disaster kind of films or, or sci fi, animal horror, this idea of nature as a destroyer,&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kind of man v nature.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. And I mean, of course, ambivalence towards nature is maybe not as interesting as those two extremes, but I'm sure there must be stories and narratives, which could bridge that gap and to be a little bit more interesting.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well on that actually, one piece that I think maybe &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; point to this kind of more nuanced depiction that you're looking for, &lt;a href="/articles/5542/in-search-of-the-nature-cure"&gt;is this piece&lt;/a&gt; I was going to ask you about, actually from the &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; archive by Richard Smyth. It's from a couple of years ago, and it's called &amp;ldquo;In Search of the Nature Cure.&amp;rdquo; And that piece notes that we've pretty much kind of always believed in the healing power of our natural landscape in some way. But he wonders, as you did just there, whether kind of this healing power of nature has been overstated. And I think his concern is that whilst nature can provide the context for healing, you know, for a kind of therapy, it's not this instant cure, and it shouldn't always been be presented as such.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think he quotes this poet Polly Atkin who lives with a life-affecting health condition. And you know, she says, well, Wordsworth wrote &amp;ldquo;let nature be your teacher&amp;rdquo;, not &amp;ldquo;let nature be your only recognised healthcare system&amp;rdquo;. And you have looked into eco-therapy, and I guess a cynic might say, the rise of eco-therapy and, you know, doctors prescribing just a nice old stroll in the park, you know, it could just be a way of kind of cutting costs for the NHS, which is no bad thing in itself, but I guess not so great. If the outcomes aren't ultimately great. I wonder what your thoughts are on this. And whether there's any evidence that this kind of thing is going on, I guess, almost &amp;ldquo;greenwashing&amp;rdquo; something, a different type of greenwashing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, I'm very concerned about that. I haven't come across examples where a doctor has kind of just said, &amp;ldquo;go out for a walk&amp;rdquo;. But there is social prescribing increasing across the country and doctors are prescribing things like bird watching and so on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;How extensive is that as a as a trend? I'm interested in that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I spoke to a practitioner in Bristol, he does woodland therapy. In Shetland, I think they do bird walks. They're kind of is few and far between, but I think it is increasing. But I saw no evidence to suggest that nature is being prescribed kind of in and of itself. I think it is worrying though that it also puts pressure on communities to fund these kind of health and wellness initiatives. And I worry that it would shift resources that are so needed from doctors and so on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Also, if the environment around you has been degraded, due to kind of macro stuff that's going on, or interventions or lack of interventions, it must be kind of frustrating for you, as the individual to be told, hey, go out and enjoy this. When, actually, maybe, you know, all the trees on your street have just been cut down or something because there's local authority cuts, and the council's decided that cutting them down is cheaper than maintaining them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, which may have the opposite effect, you actually feel really shit. But also, you know, there are a constellation of social factors that influence nature and wellbeing as you know, people from different backgrounds, people of colour face hostility in natural environments. And, you know, it's all very well saying to someone go for a walk in the woods, but if they don't have a background, or they've had opportunities to do that, or even want to do that, you know, it's not very helpful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I mean, in the writing of &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden&lt;/em&gt;, I was really conscious that I have so many friends who don't go to nature for their restoration, you know. There's so many different ways of feeling well, and so on. But one aspect that I found really interesting and compelling is this idea of background nature. So there's a lot of studies now, which suggests that background nature by which I mean, you know, trees, on your street, and so on, being able to walk through parks, higher levels of biodiversity, have measurable impacts on population and individual mental health. So even if you're someone who doesn't want to go and climb trees on the weekend, just walking through a park, actually, studies suggest that that does have important potential therapeutic benefits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That's reassuring, so it doesn't have to be fell running or scaling a mountain or doing sort of a Caspar David Friedrich pose, you know, atop a peak, it can just be a few pollarded trees and a nice stroll in your local park, by your outdoor gym, or whatever. Well, that's the positive note to end on. So thank you very much, Lucy, for joining us. That was that was really interesting. Thanks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;L J:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thank you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We're returning to Samira shackle, the editor of &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; magazine, who's been listening in. Samira, what's your take on what we've heard from Lucy there? I'm wondering if it reminds you of other pieces recently for the magazine, or of emerging themes that you think we could or should hear more about in the future?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, listening to Lucy talk about the Romantic conception of nature did make me think of &lt;a href="/articles/5173/how-we-invented-nature"&gt;a piece we published&lt;/a&gt; a few years back in 2017, by the philosopher Jonathan Ree, about Alexander von Humboldt, who was the Prussian polymath who came up with our modern conception of nature. And it just made me think about how the way that we think about nature and its relationship to us and our relationship to the, you know, quote, unquote, &amp;ldquo;natural world&amp;rdquo; has, in some ways stayed the same as in some ways changed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I guess it's this kind of nebulous concept, and certainly a concept that we hear a lot about, because there are so many books about this idea of the &amp;ldquo;nature cure&amp;rdquo; and the healing properties of the natural world. I have to confess, I have a kind of scepticism about that, I think, which I know you touched on that in your, in your discussion with Lucy, the prevalence of a certain type of nature writing, which can overstate its healing properties as the be all and end all. I don't know, I guess part of my scepticism comes from the fact that I think there's a lot of psychobabble in this genre, it seems quite susceptible to this sort of presentation of nature as having these sort of inherent transcendental transformative properties, which I think I can find quite alienating. So I enjoyed listening to a more sort of evidenced focus take on some of those issues and thinking &amp;ldquo;Okay, actually, where is this useful? And where do we know about the impact this has?&amp;rdquo; Rather than the tendency towards kind of, you know, a kind of semi-religious way of talking about nature as if it's transformative and if you're not feeling transformed by a walk in the hills, then there&amp;rsquo;s something wrong with you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah. And you certainly don't want to have that kind of individualising blame focused sort of ideas about getting out in nature &amp;ndash; and not doing it as being something you should be ashamed of. That's definitely not the direction you want to go in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I do think it's interesting though you picked up on this word &amp;ldquo;psychobabble&amp;rdquo; there and I totally agree there's certain works that maybe are a bit more sort of wishy-washy around ideas to do with the benefits of being out in the rest of nature and so on. But I would be slightly wary of using the term psychobabble myself &amp;ndash; just I think it gets attached to say, as Lucy and I were talking about, say, the idea of &amp;ldquo;tree hugging&amp;rdquo;, which actually, you know, some argue does have real health benefits. It gets attached to things like that, where it doesn't get attached, not so much, to other things. So you know, actually the Guardian review of Lucy's book was very quick to say, and I quote, you know, &amp;ldquo;Lucy Jones&amp;rsquo; ideas are not psychobabble, but rooted firmly in peer reviewed science&amp;rdquo;. It does seem there's this, this sort of nerdiness around talking about nature and ideas of the benefits of being out in nature, where people are very quick to say, you know, it's not psychobabble, or anything, it's real. And I think that says a lot about what we dismiss and what we value in our culture and you know, maybe actually what we should value and take seriously a little bit more. And maybe one day, there'll be a time when we're not sort of so ashamed to talk about it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, listening to the conversation, I wondered whether we should be thinking and talking structurally rather than individually. So thinking about policies that have meant we are so divorced from our surroundings. And that has meant we have such dire biodiversity in this country, and so on, rather than thinking about the onus on the individual to seek out trees and hills and streams in order to help their own stress and depression. Obviously, those things aren't mutually exclusive. But I just wonder if that it would be more sort of useful and prescient.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, Lucy certainly talks about that. And she did also obviously, in the interview, as we heard, but also very much in her book, especially towards the end, she talks about biodiversity, she talks about things like urban planning, about making cities better in terms of nature and access to nature. And so she's very, very alert to that. But I think, yeah, we do need to remain critical about the idea of nature, I suppose as a bit of a kind of sticking plaster solution to various problems and things that actually need kind of much more large scale reforms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SS:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yeah, it makes me think of, you know, &amp;ldquo;self-care&amp;rdquo; is such an overused term at the moment, it makes me think of the recommendation that a candle and a face mask will help you recover from burnout because of your terrible working conditions. And obviously, that's a slightly misplaced, but obviously, you know, I mean, it's something that's come up in our other discussions that we've had in the podcast: this complicated idea of all the myriad impacts of the modern conditions of living, I guess, and the way in which technology and urban living and so on have sort of separated us from our natural rhythms. And that's something that in &lt;a href="/articles/5774/the-cosmos-us-w-jo-marchant"&gt;our episode with Jo Marchant&lt;/a&gt;, she talks about: the cosmos and our lost relationship with the skies and so on. So listeners might want to go back and listen to as well.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AB:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Certainly. I mean, you can't knock it can you. I mean, she talked with Niki, our deputy editor, about the joy of stargazing, and Niki was talking about getting a telescope and doing that in lockdown, and Jo was saying she'd been enjoying stargazing, I think with her neighbours. Anyway, that's one to listen to.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But as far as today's episode goes, that's it for today. We'll be back next week with more. And remember, you can find transcripts for every episode of &lt;em&gt;With Reason&lt;/em&gt; at newhumanist.org.uk and you can find us on Twitter @NewHumanist. This podcast was presented by me, series producer Alice Bloch, with New Humanist editor Samira Shackle. Our sound engineer was Dave Crackles. Meet you back here soon. Bye.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Reading list:&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lucy Jones (2020) &lt;em&gt;Losing Eden: Why Our Minds Need the Wild&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Richard Mabey (2005) &lt;em&gt;The Nature Cure&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Mary-Jayne Rust (2020) &lt;em&gt;Towards an Ecopsychotherapy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Carl Jung, collected works.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href="/articles/5542/in-search-of-the-nature-cure"&gt; Richard Smyth (2019), &amp;lsquo;In search of the "nature cure"&amp;rsquo;, &lt;em&gt;New Humanist &lt;/em&gt;magazine. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5864/why-our-minds-need-the-wild-wlucy-jones#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-28T09:35:43Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-28T09:35:43Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In a word</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5856/in-a-word#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/cancel.jpg" height="789" alt="cancel" width="1200" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The verb &amp;ldquo;to cancel&amp;rdquo; has had a long life. English speakers have been cancelling (or cancelling out) words on a page since at least 1440; Shakespeare wrote of cancelling hopes; by 1619, vows were being cancelled; Milton cancelled people from heaven (that is: they were evicted); Byron thought that his anxieties could be cancelled by a kind letter, and by 1925, &amp;ldquo;effects&amp;rdquo; or forces could cancel each other out. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As with many words of Latin origin, a metaphorical meaning is lost when they are brought into English. &amp;ldquo;Cancelli&amp;rdquo; in Latin were lattice-work. This was used to describe the crossing-out of letters on a manuscript. So now, when we cancel an engagement, we are metaphorically crossing it out. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;cancel&amp;rdquo; has had a huge revival in recent times with the term &amp;ldquo;cancel culture&amp;rdquo;. As with the use of the phrase &amp;ldquo;political correctness&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;PC&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;PC gone mad&amp;rdquo;, the phrase itself becomes part of the &amp;ldquo;culture wars&amp;rdquo;. Some claim that the American use of &amp;ldquo;cancel&amp;rdquo; in this context is a lift from African American vernacular, as with the band Chic&amp;rsquo;s song, &amp;ldquo;Your Love is Cancelled&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s not beat about the bush. Right now it&amp;rsquo;s being used by politicians who believe that the culture they want to preserve is being cancelled by liberals (in the US sense), museum decolonisers, campus radicals and the like. This raises the question of who is cancelling whom. When politicians in power complain of culture being cancelled, they suggest that a whole way of life is being threatened. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The UK&amp;rsquo;s Secretary of State for Digital, Culture, Media and Sport, Oliver Dowden, wrote an article in the Daily Telegraph in May, headlined &amp;ldquo;We Won&amp;rsquo;t Allow Britain&amp;rsquo;s History to be Cancelled&amp;rdquo;, expressing concern about the &amp;ldquo;pressure&amp;rdquo; being put on heritage organisations. Although the article itself is reasonably nuanced, the hostile use of the word &amp;ldquo;cancel&amp;rdquo; in the headline suggests that this government won&amp;rsquo;t allow imperial history to be negated or critiqued too fiercely, and indeed that it, through Dowden, has the power to, well, cancel (!) those it disagrees with.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist autumn 2021 edition. &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5856/in-a-word#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2021-09-28T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-28T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Study: Does Cheaper Viagra Reduce Suicides?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/owColEH7MXA/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Heads up, here’s a content warning: today I’m going to talk about sex and suicide, so if either of those things upset you, maybe give this video a skip! Earlier this year, researchers published …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=owColEH7MXA:exR7YkgjYKU:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/owColEH7MXA" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131156</id>
    <published>2021-09-27T17:21:19Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-27T17:21:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Psychic TikTok is a Cesspit of Sylvia Brownes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/55pGvkhCsg0/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! In the past few years, I’ve seen a resurgence in a “belief” in astrology, at least amongst my friends and social media follows. I say “belief,” with quotation marks, because honestly I’ve never been sure …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=55pGvkhCsg0:oyLQNQePVDw:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/55pGvkhCsg0" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131151</id>
    <published>2021-09-24T12:25:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-24T12:25:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Brief History of Vaccine Mandates (and How to Do it Right)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/Ra7AAsFBdiw/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Let’s talk about this hot new idea, “vaccine mandates.” Conservatives across the US are up in arms (and I mean that literally, because this is America, so of course the people scared of needles own …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Ra7AAsFBdiw:4cT08mHRzTU:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/Ra7AAsFBdiw" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131149</id>
    <published>2021-09-22T19:59:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-22T19:59:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Anti-Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Teens Around the World are “Catching” Tourettes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/Skepchick/~3/zJsHMsngzlg/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: I’ve long been fascinated by people who “fake” illnesses. It’s such a complicated mash-up of psychological disorders, real physical issues, medical neglect, marginalization — just a big mishmash of things I weirdly enjoy thinking …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=zJsHMsngzlg:5yL9HBSygeQ:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Skepchick/~4/zJsHMsngzlg" height="1" width="1" alt=""/></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131144</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T15:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T15:00:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Rollercoaster of Faith that led to Atheism (twice)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/09/the-rollercoaster-of-faith-that-led-to-atheism-twice/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mine is not a terrible, bloodshed, or torturing example of the evil side of religion, but rather a story of how logic got me in and out of religious thinking. It is interesting, to say the least, so please stick to me until the end. I was born and raised a Roman Catholic, as most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Marc Kreidler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977256</id>
    <published>2021-09-07T13:47:24Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-07T13:47:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Converts Corner"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION SEPTEMBER 2021</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/09/open-discussion-september-2021/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for discussion on themes relevant to Reason and Science for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977239</id>
    <published>2021-09-01T10:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-01T10:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I was told that I was demon-possessed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/08/i-was-told-that-i-was-demon-possessed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since entering this world as a conscious autonomous human being I feel I have experienced a somewhat well-rounded experience of Christianity, suffering both at the hands of Christians as well as experiencing some kindness and love. I began my journey as a child under a thunderous pulpit preacher in Edinburgh where the women wore hats …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Marc Kreidler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977198</id>
    <published>2021-08-17T15:50:43Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-17T15:50:43Z</updated>
    <category term="Converts Corner"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Abracadabra!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2021/08/abracadabra/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! Words can have incredible power. If we didn’t think so, we wouldn’t produce magazines, podcasts, or this newsletter! But their power comes from how they transmit information, how they make us feel, and how they move us to act.  What words cannot do is cause things to …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=977071</id>
    <published>2021-08-04T16:18:17Z</published>
    <updated>2021-08-04T16:18:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Magic Award</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our first award focused on performers who use magic tricks to improve the lives of others, including work with disadvantaged groups, hospital patients, and schools. The judges selected two great winners: Megan Swann (who presents a magic show that promotes environmental issues) and Breathe Magic (who support children with hemiplegia by helping them to learn tricks that improve physical and psychological wellbeing).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This year, the award will provide £2,000 to support a new and innovative project that promotes the art of magic. This might, for example, include developing a live or virtual performance, writing a magic-related book or essay, creating a podcast, devising a new form of illusion or presentation, or undertaking research into the history of magic. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Applicants need to be over 18 years old and currently residing in the UK, and nominations will close at 5pm (GMT) on 20th February 2021.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To enter, please head over to &lt;a href="https://goodthinkingsociety.org/projects/the-good-magic-awards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"&gt;The Good Thinking Society&lt;/a&gt; now! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards. Our first award focused… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Good Magic Award</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12851</id>
    <published>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/07/science-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>A few years ago I produced three videos containing ten magic-based science stunts. I thought that they might help educate and entertain children during lockdown, or indeed anyone with a curious disposition. Here they are…..</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/yKxnnKLn9Hc?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/rHoLqvzvDFc?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NkyEOrQiGMQ?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;start=1&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/>
</div></figure>



<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I produced three videos containing ten magic-based science stunts. I thought that they might help educate… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/07/science-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Science magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12825</id>
    <published>2021-01-07T14:20:22Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-07T14:20:22Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this episode of the podcast, Sam discusses the recent social protests and civil unrest, in light of what we know about racism and police violence in America.</p>
<p>This is a transcript of a <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/207-can-pull-back-brink/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">recorded podcast</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">* * *</p>
<p>Welcome to the Making Sense podcast… This is Sam Harris.</p>
<p>OK…. Well, I’ve been trying to gather my thoughts for this podcast for more than a week—and have been unsure about whether to record it at all, frankly.</p>
<p>Conversation is the only tool we have for making progress, I firmly believe that. But many of the things we most need to talk about, seem impossible to talk about.</p>
<p>I think social media is a huge part of the problem. I’ve been saying for a few years now that, with social media, we’ve all been enrolled in a psychological experiment for which no one gave consent, and it’s not at all clear how it will turn out. And it’s still not clear how it will turn out, but it’s not looking good. It’s fairly disorienting out there. All information is becoming weaponized. All communication is becoming performative. And on the most important topics, it now seems to be fury and sanctimony and bad faith almost all the time.</p>
<p>We appear to be driving ourselves crazy. Actually, crazy. As in, incapable of coming into contact with reality, unable to distinguish fact from fiction—and then becoming totally destabilized by our own powers of imagination, and confirmation bias, and then lashing out at one other on that basis.</p>
<p>So I’d like to talk about the current moment and the current social unrest, and its possible political implications, and other cultural developments, and suggest what it might take to pull back from the brink here. I’m going to circle in on the topics of police violence and the problem of racism, because that really is at the center of this. There is so much to talk about here, and it’s so difficult to talk about. And there is so much we don’t know. And yet, most people are behaving as though every important question was answered a long time ago.</p>
<p>I’ve been watching our country seem to tear itself apart for weeks now, and perhaps lay the ground for much worse to come. And I’ve been resisting the temptation to say anything of substance—not because I don’t have anything to say, but because of my perception of the danger, frankly. And if that’s the way I feel, given the pains that I’ve taken to insulate myself from those concerns, I know that almost everyone with a public platform is terrified. Journalists, and editors, and executives, and celebrities are terrified that they might take one wrong step here, and never recover.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YdsmxzaHtSQ" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"/></p>
<p>And this is really unhealthy—not just for individuals, but for society. Because, again, all we have between us and the total breakdown of civilization is a series of successful conversations. If we can’t reason with one another, there is no path forward, other than violence. Conversation or violence.</p>
<p>So, I’d like to talk about some of the things that concern me about the current state of our communication. Unfortunately, many things are compounding our problems at the moment. We have a global pandemic which is still very much with us. And it remains to be seen how much our half-hearted lockdown, and our ineptitude in testing, and our uncoordinated reopening, and now our plunge into social protest and civil unrest will cause the Covid-19 caseload to spike. We will definitely see. As many have pointed out, the virus doesn’t care about economics or politics. It only cares that we keep breathing down each other’s necks. And we’ve certainly been doing enough of that.</p>
<p>Of course, almost no one can think about Covid-19 right now. But I’d just like to point out that many of the costs of this pandemic and the knock-on effects in the economy, and now this protest movement, many of these costs are hidden from us. In addition to killing more than 100,000 people in the US, the pandemic has been a massive opportunity cost. The ongoing implosion of the economy is imposing tangible costs, yes, but it is also a massive opportunity cost. And now this civil unrest is compounding those problems—whatever the merits of these protests may be or will be, the opportunity costs of this moment are staggering. In addition to all the tangible effects of what’s happening—the injury and death, the lost businesses, the burned buildings, the neighborhoods that won’t recover for years in many cities, the educations put on hold, and the breakdown in public trust of almost every institution—just think about all the good and important things we cannot do—cannot even <em>think</em> of doing now—and perhaps won’t contemplate doing for many years to come, because we’ll be struggling to get back to that distant paradise we once called “normal life.”</p>
<p>Of course, normal life for many millions of Americans was nothing like a paradise. The disparities in wealth and health and opportunity that we have gotten used to in this country, and that so much of our politics and ways of doing business seem to take for granted, are just unconscionable. There is no excuse for this kind of inequality in the richest country on earth. What we’re seeing now is a response to that. But it’s a confused and confusing response. Worse, it’s a response that is systematically silencing honest conversation. And this makes it dangerous.</p>
<p>This isn’t just politics and human suffering on display. It’s philosophy. It’s ideas about truth—about what it means to say that something is “true.” What we’re witnessing in our streets and online and in the impossible conversations we’re attempting to have in our private lives is a breakdown in epistemology. How does anyone figure out what’s going on in the world? What is real? If we can’t agree about what is real, or likely to be real, we will never agree about how we should live together. And the problem is, we’re stuck with one other.</p>
<p>So, what’s happening here?</p>
<p>Well, again, it’s hard to say. What is happening when <a href="https://youtu.be/viika57hTO4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a police officer or a mayor takes a knee</a> in front of a crowd of young people who have been berating him for being a cog in the machinery of systemic racism? Is this a profound moment of human bonding that transcends politics, or is it the precursor to the breakdown of society? Or is it both? It’s not entirely clear.</p>
<p>In the most concrete terms, we are experiencing widespread social unrest in response to what is widely believed to be an epidemic of lethal police violence directed at the black community by racist cops and racist policies. And this unrest has drawn a counter-response from law enforcement—much of which, ironically, is guaranteed to exacerbate the problem of police violence, both real and perceived. And many of the videos we’ve seen of the police cracking down on peaceful protesters are hideous. Some of this footage has been unbelievable. And this is one of many vicious circles that we must find some way to interrupt.</p>
<p>Again, there is so much to be confused about here. We’ve now seen endless video of police inflicting senseless violence on truly peaceful protesters, and yet we have also seen video of the police <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xrVp8vlQyU">standing idly by</a> while looters completely destroy businesses. What explains this? Is there a policy that led to this bizarre inversion of priorities? Are the police angry at the protesters for vilifying them, and simultaneously trying to teach society a lesson by letting crime and mayhem spread elsewhere in the city? Or is it just less risky to collide with peaceful protesters? Or is the whole spectacle itself a lie? How representative are these videos of what’s actually going on? Is there much less chaos actually occurring than is being advertised to us?</p>
<p>Again, it’s very hard to know.</p>
<p>What’s easy to know is that civil discourse has broken down. It seems to me that we’ve long been in a situation where the craziest voices on both ends of the political spectrum have been amplifying one another and threatening to produce something truly dangerous. And now I think they have. The amount of misinformation in the air—the degree to which even serious people seem to be ruled by false assumptions and non sequiturs—is just astonishing.</p>
<p>And it’s important to keep in mind that, with the presidential election coming in November, the stakes are really high. As most of you know, I consider four more years of Trump to be an existential threat to our democracy. And I believe that the last two weeks have been very good for him, politically, even when everything else seemed to go very badly for him. I know the polls don’t say this. A large majority of people disapprove of his handling this crisis so far. But I think we all know now to take polls with a grain of salt. There is the very real problem of preference falsification—especially in an environment of intense social pressure. People will often say what they think is socially acceptable, and then think, or say, or do something very different in private—like when they’re alone in a voting booth.</p>
<p>Trump has presided over the complete dismantling of American influence in the world and the destruction of our economy. I know the stock market has looked good, but the stock market has become totally uncoupled from the economy. According to the stock market, the future is just as bright now as it was in January of this year, before most of us had even heard of a novel coronavirus. That doesn’t make a lot of sense. And a lot can happen in the next few months. The last two weeks feel like a decade. And my concern is that if Trump now gets to be the law-and-order President, that may be his path to re-election, if such a path exists. Of course, this crisis has revealed, yet again, how unfit he is to be President. The man couldn’t strike a credible note of reconciliation if the fate of the country depended on it—and the fate of the country has depended on it. I also think it’s possible that these protests wouldn’t be happening, but for the fact that Trump is President. Whether or not the problem of racism has gotten worse in our society, having Trump as President surely makes it seem like it has. It has been such a repudiation of the Obama presidency that, for many people, it has made it seem that white supremacy is now ascendant. So, all the more reason to get rid of Trump in November.</p>
<p>But before this social unrest, our focus was on how incompetent Trump was in the face of the Covid-19 pandemic. And now he has been given a very different battle to fight. A battle against leftwing orthodoxy, which is growing more stifling by the minute, and civil unrest. If our social order frays sufficiently, restoring it will be the only thing that most people care about in November. Just think of what an act of domestic terrorism would do politically now. Things can change very, very quickly. And to all a concern for basic law and order “racist”, isn’t going to wash.</p>
<p>Trust in institutions has totally broken down. We’ve been under a very precarious quarantine for more than 3 months, which almost the entire medical profession has insisted is necessary. Doctors and public health officials have castigated people on the political Right for protesting this lockdown. People have been unable to be with their loved ones in their last hours of life. They’ve been unable to hold funerals for them. But now we have doctors and public officials by the thousands, signing <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/05/health/health-care-open-letter-protests-coronavirus-trnd/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open letters</a>, making public statements, saying it’s fine to stand shoulder to shoulder with others in the largest protests our nation has ever seen. The degree to which this has undermined confidence in public health messaging is hard to exaggerate. Whatever your politics, this has been just a mortifying piece of hypocrisy. Especially so, because the pandemic has been hitting the African American community hardest of all. How many people will die because of these protests? It’s a totally rational question to ask, but the question itself is taboo now.</p>
<p>So, it seems to me that almost everything appears upside down at the moment.</p>
<p>Before I get into details on police violence, first let me try to close the door to a few misunderstandings.</p>
<p>Let’s start with the proximate cause of all this: The killing of George Floyd by the Minneapolis police. I’ll have more to say about this in a minute, but nothing I say should detract from the following observation: That <a href="https://youtu.be/vksEJR9EPQ8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a> was absolutely sickening, and it revealed a degree of police negligence and incompetence and callousness that everyone was right to be horrified by. In particular, the actions of Derek Chauvin, the cop who kept his knee on Floyd’s neck for nearly 9 minutes, his actions were so reckless and so likely to cause harm that there’s no question he should be prosecuted. And he is being prosecuted. He’s been indicted for 2nd degree murder and manslaughter, and I suspect he will spend many, many years in prison. And, this is not to say “the system is working.” It certainly seems likely that without the cell phone video, and the public outrage, Chauvin might have gotten away with it—to say nothing of the other cops with him, who are also now being prosecuted. If this is true, we clearly need a better mechanism with which to police the police.</p>
<p>So, as I said, I’ll return to this topic, because I think most people are drawing the wrong conclusions from this video, and from videos like it, but let me just echo everyone’s outrage over what happened. This is precisely the kind of police behavior that everyone should find abhorrent.</p>
<p>On the general topic of racism in America, I want to make a few similarly clear, preemptive statements:</p>
<p>Racism is still a problem in American society. No question. And slavery—which was racism’s most evil expression—was this country’s founding sin. We should also add the near-total eradication of the Native Americans to that ledger of evil. Any morally sane person who learns the details of these historical injustices finds them shocking, whatever their race. And the legacy of these crimes—crimes that were perpetrated for centuries—remains a cause for serious moral concern today. I have no doubt about this. And nothing I’m about to say, should suggest otherwise.</p>
<p>And I don’t think it’s an accident that the two groups I just mentioned, African Americans and Native Americans, suffer the worst from inequality in America today. How could the history of racial discrimination in this country not have had lasting effects, given the nature of that history? And if anything good comes out of the current crisis, it will be that we manage to find a new commitment to reducing inequality in all its dimensions. The real debate to have is about how to do this, economically and politically. But the status quo that many of us take for granted to is a betrayal of our values, whether we realize it or not. If it’s not a betrayal or your values now, it will be a betrayal of your values when you become a better person. And if you don’t manage that, it will be a betrayal of your kid’s values when they’re old enough to understand the world they are living in. The difference between being very lucky in our society, and very unlucky, should not be as enormous as it is.</p>
<p>However, the question that interests me, given what has been true of the past and is now true of the present, is what should we do next? What should we do to build a healthier society?</p>
<p>What should we do next?  Tomorrow… next week…. Obviously, I don’t have the answers. But I am very worried that many of the things we’re doing now, and seem poised to do, will only make our problems worse. And I’m especially worried that it has become so difficult to talk about this. I’m just trying to have conversations. I’m just trying to figure these things out in real time, with other people. And there is no question that conversation itself has become dangerous.</p>
<p>Think about the politics of this. Endless imagery of people burning and looting independent businesses that were struggling to survive, and seeing the owners of these businesses beaten by mobs, cannot be good for the cause of social justice. Looting and burning businesses, and assaulting their owners, isn’t social justice, or even social protest. It’s crime. And having imagery of these crimes that highlight black involvement circulate endlessly on Fox News and on social media cannot be good for the black community. But it might yet be good for Trump.</p>
<p>And it could well kick open the door to a level of authoritarianism that many of us who have been very worried about Trump barely considered possible. It’s always seemed somewhat paranoid to me to wonder whether we’re living in Weimar Germany. I’ve had many conversations about this. I had <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/the-road-to-tyranny/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Timothy Snyder on the podcast</a>, who’s been worrying about the prospect of tyranny in the US for several years now. I’ve known, in the abstract, that democracies can destroy themselves. But the idea that it could happen here still seemed totally outlandish to me. It doesn’t anymore.</p>
<p>Of course, what we’ve been seeing in the streets isn’t just one thing. Some people are protesting for reasons that I fully defend. They’re outraged by specific instances of police violence, like the killing of George Floyd, and they’re worried about creeping authoritarianism—which we really should be worried about now. And they’re convinced that our politics is broken, because it is broken, and they are deeply concerned that our response to the pandemic and the implosion of our economy will do nothing to address the widening inequality in our society. And they recognize that we have a President who is an incompetent, divisive, conman and a crackpot at a time when we actually need wise leadership.</p>
<p>All of that is hard to put on a sign, but it’s all worth protesting.</p>
<p>However, it seems to me that most protesters are seeing this moment exclusively through the lens of identity politics—and racial politics in particular. And some of them are even celebrating the breakdown of law and order, or at least remaining nonjudgmental about it. And you could see, in the early days of this protest, news anchors take that line, on CNN, for instance. Talking about the history of social protest, “Sometimes it has to be violent, right? What, do you think all of these protests need to be nonviolent?” Those words came out of Chris Cuomo’s mouth, and Don Lemon’s mouth. Many people have been circulating a half quote from Martin Luther King Jr. about riots being “the language of the unheard.” They’re <a href="https://youtu.be/pjYZZC5i_AU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">leaving out the part</a> where he made it clear that he believed riots harmed the cause of the black community and helped the cause of racists.</p>
<p>There are now calls to defund and even to abolish the police. This may be psychologically understandable when you’ve spent half your day on Twitter watching videos of cops beating peaceful protesters. Those videos are infuriating. And I’ll have a lot more to say about police violence in a minute. But if you think a society without cops is a society you would want to live in, you have lost your mind. Giving a monopoly on violence to the state is just about the best thing we have ever done as a species. It ranks right up there with keeping our shit out of our food. Having a police force that can deter crime, and solve crimes when they occur, and deliver violent criminals to a functioning justice system, is the necessary precondition for almost anything else of value in society.</p>
<p>We need police reform, of course. There are serious questions to ask about the culture of policing—its hiring practices, training, the militarization of so many police forces, outside oversight, how police departments deal with corruption, the way the police unions keep bad cops on the job, and yes, the problem of racist cops. But the idea that any serious person thinks we can do without the police—or that less trained and less vetted cops will magically be better than more trained and more vetted ones—this just reveals that our conversation on these topics has run completely off the rails. Yes, we should give more resources to community services. We should have psychologists or social workers make first contact with the homeless or the mentally ill. Perhaps we’re giving cops jobs they shouldn’t be doing. All of that makes sense to rethink. But the idea that what we’re witnessing now is a matter of the cops being over-resourced—that we’ve given them too much training, that we’ve made the job too attractive—so that the people we’re recruiting are of too high a quality. That doesn’t make any sense.</p>
<p>What’s been alarming here is that we’re seeing prominent people—in government, in media, in Hollywood, in sports—speak and act as though the breakdown of civil society, and of society itself, is a form of progress and any desire for law enforcement is itself a form of racist oppression. At one point the woman who’s running the City Council in Minneapolis, which just decided to abolish the police force, was asked by a journalist, I believe on CNN, “What do I do if someone’s breaking into my house in the middle of the night? Who do I call?” And her first response to that question was, “You need to recognize what a statement of privilege that question is.” She’s since had to walk that back, because it’s one of the most galling and embarrassing things a public official has ever said, but this is how close the Democratic Party is to sounding completely insane. You cannot say that if someone is breaking into your house, and you’re terrified, and you want a police force that can respond, that fear is a symptom of “white privilege.” This is where Democratic politics goes to die.</p>
<p>Again, what is alarming about this is that this woke analysis of the breakdown of law and order will only encourage an increasingly authoritarian response, as well as the acceptance of that response by many millions of Americans.</p>
<p>If you step back, you will notice that there is a kind of ecstasy of ideological conformity in the air. And it’s destroying institutions. It’s destroying the very institutions we rely on to get our information—universities, the press. The New York Times in recent days, seems to be preparing for a self-immolation in recent days. No one wants to say or even think anything that makes anyone uncomfortable—certainly not anyone who has more wokeness points than they do. It’s just become too dangerous. There are people <a href="https://wwos.nine.com.au/news/nba-announcer-fired-over-controversial-all-lives-matter-tweet/a9a50198-4b52-4cb7-a800-e0ffacb3302d" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">being fired</a> for tweeting “All Lives Matter.” #AllLivesMatter, in the current environment, is being read as a naked declaration of white supremacy. That is how weird this moment is. A soccer player on the LA Galaxy <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/sports/rowdies/2020/06/05/la-galaxy-releases-player-after-wifes-racist-and-violent-social-media-posts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">was fired</a> for something his wife tweeted…</p>
<p>Of course, there are real problems of inequality and despair at the bottom of these protests. People who have never found a secure or satisfying place in the world—or young people who fear they never will—people who have seen their economic prospects simply vanish, and people who have had painful encounters with racism and racist cops—people by the millions are now surrendering themselves to a kind of religious awakening. But like most religious awakenings, this movement is not showing itself eager to make honest contact with reality.</p>
<p>On top of that, we find extraordinarily privileged people, whatever the color of their skin—people who have been living wonderful lives in their gated communities or 5<sup>th</sup> avenue apartments—and who feel damn guilty about it—they are supporting this movement uncritically, for many reasons. Of course, they care about other people—I’m sure most of them have the same concerns about inequality that I do—but they are also supporting this movement because it promises a perfect expiation of their sins. If you have millions of dollars, and shoot botox into your face, and vacation on St. Bart’s, and you’re liberal—the easiest way to sleep at night is to be as woke as AOC and like every one of her tweets.</p>
<p>The problem isn’t just with the looting, and the arson, and the violence. There are problems with these peaceful protests themselves.</p>
<p>Of course, I’m not questioning anyone’s right to protest. Even our deranged president can pay lip service to that right—which he did as the DC police were violently dispersing a peaceful protest so that he could get his picture taken in front of that church, awkwardly holding a bible, as though he had never held a book in life.</p>
<p>The problem with the protests is that they are animated, to a remarkable degree, by confusion and misinformation. And I’ll explain why I think that’s the case. And, of course, this will be controversial. Needless to say, many people will consider the color of my skin to be disqualifying here. I could have invited any number of great, black intellectuals onto the podcast to make these points for me. But that struck me as a form of cowardice. Glenn Loury, John McWhorter, Thomas Chatterton Williams, Coleman Hughes, Kmele Foster, these guys might not agree with everything I’m about to say, but any one of them could walk the tightrope I’m now stepping out on far more credibly than I can.</p>
<p>But, you see, that’s part of the problem. The perception that the color of a person’s skin, or even his life experience, matters for this discussion is a pernicious illusion. For the discussion we really need to have, the color of a person’s skin, and even his life experience, simply does not matter. It cannot matter. We have to break this spell that the politics of identity has cast over everything.</p>
<p>Ok…</p>
<p>As I’ve already acknowledged, there is a legacy of racism in the United States that we’re still struggling to outgrow. That is obvious. There are real racists out there. And there are ways in which racism became institutionalized long ago. Many of you will remember that during the crack epidemic the penalties for crack and powder cocaine were quite different. And this led black drug offenders to be locked up for much longer than white ones. Now, whether the motivation for that policy was consciously racist or not, I don’t know, but it was effectively racist. Nothing I’m about to say entails a denial of these sorts of facts. There just seems to be no question that boys who grow up with their fathers in prison start life with a significant strike against them. So criminal justice reform is absolutely essential.</p>
<p>And I’m not denying that many black people, perhaps most, have interactions with cops, and others in positions of power, or even random strangers, that seem unambiguously racist. Sometimes this is because they are actually in the presence of racism, and perhaps sometimes it only seems that way. I’ve had unpleasant encounters with cops, and customs officers, and TSA screeners, and bureaucrats of every kind, and even with people working in stores or restaurants. People aren’t always nice or ethical. But being white, and living in a majority white society, I’ve never had to worry about whether any of these collisions were the result of racism. And I can well imagine that in some of these situations, had I been black, I would have come away feeling that I had encountered yet another racist in the wild. So I consider myself very lucky to have gone through life not having to think about any of that. Surely that’s one form of white privilege.</p>
<p>So, nothing I’m going to say denies that we should condemn racism—whether interpersonal or institutional—and we should condemn it wherever we find it. But as a society, we simply can’t afford to find and condemn racism where it doesn’t exist. And we should be increasingly aware of the costs of doing that. The more progress we make on issues of race, the less racism there will be to find, and the more likely we’ll find ourselves chasing after its ghost.</p>
<p>The truth is, we have made considerable progress on the problem of racism in America. This isn’t 1920, and it isn’t 1960. We had a two-term black president. We have black congressmen and women. We have black mayors and black chiefs of police. There are major cities, like Detroit and Atlanta, going on their fifth or sixth consecutive black mayor. Having more and more black people in positions of real power, in what is still a majority white society, is progress on the problem of racism. And the truth is, it might not even solve the problem we’re talking about. When Freddy Gray was killed in Baltimore, virtually everyone who could have been held accountable for his death was black. The problem of police misconduct and reform is complicated, as we’re about to see. But obviously, there is more work to do on the problem of racism. And, more important, there is much more work to do to remedy the inequalities in our society that are so correlated with race, and will still be correlated with race, even after the last racist has been driven from our shores.</p>
<p>The question of how much of today’s inequality is due to existing racism—whether racist people or racist policies—is a genuinely difficult question to answer. And to answer it, we need to distinguish the past from the present.</p>
<p>Take wealth inequality, for example: The median white family has a net worth of around $170,000—these data are a couple of years old, but they’re probably pretty close to what’s true now. The median black family has a net worth of around $17,000. So we have a <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/blog/brookings-now/2019/06/18/a-conversation-about-the-racial-wealth-gap-and-how-to-address-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tenfold difference in median wealth</a>. (That’s the median, not the mean: Half of white families are below 170,000 and half above; half of black families are below 17,000 and half above. And we’re talking about wealth here, not income.)</p>
<p>This disparity in wealth persists even for people whose incomes are in the top 10 percent of the income distribution. For whites in the top 10 percent for income, the median net worth is $1.8 million; for blacks it’s around $350,000. There are probably many things that account for this disparity in wealth. It seems that black families that make it to the top of the income distribution fall out of it more easily than white families do. But it’s also undeniable that black families have less intergenerational wealth accumulated through inheritance.</p>
<p>How much of this is inequality due to the legacy of slavery? And how much of it is due to an ensuing century of racist policies? I’m prepared to believe quite a lot. And it strikes me as totally legitimate to think about paying reparations as a possible remedy here. Of course, one will then need to talk about reparations for the Native Americans. And then one wonders where this all ends. And what about blacks who aren’t descended from slaves, but who still suffered the consequences of racism in the US? In listening to people like <a href="https://youtu.be/FXt9Q5h1sCY" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">John McWhorter</a> and Coleman Hughes discuss this topic, I’m inclined to think that reparations is probably unworkable as a policy. But the truth is that I’m genuinely unsure about this.</p>
<p>Whatever we decide about the specific burdens of the past, we have to ask, how much of current wealth inequality is due to existing racism and to existing policies that make it harder for black families to build wealth? And the only way to get answers to those questions is to have a dispassionate discussion about facts.</p>
<p>The problem with the social activism we are now seeing—what John McWhorter has called “the new religion of anti-Racism”—is that it finds racism nearly everywhere, even where it manifestly does not exist. And this is incredibly damaging to the cause of achieving real equality in our society. It’s almost impossible to exaggerate the evil and injustice of slavery and its aftermath. But it is possible to exaggerate how much racism currently exists at an Ivy League university, or in Silicon Valley, or at the Oscars. And those exaggerations are toxic—and, perversely, they may produce more real racism. It seems to me that false claims of victimhood can diminish the social stature of any group, even a group that has a long history of real victimization.</p>
<p>The imprecision here—the bad-faith arguments, the double standards, the goal-post shifting, the <a href="https://nyti.ms/2hrFzz1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">idiotic opinion pieces</a> in the New York Times, the defenestrations on social media, the general hysteria that the cult of wokeness has produced—I think this is all extremely harmful to civil society, and to effective liberal politics, and to the welfare of African Americans.</p>
<p>So, with that as preamble, let’s return to the tragic death of George Floyd.</p>
<p>As I said, I believe that any sane person who watches that video will feel that they have witnessed a totally unjustified killing. So, people of any race, are right to be horrified by what happened there. But now I want to ask a few questions, and I want us to try to consider them dispassionately. And I really want you to watch your mind while you do this. There are very likely to be few tripwires installed there, and I’m about to hit them. So just do your best to remain calm.</p>
<p>Does the killing of George Floyd prove that we have a problem of racism in the United States?</p>
<p>Does it even suggest that we have a problem of racism in the United States?</p>
<p>In other words, do we have reason to believe that, had Floyd been white, he wouldn’t have died in a similar way?</p>
<p>Do the dozen or so other videos that have emerged in recent years, of black men being killed by cops, do they prove, or even suggest, that there is an epidemic of lethal police violence directed especially at black men and that this violence is motivated by racism?</p>
<p>Most people seem to think that the answers to these questions are so obvious that to even pose them as I just did is obscene. The answer is YES, and it’s a yes that now needs to be shouted in the streets.</p>
<p>The problem, however, is that if you take even 5 minutes to look at the data on crime and police violence, the answer appears to be “no,” in every case, albeit with one important caveat. I’m not talking about how the police behaved in 1970 or even 1990. But in the last 25 years, violent crime has come down significantly in the US, and so has the police use of deadly force. And as you’re about to see, the police used more deadly force against white people—both in absolute numbers, and in terms of their contribution to crime and violence in our society. But the public perception is, of course, completely different.</p>
<p>In a city like Los Angeles, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/california/story/2020-05-12/lapd-use-of-force-report" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2019 was a 30-year low</a> for police shootings. Think about that…. Do the people who were protesting in Los Angeles, peacefully and violently, do the people who were ransacking and burning businesses by the hundreds—in many cases, businesses that will not return to their neighborhoods—do the people who caused so much damage to the city, that certain neighborhoods, ironically the neighborhoods that are disproportionately black, will take years, probably decades to recover, do the celebrities who supported them, and even bailed them out of jail—do any of these people know that 2019 was the 30-year low for police shootings in Los Angeles?</p>
<p>Before I step out further over the abyss here, let me reiterate: Many of you are going to feel a visceral negative reaction to what I’m about to say. You’re not going to like the way it sounds. You’re especially not going to like the way it sounds coming from a white guy. This feeling of not liking, this feeling of outrage, this feeling of disgust—this feeling of “Sam, what the fuck is wrong with you, why are you even touching this topic?”—this feeling isn’t an argument. It isn’t, or shouldn’t be, the basis for your believing anything to be true or false about the world.</p>
<p>Your capacity to be offended isn’t something that I or anyone else needs to respect. Your capacity to be offended isn’t something that you should respect. In fact, it is something that you should be on your guard for. Perhaps more than any other property of your mind, this feeling can mislead you.</p>
<p>If you care about justice—and you absolutely should—you should care about facts and the ability to discuss them openly. Justice requires contact with reality. It simply isn’t the case—it cannot be the case—that the most pressing claims on our sense of justice need come from those who claim to be the most offended by conversation itself.</p>
<p>So, I’m going to speak the language of facts right now, in so far as we know them, all the while knowing that these facts run very much counter to most people’s assumptions. Many of the things you think you know about crime and violence in our society are almost certainly wrong. And that should matter to you.</p>
<p>So just take a moment and think this through with me.</p>
<p>How many people are killed each year in America by cops? If you don’t know, guess. See if you have any intuitions for these numbers. Because your intuitions are determining how you interpret horrific videos of the sort we saw coming out of Minneapolis.</p>
<p>The answer for many years running is <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/investigations/police-shootings-database/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">about 1000</a>. One thousand people are killed by cops in America each year. There are about 50 to 60 million encounters between civilians and cops each year, and <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2017/crime-in-the-u.s.-2017/tables/table-29" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">about 10 million arrests</a>. That’s down from a high of over 14 million arrests annually throughout the 1990’s. So, of the 10 million occasions where a person attracts the attention of the police, and the police decide to make an arrest, about 1000 of those people die as a result. (I’m sure a few people get killed even when no arrest was attempted, but that has to be a truly tiny number.) So, without knowing anything else about the situation, if the cops decide to arrest you, it would be reasonable to think that your chance of dying is around 1/10,000. Of course, in the United States, it’s higher than it is in other countries. So I’m not saying that this number is acceptable. But it is what it is for a reason, as we’re about to see.</p>
<p>Now, there are a few generic things I’d like to point here before we get further into the data. They should be uncontroversial.</p>
<p>First, it’s almost certainly the case that of these 1000 officer-caused deaths each year, some are entirely justified—it may even be true that most are entirely justified—and some are entirely unjustified, and some are much harder to judge. And that will be true next year. And the year after that.</p>
<p>Of the unjustified killings, there are vast differences between them. Many have nothing in common but for the fact that a cop killed someone unnecessarily. It might have been a terrible misunderstanding, or incompetence, or just bad luck, and in certain cases it could be a cop who decides to murder someone because he’s become enraged, or he’s just a psychopath. And it is certainly possible that racial bias accounts for some number of these unjustified killings.</p>
<p>Another point that should be uncontroversial—but may sound a little tone-deaf in the current environment, where we’ve inundated with videos of police violence in response to these protests. But this has to be acknowledged whenever we’re discussing this topic: Cops have a very hard job. In fact, in the current environment, they have an almost impossible job.</p>
<p>If you’re making 10 million arrests every year, some number of people will decide not to cooperate. There can be many reasons for this. A person could be mentally ill, or drunk, or on drugs. Of course, rather often the person is an actual criminal who doesn’t want to be arrested.</p>
<p>Among innocent people, and perhaps this getting more common these days, a person might feel that resisting arrest is the right thing to do, ethically or politically or as a matter of affirming his identity. After all, put yourself in his shoes, he did nothing wrong. Why are the cops arresting him? I don’t know if we have data on the numbers of people who resist arrest by race. But I can well imagine that if it’s common for African Americans to believe that the only reason they have been singled out for arrest is due to racism on the part of the police, that could lead to greater levels of non-compliance. Which seems very likely to lead to more unnecessary injury and death. This is certainly one reason why it is wise to have the racial composition of a police force mirror that of the community it’s policing. Unfortunately, there’s no evidence that this will reduce lethal violence from the side of the police. In fact, the evidence we have suggests that black and Hispanic cops are <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/116/32/15877.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">more likely</a> to shoot black and Hispanic suspects than white cops are. But it would surely change the perception of the community that racism is a likely explanation for police behavior, which itself might reduce conflict.</p>
<p>When a cop goes hands on a person in an attempt to control his movements or make an arrest, that person’s resistance poses a problem that most people don’t understand. If you haven’t studied this topic. If you don’t know what it physically takes to restrain and immobilize a non-compliant person who may be bigger and stronger than you are, and if you haven’t thought through the implications of having a gun on your belt while attempting to do that—a gun that can be grabbed and used against you, or against a member of the public—then your intuitions about what makes sense here, tactically and ethically, are very likely to be bad.</p>
<p>If you haven’t trained with firearms under stress. If you don’t know how suddenly situations can change. If you haven’t experienced how quickly another person can close the distance on you, and how little time you have to decide to draw your weapon. If you don’t know how hard it is to shoot a moving target, or even a stationary one, when your heart is beating out of your chest. You very likely have totally unreasonable ideas about what we can expect from cops in situations like these. [<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9NwWado4SVY&amp;bpctr=1592453276" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ygbOLb0O7Pw&amp;bpctr=1592455027" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_87GBOCVYTM" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>]</p>
<p>And there is another fact that looms over all this like the angel of Death, literally: Most cops do not get the training they need. They don’t get the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YQLOmfx8X_E&amp;feature=emb_title">hand-to-hand training</a> they need—they don’t have good skills to subdue people without harming them. All you need to do is watch YouTube videos of botched arrests to see this. The martial arts community stands in perpetual astonishment at <a href="https://youtu.be/F4VeHOkt_o8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the kinds of things cops do and fail to do</a> once they start fighting with suspects. Cops also don’t get the firearms training they need. Of course, there are elite units in many police departments, but most cops do not have the training they need to do the job they’re being asked to do.</p>
<p>It is also true, no doubt, that some cops are racist bullies. And there are corrupt police departments that cover for these guys, and cover up police misconduct generally, whether it was borne of racism or not.</p>
<p>But the truth is that even if we got rid of all bad cops, which we absolutely should do, and there were only good people left, and we got all these good people the best possible training, and we gave them the best culture in which to think about their role in society, and we gave them the best methods for de-escalating potentially violent situations—which we absolutely must do—and we scrubbed all the dumb laws from our books, so that when cops were required to enforce the law, they were only risking their lives and the lives of civilians for reasons that we deem necessary and just—so the war on drugs is obviously over—even under these conditions of perfect progress, we are still guaranteed to have some number of cases each year where a cop kills a civilian in a way that is totally unjustified, and therefore tragic. Every year, there will be some number of families who will be able to say that the cops killed their son or daughter, or father or mother, or brother or sister. And videos of these killings will occasionally surface, and they will be horrific. This seems guaranteed to happen.</p>
<p>So, while we need to make all these improvements, we still need to understand that there are very likely always to going to be videos of cops doing something inexplicable, or inexplicably stupid, that results in an innocent person’s death, or a not-so-innocent person’s death. And sometimes the cop will be white and the victim will be black. We have 10 million arrests each year. And we now live in a panopticon where practically everything is videotaped.</p>
<p>I’m about to get further into the details of what we know about police violence, but I want to just put it to you now: If we’re going to let the health of race relations in this country, or the relationship between the community and the police, depend on whether we ever see a terrible video of police misconduct again, the project of healing these wounds in our society is doomed.</p>
<p>About a week into these protests I heard Van Jones on CNN say, “If we see one more video of a cop brutalizing a black man, this country could go over the edge.” He said this, not as indication of how dangerously inflamed people have become. He seemed to be saying it as an ultimatum to the police. With 10 million arrests a year, arrests that have to take place in the most highly armed society in the developed world, I hope you understand how unreasonable that ultimatum is.</p>
<p>We have to put these videos into context. And we have to acknowledge how different they are from one another. Some of them are easy to interpret. But some are quite obviously being interpreted incorrectly by most people—especially by activists. And there are a range of cases—some have video associated with them and some don’t—that are now part of a litany of anti-racist outrage, and the names of the dead are intoned as though they were all evidence of the same injustice. And yet, they are not.</p>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/XKQqgVlk0NQ" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Walter Scott</a> was stopped for a broken taillight and got out of his car and tried to flee. There might have been a brief struggle over the officer’s taser, that part of the video isn’t clear. But what is clear is that he was shot in the back multiple times as he was running away. That was insane. There was zero reason for the officer to feel that his life was under threat at the point he opened fire. And for that unjustified shooting, he was sentenced to 20 years in prison. I’m not sure that’s long enough. That seemed like straight-up murder.</p>
<p>The George Floyd video, while even more disturbing to watch, is harder to interpret. I don’t know anything about Derek Chauvin, the cop who knelt on his neck. It’s quite possible that he’s a terrible person who should have never been a cop. He seems to have a significant number of complaints against him—though, as far as I know, the details of those complaints haven’t been released. And he might be a racist on top of being a bad cop. Or he might be a guy who was totally in over his head and thought you could restrain someone indefinitely by keeping a knee on their neck indefinitely. I don’t know. I’m sure more facts will come out. But whoever he is, I find it very unlikely that he was intending to kill George Floyd. Think about it. He was surrounded by irate witnesses and being filmed. Unless he was aspiring to become the most notorious murderer in human history, it seems very unlikely that he was intending to commit murder in that moment. It’s possible, of course. But it doesn’t seem the likeliest explanation for his behavior.</p>
<p>What I believe we saw on that video was the result of a tragic level of negligence and poor training on the part of those cops. Or terrible recruitment—it’s possible that none of these guys should have ever been cops. I think for one of them, it was only his fourth day on the job. Just imagine that. Just imagine all things you don’t know as a new cop.  It could also be a function of bad luck in terms of Floyd’s underlying health. It’s been reported that he was complaining of being unable to breath before Chauvin pinned him with his knee. The knee on his neck might not have been the only thing that caused his death. It could have also been the weight of the other officer pinning him down.</p>
<p>This is almost certainly what happened in the cast of Eric Garner. Half the people on earth believe they witnessed a cop choke Eric Garner to death in that video. That does not appear to be what happened. When Eric Garner is saying “I can’t breathe” he’s not being choked. He’s being held down on the pavement by several officers. Being forced down on your stomach under the weight of several people can kill a person, especially someone with lung or heart disease. In the case of Eric Garner, it is absolutely clear that the cop who briefly attempted to choke him was no longer choking him. If you doubt that, watch the <a href="https://youtu.be/Nql1xRtWKOU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">video</a> again.</p>
<p>And if you are recoiling now from my interpretation of these videos, you really should watch <a href="https://youtu.be/_c-E_i8Q5G0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the killing of Tony Timpa</a>. It’s also terribly disturbing, but it removes the variable of race and it removes any implication of intent to harm on the part of the cops about as clearly as you could ask. It really is worth watching as a corrective to our natural interpretation of these other videos.</p>
<p>Tony Timpa was a white man in Dallas, who was suffering some mental health emergency and cocaine intoxication. And he actually called 911 himself. What we see is the bodycam footage from the police, which shows that he was already in handcuffs when they arrived—a security guard had cuffed him. And then the cops take over, and they restrain Timpa on the ground, by rolling him onto a stomach and putting their weight on him, very much like in the case of Eric Garner. And they keep their weight on him—one cop has a knee on his upper back, which is definitely much less aggressive than a knee on the neck—but they crush the life out of him all the same, over the course of 13 minutes. He’s not being choked. The cops are not being rough. There’s no animus between them and Timpa. It was not a hostile arrest. They clearly believe that they’re responding to a mental health emergency. But they keep him down on his belly, under their weight, and they’re cracking jokes as he loses consciousness. Now, your knowledge that he’s going to be dead by the end of this video, make their jokes seem pretty callous. But this was about as benign an imposition of force by cops as you’re going to see. The crucial insight you will have watching this video, is that the officers not only had no intent to kill Tony Timpa, they don’t take his pleading seriously because they have no doubt that what they’re doing is perfectly safe—perfectly within protocol. They’ve probably done this hundreds of times before.</p>
<p>If you watch that video—and, again, fair warning, it is disturbing—but imagine how disturbing it would have been to our society if Tony Timpa had been black. If the only thing you changed about the video was the color of Timpa’s skin, then that video would have detonated like a nuclear bomb in our society, exactly as the George Floyd video did. In fact, in one way it is worse, or would have been perceived to be worse. I mean, just imagine white cops telling jokes as they crushed the life out of a black Tony Timpa… Given the nature of our conversation about violence, given the way we perceive videos of this kind, there is no way that people would have seen that as anything other than a lynching. And yet, it would not have been a lynching.</p>
<p>Now, I obviously have no idea what was in the minds of cops in Minneapolis. And perhaps we’ll learn at trial. Perhaps a tape of Chauvin using the N-word in another context will surface, bringing in a credible allegation of racism. It seems to me that Chauvin is going to have a very hard time making sense of his actions. But most people who saw that video believe they have seen, with their own eyes, beyond any possibility of doubt, a racist cop intentionally murder an innocent man. That’s not what the video necessarily shows.</p>
<p>As I said, these videos can be hard to interpret, even while seeming very easy to interpret. And these cases, whether we have associated video or not, are very different. Michael Brown is reported to have punched a cop in the face and attempted to get his gun. As far as I know, there’s no video of that encounter. But, if true, that is an entirely different situation. If you’re attacking a cop, trying to get his gun, that is a life and death struggle that almost by definition for the cop, and it most cases justifies the use of lethal force. And honestly, it seems that no one within a thousand miles of Black Lives Matter is willing to make these distinctions. An attitude of anti-racist moral outrage is not the best lens through which to interpret evidence of police misconduct.</p>
<p>I’ve seen many videos of people getting arrested. And I’ve seen the outraged public reaction to what appears to be inappropriate use of force by the cops. One overwhelming fact that comes through is that people, whatever the color of their skin, don’t understand how to behave around cops so as to keep themselves safe. People have to stop resisting arrest. This may seem obvious, but judging from most of these videos, and from the public reaction to them, this must be a totally arcane piece of information. When a cop wants to take you into custody, you don’t get to decide whether or not you should be arrested. When a cop wants to take you into custody, for whatever reason, it’s not a negotiation. And if you turn it into a wrestling match, you’re very likely to get injured or killed.</p>
<p>This is a point I once belabored in a <a href="https://samharris.org/podcasts/racism-and-violence-in-america/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">podcast with Glenn Loury</a>, and it became essentially a public service announcement. And I’ve gone back and listened to those comments, and I want to repeat them here. This is something that everyone really needs to understand. And it’s something that Black Lives Matter should be teaching explicitly: If you put your hands on a cop—if you start wrestling with a cop, or grabbing him because he’s arresting your friend, or pushing him, or striking him, or using your hands in way that can possibly be interpreted as your reaching for a gun—you are likely to get shot in the United States, whatever the color of your skin.</p>
<p>As I said, when you’re with a cop, there is always a gun out in the open. And any physical struggle has to be perceived by him as a fight for the gun. A cop doesn’t know what you’re going to do if you overpower him, so he has to assume the worst. Most cops are not confident in their ability to physically control a person without shooting him—for good reason, because they’re not well trained to do that, and they’re continually confronting people who are bigger, or younger, or more athletic, or more aggressive than they are. Cops are not superheroes. They’re ordinary people with insufficient training, and once things turn physical they cannot afford to give a person who is now assaulting a police officer the benefit of the doubt.</p>
<p>This is something that most people seem totally confused about. If they see a video of somebody trying to punch a cop in the face and the person’s unarmed, many people think the cop should just punch back, and any use of deadly force would be totally disproportionate. But that’s not how violence works. It’s not the cop’s job to be the best bare-knuckled boxer on Earth so he doesn’t have to use his gun. A cop can’t risk getting repeatedly hit in the face and knocked out, because there’s always a gun in play. This is the cop’s perception of the world, and it’s a justifiable one, given the dynamics of human violence.</p>
<p>You might think cops shouldn’t carry guns. Why can’t we just be like England? That’s a point that can be debated. But it requires considerable thought in a country where there are over 300 million guns on the street. The United States is not England.</p>
<p>Again, really focus on what is happening when a cop is attempting to arrest a person. It’s not up to you to decide whether or not you should be arrested. Does it matter that you know you didn’t do anything wrong? No. And how could that fact be effectively communicated in the moment by your not following police commands? I’m going to ask that again: How could the fact that you’re innocent, that you’re not a threat to cop, that you’re not about to suddenly attack him or produce a weapon of your own, how could those things be effectively communicated at the moment he’s attempting to arrest you by your resisting arrest?</p>
<p>Unless you called the cops yourself, you never know what situation you’re in. If I’m walking down the street, I don’t know if the cop who is approaching me didn’t get a call that some guy who looks like Ben Stiller just committed an armed robbery. I know I didn’t do anything, but I don’t know what’s in the cop’s head. The time to find out what’s going on—the time to complain about racist cops, the time to yell at them and tell them they’re all going to get fired for their stupidity and misconduct—is after cooperating, at the police station, in the presence of a lawyer, preferably. But to not comply in the heat of the moment, when a guy with the gun is issuing commands—this raises your risk astronomically, and it’s something that most people, it seems, just do not intuitively understand, even when they’re not in the heat of the moment themselves, but just watching video of other people getting arrested.</p>
<p>Ok. End of public-service announcement.</p>
<p>The main problem with using individual cases, where black men and women have been killed by cops, to conclude that there is an epidemic of racist police violence in our society, is that you can find nearly identical cases of white suspects being killed by cops, and there are actually more of them.</p>
<p>In 2016, John McWhorter wrote a <a href="https://time.com/4404987/police-violence/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">piece</a> in Time Magazine about this.</p>
<p>Here’s a snippet of what he wrote:</p>
<p>“The heart of the indignation over these murders is a conviction that racist bias plays a decisive part in these encounters. That has seemed plausible to me, and I have recently challenged those who disagree to present a list of white people killed within the past few years under circumstances similar to those that so enrage us in cases such as what happened to Tamir Rice, John Crawford, Walter Scott, Sam Debose, and others.”</p>
<p>So, McWhorter issued that challenge, as he said, and he was presented with the cases [<a href="https://youtu.be/EPxNUKw0kV8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/VBUUx0jUKxc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>, <a href="https://youtu.be/6KhRcIOuurI" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">VIDEO</a>]. But there’s no song about these people, admonishing us to say their names. And the list of white names is longer, and I don’t know any of them, other than Tony Timpa. I know the black names. In addition to the ones I just read from McWhorter’s article, I know the names of Eric Garner, and Michael Brown, and Alton Sterling, and Philando Castile, and now, of course, I know the name of George Floyd. And I’m aware of many of the details of these cases where black men and women have been killed by cops. I know the name of Breonna Taylor. I can’t name a single white person killed by cops in circumstances like these—other than Timpa—and I just read McWhorter’s article where he lists many of them.</p>
<p>So, this is also a distortion in the media. The media is not showing us videos of white people being killed by cops; activists are not demanding that they do this. I’m sure white supremacists talk about this stuff a lot, who knows? But in terms of the story we’re telling ourselves in the mainstream, we are not actually talking about the data on lethal police violence.</p>
<p>So back to the data: Again, cops kill around 1000 people every year in the United States. About 25 percent are black. About 50 percent are white. The data on police homicide are all over the place. The federal government does not have a single repository for data of this kind. But they have been pretty carefully tracked by outside sources, like the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/graphics/investigations/police-shootings-database/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Washington Post</a>, for the last 5 years. These ratios appear stable over time. Again, many of these killings are justifiable, we’re talking about career criminals who are often armed and, in many cases, trying to kill the cops. Those aren’t the cases we’re worried about. We’re worried about the unjustifiable homicides.</p>
<p>Now, some people will think that these numbers still represent an outrageous injustice. Afterall, African Americans are only 13 percent of the population. So, at most, they should be 13 percent of the victims of police violence, not 25 percent. Any departure from the baseline population must be due to racism.</p>
<p>Ok. Well, that sounds plausible, but consider a few more facts:</p>
<p>Blacks are 13 percent of the population, but they commit <a href="https://ucr.fbi.gov/crime-in-the-u.s/2015/crime-in-the-u.s.-2015/offenses-known-to-law-enforcement/expanded-homicide" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">at least 50 percent</a> of the murders and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/the-myth-of-systemic-police-racism-11591119883">other violent crimes</a>.</p>
<p>If you have 13 percent of the population responsible for 50 percent of the murders—and in some cities committing 2/3rds of all violent crime—what percent of police attention should it attract? I don’t know. But I’m pretty sure it’s not just 13 percent. Given that the overwhelming majority of their victims are black, I’m pretty sure that most black people wouldn’t set the dial at 13 percent either.</p>
<p>And here we arrive at the core of the problem. The story of crime in America is overwhelmingly the story of black-on-black crime. It is also, in part, a story of black-on-white crime. For more than a generation, crime in America really hasn’t been a story of much white-on-black crime. [Some listeners mistook my meaning here. I’m not denying that most violent crime is intraracial. So, it’s true that most white homicide victims are killed by white offenders. Per capita, however, the white crime rate is much lower than the black crime rate. And there is more black-on-white crime than white-on-black crime.—SH]</p>
<p>The murder rate has come down steadily since the early 1990’s, with only minor upticks. But, nationwide, blacks are still <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nvsr/nvsr68/nvsr68_09-508.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">6 times more likely</a> to get murdered than whites, and in some cities their risk is double that. And <a href="https://www.hks.harvard.edu/sites/default/files/centers/wiener/programs/pcj/files/PoliceandPublicDiscourseBlackonBlackViolence.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">around 95 percent</a> of the murders are committed by members of the African American community. [While reported in 2015, these data were more than a decade old. Looking at more recent data from the <a href="https://www.fbi.gov/services/cjis/ucr/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">FBI’s Uniform Crime Report</a>, the number appears to be closer to 90 percent.—SH]</p>
<p>The weekend these protests and riots were kicking off nationwide—when our entire country seemed to be tearing itself apart over a perceived epidemic of racist police violence against the black community, <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/US/chicago-sees-18-homicides-deadliest-day-60-years/story?id=71150234" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">92 people were shot, and 27 killed</a>, in Chicago alone—one city. This is almost entirely a story of black men killing members of their own community. And this is far more representative of the kind of violence that the black community needs to worry about. And, ironically, it’s clear that one remedy for this violence is, or would be, effective policing.</p>
<p>These are simply the facts of crime in our society as we best understand them. And the police have to figure out how to respond to these facts, professionally and ethically. The question is, are they doing that? And, obviously, there’s considerable doubt that they’re doing that, professionally and ethically.</p>
<p>Roland Fryer, the Harvard economist who’s work I discussed on the podcast with Glenn Loury, studied police encounters involving black and white suspects and the use of force.</p>
<p>His <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w22399" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">paper</a> is titled, this from 2016, “An Empirical Analysis of Racial Differences in Police Use of Force.”</p>
<p>Fryer is black, and he went into this research with the expectation that the data would confirm that there’s an epidemic of lethal police violence directed at black men. But he didn’t find that. However, he did find support for the suspicion that black people suffer more nonlethal violence at the hands of cops than whites do.</p>
<p>So let’s look at this.</p>
<p>The study examined data from 10 major police departments, in Texas, Florida and California. Generally, Fryer found that there is 25 percent greater likelihood that the police would go hands on black suspects than white ones—cuffing them, or forcing them to ground, or using other non-lethal force.</p>
<p>Specifically, in New York City, in encounters where white and black citizens were matched for other characteristics, they found that:</p>
<p>Cops were…</p>
<ul>
<li>17 percent more likely to go hands on black suspects</li>
<li>18 percent more likely to push them into a wall</li>
<li>16 percent more likely to put them in handcuffs (in a situation in which they aren’t arrested)</li>
<li>18 percent more likely to push them to the ground</li>
<li>25 percent more likely to use pepper spray or a baton</li>
<li>19 percent more likely to draw their guns</li>
<li>24 percent more likely to point a gun at them.</li>
</ul>
<p>This is more or less the full continuum of violence short of using lethal force. And it seems, from the data we have, that blacks receive more of it than whites. What accounts for this disparity? Racism? Maybe. However, as I said, it’s inconvenient to note that other data suggest that black cops and Hispanic cops are more likely to shoot black and Hispanic suspects than white cops are. I’m not sure how an ambient level of racism explains that.</p>
<p>Are there other explanations? Well, again, could it be that blacks are less cooperative with the police. If so, that’s worth understanding. A culture of resisting arrest would be a very bad thing to cultivate, given that the only response to such resistance is for the police to increase their use of force.</p>
<p>Whatever is true here is something we should want to understand. And it’s all too easy to see how an increased number of encounters with cops, due to their policing in the highest crime neighborhoods, which are disproportionately black, and an increased number of traffic stops in those neighborhoods, and an increased propensity for cops to go hands-on these suspects, with or without an arrest, for whatever reason—it’s easy to see how all of this could be the basis for a perception of racism, whether or not racism is the underlying motivation.</p>
<p>It is totally humiliating to be arrested or manhandled by a cop. And, given the level of crime in the black community, a disproportionate number of innocent black men seem guaranteed to have this experience. It’s totally understandable that this would make them bitter and mistrustful of the police. This is another vicious circle that we must find some way to interrupt.</p>
<p>But Fryer also found that black suspects are around 25 percent less likely to be shot than white suspects are. And in the most egregious situations, where officers were not first attacked, but nevertheless fired their weapons at a suspect, they were more likely to do this when the suspect was white.</p>
<p>Again, the data are incomplete. This doesn’t not cover every city in the country. And a larger study tomorrow might paint a different picture. But, as far as I know, the best data we have suggest that for, whatever reason, whites are more likely to be killed by cops once an arrest is attempted. And a <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/116/32/15877.short" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">more recent study</a> in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences  by David Johnson and colleagues found similar results. And it is simply undeniable that more whites are killed by cops each year, both in absolute numbers and in proportion to their contributions to crime and violence in our society.</p>
<p>Can you hear how these facts should be grinding in that well-oiled machine of woke outrage? Our society is in serious trouble now. We are being crushed under the weight of a global pandemic and our response to it has been totally inept. On top of that, we’re being squeezed by the growing pressure of what might become a full-on economic depression. And the streets are now filled with people who imagine, on the basis of seeing some horrific videos, that there is an epidemic of racist cops murdering African Americans. Look at what this belief is doing to our politics. And these videos will keep coming. And the truth is they could probably be matched 2 for 1 with videos of white people being killed by cops. What percentage of people protesting understand that the disparity runs this way? In light of the belief that the disparity must run the other way, people are now quite happy to risk getting beaten and arrested by cops themselves, and to even loot and burn businesses. And most people and institutions are supporting this civil unrest from the sidelines, because they too imagine that cops are killing black people in extraordinary numbers. And all of this is calling forth an authoritarian response from Trump—and leading to more examples of police violence caught on video.</p>
<p>As I hope I’ve made clear, we need police reform—there’s no question about this. And some of the recent footage of the police attacking peaceful protests is outrageous. Nothing I just said should signify that I’m unaware of that. From what I’ve seen—and by the time I release this podcast, the character of all this might have changed—but, from what I’ve seen, the police were dangerously passive in the face of looting and real crime, at least in the beginning. In many cities, they just stood and watched society unravel. And then they were far too aggressive in the face of genuinely peaceful protests. This is a terrible combination. It is the worst combination. There’s no better way to increase cynicism and anger and fear, on all sides.</p>
<p>But racializing how we speak about the problem of police violence, where race isn’t actually the relevant variable—again, think of Tony Timpa— this has highly negative effects. First, it keeps us from talking about the real problems with police tactics. For instance, we had the recent case of Breonna Taylor who was killed in a so-called “no knock” raid of her home. As occasionally happens, in this carnival of moral error we call “the war on drugs,” the police had the wrong address, and they kicked in the wrong door. And they wound up killing a totally innocent woman. But this had nothing to do with race. The problem is not, as some commentators have alleged, that it’s not safe to be “sleeping while black.” The problem is that these no-knock raids are an obscenely dangerous way of enforcing despicably stupid laws. White people die under precisely these same circumstances, and very likely in greater numbers (I don’t have data specifically on no-knock raids, but we can assume that the ratio is probably conserved here).</p>
<p>Think about how crazy this policy is in a nation where gun ownership is so widespread. If someone kicks in your door in the middle of the night, and you’re a gun owner, of course you’re going to reach for your gun. That’s why you have a gun in the first place. The fact that people bearing down on you and your family out of the darkness might have yelled “police” (or might have not yelled “police”; it’s alleged in some of these cases that they don’t yell anything)—the fact that someone yells “police” isn’t necessarily convincing. Anyone can yell “police.” And, again, think of the psychology of this: If the police have the wrong house, and you know there is no reason on earth that real cops would take an interest in you, especially in the middle of the night, because you haven’t done anything (you’re not the guy running a meth lab)—and now you’re reaching for your gun in the dark—of course, someone is likely to get killed. This is not a racial issue. It’s a terrible policy.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, the process of police reform isn’t straightforward—and it is made massively more complicated by what’s happening now. Yes, we will be urging police reform in a very big way now, that much seems clear. But Roland Fryer <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w27324" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">has also shown</a> that investigations of the cops, in a climate where viral videos and racial politics are operating, have dramatic effects, many of which are negative.</p>
<p>He studied the aftermath of the investigations into police misconduct that followed the killings Freddie Gray, Michael Brown, and Lequan McDonald, and found that, for reasons that seem pretty easy to intuit, proactive police contact with civilians decreases drastically, sometimes by as much 100 percent, once these investigations get started. This is now called “The Ferguson Effect.” The police still answer 911 calls, but they don’t investigate suspicious activity in the same way. They don’t want to wind up on YouTube. And when they alter their behavior like this, homicides go up. Fryer estimates that the effects of these few investigations translated into 1000 extra homicides, and almost 40,000 more felonies, over the next 24 months in the US. And, of course, most of the victims of those crimes were black. One shudders to imagine the size of the Ferguson effect we’re about to see nationwide… I’m sure the morale among cops has never been lower. I think it’s almost guaranteed that cops by the thousands will be leaving the force. And it will be much more difficult to recruit good people.</p>
<p>Who is going to want to be a cop now? Who could be idealist about occupying that role in society? It seems to me that the population of people who will become cops now will be more or less indistinguishable from the population of people who become prison guards. I’m pretty sure there’s a difference there, and I think we’re likely to see that difference expressed in the future. It’s a grim picture, unless we do something very creative here.</p>
<p>So there’s a real question about how we can reform police departments, and get rid of bad cops, without negatively impacting the performance of good cops? That’s a riddle we have to solve—or at least we have to understand what the trade-offs are here.</p>
<p>Why is all of this happening now? Police killings of civilians have gone way down. And they are rare events. They are 1/10,000 level events, if measured by arrests. 1/50-60,000 level events if measured by police encounters. And the number of unarmed people who are killed is smaller still. Around 50 last year, again, more were white than black. And not all unarmed victims are innocent. Some get killed in the act of attacking the cops.  [<a href="https://www.arlnow.com/2015/05/19/breaking-officer-involved-shooting-in-buckingham/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>, <a href="https://www.5newsonline.com/article/news/local/outreach/back-to-school/officer-involved-shooting-in-adair-county-oklahoma/527-e8cdc435-dcd0-429c-962f-b2c82c22068e" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>, <a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/news/local/crime/article36802032.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EXAMPLE</a>]</p>
<p>Again, the data don’t tell a clean story, or the whole story. I see no reason to doubt that blacks get more attention from the cops—though, honestly, given the distribution of crime in our society, I don’t know what the alternative to that would be. And once the cops get involved, blacks are more likely to get roughed up, which is bad. But, again, it simply isn’t clear that racism is the cause. And contrary to everyone’s expectations, whites seem more likely to get killed by cops. Actually, one factor seems to be that whites are <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/pnas/116/32/15877.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">7 times more likely</a> to commit “suicide by cop” (and <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/nchs/data/nvsr/nvsr68/nvsr68_09-508.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">3 times more likely</a> to commit suicide generally). What’s going on there? Who knows?</p>
<p>There’s a lot we don’t understand about these data. But ask yourself, would our society seem less racist if the disparity ran the other way? Is less physical contact, but a greater likelihood of getting shot and killed a form of white privilege? Is a higher level of suicide by cop, and suicide generally, a form of white privilege? We have a problem here that, read either way, you can tell a starkly racist narrative.</p>
<p>We need ethical, professional policing, of course. But the places with the highest crime in our society need the most of it. Is there any doubt about that? In a city like Milwaukee, blacks are 12 times more likely to get murdered than whites [Not sure where I came by this number, probably a lecture or podcast. It appears the rate is closer to <a href="https://urbanmilwaukee.com/2015/01/12/gun-homicides-milwaukee-has-two-thirds-of-states-gun-killings/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">20 times more likely</a> and <a href="https://www.bu.edu/sph/2018/07/13/residential-segregation-associated-with-black-white-disparity-in-firearm-homicide-rates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">22 times more likely</a> in Wisconsin as a whole—SH], again, they are being killed by other African Americans, nearly 100 percent of the time. I think the lowest figure I’ve seen is 93 percent of the time. [As noted above, more recent data suggest that it’s closer to 90 percent]. What should the police do about this? And what are they likely to do now that our entire country has been convulsed over one horrific case of police misconduct?</p>
<p>We need to lower the temperature on this conversation, and many other conversations, and understand what is actually happening in our society.</p>
<p>But instead of doing this, we now have a whole generation of social activists who seem eager to play a game of chicken with the forces of chaos. Everything I said about the problem of inequality and the need for reform stands. But I think that what we are witnessing in our streets, and on social media, and even in the mainstream press, is a version of mass hysteria. And the next horrific video of a black person being killed by cops won’t be evidence to the contrary. And there will be <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2020/06/17/us/rayshard-brooks-atlanta-shooting-wednesday/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">another video</a>. There are 10 million arrests every year. There will always be another video.</p>
<p>And the media has turned these videos into a form of political pornography. And this has deranged us. We’re now unable to speak or even think about facts. The media has been poisoned by bad incentives, in this regard, and social media doubly so.</p>
<p>In the mainstream of this protest movement, it’s very common to hear that the only problem with what is happening in our streets, apart from what the cops are doing, is that some criminal behavior at the margins—a little bit of looting, a little bit of violence—has distracted us from an otherwise necessary and inspiring response to an epidemic of racism. Most people in the media have taken exactly this line. People like Anderson Cooper on CNN or the editorial page of the New York Times or public figures like President Obama or Vice President Biden. The most prominent liberal voices believe that the protests themselves make perfect moral and political sense, and that movements like Black Lives Matter are guaranteed to be on the right side of history. How could anyone who is concerned about inequality and injustice in our society see things any other way? How could anyone who isn’t himself racist not support Black Lives Matter?</p>
<p>But, of course, there’s a difference between slogans and reality. There’s a difference between the branding of a movement and its actual aims. And this can be genuinely confusing. That’s why propaganda works. For instance, many people assume there’s nothing wrong with ANTIFA, because this group of total maniacs has branded itself as “anti-fascist.” What could be wrong with being anti-fascist? Are you pro fascism?</p>
<p>There’s a similar problem with Black Lives Matter—though, happily, unlike ANTIFA, Black Lives Matter actually seems committed to peaceful protest, which is hugely important. So the problem I’m discussing is more ideological, and it’s much bigger than Black Lives Matter—though BLM is its most visible symbol of this movement. The wider issue is that we are in the midst of a public hysteria and moral panic. And it has been made possible by a near total unwillingness, particularly on the Left, among people who value their careers and their livelihoods and their reputations, and fear being hounded into oblivion online—this is nearly everyone left-of-center politically. People are simply refusing to speak honestly about the problem of race and racism in America.</p>
<p>We are making ourselves sick. We are damaging our society. And by protesting the wrong thing, even the slightly wrong thing, and unleashing an explosion of cynical criminality in the process—looting that doesn’t even have the pretense of protest—the Left is empowering Trump, whatever the polls currently show. And if we are worried about Trump’s authoritarian ambitions, as I think we really should be, this is important to understand. He recently had what looked like paramilitary troops guarding the White House. I don’t know if we found out who those guys actually were, but that was genuinely alarming. But how are Democrats calls to “abolish the police” going to play to half the country that just watched so many cities get looted? We have to vote Trump out of office and restore the integrity of our institutions. And we have to make the political case for major reforms to deal with the problem of inequality—a problem which affects the black community most of all.</p>
<p>We need police reform; we need criminal justice reform; we need tax reform; we need health care reform; we need environmental reform—we need all of these things and more. And to be just, these policies will need to reduce the inequality in our society. If we did this, African Americans would benefit, perhaps more than any other group. But it’s not at all clear that progress along these dimensions primarily entails us finding and eradicating more racism in our society.</p>
<p>Just ask yourself, what would real progress on the problem of racism look like? What would utter progress look like?</p>
<p>Here’s what I think it would look like: More and more people (and ultimately all people) would care less and less (and ultimately not at all) about race. As I’ve said before in various places, skin color would become like hair color in its political and moral significance—which is to say that it would have none.</p>
<p>Now, maybe you don’t agree with that aspiration. Maybe you think that tribalism based on skin color can’t be outgrown or shouldn’t be outgrown. Well, if you think that, I’m afraid I don’t know what to say to you. It’s not that there’s nothing to say, it’s just there is so much we disagree about, morally and politically, that I don’t know where to begin. So that debate, if it can even be had, will have to be left for another time.</p>
<p>For the purposes of this conversation, I have to assume that you agree with me about the goal here, which is to say that you share the hope that there will come a time where the color of a person’s skin really doesn’t matter. What would that be like?</p>
<p>Well, how many blondes got into Harvard this year? Does anyone know? What percentage of the police in San Diego are brunette? Do we have enough red heads in senior management in our Fortune 500 companies? No one is asking these questions, and there is a reason for that. No one cares. And we are right not to care.</p>
<p>Imagine a world in which people cared about hair color to the degree that we currently care—or seem to care, or imagine that others care, or allege that they secretly care—about skin color. Imagine a world in which discrimination by hair color was a thing, and it took centuries to overcome, and it remains a persistent source of private pain and public grievance throughout society, even where it no longer exists. What an insane misuse of human energy that would be. What an absolute catastrophe.</p>
<p>The analogy isn’t perfect, for a variety of reasons, but it’s good enough for us to understand what life would be like if the spell of racism and anti-racism were truly broken. The future we want is not one in which we have all become passionate anti-racists. It’s not a future in which we are forever on our guard against the slightest insult—the bad joke, the awkward compliment, the tweet that didn’t age well. We want to get to a world in which skin color and other superficial characteristics of a person become morally and politically irrelevant. And if you don’t agree with that, what did you think Martin Luther King Jr was talking about?</p>
<p>And, finally, if you’re on the Left and don’t agree with this vision of a post-racial future, please observe that the people who agree with you, the people who believe that there is no overcoming race, and that racial identity is indissoluble, and that skin color really matters and will always matter—these people are white supremacists and neo-Nazis and other total assholes. And these are also people I can’t figure out how to talk to, much less persuade.</p>
<p>So the question for the rest of us—those of us who want to build a world populated by human beings, merely—the question is, how do we get there? How does racial difference become uninteresting? Can it become uninteresting by more and more people taking a greater interest in it? Can it become uninteresting by becoming a permanent political identity? Can it become uninteresting by our having thousands of institutions whose funding (and, therefore, very survival) depends on it remaining interesting until the end of the world?</p>
<p>Can it become less significant by being granted more and more significance? By becoming a fetish, a sacred object, ringed on all sides by taboos? Can race become less significant if you can lose your reputation and even your livelihood, at any moment, by saying one wrong word about it?</p>
<p>I think these questions answer themselves. To outgrow our obsession with racial difference, we have outgrow our obsession with race. And you don’t do that by maintaining your obsession with it.</p>
<p>Now, you might agree with me about the goal and about how a post-racial society would seem, but you might disagree about the path to get there—the question of what to do next. In fact, one podcast listener wrote to me recently to say that while he accepted my notion of a post-racial future, he thinks it’s just far too soon to talk about putting racial politics behind us. He asked me to imagine just how absurd it would have been to tell Martin Luther King Jr, at the dawn of the civil rights movement, that the path beyond racism requires that he become less and less obsessed with race.</p>
<p>That seems like a fair point, but Coleman Hughes has drawn my attention to a string of MLK quotes that seem to be just as transcendent of racial identity politics as I’m hoping to be here. You can <a href="https://twitter.com/coldxman/status/1087593991976243200?lang=en" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">see these quotations</a> on his Twitter feed. None of those statements by King would make sense coming out of Black Lives Matter at the moment.</p>
<p>In any case, as I said, I think we are living in a very different time than Martin Luther King was. And what I see all around me is evidence of the fact that we were paying an intolerable price for confusion about racism, and social justice generally—and the importance of identity, generally—and this is happening in an environment where the path to success and power for historically disadvantaged groups isn’t generally barred by white racists who won’t vote for them, or hire them, or celebrate their achievements, or buy their products, and it isn’t generally barred by laws and policies and norms that are unfair. There is surely still some of that. But there must be less of it now than there ever was.</p>
<p>The real burden on the black community is the continued legacy of inequality—with respect to wealth, and education, and health, and social order—levels of crime, in particular, and resulting levels of incarceration, and single-parent families—and it seems very unlikely that these disparities, whatever their origin in the past, can be solved by focusing on problem of lingering racism, especially where it doesn’t exist. And the current problem of police violence seems a perfect case in point.</p>
<p>And yet now we’re inundated with messages from every well-intentioned company and organization singing from the same book of hymns. Black Lives Matter is everywhere. Of course, black lives matter. But the messaging of this movement about the reality of police violence is wrong, and it’s creating a public hysteria.</p>
<p>I just got a message from the American Association for the Advancement of Science talking about fear of the other. The quote from the email: “Left unchecked, racism, sexism, homophobia, and fear of the other can enter any organization or community – and destroy the foundations upon which we must build our future.” Ok, fine. But is that really the concern in the scientific community right now, “unchecked racism, sexism, and homophobia.” Is that really what ails science in the year 2020? I don’t think so.</p>
<p>I’ll tell you the fear of the other that does seem warranted, everywhere, right now. It’s the other who has rendered him or herself incapable of dialogue. It’s the other who will not listen to reason, who has no interest in facts, who can’t join a conversation that converges on the truth, because he knows in advance what the truth must be. We should fear the other who thinks that dogmatism and cognitive bias aren’t something to be corrected for, because they’re the very foundations of his epistemology.  We should fear the other who can’t distinguish activism from journalism or politics from science. Or worse, can make these distinctions, but refuses to. And we’re all capable of becoming this person. If only for minutes or hours at a time. And this is a bug in our operating system, not a feature. We have to continually correct for it.</p>
<p>One of the most shocking things that many of us learned when the Covid-19 pandemic was first landing on our shores, and we were weighing the pros and cons of closing the schools, was that for tens of millions of American kids, going to school represents the only guarantee of a decent meal on any given day. I’m pretty confident that most of the kids we’re talking about here aren’t white. And whatever you think about the opportunities in this country and whatever individual success stories you can call to mind, there is no question that some of us start on third base, or second base. Everyone has a lot to deal with, of course. Life is hard. But not everyone is a single mom, or single grandparent, struggling to raise kids in the inner city, all the while trying to keep them from getting murdered. The disparities in our society are absolutely heartbreaking and unacceptable. And we need to have a rational discussion about their actual causes and solutions.</p>
<p>We have to pull back from the brink here. And all we have with which to do that is conversation. And the only thing that makes conversation possible is an openness to evidence and arguments—a willingness to update one’s view of the world when better reasons are given. And that is an ongoing process, not a place we ever finally arrive.</p>
<p>Ok… Well, perhaps that was more of an exhortation than I intended, but it certainly felt like I needed to say it. I hope it was useful. And the conversations will continue on this podcast.</p>
<p>Stay safe, everyone.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>In this episode of the podcast, Sam discusses the recent social protests and civil unrest, in light of what we know about racism and police violence in America. This is a transcript of a recorded podcast. * * * Welcome to the Making Sense podcast… This is Sam Harris. OK…. Well, I’ve been trying to … <a href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/can-pull-back-brink/">Can We Pull Back From The Brink?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Porscha Pressler</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=1571161</id>
    <published>2020-06-18T21:59:09Z</published>
    <updated>2020-06-18T21:59:09Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Personal Note</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear Making Sense and Waking Up subscribers—</p>
<p>Those of you who have been listening to my podcast or following me on Twitter know that I’m quite worried about the emerging coronavirus pandemic. Barring some extraordinarily good luck, I believe that we have some very rough months ahead of us. Health concerns aside, it now seems inevitable that we will experience considerable economic uncertainty as a wave of illness disrupts normal life in a hundred countries simultaneously.</p>
<p>As you know, both the <a href="https://wakingup.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="https://wakingup.com/">Waking Up app</a> and the <a href="https://samharris.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="https://samharris.org/">Making Sense podcast</a> are subscription services. However, it has always been my policy that money should never be the reason why someone can’t get access to them. As we collectively respond to this global emergency, please know that if you can no longer afford a subscription to Waking Up or Making Sense, you need only send an email to <a href="mailto:support@wakingup.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="mailto:support@wakingup.com">support@wakingup.com</a> or <a href="mailto:support@samharris.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-cke-saved-href="mailto:support@samharris.org">support@samharris.org</a>, and you’ll receive a free account when your subscription expires.</p>
<p>I’m incredibly fortunate to have found work that I love to do, along with a community of people willing to support it—and I feel especially good knowing that I can be of use to many of you at a time like this. I’m also very happy that both Waking Up and Making Sense are supported by a wonderful team of employees and contractors who can work from home indefinitely.</p>
<p>So please don’t forget: The work we are doing is for you, whether you can pay for it or not. And don’t hesitate to be in touch if you need help.</p>
<p>Wishing you all health and happiness,</p>
<p>Sam</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">A Personal Note</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear Making Sense and Waking Up subscribers— Those of you who have been listening to my podcast or following me on Twitter know that I’m quite worried about the emerging coronavirus pandemic. Barring some extraordinarily good luck, I believe that we have some very rough months ahead of us. Health concerns aside, it now seems … <a href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/a-personal-note/">A Personal Note</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Mary Morrison</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=1570286</id>
    <published>2020-03-14T19:26:17Z</published>
    <updated>2020-03-14T19:26:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As many of you know, the Day of Reflection conference, scheduled for November 17 in NYC, has been cancelled, and some hundreds of ticket holders are now left seeking refunds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was forced to pull out of this event &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SamHarrisOrg/status/1043277230632132608"&gt;nearly two months ago&lt;/a&gt; and have said very little about it since. Now that Travis Pangburn has officially announced that he will be &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/PangburnInspire/status/1062431248205864962"&gt;“folding” his touring company&lt;/a&gt;, Pangburn Philosophy, I can give a brief account of what happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I participated in 10 events organized by Pangburn Philosophy between September 2017 and July 2018. I didn’t always approve of the way those events were staged or marketed, but all of them appeared to be successful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="2"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;However, after the cancellation of an August 2018 conference in Auckland, Pangburn seemed intent on running his business off a cliff. He owed a lot of money to several speakers at that point, in the form of unpaid fees and reimbursements. Most egregiously, he seemed less than fully committed to refunding ticket holders for the cancelled Auckland conference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="3"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At this point, I had two more dates on the calendar with Pangburn in 2018: a dialogue with Brian Greene in Toronto (September 5) and the Day of Reflection conference in New York (November 17). I kept my appointment in Toronto because I was contractually obligated to do so. I also didn’t want to do anything that would harm Pangburn’s ability to pay his mounting debts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="4"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After Toronto, however, it became clear that Pangburn could not be trusted to put his house in order. Facing a total lack of transparency, and realizing that Pangburn was using my ongoing association with him to book future speakers, I withdrew from the NYC conference on September 21 (as well as from a Vancouver conference scheduled for March 2019). Legally, I was able to do this because Pangburn was in breach of my speaking contract. Ethically, I had a far more compelling reason to back out: I couldn’t promote or participate in an event for which I believed other speakers were unlikely to get paid; nor could I continue to work with someone who still hadn’t given refunds to ticket holders for a conference that had been canceled more than a month before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="5"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;After I withdrew from the NYC conference, my management team asked Pangburn to give us the email addresses of all ticket holders so that we could notify them that I was no longer involved with the event. Pangburn refused to provide this information. However, he assured us that he would notify everyone himself. (I do not know whether he ever did.) He then stopped responding to our emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="6"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the time I pulled out of the NYC conference, I assumed that the revenue from ticket sales was still safely in the box office and that Pangburn would be obliged to issue refunds should the conference fail. That’s how things normally work, especially at a reputable venue like Lincoln Center. It hadn’t occurred to me that New York ticketholders might suffer the same fate as those in Auckland.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ol start="7"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was left with a legal and ethical puzzle that I could not solve. Again, I had no way to communicate with ticket holders directly, and discussing the chaos surrounding Pangburn on my podcast never seemed like an option. Several friends and colleagues still had events on the calendar with him, and I didn’t want to do anything to derail them. In addition, many speakers who were aware of my reasons for pulling out of the NYC conference were still signed on and seemed intent on making it work. I couldn’t see anything to do that wouldn’t risk creating further harms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Pangburn still owes several speakers (including me) an extraordinary amount of money, we were willing to participate in the NYC conference for free as recently as a few days ago, if he would have handed it over to us and stepped away. I have been told that this offer was made, and he declined it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find it appalling that so many people were needlessly harmed by the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy. I can assure you that every speaker associated with the NYC event will be much wiser when working with promoters in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Harris&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The post &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/"&gt;A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy&lt;/a&gt; appeared first on &lt;a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org"&gt;Sam Harris&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>As many of you know, the Day of Reflection conference, scheduled for November 17 in NYC, has been cancelled, and some hundreds of ticket holders are now left seeking refunds. I was forced to pull out of this event nearly two months ago and have said very little about it since. Now that Travis Pangburn has … <a href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/">Continued</a></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/thoughts-implosion-pangburn-philosophy/">A few thoughts on the implosion of Pangburn Philosophy</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Sam Harris</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=675963</id>
    <published>2018-11-16T15:36:59Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-16T15:36:59Z</updated>
    <category term="Announcements"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><iframe loading="lazy" class="youtube-player" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/h1oaSt60b0o?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-one/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night One)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=474318</id>
    <published>2018-09-04T20:00:04Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-04T20:00:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><iframe loading="lazy" class="youtube-player" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/m0-oC_49fq4?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org/sam-harris-jordan-peterson-vancouver-night-two/">Sam Harris &amp; Jordan Peterson in Vancouver (Night Two)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://samharris.org">Sam Harris</a>.</p>
</div>
    </summary>
    <id>https://samharris.org/?p=474326</id>
    <published>2018-09-04T19:30:31Z</published>
    <updated>2018-09-04T19:30:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorised"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evidence to House of Commons Sci Tech Select Committee on Research Integrity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/12/evidence-to-house-of-commons-sci-tech-select-committee-on-research-integrity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry not to be in regular blogging mode at the moment. Here’s a video of our evidence session to parliament, where they are running an inquiry into research integrity. I think clinical trials are the best possible way to approach this issue. Lots of things in “research integrity” are hard to capture in hard logical […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3498</id>
    <published>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</updated>
    <category term="alltrials campaign"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do the world’s biggest drug companies compare, in their transparency commitments?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/how-do-the-worlds-biggest-drug-companies-compare-in-their-transparency-commitments/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hereâ€™s a paper, and associated website, that we launch today: we have assessed, and then ranked, all the biggest drug companies in the world, to compare their public commitments on trials transparency. Regular readers will be familiar with this ongoing battle. In medicine we use the results of clinical trials to make informed treatments about […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3485</id>
    <published>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meaningful Transparency Commitments: the WHO Joint Statement from Trial Funders</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/meaningful-transparency-commitments-the-who-joint-statement-from-trial-funders/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By now I hope you all know about the ongoing global scandal of clinical trial results being left unpublished, and of course our AllTrials campaign. Doctors, researchers, and patients cannot make truly informed choices about which treatments work best if they don’t have access to all the trial results. Earlier this year, I helped out […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3481</id>
    <published>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/02/how-many-epidemiologists-does-it-take-to-change-a-lightbulb/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robin Ince just asked if I know any epidemiologist lightbulb jokes. I wrote this for him. How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb? Weâ€™ve found 12,000 switches hidden around the house. Some of them turn this lightbulb on, some of them donâ€™t; some of them only work sometimes; and some of them […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3472</id>
    <published>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“Transparency, Beyond Publication Bias”. A video of my super-speedy talk at IJE.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2016/10/transparency-beyond-publication-bias-a-video-of-my-super-speedy-talk-at-ije/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">People oftenÂ talk about “trials transparency” as if this means “all trials must be published in an academic journal”. In reality, true transparency goes much further than this. We need Clinical Study Reports, and individual patient data, of course. But we also need the consent forms, so we can see what patients were told. We need […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3463</id>
    <published>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
