<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-05-04T09:39:36Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>So this is how the semester ends</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/03/so-this-is-how-the-semester-ends/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I just finished my third zoom meeting of the day, and also buckled down and got all those lab reports graded, and then wrapped it all up by calculating my students’ tentative final grades. Tomorrow I’ll write up the optional final, which I expect only a few students will take, and then I’m done.</p>
<p>I gotta say, though, seeing that all the women in the country are being stripped of their reproductive rights did put it all in perspective, making my struggles relatively light work. It would have been nicer to see certain horrible people hauled off in chains, though — it’s hard to whistle while you work when the fascists are taking over, and even now I can’t feel much relief at the finish.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I just finished my third zoom meeting of the day, and also buckled down and got all those lab reports graded, and then wrapped it all up by calculating my students’ tentative final grades. Tomorrow I’ll write up the optional final, which I expect only a few students will take, and then I’m done. I […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66441</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T22:57:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T22:57:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everything everywhere all at once</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/03/everything-everywhere-all-at-once/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">This would be a good day to sit and seethe until I melt down into an angry little puddle, but unfortunately, today is also the last major hoorah of the semester. The lab reports are in, I just have to grade them, and I’ve also got three seminars I have to attend, and then I have to assemble all the grades into a final assessment for the students.</p>
<p>At least I’ve got lots of distractions, I guess.</p>
<p>(Oh, yeah, I also saw the movie with the same title as this post the other day, in a gap in my schedule as I was waiting for more assignments to flood in. It was very good, highly recommended, I want to go see it again.)</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This would be a good day to sit and seethe until I melt down into an angry little puddle, but unfortunately, today is also the last major hoorah of the semester. The lab reports are in, I just have to grade them, and I’ve also got three seminars I have to attend, and then I […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66439</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T14:02:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T14:02:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>George Carlin knew what was going on</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/03/george-carlin-knew-what-was-going-on/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/AvF1Q3UidWM" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66437</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T13:43:26Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T13:43:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Abortion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Supreme Court is broken</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/03/the-supreme-court-is-broken/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/slavegirlofgor.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/slavegirlofgor-91x150.jpeg" alt="" width="91" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-66435" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/slavegirlofgor-91x150.jpeg 91w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/slavegirlofgor.jpeg 175w" sizes="(max-width: 91px) 100vw, 91px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="lead"&gt;It&amp;#8217;s happening. The Supreme Court, packed with regressive assholes, intends to overthrow Roe v Wade and throw the country into chaos. A copy of &amp;#8220;Justice&amp;#8221; Samuel Alito&amp;#8217;s decision was leaked, and quotes from this terrible document are circulating on the internet, and we can see where Alito waxed poetic about his decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have wondered sometimes if a man, to be a man, must not master a woman and if a woman to be a woman must not know herself mastered.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;&lt;p&gt;No man who has seen a woman in Pleasure Silk, or watched her dance, or heard the sound of a belled ankle or watched a woman&amp;#8217;s hair, unbound, fall to her waist can long live without the possession of such a delicious creature.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is said, in a Gorean proverb, that a man, in his heart, desires freedom, and that a woman, in her belly, yearns for love. The collar, in its way, answers both needs. The man is most free, owning the slave. He may do what he wishes with her. The woman, on the other hand, being owned, is institutionally and helplessly subject, in her status as slave, to the submissions of love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it should only be added that the Gorean master, though often strict, is seldom cruel. The girl knows, if she pleases him, her lot will be an easy one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is one thing to own a woman, and it is another to have her within the bonds of an excellent mastery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, sorry. Those are quotes from John Norman&amp;#8217;s &lt;i&gt;Gor&lt;/i&gt; series, you know the fantasy novel where men enslave women and the women like it. I wonder if Alito has a basement stash of those horrible old books?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s what &lt;a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2022/05/02/supreme-court-abortion-draft-opinion-00029473"&gt;he actually wrote&lt;/a&gt;. The sentiment is similar, if not quite as openly expressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Alito’s draft ruling would overturn a decision by the New Orleans-based 5th Circuit Court of Appeals that found the Mississippi law ran afoul of Supreme Court precedent by seeking to effectively ban abortions before viability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roe’s “survey of history ranged from the constitutionally irrelevant to the plainly incorrect,” Alito continues, adding that its reasoning was “exceptionally weak,” and that the original decision has had “damaging consequences.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The inescapable conclusion is that a right to abortion is not deeply rooted in the Nation’s history and traditions,” Alito writes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm. Well. Roger B. Taney &amp;#8212; I mean, Slimy Sam Alito &amp;#8212; is right, you know. The oppression of women has a long history in this country &amp;#8212; after all, women only won the right to vote 100 years ago, with the ratification of the 19th amendment. Let&amp;#8217;s just roll all the progress acquired in the last century to something more like the era when women were chattel. Instead of recognizing that it takes roots a long time to grow, just rip them out now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, you know what else isn&amp;#8217;t deeply rooted in this country? Equal rights for black people. Using Alito&amp;#8217;s reasoning, one could argue that we should bring back slavery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don&amp;#8217;t worry. This decision won&amp;#8217;t strip away abortion rights in and of itself, it&amp;#8217;s just going to give state governments the right to do so. The Supreme Court will then sit back and smile benignly on every repressive measure the Republicans impose on their citizens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“The Constitution does not prohibit the citizens of each State from regulating or prohibiting abortion,” the draft concludes. “Roe and Casey arrogated that authority. We now overrule those decisions and return that authority to the people and their elected representatives.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well then, our elected representatives need to get to work and pass legislation to make abortion and health care a protected right. For once, I might agree with &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/politics/2022/05/02/roe-v-wade-supreme-court-draft-politico/"&gt;the old fossils of the Democratic party&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“If the report is accurate, the Supreme Court is poised to inflict the greatest restriction of rights in the past fifty years — not just on women but on all Americans,” read a joint statement from Senate Majority Leader Charles E. Schumer (D-N.Y.) and House Speaker Nancy Pelosi (D-Calif.). “… Several of these conservative Justices, who are in no way accountable to the American people, have lied to the U.S. Senate, ripped up the Constitution and defiled both precedent and the Supreme Court’s reputation — all at the expense of tens of millions of women who could soon be stripped of their bodily autonomy and the constitutional rights they’ve relied on for half a century.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I notice that they don&amp;#8217;t say what they&amp;#8217;re going to do about it, other than be outraged and send more fundraising letters to me. At least Bernie Sanders has the right idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;“Congress must pass legislation that codifies Roe v. Wade as the law of the land in this country NOW,” Sen. Bernie Sanders (I-Vt.) wrote on Twitter on Monday night, calling for an end to the Senate’s filibuster rule to enact such a bill with a simple majority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, a Democratic bill that would have done just that garnered only 46 votes in February, thanks to the opposition of Sen. Joe Manchin III (D-W.Va.) and the absences of several other Democrats.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the Republicans are more upset that anyone &lt;em&gt;dared&lt;/em&gt; to leak the decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;It’s impossible to overstate the earthquake this will cause inside the Court, in terms of the destruction of trust among the Justices and staff. This leak is the gravest, most unforgivable sin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; SCOTUSblog (@SCOTUSblog) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/SCOTUSblog/status/1521295411545260035?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 3, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Rep. Mike Johnson (R-La.) deemed it a “a shameless attempt to pressure justices into reversing their correct position that individual states can outlaw killing unborn babies.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sen. Tom Cotton (R-Ark.) called on the court and the Justice Department to “get to the bottom of this leak immediately using every investigative tool necessary.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, women will die because of this decision, but oh, dear, the decorum! The loss of trust!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poor guy. Who wants to break the news to him that our trust in the Supreme Court was broken a long time ago? The final straw was when Mitch McConnell decided to deny a nominee so that he could pack the court with the assholes we&amp;#8217;ve got there now. It&amp;#8217;s a politicized pigsty for the Right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be fair, though, obviously there are some citizens who approve of any decision to restrict the rights of &lt;em&gt;other&lt;/em&gt; women to get healthcare and abortions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A woman named Hannah, who declined to provide her last name, stood in the middle of First Street and prayed that the justices “would find resolve.” She said she was “very sad to see people cheering to kill our children” and “was praying that people’s hearts will be softened.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="creationist"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes,&amp;#8221; she said, &amp;#8220;we also wish to be free.&amp;#8221; She smiled. &amp;#8220;In every woman,&amp;#8221; she said, &amp;#8220;there is something of the Free Companion and something of the Slave Girl.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It’s happening. The Supreme Court, packed with regressive assholes, intends to overthrow Roe v Wade and throw the country into chaos. A copy of “Justice” Samuel Alito’s decision was leaked, and quotes from this terrible document are circulating on the internet, and we can see where Alito waxed poetic about his decision. I have wondered […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66434</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T12:44:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T12:44:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For explorer Bruce Parry, the journey home may be the hardest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5956/for-explorer-bruce-parry-the-journey-home-may-be-the-hardest#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-15.23.37.jpg" height="951" alt="Bruce Parry" width="1252" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sitting with Bruce Parry outside his new home in the Cambrian Mountains of Wales. Parry is an explorer in every sense of the word. Famous for his travels to far-flung places, it&amp;rsquo;s his latest, more personal journey that most interests and intrigues me. Why, several years ago, did he abandon his life of global adventure, disappear from our screens and leave his home in Ibiza to attempt the founding of an egalitarian community in the UK?&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve travelled through the winding roads of mid-Wales, down a long track to his secluded stone house, in order to find out. As we look out over hundreds of trees and listen to the gushing of a waterfall, he reflects on the life-changing events, beginning many years ago, that led him here.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Over the last two decades as a television presenter, Parry lived with indigenous groups for the BBC series &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt; and journeyed to the Amazon and Arctic to document the impacts of globalisation and climate change. He tells me that every tribal group he met was struggling due to &amp;ldquo;global events &amp;ndash; mostly globalisation and trade&amp;rdquo;. Loggers, miners and the meat industry were encroaching on formerly pristine habitat and ancestral homes. For Parry it was obvious that &amp;ldquo;the problem is us&amp;rdquo;. The impact of our lifestyles on places that are normally out of sight are &amp;ldquo;not abstract&amp;rdquo; to him, but a lived reality. When he fills his car with petrol, he says, the images of the tar sands are in his heart.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Having seen how our consumption is ravaging the natural world and the lives of people who still live in some harmony with it, Parry&amp;rsquo;s experiences also offered him some valuable insights into alternative ways of being. Whilst filming the first series of &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt; (broadcast in 2005) and living with the Babongo in Gabon, on the western coast of Africa, Parry took Iboga &amp;ndash; used by the tribe as a medicine &amp;ndash; and had extraordinary visions, &amp;ldquo;which were all about connecting to nature and being at one with the universe&amp;rdquo;. Afterwards, he sought out his friend, the doctor and broadcaster Chris van Tulleken, to explain the experience. &amp;ldquo;He said, &amp;lsquo;Bruce, you were just taking a drug. Stop being an idiot&amp;rsquo; . . . And so sure enough, I stuck that experience into the box called &amp;lsquo;Just taken a drug; doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean anything&amp;rsquo;, to get on with my life. Because that&amp;rsquo;s what we do.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The power of meditation and psychedelics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Years later Parry came across a TED talk by the neuroanatomist Jill Bolte Taylor called &amp;ldquo;My Stroke of Insight&amp;rdquo;. She describes how having a stroke in the left hemisphere of her brain, the side that many believe is highly proficient at logic and language, made her experience the most incredible revelations from the right side, which is more to do with the experience of the present moment, what Taylor describes as the &amp;ldquo;right here, right now&amp;rdquo;. She felt at one with the universe, connected to everything. Parry remembers listening to the talk and thinking &amp;ldquo;Fuck, that&amp;rsquo;s me . . . I&amp;rsquo;ve had that experience. Here&amp;rsquo;s a scientist and she&amp;rsquo;s got an explanation for it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While the exact nature of the left-right brain distinction is subject to debate, Parry believes that we&amp;rsquo;d feel more connected to our surroundings and each other if we spent more time using the right side of our brains. He thinks psychedelic substances, like Iboga, can help with this, as can other tools and practices: meditation, for example, or foraging, which calls for you to be totally present in the moment and responsive to surroundings.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Penan people of Borneo, the final group Parry met while filming &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt;, made a huge impression on him. The moment he encountered them, he felt that, of the 15 he had lived with over the course of four years, there was something completely different about this tribe. After further research, he realised that the Penan are one of the last surviving groups that still live as nomadic hunter-gatherers, within egalitarian structures. &amp;ldquo;For 95 per cent of our time on this planet we were in egalitarian communities,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s our most resilient state. I genuinely think there&amp;rsquo;s something for us to learn from that&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Parry was so taken by the Penan that he made an independent documentary about them, called &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tawai&lt;/span&gt; (released 2017). The title is the Penan&amp;rsquo;s word for their relationship with the forest. One Penan member explains, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like when I&amp;rsquo;m with my mother, every day I know I can rely on her to breastfeed me. That&amp;rsquo;s why I feel &lt;span class="s1"&gt;tawai&lt;/span&gt; about the forest. It&amp;rsquo;s a guarantee of life.&amp;rdquo; Another mentions planes and cars but says if they don&amp;rsquo;t last for ever then he doesn&amp;rsquo;t want them, because they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;not the same as the forest that we can have until the end of time&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Tragically, the Penan&amp;rsquo;s forest is being decimated. Parry is currently seeking funds for a new documentary, which he hopes will express his thinking on these issues more explicitly than in the past. But he&amp;rsquo;s also trying to put the Penan&amp;rsquo;s lessons into practice on a personal level.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Having spent much of his adult life travelling, Parry, now 52, doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel that he belongs to any particular place. However, this hasn&amp;rsquo;t stopped him from wanting to settle down. &amp;ldquo;I have a belief that finding a place is where our deeper contentment can lie. I know that the sooner I can put my roots in the better.&amp;rdquo; He sees value in &amp;ldquo;knowing that you&amp;rsquo;ll be buried somewhere, that you&amp;rsquo;ll be remembered as the ancestor of that place, that you&amp;rsquo;ll be nourishing the trees that feed the next generations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;From Ibiza to rural Wales&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Parry spent 10 blissful years living in a farmhouse in Ibiza. But, he tells me, he always knew it was a bubble. He yearned to live a life more aligned with his values: low-impact, low-consumption, more local, more connected to nature and other people. He felt a moral responsibility to speak out about these views, and realised they would have more legitimacy if he was speaking from his home country. &amp;ldquo;As a public voice, I have more sway in the UK.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But why build a community in this particular spot? Mid-Wales has long been a Mecca for people interested in green living, with alternative communities clustering near the town of Machynlleth, and Parry was initially drawn into its orbit by a foraging course. The course involved having tea in a remote stone house surrounded by woodland. Later, when he saw it was up for sale, he told the seller about his desire to use it as a base for some kind of egalitarian community. He didn&amp;rsquo;t have the funds to buy it at the time, but the owner said that if he wanted it, she would wait for him.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In 2018, he moved in. But this only opened up more questions. Initially, Parry was hoping to start a community with three women who were skilled foragers and crafts-people with deep ecological knowledge. &amp;ldquo;These amazing women will go for three months into the woods in Sweden with nothing other than the clothing that they&amp;rsquo;ve made, and nets they&amp;rsquo;ve made.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Unfortunately, their life together hit a stumbling block as soon as the women went to see the house. &amp;ldquo;They hated it. They said there were too many conifers and that there was lead in the river.&amp;rdquo; The water runs through a mine upstream. &amp;ldquo;But I also think it wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much the place, it was more that I&amp;rsquo;d jumped the gun ahead of the group and made the decision to buy it without them. Maybe it all fell apart because I made a power move.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a painful first lesson. &amp;ldquo;I was talking about an egalitarian, co-owned, shared space and then I went and decided where it is going to be &amp;ndash; that clearly killed it right from the start.&amp;rdquo; He&amp;rsquo;s currently talking to 15 people in nearby shared-living communities to produce a joint vision statement, with the ultimate goal of living together in the stone house. He wonders, however, if it might be better to sell and buy somewhere collectively, so the project isn&amp;rsquo;t influenced by his &amp;ldquo;founder energy&amp;rdquo; from the start.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Whilst living alone, he often has visitors to stay, and enjoys feeding them with food harvested from his polytunnel. He&amp;rsquo;s part of a nearby community garden project, and loves the house being full of friends, pickling and fermenting. But he admits looking out the window some days, seeing it &amp;ldquo;pissing it down&amp;rdquo;, and asking &amp;ldquo;Why did I choose here?&amp;rdquo; It appears that he hasn&amp;rsquo;t completely ruled out heading further afield.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Our explorer seems a little lost, yet his personal struggle resonates with the crossroads faced by our society. We know things can&amp;rsquo;t carry on as they are, in the face of mounting climate and ecological crises, but we don&amp;rsquo;t know how to transition into a different mode of living. Parry is famous for his bravery &amp;ndash; he&amp;rsquo;s run naked over a line of cattle, taken countless mind-altering drugs and survived perilous expeditions in the Arctic and the deep jungle &amp;ndash; but his current venture may be his most daring yet.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;He still believes it&amp;rsquo;s right for him &amp;ldquo;to retreat from all the madness going on outside&amp;rdquo; and to try out a different &amp;ldquo;fun, cool, interesting way of living that may be enticing to others&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a journey that demands moral courage. And while he might not have the map yet, his compass is set on the way ahead.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5956/for-explorer-bruce-parry-the-journey-home-may-be-the-hardest#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T09:39:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T09:39:06Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And the winners are…</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/02/and-the-winners-are/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway-300x225.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="225" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-66348" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway-300x225.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway-150x113.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway-768x576.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway-500x375.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/04/bookgiveaway.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">The <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/04/25/textbook-give-away/">first textbook giveaway</a> is settled. I’ll be sending a few books away as soon as I have addresses to send them to.</p>
<p>Set A, <i>Essential Cell Biology</i> and the wretched Behe book, goes to <strong>logicalcat</strong>, the EMT with aspirations.</p>
<p>Set B, <i>Essentials of Genetics</i> with the atrocious Jeanson garbage, goes to <strong>Eric</strong> on Patreon, who wants to be more up to date on plant hybridization.</p>
<p>Set C, <i>Neuroscience</i> plus Meyer’s narcissistic tome, goes to <strong>Crip Dyke</strong>, who wants to supplement their knowledge of psychology.</p>
<p>Those will go in the mail as soon as they <a href="mailto:pzmyers@gmail.com">email me an address</a>.</p>
<p>There are more books to go! I’ll post the next set tomorrow, so if you lost out, you’ve got another shot.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first textbook giveaway is settled. I’ll be sending a few books away as soon as I have addresses to send them to. Set A, Essential Cell Biology and the wretched Behe book, goes to logicalcat, the EMT with aspirations. Set B, Essentials of Genetics with the atrocious Jeanson garbage, goes to Eric on Patreon, […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66431</id>
    <published>2022-05-02T18:34:33Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-02T18:34:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Books"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/open-discussion-may-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978329</id>
    <published>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5954/book-review-video-games-violence-and-the-ethics-of-fantasy#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-14.44.36.jpg" height="678" alt="Video Games book" width="856" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m standing in an elevator in Zakhaev International Airport, Moscow. As I brace myself for the opening of the doors, my comrade stoically utters, &amp;ldquo;Remember, no Russian.&amp;rdquo; What follows is brutal slaughter. I light the place up with my fully automatic PKM light machine gun and the tourists flee in terror. With the airport in ruins, I casually stroll over the bodies. This is a simulated reality &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, to be specific. I was a bright-eyed 12-year-old boy at the time, enamoured of the violence. But does that make me sadistic? &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The debate over gaming and violence is often reinvigorated by a grisly crime. After the Columbine High School massacre in Colorado in 1999, the press famously, and without evidence, linked the perpetrators&amp;rsquo; actions to shooter games they had been known to play such as &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Doom&lt;/span&gt;. The issue recently hit the news in the UK after a 16-year-old shot his schoolmate: a court heard that that the boy&amp;rsquo;s playing of first-person shooter games was a &amp;ldquo;significant factor&amp;rdquo; in his &amp;ldquo;violent fantasies&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One might expect a book called &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to engage with the long-running debate around whether virtual violence increases aggression in players, or even the predisposition to kill. Instead, Christopher Bartel, Professor of Philosophy at Appalachian State University, turns his attention to the morality of the player, asking whether the fictitious nature of video games make them &amp;ldquo;okay to engage in&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;He surveys a variety of video games, examining in particular how a developer&amp;rsquo;s intentions can interact with those of the players. He notes that this may differ where the violence is contextualised, such as in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, where the non-playable characters (fictional people in the game) approve or disapprove of the players&amp;rsquo; conduct. &amp;ldquo;The use of honour as the basis for a moral system in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; subtly suggests what sort of choices the player ought to make,&amp;rdquo; writes Bartel. &amp;ldquo;The story of &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is &amp;ndash; as the name implies &amp;ndash; one of moral redemption.&amp;rdquo; In doing this, the developers have signalled their preference for their ideal, archetypal player.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;As may be evident, the &amp;ldquo;No Russian&amp;rdquo; mission in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a very different affair, and is now infamous: in order not to blow your cover as a spy, you are tasked with slaughtering an airport&amp;rsquo;s worth of innocent bystanders. But Bartel does not simply dismiss it as amoral. He argues that it highlights the ambiguities of warfare, which is never black and white: after all, many governments have carried out similarly &amp;ldquo;grey&amp;rdquo; missions. He also includes a striking thought-experiment related to his adaptation of the &amp;ldquo;gamer&amp;rsquo;s dilemma&amp;rdquo;, developed by philosopher Morgan Luck. Bartel points out that although &amp;ldquo;many players defend murder in video games as merely harmless fun because it causes no real-world harm, the exact same argument could be employed to defend paedophilia in video games with equal force&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is an intriguing, thought-provoking read. An academic title, it is still of interest to the general reader, although we are tested at times by dense passages of specialist vocabulary. It fails, however, to explore some key areas of the wider debate. As a child playing &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, I didn&amp;rsquo;t possess the critical thinking skills required to absorb any message about the ambiguities of war, yet Bartel appears not to make the distinction between gaming as a child and as an adult.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Ultimately, Bartel concludes that it isn&amp;rsquo;t as simple as saying that games are fictitious and thus have no moral implications. He proposes that we do more to understand why individual players are motivated to entertain immoral and violent fantasies. Yet he states that his aim is &amp;ldquo;not to condemn players for their actions; nor is it to defend or suggest any legislation regarding the sale or availability of games&amp;rdquo;. The reader is therefore left in doubt as to how his conclusions might apply to the world outside the game.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5954/book-review-video-games-violence-and-the-ethics-of-fantasy#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-28T09:47:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-28T09:47:04Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Antidepressants Work (Why You Can Ignore that Study Saying They Don’t)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/antidepressants-work-why-you-can-ignore-that-study-saying-they-dont/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Before we get started, I’ve set up an alternate channel where I’ll be posting more casual videos of my life, like hiking and playing with my dog and whatnot. If that interests you, please …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131449</id>
    <published>2022-04-27T15:19:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-27T15:19:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Playground for the soul</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5963/playground-for-the-soul#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/bZZTUqMo.jpeg" height="797" alt="How The Light Gets In festival" width="1417" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dreams and jeopardy. It&amp;rsquo;s an intriguing theme for a festival, but wholly in keeping with the ambitious and boundary-hopping spirit of &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;HowTheLightGetsIn&lt;/a&gt;, which will be welcoming guests to sample its smorgasbord of big ideas in early June this year. In part, it&amp;rsquo;s an acknowledgement of a historical moment: the summer of 2022. Things are starting to move again, the future is once more opening up, and yet, as the organisers put it, &amp;ldquo;we are faced once more with some of the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest questions, and are asking the world&amp;rsquo;s leading thinkers to help us solve them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Held on the banks of the River Wye, the festival attracting the kinds of people who want to engage with philosophical questions, outside of the ivory tower of academia. As its founder Hilary Lawson told us in a &lt;a href="/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture"&gt;recent interview&lt;/a&gt;, the festival aims to encourage debate between disciplines, and &amp;ldquo;change the way people think about what philosophy is.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Speakers this year include Nobel-prize winning physicist Roger Penrose, Pulitzer Prize winning journalist Andrea Elliott, best-selling author Yuval Noah Harari and trailblazing physicist and author Lisa Randall. The idea is to bring international philosophers at the top of their fields together with influential politicians, scientists and cultural figures. As philosophy partners of the festival, we&amp;rsquo;re delighted to also see a fair few New Humanist contributors in the lineup, including the writer and theoretician of desire Katherine Angel, philosopher Massimo Puggluci, journalist and feminist Minna Salami, and legendary biologist and honorary associate of the Rationalist Assocation, Richard Dawkins.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, New Humanist Editor Samira Shackle will be chairing a debate on &amp;ldquo;Necessity and Lies&amp;rdquo;, with the founder of the festival and philosopher Hilary Lawson, scientist Simon Baron-Cohen and alt-left thinker Rebecca Roache. Should we recognise that lying can be valuable, and sometimes necessary, for ourselves and those in power? Or is honesty not only essential in public life but vital in all aspects of our everyday life as well?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Jubilee Bank Holiday, and part of bringing the big ideas down to earth is to unwind and have some fun - hence the inclusion of comedy, art and music. It's why the festival bills itself as a "playground of the soul". The London Afrobeat Collective will be there, along with sequin-clad satirical performers Bourgeois and Maurice, &amp;ldquo;Essex Arab Girl Comedian&amp;rdquo; Esther Manito, and Groove Armada&amp;rsquo;s Tom Findlay on the decks - just some of the 450 speakers and performers, on 12 stages over the festival's four days. You can see the full programme &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/programme?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including events for children and young adults. As Socrates said, philosophy begins in wonder, and who is more awestruck than the young?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Started in a chapel, with a small attendance, in 2018, HowTheLightGetsIn has been something of an unexpected success. Yet why should it be a surprise that people want to engage in the fundamental questions around their own existence. We're all human, after all, and life is a wonderful, puzzling thing. After the inevitable hiatus of the pandemic, it feels right to come together to challenge and enrich our ideas about the world, to learn to dream again, while sounding a note of caution around the need for care and reflection: the "jeopardy" of this year's theme. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We hope to see you there, in Hay-on-Wye, on 2-5 June. New Humanist readers get a 20 per cent discount, with the promo code NEWHUMANIST20. Otherwise, for those who can&amp;rsquo;t attend in person, the festival will be streamed online.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for tickets to the event. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those of you who can't be with us in person, the festival will also be streaming online during the 2nd-5th June. Click &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/online?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="1"&gt;here &lt;/a&gt;for more information and to purchase online tickets to watch the festival livestream. Additionally, all the debates and talks from the festival will be gradually released online in the months following the festival on the &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/about-iai/introducing-the-iai?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="2"&gt;Institute of Art and Ideas&lt;/a&gt; online platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="3"&gt;IAI.TV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="4"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5963/playground-for-the-soul#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:16:29Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:16:29Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Does Shotspotter Help Cops Keep Us Safe?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/does-shotspotter-help-cops-keep-us-safe/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Last week I had an experience that was weirdly scary not in the moment I was in danger but hours later when I realized I had been in danger. I was in a car on …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131446</id>
    <published>2022-04-25T15:19:24Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-25T15:19:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In a word: "Immunise"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5952/in-a-word-immunise#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Two glass ampoules of cholera serum, Paris, France, 1916 (Wellcome Images / Wikimedia Commons)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Two_glass_ampoules_of_cholera.jpg" height="961" alt="cholera serum" width="1252" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The word &amp;ldquo;immunise&amp;rdquo; is a latecomer into English. The first known recorded use is in 1889 in a journal called &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Sanatorian.&lt;/span&gt; It noted that living organisms could be &amp;ldquo;immunized&amp;rdquo; through injection without tissue damage. This turning of the word &amp;ldquo;immune&amp;rdquo; into a verb may have come via the German verb &amp;ldquo;immunisieren&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The root of the word, however, is the Latin &amp;ldquo;immunis&amp;rdquo;, meaning exempt from taxation. &amp;ldquo;Munis&amp;rdquo; meant being ready for service, so with &amp;ldquo;im&amp;rdquo; in front of it, you were the opposite. As was often the case, the word was absorbed into Romance languages, taking the usual pathway into English via French.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;In the 15th century, you could talk of clergymen being &amp;ldquo;immune&amp;rdquo; from tithes (taxes). By 1440 it was already being used in a broader sense, with God being described as immune from fraud, meaning that he was free or clear of it. Over time the term began to be used more figuratively. In 1922, D. H. Lawrence wrote in his short story &amp;ldquo;England, my England&amp;rdquo;: &amp;ldquo;Among the graves, she was immune to the world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;As a medical term, the word is a keyhole into the history of a form of treatment that now dominates the airwaves. A 30 June 1866 article in the &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Lancet&lt;/span&gt; notes: &amp;ldquo;Mr Lee then goes on to say that the skin will in time become immune to other irritants as well.&amp;rdquo; Being immune as a result of an inoculation was first recorded in English in 1882, with the great Louis Pasteur credited with creating immunity to anthrax.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The Covid-19 virus has turned a lot of us, somewhat dangerously, into amateur medics talking in our living rooms about an &amp;ldquo;immune response&amp;rdquo; (first recorded in 1923), our &amp;ldquo;immune system&amp;rdquo; (1943), or an &amp;ldquo;immune deficiency&amp;rdquo; (1965). The phrase &amp;ldquo;herd immunity&amp;rdquo; first appeared in 1917, applied, as you might expect, to cattle. As the pandemic hit the UK in March 2020, I noted that three government scientists used the phrase on a single day on radio and TV, as did the journalist Robert Peston in the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; Spectator. &lt;/span&gt;By then, we had become the &amp;ldquo;herd&amp;rdquo;. However, the phrase &amp;ldquo;death rate&amp;rdquo; (1849) did not accompany it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5952/in-a-word-immunise#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-25T11:27:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-25T11:27:03Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Justice delayed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5961/justice-delayed#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Srebrenica Genocide Memorial, Srebrenica" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/43550402932_d583d51855_o.jpg" height="864" alt="Srebrenica&amp;ndash;Potočari Memorial and Cemetery for the Victims of the 1995 Genocide. Image: Mike Norton" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Journalist Ed Vulliamy once noted that &amp;ldquo;within 20 years of the liberation of Dachau&amp;hellip; the Beatles were playing Hamburg&amp;rdquo;. No such thawing of relations or moving-on has meaningfully taken place in the Balkan region. There is still an urgent need for reconciliation. Meanwhile, a whole generation have grown up in the long shadow of the war, hearing three rival nationalist narratives from respective governments. To this day, the government in Serbia refuses to recognise that the massacre of 8,000 Bosnia Muslim (or Bosniak) boys and men in the town of Srebrenica in 1992 constitutes genocide.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why has transitional justice proved so challenging in the Balkans? On the face of it, there seems to be progress. The final two criminal cases related to the Yugoslav wars were concluded last year by the international court in the Hague. However, the process of pursuing justice at a local level has largely stalled, with many cases yet to be heard. Meanwhile, nationalist politicians have sought to undermine the institutions of Bosnia and dismember the state. Still, there are people and organisations working to pursue transitional justice in the region, holding perpetrators to account and attempting a measure of reconciliation between groups on different sides of the conflicts. How can the region move on from the current reality of frozen conflict?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The first war crimes court since Nuremberg&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The reconciliation process had once been geared around the International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia, set up in 1993 by the UN to prosecute war crimes committed in the region. It later spread to the whole region, including Kosovo. The court operated for twenty-four years, indicting 161 people, conducting 111 trials, and convicting 90 people from all sides of the conflict &amp;ndash; including the first sitting head of a state to be indicted for war crimes, Slobodan Milosevic. In many ways it was ground-breaking. The first war crimes court to be established since the end of the Second World War, it issued important judgements on rape as a weapon of war.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;David Tolbert worked at the court on and off for nine years, starting as a senior legal officer. While many people looked back to the Nuremberg Trials as an antecedent, he feels that the ICTY was &amp;ldquo;the first of its kind&amp;rdquo;. He is positive about the record of the court, which indicted a larger number of people and accounted for all of them, when comparable efforts at justice in countries such as Rwanda and Cambodia have struggled. The prosecutors were facilitated by political will to make arrests and were also able to make links between some of the defendants where they had been working together to commit crimes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="The ICTY building, The Hague" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/ICTY_Building,_The_Hague.jpg" height="867" alt="ICTY building, The Hague" width="1417" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the court also faced challenges and attracted criticism from all sides. Securing the support of national governments was a significant block, especially early on. &amp;ldquo;In Serbia the cooperation was really difficult and also in Republic Srpska [the majority Serb areas in Bosnia],&amp;rdquo; says Tolbert, &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rsquo;s where we really needed political support from NATO and the NATO countries.&amp;rdquo; That support did come, with NATO troops making arrests and transferring a suspected war criminal to the ICTJ. Tolbert feels the court improved over time in terms of dealing with this political engagement and in helping make arrests. He noted that there was a &amp;ldquo;pretty big learning curve&amp;rdquo; for those involved to begin to understand the context, and then to create the mechanisms to make arrests and gather evidence, given that the ICTY was an international court and those involved mostly came from outside the region.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The court also made its own blunders. One of the most emotive was the loss of personal belongings of Srebrenica victims. Originally removed from mass grave sites in 1996-97, these items were destroyed in 2009 on the grounds they had started to decompose. They included documents and photos that could help identify the remains of victims. The convoluted and opaque system that allowed this to happen without the prior knowledge of victims&amp;rsquo; groups and families underlined the failures of trust and communication. The ICTY finally closed its doors in 2017, leaving a mixed legacy and a handful of cases to finish.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Failing survivors?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A year later, the Balkans Investigative Reporting Network (BIRN) published a report into the state of transitional justice in the region. &amp;ldquo;Accountability, truth and justice still seem more like ideals than reality,&amp;rdquo; the report said, going on to set out how prosecutions by national governments had fallen, regional cooperation had collapsed, and victims and survivors had been &amp;ldquo;betrayed&amp;rdquo;. For example, the report noted that while there had been 3,500 prosecutions in Croatia, just 119 were against Croatian soldiers, and their sentences were lower than for people from other ethnicities for the same categories of crimes. While the ICTY did set those ground-breaking precedents on rape as a weapon of war, a recent survey of survivors found a majority of survivors felt abandoned by the civil justice system because it is very difficult for them to claim compensation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The ICTY is now seen by many as a failure. Rather than bringing closure to victims, or paving the way for societal-level reconciliation, they see the court as having amplified the voices of wartime leaders. While many such leaders were prosecuted, their trials gave them the platform and space to pontificate and propagate their ultranationalist ideologies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most surreal example of this was the infamous suicide of Slobodan Praljak in the Hague court. A former Bosnian Croat general, Praljac had been found guilty of committing violations of the laws of war, crimes against humanity, and breaches of the Geneva Convention. On hearing the guilty verdict in 2017, he swallowed cyanide in the courtroom. The act somewhat grotesquely became an internet meme in the late 2010s to characterise an excessive emotional reaction to a situation ("excuse me while I drink my poison").&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The later acquittal of Serb leader Vojislav Seselj &amp;ndash; who had been charged with incitement of torture, murder, forcible deportations and persecution on religious and racial grounds, but was found to have had had no military &amp;ldquo;hierarchical responsibility&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; was for many anti-nationalist campaigners in the region the death knell of the ICTY&amp;rsquo;s legitimacy. Seselj received and was quickly rehabilitated by the Serbian political establishment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Vojislav Seselji on TV Kopernikus, 2018" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Snezana_Djordjevic_i_Vojislav_Seselj.jpg" height="900" alt="Vojislav &amp;Scaron;e&amp;scaron;elj" width="1600" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in the absence of meaningful and effective transitional justice in the region, society continues to be divided along ethnic lines. The starkest example is Bosnia, a multi-ethnic state of Bosniaks (or, as many prefer to be called, Bosnian Muslims), Croats and Serbs. While schools in the country nominally promote &amp;ldquo;democratic&amp;rdquo; values, in practice they are ethnically and linguistically segregated, meaning three very different versions of history are being taught. This not only reinforces those ethno-nationalist discourses, but has made it more challenging for those children and young people, to process the pasts and their sense of who they are and where they belong. Many of the Bosnia-wide institutions, such as public broadcasting and sports, that might have contributed to a sense of national unity beyond ethnic divides, have been undermined over the years by a persistent campaign from Serb and Croat separatists. Nor are the tensions confined to Bosnia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Transitional justice from the grassroots&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;What might the future hold for the region&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;frozen conflict&amp;rdquo;? Despite the failures of the ICTY and other &amp;ldquo;top-down&amp;rdquo; efforts, some remarkable people and organisations have stepped up at the grassroots. One of the earliest bodies to pursue transitional justice, the Humanitarian Law Centre, was founded in the early stages of the conflicts in 1992. The HLC has played a significant role in Balkan civil society over the last three decade, both tirelessly documenting the Milosevic-era war crimes and human rights violations committed in the 1992-1995 conflict, predominantly against Croats and Bosnian Muslims, and, simultaneously, collecting evidence &amp;ndash; with a view to both prosecutions and societal-level "truth-telling" &amp;ndash; of war crimes and human rights violations in the 1999 conflict in Kosovo.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;HLC&amp;rsquo;s work in Kosovo is crucial, as many other Serbian human rights organisations would still rather not engage in the country. The idea that "Kosovo is Serbia" still holds sway among sections of Serbian society steeped in the mythologised narrative of the 1389 Field of Blackbirds battle and glorified in the poetry of the nineteenth-century Serb Orthodox/ Montegrin poet Njegos, and the claim was arguably the most central tenet of Milosevic&amp;rsquo;s ultranationalist ideology, from whence all other racist and exclusivist positions emanated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;HLC&amp;rsquo;s founder, Natasha Kandic, has been the subject of dozens of lawsuits from Serbian public officials during the past 25 years as a result of her public criticism and work on Serbia&amp;rsquo;s war crimes, documenting atrocities committed in both 1992-1995 in Bosnia and Croatia, and 1999 in Kosovo. It was Kandic who provided what is considered the &amp;ldquo;smoking gun&amp;rdquo; for Serbia&amp;rsquo;s involvement in the Srebrenica Massacre: a video of Serbian soldiers from the Skorpions Unit executing six Bosnian Muslim prisoners. The video, presented as evidence to the ICTY, was also partially broadcast on Serbian and Bosnian TV. She continues to be a key figure across the human rights and transitional justice movement in the former Yugoslavia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kandic also spearheaded the RECOM initiative, which in 2008 initiated the creation of a regional &amp;ldquo;peace commission for the people&amp;rdquo;, focusing on documenting war crimes along with truth-telling and processing the past through public initiatives. The aim was that this documentation of war crimes committed by "all sides" in the 1990s would be used to secure prosecution. RECOM made significant breakthroughs, not only in presenting an alternative to the one-sided narratives and ultranationalist rhetoric of leading political parties in Bosnia, Croatia, and Serbia, but also in helping to mobilise and coordinate progressive and pro-human rights actors across all countries in the region.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;RECOM&amp;rsquo;s work spoke to the need articulated by anti-nationalist, feminist Croatian writer Slavenka Drakulic to bridge the chasm "between official history and collective memory", as a necessary stage of societal-level healing. Its work dovetailed with the Croatian-based initiative, Dokumenta, an organisation formed in 2004 with the aim of investigating and establishing truth so as to create a &amp;ldquo;sustainable peace by dealing with the past.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The emergence of these independent bodies in the late 2000s thus seemed to many progressive activists and academics in the region a tonic to the toxic legacies of the 1990s war that had begun to appear in the election of ultranationalists and the routine denial of facts (even when, as in the case of the 1995 genocide in Srebrenica, such facts had been established both in the ICTY and other international courts).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Both RECOM and Dokumenta speak to a need for shared narratives, whether these emerge through trials or through truth-telling. As Bosnian filmmaker Jasmila Zbanic illustrated through her 2010 film &lt;em&gt;For Those Who Can Tell No Tales&lt;/em&gt;, about what she calls the &amp;ldquo;endangered&amp;rdquo; memory of the Visegrad massacre, there is no justice without truth and no truth without justice. She recently won an Oscar for &lt;em&gt;Quo Vadis, Aida&lt;/em&gt; her exploration of collective memory and Srebrenica.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Still from the film " src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Quo_vadis__Aida_Film_Still_2.jpg" height="844" alt="Still from Quo Vadis, Aida" width="1500" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet, as RECOM representatives noted in an interview with us, these initiatives stand little chance of shifting from shared recognition of the facts to securing prosecutorial victories, in the face of the continued damage of ultranationalism in party politics. As they note: &amp;ldquo;Unfortunately, the situation in the region is very discouraging: number of war crime trials has been decreased; there are no indictments against high-ranked military and police officers; only judgments condemning members of other ethnic communities.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Learning from the past&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The tireless and painstaking work of documenting what actually happened during the conflict &amp;ndash; who did what to whom and when &amp;ndash; is both specific to the nature of the atrocities of the former Yugoslavia, and central to the development of what "transitional justice" as a whole can mean. Transitional justice, as a concept and practice, originally emerged out of the South American experiences of authoritarianism in the 1970s. The "right to know" emerged out of South America - and in particular Chile&amp;rsquo;s attempts to deal with the legacy of the Pinochet regime &amp;ndash; as the assertion by families that they, literally, had a right to know where "disappeared" loved ones were buried.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In practice, "transitional justice" quickly developed a binary. There was "truth and reconciliation" without prosecution on the one hand, such as the societal-level initiatives of post-apartheid South Africa. On the other hand, there was "prosecutorial justice",&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;such as the formal legal spaces of the ICTY and ICTR (the International Criminal Tribunal on Rwanda).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The last decade has seen a new "wave" of transitional justice in the wake of the 2011 Arab revolutions, and in fora such as the Tunisian Truth and Dignity Commission, a national organisation to process the authoritarian past of pre-2011 Tunisia. This new wave, and other national attempts to process the injustices of the past, owe the ICTY a debt of thanks for the paradigms they developed. However, is notable that those involved chose to combine the prosecutorial model of the ICTY with learning from South Africa&amp;rsquo;s reconciliatory experience of "processing the past". This suggests that it isn&amp;rsquo;t that the ICTY was a failure, but rather that it was "necessary but not sufficient" for the people of the region to gain closure from the horrors of the 1990s.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bodies like RECOM and Dokumenta are effective where they work in tandem with the "official" transitional justice processes, such as the work that was undertaken at the ICTY. As RECOM said to us: &amp;ldquo;The International Criminal Tribunal for the former Yugoslavia (ICTY) was crucial for judicially established facts that should serve as a basis for the establishment of the rule of law through domestic war crime trials. The RECOM Reconciliation Network as most trustworthy and credible actor of regional reconciliation is establishing a regional record of all the victims regardless of their ethnicity, despite the absence of political support&amp;rdquo;, using the ICTY judgments as the basis of their work.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In some sense, the greatest "victory" of the former Yugoslavia&amp;rsquo;s war-time victims in securing formal and structural change and recognition is a victory that has protected others who have suffered in subsequent conflicts &amp;ndash; that of UN Security Council Resolution 1325, which was adopted unanimously in 2000, and acknowledges the disproportionate and unique impact of armed conflict on women and girls, and provided the legal basis to prosecute war-time rape as a weapon of war. Securing Resolution 1325 remains an astonishing victory secured in large part through the work of Bosnian women's rights activists and NGOs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Prosecutions are important, particularly of senior leaders, military and political leaders, but I think a whole lot more needs to be done and that hasn&amp;rsquo;t happened,&amp;rdquo; says David Tolbert. &amp;ldquo;I would have wanted to have seen more transitional justice approaches.&amp;rdquo; Those could have included a truth commission, reparations, a lot of reforms, and political realignment. While he said there were discussions about a truth commission in Serbia, it was unclear whether they were serious. In the generation since the end of the wars of the former Yugoslavia, as Afghanistan and Iraq reformulated the concept of "humanitarian intervention" in the 2000s, and the Arab Revolutions and Euromaidan in Ukraine offered new modes and templates of how to "process the past" after an end of authoritarianism, the ICTY&amp;rsquo;s legacy, and the lessons it offers transitional justice processes that have followed it, remains a bridge &amp;ndash; towards justice, but not there yet.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5961/justice-delayed#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-22T17:03:01Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-22T17:03:01Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Bromeopathy: Tucker Carlson Wants to Roast Your Balls to Increase Testosterone</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/bromeopathy-tucker-carlson-wants-to-roast-your-balls-to-increase-testosterone/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Homeopathy: is there any pseudoscience that’s less based in reality, or less embarrassing for its adherents? I mean after all, it’s literally sugar water that quacks say “remembers” molecules that used to be in it …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=x6CsbKGUh7A:4KkhwLyFE_0:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131444</id>
    <published>2022-04-19T23:00:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-19T23:00:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Terrible “Study” that Says Liberal States Failed at COVID</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/the-terrible-study-that-says-liberal-states-failed-at-covid/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Way back in early 2020 as the pandemic was just beginning, I made a video in which I said that we may not know the full extent of the damage of COVID, and the true …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=uObQy7RKbl8:0knu_dcTtIg:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131442</id>
    <published>2022-04-18T16:53:26Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-18T16:53:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How the “Don’t Say Gay” Bill May INCREASE Child Grooming</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/how-the-dont-say-gay-bill-may-increase-child-grooming/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Over the past few weeks I’ve had a few requests from viewers to talk about the now-infamous “Don’t Say Gay” Bill that Ron DeSantis has just signed into law in the state of Florida. I’ve …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=XfqkZLkiC1M:TPObLxdGv9g:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131440</id>
    <published>2022-04-15T19:28:48Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-15T19:28:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/04/open-discussion-april-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978276</id>
    <published>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intolerance of Inquiry, Failures of Imagination</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/intolerance-of-inquiry-failures-of-imagination/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! A few days ago, Raif Badawi walked out of his prison cell.  A progressive Saudi writer, Badawi was arrested in 2012 on charges of “insulting Islam” and apostasy for daring to question religion and criticize the Saudi Arabian government through his website. The Center for Inquiry (CFI) …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978231</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VIDEO: Paul Offit on Medical Risk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/video-paul-offit-on-medical-risk/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We live in an unprecedented age of medical marvels, but success never comes free. In his third appearance on Skeptical Inquirer Presents, renowned virologist Paul Offit discussed the ideas behind his new book You Bet Your Life, explaining that the path to each medical advancement is paved with failures and risk.  “I wrote this book knowing …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978225</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dreaming of Mars and the Aliens Who Aren’t There</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/dreaming-of-mars-and-the-aliens-who-arent-there/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no evidence that Earth has ever been visited by extraterrestrials, yet many people are firmly convinced that aliens are among us. A team of researchers at California State University, Fresno, led by psychologist Matthew J. Sharps, set out to understand the psychological traits that influence a person’s beliefs about alien visitations and abductions. …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978223</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
