<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-05-07T17:34:23Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>A little too true to be funny</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/07/a-little-too-true-to-be-funny/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Hey! I was hit by that same truck!</p>
<div id="attachment_66475" style="width: 438px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/theoldagetruck.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/theoldagetruck.png" alt="" width="428" height="552" class="size-full wp-image-66475" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/theoldagetruck.png 428w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/theoldagetruck-116x150.png 116w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/theoldagetruck-233x300.png 233w" sizes="(max-width: 428px) 100vw, 428px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.thefarside.com/2022/05/07/1">The Far Side</a></p></div>
<p>How come that driver still has his license?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hey! I was hit by that same truck! How come that driver still has his license?</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66474</id>
    <published>2022-05-07T12:36:18Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-07T12:36:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Time to Re-Open…</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/a-time-to-re-open/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I started tweeting about this a little bit ago, but I now realize it might be enough thinking to be its own post. On Monday I was invited to give a talk, hosted by some old friends and new collaborators. On the way there, I was thinking about what I would talk about and looking …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=HdSQSoh8T8Y:BHZJ9Gn5rIQ:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131473</id>
    <published>2022-05-06T20:33:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-06T20:33:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Activism"/>
    <category term="Feminism"/>
    <category term="Life Style"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What do scientists do over summer break?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/06/what-do-scientists-do-over-summer-break/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Well, today Mary and I scrubbed up the genetics lab all morning, I cleaned out a lot of fly bottles and emptied the incubator, and now those bottles are sitting in the autoclave getting a super-sauna. The lab is now mostly sparkling clean and ready for the next class in the Fall!</p>
<p>This is what I get paid to do, and what my degree qualified me for. Mary, unfortunately, doesn’t get paid, although she too has an advanced degree, and helped out so I wouldn’t have to spend all day in the nasty drudgery. So many dead flies and pupae!</p>
<div id="attachment_66472" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab-500x334.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="334" class="size-large wp-image-66472" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab-500x334.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab-150x100.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/spookylab.jpeg 640w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text">This is exactly what it looked like, <em>after</em> we got done cleaning it.</p></div>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Well, today Mary and I scrubbed up the genetics lab all morning, I cleaned out a lot of fly bottles and emptied the incubator, and now those bottles are sitting in the autoclave getting a super-sauna. The lab is now mostly sparkling clean and ready for the next class in the Fall! This is what […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66471</id>
    <published>2022-05-06T17:01:45Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-06T17:01:45Z</updated>
    <category term="My classes"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A Dreamy Tour of Monterey Bay Aquarium</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/a-dreamy-tour-of-monterey-bay-aquarium/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Good news, everyone! I’ve launched an alternate YouTube channel where I’ll be posting more casual videos about my hobbies, pets, plants, travels, and whatever else I happen to be doing. If you prefer my usual scripted science videos, don’t worry! I’ll continue my usual two videos per week. But I do hope you like this …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=G2-do4xFopY:7OR9hbAOhbw:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131470</id>
    <published>2022-05-06T16:24:01Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-06T16:24:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Friday Cephalopod: Time to FIGHT</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/06/friday-cephalopod-time-to-fight/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Even the peaceful octopus knows that sometimes you have to do battle.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle-500x328.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="328" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66469" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle-500x328.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle-150x98.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle-300x197.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/octobattle.jpeg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even the peaceful octopus knows that sometimes you have to do battle.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66468</id>
    <published>2022-05-06T12:55:12Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-06T12:55:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Cephalopods"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No, I’m not done!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/05/no-im-not-done/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I got out of the house to celebrate the end of the semester yesterday, but it was <em>slightly</em> premature. Next week is finals week. I have to slap myself to attention and buckle down and write the genetics final and post it on Canvas.</p>
<p>It shouldn’t be too bad. I’m planning to take full advantage of the Canvas autograder, so I mainly have to invest time this morning in setting up the problems with discrete answers and plugging the answer key into the software, and then grading next week will mainly involve updating the grade sheet.</p>
<p>I slept in until 7am this morning! The stress is fading already!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I got out of the house to celebrate the end of the semester yesterday, but it was slightly premature. Next week is finals week. I have to slap myself to attention and buckle down and write the genetics final and post it on Canvas. It shouldn’t be too bad. I’m planning to take full advantage […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66466</id>
    <published>2022-05-05T14:42:45Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-05T14:42:45Z</updated>
    <category term="My classes"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I knew the place was missing something</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/05/05/i-knew-the-place-was-missing-something/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Our lack has been filled. <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/iris/2022/05/03/the-abattoir/">Iris has opened a Freethoughtblogs Abbatoir</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Here, we perform extractions of lifesaving organs–whether people consent to them or not!</p>
<p>Don’t worry! The Abattoir does not harvest organs from just anyone, willy-nilly. That would be morally reprehensible, barbaric, and inhumane. You see, all of our involuntary organ donors meet one, and only one, very specific criteria: they would eagerly and happily force other people to donate lifesaving organs  without the donor’s consent. And these donors do so with absolutely no regard for the harm this may cause, whether physically, psychologically or financially. Since all of The Abattoir’s donors feel so very strongly about this particular principle, it is only just and fair that they live by it!</p></blockquote>
<p>She has a few photos of the place, I think prior to the actual opening. Once the site gets going, it’s going to be significantly less tidy, and things will get blood-drenched quickly.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/abattoir.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/abattoir-500x397.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="397" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66464" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/abattoir.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/abattoir-150x119.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/05/abattoir-300x238.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Uh-oh. Do we have a Freethoughtblogs Laundry? No, we do not. Do we have a Freethoughtblogs Autoclave? Nope. I’m not in any hurry to open one, I think we can satisfy our donors with reassurances that it’s somewhat cleaner than a back alley.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our lack has been filled. Iris has opened a Freethoughtblogs Abbatoir. Here, we perform extractions of lifesaving organs–whether people consent to them or not! Don’t worry! The Abattoir does not harvest organs from just anyone, willy-nilly. That would be morally reprehensible, barbaric, and inhumane. You see, all of our involuntary organ donors meet one, and […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66463</id>
    <published>2022-05-05T14:18:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-05T14:18:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Abortion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: What Strange Paradise</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5955/book-review-what-strange-paradise#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-15.01.46.jpg" height="758" alt="What strange paradise" width="942" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;Along the far end of the port of Lesbos, I watch two Afghan boys push battered mountain bikes against a wind that drives in from the water, past a military vessel emblazoned with an EU flag. Farther out at sea, the forms of violence &amp;ndash; from the elements or at the hands of those commanding such vessels &amp;ndash; being delivered to others like these boys are difficult to think about. Yet it is into just such a world that Omar El Akkad draws us. &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Set on an unnamed Aegean island, as well as in Egypt and on the fickle waters in between, &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;What Strange Paradise&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; traces the journey of a young Syrian boy across the Mediterranean to Europe. Nine-year-old Amir inadvertently finds himself aboard a smuggler&amp;rsquo;s rickety vessel in Alexandria whose wreckage is ultimately washed up on a European beach. The novel is structured into interlacing chapters of before and after, which recount Amir&amp;rsquo;s hazardous passage and the similarly perilous adventure following his arrival.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Central to the latter is the novel&amp;rsquo;s other key protagonist, the teenage Vanna: a second-generation northern European migrant whose family owns a failed guesthouse on the tourist-laden island. It is Vanna who first encounters Amir after his apparent brush with death. She becomes his accomplice in a mission to deliver him from the hands of the local police and asylum system to the mainland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;It is a Manichean world of azure sunlit beaches and blackened nights on a tormenting sea, where those seeking safety are ruthlessly exploited by smugglers and then rounded up at gunpoint by the authorities on arrival. Yet it is illuminated by individual acts of solidarity and heroism. El Akkad&amp;rsquo;s portrait of contemporary asylum-seeking &amp;ndash; its violence, mercilessness and tedium, relieved by flashes of altruism &amp;ndash; gives the uninitiated vivid insight into the realities of what is commonly called the EU&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;migrant crisis&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Indeed, the opening passage in which Amir&amp;rsquo;s small body lies prostrate in the sand is an obvious reanimation of the image of the Kurdish toddler Alan Kurdi, whose tiny corpse unleashed a tide of global attention when it appeared in 2015. Yet El Akkad simultaneously plays with the boundaries of social realism, stretching them such that the story takes on a fable-like hue. It is unsurprising then that the author expresses a love of alchemy in writing, describing the book as a repurposing of the tale of Peter Pan: Vanna the young Wendy on the threshold of adulthood and escapism, and Captain Hook manifest in the novel&amp;rsquo;s steely Colonel Kethros, who, with his amputated leg, doggedly pursues the two children across the island.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The novel is thus also distinctly cinematic, populated by archetypes (the villainous smuggler, the conflicted young officer, the maternal Muslim woman) and driven by fast-paced action and pithy dialogue. At times, this dynamic can feel on the verge of trite. Kethros suffers from PTSD from military service in the Balkans, but this background of trauma is underdeveloped, while the fable-like simplicity in parts of the novel sits at odds with the nuances of its realism elsewhere, such as Vanna&amp;rsquo;s complex relationship with her distant mother. Nonetheless, the novel is interwoven with truths of such universal resonance, told with poignancy, that the reader often pauses between lines. Most resonant is El Akkad&amp;rsquo;s characterisation of the human relationship to place and to those perceived as outsiders. Vanna&amp;rsquo;s body, for example &amp;ndash; with its white skin, blue eyes and blond hair &amp;ndash; speaks to Amir of &amp;ldquo;luxury, betterment, possibility&amp;rdquo;. The novel explores how her Aryan body is dealt with differently to the dark-skinned migrants, many of them destined for the sea floor, among the &amp;ldquo;million interlocking bodies who&amp;rsquo;d braved this passage before&amp;hellip; and come to rest at the bottom, sick with the secrets of their own unallowed mourning.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The novel holds a mirror to the absurdity and cruelty of the EU migration system, while framing events in Europe against the vaster scale of disaster around the globe. As such, it is a meditation on human behaviour when pressed to its extremes: a study of universal relevance in which El Akkad weaves his tales while playing many roles, as Scheherazade does in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;One Thousand and One Nights&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;: raconteur, provocateur &amp;ndash; and, ultimately, jurist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5955/book-review-what-strange-paradise#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-05T10:27:31Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-05T10:27:31Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do we warn future generations about our toxic waste?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5958/how-do-we-warn-future-generations-about-our-toxic-waste#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-16.16.58.jpg" height="811" alt="Martin Rowson illustration" width="1252" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;With the world edging towards climate catastrophe, it is small wonder that many countries are once again looking at nuclear power. The reason is obvious: a plentiful source of energy with no direct CO2 emissions provides a clear route to helping the world reach its emissions targets.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;It is not without serious risks, of course, as the Chernobyl and Three Mile Island meltdowns demonstrate. But to focus only on present-day dangers is to miss the larger problem, for nuclear waste remains radioactive for at least 10,000 years. And because we can&amp;rsquo;t simply banish it from this earth by blasting it into space, where it might contaminate the atmosphere, we have to store it somewhere, to be left undisturbed. That raises the question of how we tell people, ten millennia from now, where we&amp;rsquo;ve put it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Speaking to the future is a &amp;ldquo;blind spot&amp;rdquo; for humans, says Vincent Ialenti, a cultural anthropologist at the University of Southern California and The Berggruen Institute, and author of &lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Deep Time Reckoning: How Future Thinking Can Help Earth Now&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &amp;ldquo;We have ancient brains, and are focused on shorter time spans, like 24-hour news cycles or quarterly earnings. Many of us, through social media, are even stuck in fast-paced, dopamine-modulating information echo chambers.&amp;rdquo; If this short-termism makes thinking about the future hard, then the prospect of communicating with someone 10,000 years from now likely feels far beyond our capacities.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;One issue is the language we would communicate in: there&amp;rsquo;s no guarantee that English, Spanish or Mandarin will exist long into the future. &amp;ldquo;Languages evolve faster than that, or they die out,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti explains. &amp;ldquo;Try reading &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Beowulf&lt;/span&gt; in Old English. That was only written down about 1,000 years ago, in an earlier form of the same language we&amp;rsquo;re speaking now. And it&amp;rsquo;s incomprehensible.&amp;rdquo; Even more so, perhaps, think how little the word &amp;ldquo;internet&amp;rdquo; would mean even to someone living in the 1970s.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Pictures are out of the question, too. &amp;ldquo;Take a skull and crossbones,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti says, widely used to indicate poisonous substances. &amp;ldquo;In some cultural settings, that means rebirth. In others, it means death. In others, it just means pirates. So, what&amp;rsquo;s it going to mean in the future? Signage can change as fast as language. Before the Second World War, the swastika had a totally different meaning.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t know whether past civilisations tried to speak to us in the present. What we do know is that if they did, their efforts were not immediately discernable. This could either be through misunderstanding or simply a tendency to dismiss the knowledge of our ancestors, rather than embracing their wisdom. &amp;ldquo;There are oral stories about lost islands and ancient sea rises in Australia, passed down for 10,000 or so years by Aboriginal Australians, that have been corroborated by climate research,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti says. &amp;ldquo;And guess what? The colonial administrators didn&amp;rsquo;t listen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;&amp;lsquo;Satan&amp;rsquo;s work in England&amp;rsquo;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;There are other instances, too. &amp;ldquo;Along the coast of Japan, there are centuries-old &amp;lsquo;tsunami stone&amp;rsquo; slabs that read &amp;lsquo;High dwellings are the peace and harmony of our descendants. Remember the calamity of the great tsunamis. Do not build any homes below this point&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo; Yet a nuclear plant was still built in a tsunami zone in coastal Fukushima, and these messages were only left a few hundred years ago &amp;ndash; barely 5 per cent of the timespan a nuclear waste warning would need to last.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This poses another issue: the durability of the message itself. Weathering has made stone tablets and ceramics as little as 1,000 years old indecipherable, while the metals that are most likely to survive exposure to wind and rain, such as gold and silver, are also the ones most likely to be stolen. In the 1990s, Sandia National Laboratories &amp;ndash; tasked with investigating safe methods of disposing of the United States&amp;rsquo; nuclear waste &amp;ndash; attempted to solve this problem by devising large monoliths as a warning, suggesting the US government build &amp;ldquo;menacing earthworks&amp;rdquo; or a &amp;ldquo;landscape of thorns&amp;rdquo; with concrete spikes designed to give a sense of fear and foreboding.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Yet these more abstract messages don&amp;rsquo;t always work either. &amp;ldquo;Look at Stonehenge,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti says, citing archaeologist Rosemary Joyce&amp;rsquo;s book &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;The Future of Nuclear Waste&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;In 1599, the poet Samuel Daniel described it as a &amp;lsquo;huge, dumb heap&amp;rsquo;. One hundred years later, Isaac Newton believed it was an antecedent of Solomon&amp;rsquo;s Temple. In the early 19th century, William Blake called it &amp;lsquo;Satan&amp;rsquo;s work in England&amp;rsquo;. Today, you have the UNESCO World Heritage perspective. We have to be cautious: a monument doesn&amp;rsquo;t project the same meaning throughout eternity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Such challenges mean that many countries have simply decided to avoid the problem of future warnings altogether. In Finland, experts concluded it could be more strategic to avoid building monuments to warn future generations about its Onkalo waste repository, due to become operational sometime in the mid-2020s. &amp;ldquo;The Finns didn&amp;rsquo;t do any of those imposing American constructions,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti says. &amp;ldquo;They plan to put their nuclear waste repository on a resource-poor islet in Western Finland, backfill it, not mark it, and try to intentionally forget about it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;And yet, given the scale of the problem when it comes to communicating with the future, it&amp;rsquo;s small wonder the dilemma posed by nuclear waste has encouraged scholars to think outside the box &amp;ndash; perhaps, it might be argued, a little too far outside.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Myth, ritual &amp;ndash; and radioactive cats&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;In 1980, the US government assembled a panel of experts to talk to the future. Since the Second World War, nuclear waste from reactors had been amassing around the world. It was buried underground or otherwise disposed of at the bottom of the sea, presenting an invisible and deadly threat of radiation poisoning to anyone nearby.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The panel, named the Human Interference Taskforce, included an archaeologist, a psychologist, a long-term climatologist and experts in verbal and non-verbal communication. It was tasked with finding ways to warn people millennia from now of the waste, and to prevent them from accessing it. In 1984 the taskforce reported back. Their solutions were, to put it mildly, imaginative. &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;One of the taskforce&amp;rsquo;s most prominent members was linguist Thomas Sebeok, a specialist in non-human communication. In addition to his contributions to the official report, he also wrote an independent report in 1984, &amp;ldquo;Communication Measures To Bridge Ten Millennia&amp;rdquo;, which considered messages that had successfully survived across thousands of years, from folklore, legend and religion. He proposed keeping the uninitiated away from nuclear repositories through creating false narratives, drawing on the tools of myth and ritual. These secrets would then be entrusted to a select group of experts. &amp;ldquo;A ritual annually renewed can be foreseen,&amp;rdquo; Sebeok wrote, &amp;ldquo;with the legend retold year-by-year (with, presumably, slight variations). The actual &amp;lsquo;truth&amp;rsquo; would be entrusted exclusively to &amp;ndash; what we might call for dramatic emphasis &amp;ndash; an &amp;lsquo;atomic priesthood&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There were major problems with the idea, Sebeok admitted: first, no culture in human history had ever attempted such a massive con as creating a fake, government-sponsored religion to scare off trespassers. It would also create a ruling class, further fragmenting human society between those with knowledge and those without. And, finally, the only examples where false narratives had been spread &amp;ndash; such as the idea of a curse to protect Pharoah burial sites in Egypt &amp;ndash; had either been completely ignored or served as encouragement to tomb raiders. &amp;ldquo;I can see an archaeologist being like, okay, [a curse] makes it ten times more interesting!&amp;rdquo; jokes Ialenti. &amp;ldquo;Sometimes frightening aesthetics just draw people in even more. I mean, people listen to heavy metal music all the time, right?&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sebeok&amp;rsquo;s idea was included in a poll of alternative ways to communicate messages about nuclear waste storage, published in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Zeitschrift f&amp;uuml;r Semiotik&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Journal of Semiotics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;). Also featured were two other concepts that deserve special mention.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The first was from semioticians Fran&amp;ccedil;oise Bastide and Paolo Fabbri, who proposed deliberately forgetting the locations to prevent a disparity of knowledge in society. Instead, they advocated creating a biological marker to detect &amp;ndash; and avoid &amp;ndash; radiation. Cats, the duo argued, had been domesticated by humans for thousands of years but had no discernible purpose. Bastide and Fabbri advocated selectively breeding cats so that their skin changed colour when in contact with radiation, thereby serving as a warning to humans to leave.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;Such an animal species should dwell within the ecological niche of humans,&amp;rdquo; the duo wrote, &amp;ldquo;and its role as a detector of radiation should be anchored in cultural tradition by introducing a suitable name (for example &amp;lsquo;ray cat&amp;rsquo;) and suitable proverbs and myths.&amp;rdquo; Sadly, the ability to breed Geiger-counter felines does not exist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Captain Picard's flute&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;The final idea of note was by Polish science fiction writer Stanisław Lem, the author of &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Solaris&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. At first, he suggested creating &amp;ldquo;information plants&amp;rdquo;, grown near atomic sites, whose DNA code could be deciphered to reveal the dangers present. But this idea was convoluted &amp;ndash; it assumed adventurers would sequence the plants&amp;rsquo; genetic code, or that they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t cross-fertilise and spread beyond the initial area. Lem&amp;rsquo;s second idea was far simpler: to create satellites that could orbit the Earth, transmitting stored information. In effect, he was proposing to create an external hard drive for the planet, backing up human knowledge in case of disaster, such as a nuclear war.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;This idea of a &amp;ldquo;back up&amp;rdquo; is already being explored. It&amp;rsquo;s inspired science fiction, such as &amp;ldquo;The Inner Light&amp;rdquo; featured in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Star Trek: The Next Generation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, where a probe sent from a dying world fires an energy beam that strikes Captain Picard, transmitting to him the memories of a person&amp;rsquo;s life. Far from having ill intent, the probe is simply a message into the future, hoping that a long-destroyed culture is remembered. Through Picard, something as simple as how to play a flute was preserved.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s this kind of legacy that the Arch Mission Foundation, a US non-profit hoping to preserve human knowledge, is aiming to deliver. &amp;ldquo;There are a lot of risks outside of our control on our planet: nuclear threats, biological threats, pandemics and the dangers of misinformation,&amp;rdquo; explains Matthew Hoerl, the organisation&amp;rsquo;s co-founder and executive director. &amp;ldquo;But there&amp;rsquo;s no comprehensive backup for our knowledge &amp;ndash; it all exists on flash drives, hard drives or the cloud. If something were to happen, it would be gone like that. And we feel it&amp;rsquo;s important to record our existence for the future.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The project has already gone extra-terrestrial in its efforts to create an archive for humanity: in 2019, it sent its Lunar Library to the Moon on board an Israeli lander, with a complete copy of the English &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/span&gt;, photos, relics and a vault of the secrets to magician David Copperfield&amp;rsquo;s tricks, stored on optical data discs.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t answer the most important question: how do you make sure your message survives? &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s no guarantee it can,&amp;rdquo; Hoerl admits. &amp;ldquo;There are two issues: the message and the format. The bigger the message, the more it needs to be compressed, which makes it increasingly difficult to decode. Future beings won&amp;rsquo;t have a copy of Windows! So we&amp;rsquo;ve identified ultra-durable storage formats that are analogue, so the message can be viewed with very limited decoding. In the beginning, the message is viewable through simple magnification: even a few drops of water is enough. It includes a full Rosetta Stone of 327 languages and an instruction manual on how to build a microscope. So, as long as some language survives, we hope the message in the archive can be reconstructed in that way.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Messages in molecules&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;And yet it could be another branch of science &amp;ndash; chemistry &amp;ndash; that already holds the answer to how humans can speak through the millennia. Scientists know that large molecules can only be formed through interaction with a biological entity; that&amp;rsquo;s how they increase their molecular complexity. If you find a molecule that&amp;rsquo;s bigger than a certain size, therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s evidence that life must have existed. Carbon dioxide, for instance, could form without life on any planet in the universe; DNA could not.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Taking this concept, Lee Cronin, a professor at the University of Glasgow, is examining whether we can use our knowledge of chemistry to leave messages for future generations that can&amp;rsquo;t exist in nature. Cronin has been working on reverse-engineering large molecules, working out how to send messages with them by chopping them up and using their constituent parts. &amp;ldquo;There will be common elements,&amp;rdquo; he says, &amp;ldquo;common parts I use again and again, like Lego bricks.&amp;rdquo; By then analysing these molecules using standard techniques, such as mass spectroscopy, predictable chemical patterns and shifts can be made to occur, allowing you to use molecules as a form of code. &amp;ldquo;You can put in different messages, using different molecules.&amp;rdquo; &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;This won&amp;rsquo;t help, Cronin concedes, unless you know that you are supposed to read the message. But he is also considering how humans could leave longlasting evidence of their presence &amp;ndash; not just of life on Earth, but of an advanced civilisation. &amp;ldquo;If life on Earth is about to be extinguished, I want to leave a warning sign on Earth for aliens,&amp;rdquo; Cronin says. &amp;ldquo;So, what could you do [with chemistry]? Well, what about leaving a molecule in the atmosphere, something that says &amp;lsquo;We were here&amp;rsquo;? You could take every element on the periodic table that forms a bond, and make a molecule out of it. Carbon, phosphorus, silicon, whatever, just daisy chain them together! You&amp;rsquo;d then have a huge macro-molecule, and the assurance that its discoverer will know that there&amp;rsquo;s no way that it was naturally occurring.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;If this sounds outlandish, scientists are already capable of detecting just such a molecule on exoplanets thousands of light years away by using near-infrared telescopes. And once his &amp;ldquo;beacon&amp;rdquo; molecule has attracted attention, Cronin says, increasingly complex molecules next to it could be used to create and explain a cypher. &amp;ldquo;Essentially you could have molecules as decryption devices,&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;You could write a relatively short chemical message, maybe a few thousand words, that would be visible from space using an infrared telescope.&amp;rdquo; With today&amp;rsquo;s technology, then, we could write a greeting in our atmosphere visible across the galaxy. The downside, however, is that such a message would take thousands of years to reach other stars.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We do not have a thousand years to solve this challenge. The advent of nuclear war and the pressing dangers of climate change mean that our civilisation is under greater threat than ever. If we survive, the least we can do is ensure that future generations don&amp;rsquo;t make our mistakes. But some remain pessimistic at the chances of this happening. &amp;ldquo;Human societies do not have the skills to communicate long term,&amp;rdquo; Ialenti concludes. &amp;ldquo;We still need to cultivate within ourselves a greater societal time-literacy, and that could take generations.&amp;rdquo; Until then, all we can do is try our best and hope someone, thousands of years from now, is listening.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5958/how-do-we-warn-future-generations-about-our-toxic-waste#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-05T10:07:53Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-05T10:07:53Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why We Must Keep Abortion Safe, Legal, and Accessible</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/05/why-we-must-keep-abortion-safe-legal-and-accessible/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Gorsuch: Roe v Wade decided 1973 is a precedent of the United States Supreme Court it has been reaffirmed..and all the other factors have to be considered. It is a precedent of the United …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=4pzmFFSgNCo:11l3YrtiBnQ:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131467</id>
    <published>2022-05-04T17:00:34Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-04T17:00:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For explorer Bruce Parry, the journey home may be the hardest</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5956/for-explorer-bruce-parry-the-journey-home-may-be-the-hardest#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-15.23.37.jpg" height="951" alt="Bruce Parry" width="1252" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sitting with Bruce Parry outside his new home in the Cambrian Mountains of Wales. Parry is an explorer in every sense of the word. Famous for his travels to far-flung places, it&amp;rsquo;s his latest, more personal journey that most interests and intrigues me. Why, several years ago, did he abandon his life of global adventure, disappear from our screens and leave his home in Ibiza to attempt the founding of an egalitarian community in the UK?&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve travelled through the winding roads of mid-Wales, down a long track to his secluded stone house, in order to find out. As we look out over hundreds of trees and listen to the gushing of a waterfall, he reflects on the life-changing events, beginning many years ago, that led him here.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Over the last two decades as a television presenter, Parry lived with indigenous groups for the BBC series &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt; and journeyed to the Amazon and Arctic to document the impacts of globalisation and climate change. He tells me that every tribal group he met was struggling due to &amp;ldquo;global events &amp;ndash; mostly globalisation and trade&amp;rdquo;. Loggers, miners and the meat industry were encroaching on formerly pristine habitat and ancestral homes. For Parry it was obvious that &amp;ldquo;the problem is us&amp;rdquo;. The impact of our lifestyles on places that are normally out of sight are &amp;ldquo;not abstract&amp;rdquo; to him, but a lived reality. When he fills his car with petrol, he says, the images of the tar sands are in his heart.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Having seen how our consumption is ravaging the natural world and the lives of people who still live in some harmony with it, Parry&amp;rsquo;s experiences also offered him some valuable insights into alternative ways of being. Whilst filming the first series of &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt; (broadcast in 2005) and living with the Babongo in Gabon, on the western coast of Africa, Parry took Iboga &amp;ndash; used by the tribe as a medicine &amp;ndash; and had extraordinary visions, &amp;ldquo;which were all about connecting to nature and being at one with the universe&amp;rdquo;. Afterwards, he sought out his friend, the doctor and broadcaster Chris van Tulleken, to explain the experience. &amp;ldquo;He said, &amp;lsquo;Bruce, you were just taking a drug. Stop being an idiot&amp;rsquo; . . . And so sure enough, I stuck that experience into the box called &amp;lsquo;Just taken a drug; doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean anything&amp;rsquo;, to get on with my life. Because that&amp;rsquo;s what we do.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The power of meditation and psychedelics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Years later Parry came across a TED talk by the neuroanatomist Jill Bolte Taylor called &amp;ldquo;My Stroke of Insight&amp;rdquo;. She describes how having a stroke in the left hemisphere of her brain, the side that many believe is highly proficient at logic and language, made her experience the most incredible revelations from the right side, which is more to do with the experience of the present moment, what Taylor describes as the &amp;ldquo;right here, right now&amp;rdquo;. She felt at one with the universe, connected to everything. Parry remembers listening to the talk and thinking &amp;ldquo;Fuck, that&amp;rsquo;s me . . . I&amp;rsquo;ve had that experience. Here&amp;rsquo;s a scientist and she&amp;rsquo;s got an explanation for it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While the exact nature of the left-right brain distinction is subject to debate, Parry believes that we&amp;rsquo;d feel more connected to our surroundings and each other if we spent more time using the right side of our brains. He thinks psychedelic substances, like Iboga, can help with this, as can other tools and practices: meditation, for example, or foraging, which calls for you to be totally present in the moment and responsive to surroundings.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The Penan people of Borneo, the final group Parry met while filming &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tribe&lt;/span&gt;, made a huge impression on him. The moment he encountered them, he felt that, of the 15 he had lived with over the course of four years, there was something completely different about this tribe. After further research, he realised that the Penan are one of the last surviving groups that still live as nomadic hunter-gatherers, within egalitarian structures. &amp;ldquo;For 95 per cent of our time on this planet we were in egalitarian communities,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s our most resilient state. I genuinely think there&amp;rsquo;s something for us to learn from that&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Parry was so taken by the Penan that he made an independent documentary about them, called &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Tawai&lt;/span&gt; (released 2017). The title is the Penan&amp;rsquo;s word for their relationship with the forest. One Penan member explains, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like when I&amp;rsquo;m with my mother, every day I know I can rely on her to breastfeed me. That&amp;rsquo;s why I feel &lt;span class="s1"&gt;tawai&lt;/span&gt; about the forest. It&amp;rsquo;s a guarantee of life.&amp;rdquo; Another mentions planes and cars but says if they don&amp;rsquo;t last for ever then he doesn&amp;rsquo;t want them, because they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;not the same as the forest that we can have until the end of time&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Tragically, the Penan&amp;rsquo;s forest is being decimated. Parry is currently seeking funds for a new documentary, which he hopes will express his thinking on these issues more explicitly than in the past. But he&amp;rsquo;s also trying to put the Penan&amp;rsquo;s lessons into practice on a personal level.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Having spent much of his adult life travelling, Parry, now 52, doesn&amp;rsquo;t feel that he belongs to any particular place. However, this hasn&amp;rsquo;t stopped him from wanting to settle down. &amp;ldquo;I have a belief that finding a place is where our deeper contentment can lie. I know that the sooner I can put my roots in the better.&amp;rdquo; He sees value in &amp;ldquo;knowing that you&amp;rsquo;ll be buried somewhere, that you&amp;rsquo;ll be remembered as the ancestor of that place, that you&amp;rsquo;ll be nourishing the trees that feed the next generations&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;From Ibiza to rural Wales&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Parry spent 10 blissful years living in a farmhouse in Ibiza. But, he tells me, he always knew it was a bubble. He yearned to live a life more aligned with his values: low-impact, low-consumption, more local, more connected to nature and other people. He felt a moral responsibility to speak out about these views, and realised they would have more legitimacy if he was speaking from his home country. &amp;ldquo;As a public voice, I have more sway in the UK.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But why build a community in this particular spot? Mid-Wales has long been a Mecca for people interested in green living, with alternative communities clustering near the town of Machynlleth, and Parry was initially drawn into its orbit by a foraging course. The course involved having tea in a remote stone house surrounded by woodland. Later, when he saw it was up for sale, he told the seller about his desire to use it as a base for some kind of egalitarian community. He didn&amp;rsquo;t have the funds to buy it at the time, but the owner said that if he wanted it, she would wait for him.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In 2018, he moved in. But this only opened up more questions. Initially, Parry was hoping to start a community with three women who were skilled foragers and crafts-people with deep ecological knowledge. &amp;ldquo;These amazing women will go for three months into the woods in Sweden with nothing other than the clothing that they&amp;rsquo;ve made, and nets they&amp;rsquo;ve made.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Unfortunately, their life together hit a stumbling block as soon as the women went to see the house. &amp;ldquo;They hated it. They said there were too many conifers and that there was lead in the river.&amp;rdquo; The water runs through a mine upstream. &amp;ldquo;But I also think it wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much the place, it was more that I&amp;rsquo;d jumped the gun ahead of the group and made the decision to buy it without them. Maybe it all fell apart because I made a power move.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a painful first lesson. &amp;ldquo;I was talking about an egalitarian, co-owned, shared space and then I went and decided where it is going to be &amp;ndash; that clearly killed it right from the start.&amp;rdquo; He&amp;rsquo;s currently talking to 15 people in nearby shared-living communities to produce a joint vision statement, with the ultimate goal of living together in the stone house. He wonders, however, if it might be better to sell and buy somewhere collectively, so the project isn&amp;rsquo;t influenced by his &amp;ldquo;founder energy&amp;rdquo; from the start.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Whilst living alone, he often has visitors to stay, and enjoys feeding them with food harvested from his polytunnel. He&amp;rsquo;s part of a nearby community garden project, and loves the house being full of friends, pickling and fermenting. But he admits looking out the window some days, seeing it &amp;ldquo;pissing it down&amp;rdquo;, and asking &amp;ldquo;Why did I choose here?&amp;rdquo; It appears that he hasn&amp;rsquo;t completely ruled out heading further afield.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Our explorer seems a little lost, yet his personal struggle resonates with the crossroads faced by our society. We know things can&amp;rsquo;t carry on as they are, in the face of mounting climate and ecological crises, but we don&amp;rsquo;t know how to transition into a different mode of living. Parry is famous for his bravery &amp;ndash; he&amp;rsquo;s run naked over a line of cattle, taken countless mind-altering drugs and survived perilous expeditions in the Arctic and the deep jungle &amp;ndash; but his current venture may be his most daring yet.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;He still believes it&amp;rsquo;s right for him &amp;ldquo;to retreat from all the madness going on outside&amp;rdquo; and to try out a different &amp;ldquo;fun, cool, interesting way of living that may be enticing to others&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s a journey that demands moral courage. And while he might not have the map yet, his compass is set on the way ahead.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5956/for-explorer-bruce-parry-the-journey-home-may-be-the-hardest#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-05-03T09:39:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-03T09:39:06Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/05/open-discussion-may-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978329</id>
    <published>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</published>
    <updated>2022-05-01T09:23:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5954/book-review-video-games-violence-and-the-ethics-of-fantasy#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-07-at-14.44.36.jpg" height="678" alt="Video Games book" width="856" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m standing in an elevator in Zakhaev International Airport, Moscow. As I brace myself for the opening of the doors, my comrade stoically utters, &amp;ldquo;Remember, no Russian.&amp;rdquo; What follows is brutal slaughter. I light the place up with my fully automatic PKM light machine gun and the tourists flee in terror. With the airport in ruins, I casually stroll over the bodies. This is a simulated reality &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, to be specific. I was a bright-eyed 12-year-old boy at the time, enamoured of the violence. But does that make me sadistic? &lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The debate over gaming and violence is often reinvigorated by a grisly crime. After the Columbine High School massacre in Colorado in 1999, the press famously, and without evidence, linked the perpetrators&amp;rsquo; actions to shooter games they had been known to play such as &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Doom&lt;/span&gt;. The issue recently hit the news in the UK after a 16-year-old shot his schoolmate: a court heard that that the boy&amp;rsquo;s playing of first-person shooter games was a &amp;ldquo;significant factor&amp;rdquo; in his &amp;ldquo;violent fantasies&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One might expect a book called &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; to engage with the long-running debate around whether virtual violence increases aggression in players, or even the predisposition to kill. Instead, Christopher Bartel, Professor of Philosophy at Appalachian State University, turns his attention to the morality of the player, asking whether the fictitious nature of video games make them &amp;ldquo;okay to engage in&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;He surveys a variety of video games, examining in particular how a developer&amp;rsquo;s intentions can interact with those of the players. He notes that this may differ where the violence is contextualised, such as in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, where the non-playable characters (fictional people in the game) approve or disapprove of the players&amp;rsquo; conduct. &amp;ldquo;The use of honour as the basis for a moral system in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; subtly suggests what sort of choices the player ought to make,&amp;rdquo; writes Bartel. &amp;ldquo;The story of &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Red Dead Redemption&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is &amp;ndash; as the name implies &amp;ndash; one of moral redemption.&amp;rdquo; In doing this, the developers have signalled their preference for their ideal, archetypal player.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;As may be evident, the &amp;ldquo;No Russian&amp;rdquo; mission in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty: Modern Warfare 2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a very different affair, and is now infamous: in order not to blow your cover as a spy, you are tasked with slaughtering an airport&amp;rsquo;s worth of innocent bystanders. But Bartel does not simply dismiss it as amoral. He argues that it highlights the ambiguities of warfare, which is never black and white: after all, many governments have carried out similarly &amp;ldquo;grey&amp;rdquo; missions. He also includes a striking thought-experiment related to his adaptation of the &amp;ldquo;gamer&amp;rsquo;s dilemma&amp;rdquo;, developed by philosopher Morgan Luck. Bartel points out that although &amp;ldquo;many players defend murder in video games as merely harmless fun because it causes no real-world harm, the exact same argument could be employed to defend paedophilia in video games with equal force&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Video Games, Violence and the Ethics of Fantasy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is an intriguing, thought-provoking read. An academic title, it is still of interest to the general reader, although we are tested at times by dense passages of specialist vocabulary. It fails, however, to explore some key areas of the wider debate. As a child playing &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Call of Duty&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, I didn&amp;rsquo;t possess the critical thinking skills required to absorb any message about the ambiguities of war, yet Bartel appears not to make the distinction between gaming as a child and as an adult.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Ultimately, Bartel concludes that it isn&amp;rsquo;t as simple as saying that games are fictitious and thus have no moral implications. He proposes that we do more to understand why individual players are motivated to entertain immoral and violent fantasies. Yet he states that his aim is &amp;ldquo;not to condemn players for their actions; nor is it to defend or suggest any legislation regarding the sale or availability of games&amp;rdquo;. The reader is therefore left in doubt as to how his conclusions might apply to the world outside the game.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5954/book-review-video-games-violence-and-the-ethics-of-fantasy#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-28T09:47:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-28T09:47:04Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Antidepressants Work (Why You Can Ignore that Study Saying They Don’t)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/antidepressants-work-why-you-can-ignore-that-study-saying-they-dont/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Before we get started, I’ve set up an alternate channel where I’ll be posting more casual videos of my life, like hiking and playing with my dog and whatnot. If that interests you, please …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=ErrBSK5bG50:oaGD9CSSSKY:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131449</id>
    <published>2022-04-27T15:19:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-27T15:19:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Playground for the soul</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5963/playground-for-the-soul#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/bZZTUqMo.jpeg" height="797" alt="How The Light Gets In festival" width="1417" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Dreams and jeopardy. It&amp;rsquo;s an intriguing theme for a festival, but wholly in keeping with the ambitious and boundary-hopping spirit of &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;HowTheLightGetsIn&lt;/a&gt;, which will be welcoming guests to sample its smorgasbord of big ideas in early June this year. In part, it&amp;rsquo;s an acknowledgement of a historical moment: the summer of 2022. Things are starting to move again, the future is once more opening up, and yet, as the organisers put it, &amp;ldquo;we are faced once more with some of the world&amp;rsquo;s biggest questions, and are asking the world&amp;rsquo;s leading thinkers to help us solve them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Held on the banks of the River Wye, the festival attracting the kinds of people who want to engage with philosophical questions, outside of the ivory tower of academia. As its founder Hilary Lawson told us in a &lt;a href="/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture"&gt;recent interview&lt;/a&gt;, the festival aims to encourage debate between disciplines, and &amp;ldquo;change the way people think about what philosophy is.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Speakers this year include Nobel-prize winning physicist Roger Penrose, Pulitzer Prize winning journalist Andrea Elliott, best-selling author Yuval Noah Harari and trailblazing physicist and author Lisa Randall. The idea is to bring international philosophers at the top of their fields together with influential politicians, scientists and cultural figures. As philosophy partners of the festival, we&amp;rsquo;re delighted to also see a fair few New Humanist contributors in the lineup, including the writer and theoretician of desire Katherine Angel, philosopher Massimo Puggluci, journalist and feminist Minna Salami, and legendary biologist and honorary associate of the Rationalist Assocation, Richard Dawkins.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, New Humanist Editor Samira Shackle will be chairing a debate on &amp;ldquo;Necessity and Lies&amp;rdquo;, with the founder of the festival and philosopher Hilary Lawson, scientist Simon Baron-Cohen and alt-left thinker Rebecca Roache. Should we recognise that lying can be valuable, and sometimes necessary, for ourselves and those in power? Or is honesty not only essential in public life but vital in all aspects of our everyday life as well?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the Jubilee Bank Holiday, and part of bringing the big ideas down to earth is to unwind and have some fun - hence the inclusion of comedy, art and music. It's why the festival bills itself as a "playground of the soul". The London Afrobeat Collective will be there, along with sequin-clad satirical performers Bourgeois and Maurice, &amp;ldquo;Essex Arab Girl Comedian&amp;rdquo; Esther Manito, and Groove Armada&amp;rsquo;s Tom Findlay on the decks - just some of the 450 speakers and performers, on 12 stages over the festival's four days. You can see the full programme &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/programme?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, including events for children and young adults. As Socrates said, philosophy begins in wonder, and who is more awestruck than the young?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Started in a chapel, with a small attendance, in 2018, HowTheLightGetsIn has been something of an unexpected success. Yet why should it be a surprise that people want to engage in the fundamental questions around their own existence. We're all human, after all, and life is a wonderful, puzzling thing. After the inevitable hiatus of the pandemic, it feels right to come together to challenge and enrich our ideas about the world, to learn to dream again, while sounding a note of caution around the need for care and reflection: the "jeopardy" of this year's theme. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We hope to see you there, in Hay-on-Wye, on 2-5 June. New Humanist readers get a 20 per cent discount, with the promo code NEWHUMANIST20. Otherwise, for those who can&amp;rsquo;t attend in person, the festival will be streamed online.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;See &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for tickets to the event. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those of you who can't be with us in person, the festival will also be streaming online during the 2nd-5th June. Click &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/online?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="1"&gt;here &lt;/a&gt;for more information and to purchase online tickets to watch the festival livestream. Additionally, all the debates and talks from the festival will be gradually released online in the months following the festival on the &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/about-iai/introducing-the-iai?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="2"&gt;Institute of Art and Ideas&lt;/a&gt; online platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="3"&gt;IAI.TV&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Hay+2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="4"&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5963/playground-for-the-soul#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:16:29Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:16:29Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Does Shotspotter Help Cops Keep Us Safe?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/04/does-shotspotter-help-cops-keep-us-safe/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Last week I had an experience that was weirdly scary not in the moment I was in danger but hours later when I realized I had been in danger. I was in a car on …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=Gxobzkro_08:6J8qJc7yPGk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131446</id>
    <published>2022-04-25T15:19:24Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-25T15:19:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/04/open-discussion-april-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978276</id>
    <published>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-01T09:33:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intolerance of Inquiry, Failures of Imagination</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/intolerance-of-inquiry-failures-of-imagination/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! A few days ago, Raif Badawi walked out of his prison cell.  A progressive Saudi writer, Badawi was arrested in 2012 on charges of “insulting Islam” and apostasy for daring to question religion and criticize the Saudi Arabian government through his website. The Center for Inquiry (CFI) …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978231</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VIDEO: Paul Offit on Medical Risk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/video-paul-offit-on-medical-risk/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We live in an unprecedented age of medical marvels, but success never comes free. In his third appearance on Skeptical Inquirer Presents, renowned virologist Paul Offit discussed the ideas behind his new book You Bet Your Life, explaining that the path to each medical advancement is paved with failures and risk.  “I wrote this book knowing …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978225</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dreaming of Mars and the Aliens Who Aren’t There</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/dreaming-of-mars-and-the-aliens-who-arent-there/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no evidence that Earth has ever been visited by extraterrestrials, yet many people are firmly convinced that aliens are among us. A team of researchers at California State University, Fresno, led by psychologist Matthew J. Sharps, set out to understand the psychological traits that influence a person’s beliefs about alien visitations and abductions. …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978223</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evidence to House of Commons Sci Tech Select Committee on Research Integrity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/12/evidence-to-house-of-commons-sci-tech-select-committee-on-research-integrity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry not to be in regular blogging mode at the moment. Here’s a video of our evidence session to parliament, where they are running an inquiry into research integrity. I think clinical trials are the best possible way to approach this issue. Lots of things in “research integrity” are hard to capture in hard logical […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3498</id>
    <published>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</updated>
    <category term="alltrials campaign"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do the world’s biggest drug companies compare, in their transparency commitments?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/how-do-the-worlds-biggest-drug-companies-compare-in-their-transparency-commitments/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hereâ€™s a paper, and associated website, that we launch today: we have assessed, and then ranked, all the biggest drug companies in the world, to compare their public commitments on trials transparency. Regular readers will be familiar with this ongoing battle. In medicine we use the results of clinical trials to make informed treatments about […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3485</id>
    <published>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meaningful Transparency Commitments: the WHO Joint Statement from Trial Funders</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/meaningful-transparency-commitments-the-who-joint-statement-from-trial-funders/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By now I hope you all know about the ongoing global scandal of clinical trial results being left unpublished, and of course our AllTrials campaign. Doctors, researchers, and patients cannot make truly informed choices about which treatments work best if they don’t have access to all the trial results. Earlier this year, I helped out […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3481</id>
    <published>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/02/how-many-epidemiologists-does-it-take-to-change-a-lightbulb/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robin Ince just asked if I know any epidemiologist lightbulb jokes. I wrote this for him. How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb? Weâ€™ve found 12,000 switches hidden around the house. Some of them turn this lightbulb on, some of them donâ€™t; some of them only work sometimes; and some of them […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3472</id>
    <published>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“Transparency, Beyond Publication Bias”. A video of my super-speedy talk at IJE.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2016/10/transparency-beyond-publication-bias-a-video-of-my-super-speedy-talk-at-ije/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">People oftenÂ talk about “trials transparency” as if this means “all trials must be published in an academic journal”. In reality, true transparency goes much further than this. We need Clinical Study Reports, and individual patient data, of course. But we also need the consent forms, so we can see what patients were told. We need […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3463</id>
    <published>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
