<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-04-01T02:11:11Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Shut up, Meyer, your schtick is getting old</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/31/shut-up-meyer-your-schtick-is-getting-old/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;As usual, Stephen Meyer tries to claim that only intelligence can generate information. My usual response to that is a combination of…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But that&amp;#8217;s the point of contention! You can&amp;#8217;t use your premise as evidence that your premise is true!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;OK, smart guy, have you examined every single piece of information in the universe to back up your claim that information &lt;q&gt;always comes from an intelligent source&lt;/q&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this is also a very good response. We have direct, observed, experimental evidence that information can arise from non-intelligent, natural processes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Q9yG8qAskrQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the thing that bugs me about Meyer. He claims to be a philosopher, yet all of his books, every long-winded one of them, rests on a logical fallacy, his unsupported claim that all information is a product of intelligent design, and that therefore all information is a product of intelligent design.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As usual, Stephen Meyer tries to claim that only intelligence can generate information. My usual response to that is a combination of… But that’s the point of contention! You can’t use your premise as evidence that your premise is true! OK, smart guy, have you examined every single piece of information in the universe to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66114</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T16:06:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T16:06:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Creationism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The (Lack of) Scientific Evidence for Life After Death</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/the-lack-of-scientific-evidence-for-life-after-death/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Hey have you ever almost DIED? Have you ever almost died so hard that you floated above your body, and then you saw a tunnel with a light at the end, and then you …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=E_yQrhgE1Cg:VKnKQAtIVjA:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131414</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T15:46:44Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T15:46:44Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The bus wasn’t even crowded</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/31/the-bus-wasnt-even-crowded/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;In the absence of sandworms in Minnesota, our fremen &lt;a href="https://www.abc12.com/news/national/rider-climbs-atop-bus-traveling-along-highway/article_743f5663-6719-596d-bc24-3742688ab23b.html"&gt;make do with&lt;/a&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="576" height="1024" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/p6EzWyqhilQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of a stillsuit, I hope she had lots and lots of layers, since that had to have been pretty chilly. And dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of sandworms in Minnesota, our fremen make do with… Instead of a stillsuit, I hope she had lots and lots of layers, since that had to have been pretty chilly. And dangerous.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66112</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T13:31:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T13:31:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>ICR has added “annoying” to their repertoire of “stupid”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/31/icr-has-added-annoying-to-their-repertoire-of-stupid/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div id="attachment_66108" style="width: 76px" class="wp-caption alignright"&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/notacat.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/notacat-66x150.jpeg" alt="" width="66" height="150" class="size-thumbnail wp-image-66108" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/notacat-66x150.jpeg 66w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/notacat-132x300.jpeg 132w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/notacat.jpeg 377w" sizes="(max-width: 66px) 100vw, 66px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p class="wp-caption-text"&gt;…yet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class="lead"&gt;The Institute for Creation Research has a series of videos titled &amp;#8220;That&amp;#8217;s A Fact&amp;#8221;, each one under 2 minutes long, with funky background music and physically painful kinetic transitions. No, really, it hurt my eyes to watch this one &amp;#8212; the gimmick is a screen full of words in random orientations, and the camera zooms around to highlight the word the narrator says, and just the esthetics broke me. And then there&amp;#8217;s the content…hoo boy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For instance, here&amp;#8217;s one titled &amp;#8220;evolving bacteria&amp;#8221;. &lt;q&gt;For instance, in a 20 year study of &lt;i&gt;E. coli&lt;/i&gt;…scientists looked at 40,000 generations of bacteria, and confirmed that the bacteria did not evolve into anything other than &lt;i&gt;E. coli&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/q&gt; That&amp;#8217;s it. That&amp;#8217;s all. Lenski set up this experiment to see bacteria evolve into a cat, didn&amp;#8217;t see any evilution at all, and therefore &lt;a href="https://www.archivesofcreation.com/post/lenski-experiment-proves-macroevolution-a-myth" rel="nofollow"&gt;&lt;q&gt;proved that macroevolution is a myth&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently, Lenski writes all these papers that just say &amp;#8220;Nope, still not a cat in any test tube&amp;#8221;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/QZmcoaG9qMA" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, guys, the Lenski long-term evolution experiment did not propose to evolve something other than &lt;i&gt;E. coli&lt;/i&gt; (it would have been surprising if it did, and would have sent everyone scurrying off to rewrite the textbooks, calling evolutionary theory into question), and it did &lt;a href="https://lenski.mmg.msu.edu/ecoli/index.html"&gt;demonstrate evolutionary changes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, ICR, do you even know what the word &amp;#8220;evolve&amp;#8221; means?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Institute for Creation Research has a series of videos titled “That’s A Fact”, each one under 2 minutes long, with funky background music and physically painful kinetic transitions. No, really, it hurt my eyes to watch this one — the gimmick is a screen full of words in random orientations, and the camera zooms […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66107</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T11:56:13Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T11:56:13Z</updated>
    <category term="Creationism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Giuliani crime family is doing their best to convince me that lizard people exist</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/31/the-giuliani-crime-family-is-doing-their-best-to-convince-me-that-lizard-people-exist/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/giulianipair.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/giulianipair-150x110.png" alt="" width="150" height="110" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-66105" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/giulianipair-150x110.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/giulianipair-300x220.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/giulianipair.png 433w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I’m not saying David Icke was right, but Rudy’s son Andrew is running for governor of New York, and he too is <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/andrew-guiliani-makes-gross-anti-trans-comments-to-far-right-group-in-ny-governor-race?ref=home">something of a sick freak</a>. Would you believe he’s talking about his baby daughter here?</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>She “made a promise to me on the first day, right? My wife was sleeping, and I’m holding her [my daughter] in my arms. And I get emotional thinking about it, but she made a promise with me. She shook my hand and I said, ‘I’m the only boyfriend till you’re 25 years old, shake hands.’</p>
<p>“Shook my hand. So I have changed the diapers. I have looked under the hood. She’s a woman. I’m gonna be the last guy in a long time that looks under the hood right there. But guess what? She was born a woman and she’s gonna stay a woman, it’s that simple.”</p>
<p>A spokesperson for Andrew Giuliani told The Daily Beast, “while Andrew does not claim to be a biologist, he can tell the difference between a male and a female.”</p></blockquote>
<p>So he’s possessive and controlling — I hate to break the news to you, Andy ol’ boy, but in less than 16 years she’s going to be talking about boys (or maybe girls) with her friends, and pining for a prom date who isn’t her creepy old man. At some point, she’s also going to get on the internet and discover her dad was talking about peeking “under the hood” when she was 4 months old — or worse, her peers at school learn this — and you will learn about the revenge of a daughter you’ve made cringe.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’m not saying David Icke was right, but Rudy’s son Andrew is running for governor of New York, and he too is something of a sick freak. Would you believe he’s talking about his baby daughter here? She “made a promise to me on the first day, right? My wife was sleeping, and I’m holding […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66104</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T11:18:26Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T11:18:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Faith in education</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5944/faith-in-education#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="A crucifix hangs on the wall of a Catholic school in Warwickshire in the UK (Alamy Stock Photo)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-03-at-14.12.22.jpg" height="888" alt="Crucifix in a classroom" width="1330" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;To anyone trying to navigate it for the first time, England&amp;rsquo;s education system can seem like an old ship, endlessly patched and repatched by successive governments until the original structure has been lost and nothing moves without taking on water. Its Byzantine edifice of rules and regulations contains many a rotting timber &amp;ndash; not least the exceptional status given to faith schools. These are defined as schools of religious &amp;ldquo;character&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;ethos&amp;rdquo;, or which may have formal links to a religious organisation. The National Secular Society (NSS), which campaigns against faith schools, estimates that about one in three schools in England and Wales, both independent and state-funded, can be so labelled.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These schools are permitted to select some or all of their students, as well as their staff, on the basis of their or their family&amp;rsquo;s religion. Then there is the curriculum. It may be no surprise that faith schools are allowed to teach religious education &amp;ldquo;within the tenets of their faith&amp;rdquo;. Yet this also applies to relationships and sex education, giving them leeway to insert bias and promote religious doctrine on important topics such as homosexuality, extra-marital sex and women&amp;rsquo;s rights.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Opponents are concerned about the extension of influence from churches, mosques and synagogues into schools &amp;ndash; particularly as, in addition to Ofsted inspections, faith schools are subject to statutory &amp;ldquo;religiosity inspections&amp;rdquo; by their sponsoring religious body. The problem becomes more worrying when it comes to unregistered faith schools, which are not regulated at all and which operate in a shadowy world on the margins of the law. Although they are far fewer in number, these schools can have a severe effect on the lives and future prospects of the children who pass through their doors.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;However, even when properly run, many faith schools fail adequately to serve the needs of their local communities &amp;ndash; a problem that grows more complex as England&amp;rsquo;s population becomes more diverse. Even if parents are happy for their children to be brought up within the narrow tenets of a particular faith and with limited exposure to different ways of thinking, it is far from clear that this is always done with children&amp;rsquo;s best interests in mind. We might question, then, why state faith schools &amp;ndash; funded in part or wholly by the taxpayer &amp;ndash; are still able to be established with apparent ease, regardless of the wishes of locals and prospective parents.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The case of one such school, which opened in September just south of Peterborough, illustrates the complexity and depth of the problem.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p1"&gt;A "Catholic ethos" in the school curriculum&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;St John Henry Newman Catholic primary school was developed to serve a growing housing development in the town of Hampton Water. Its &amp;ldquo;Catholic ethos&amp;rdquo;, according to its sponsor, the Catholic Diocese of East Anglia, &amp;ldquo;will permeate all areas of the curriculum and underpin the school&amp;rsquo;s work and objectives&amp;rdquo;. It is a voluntary aided (VA) school, benefitting from the funds set aside by the government in 2019 for 14 new VA faith schools, to add to the 2,640-odd already established in England.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Local opinion seems not to have been factored in. A consultation was conducted by Peterborough city council, but among those who gave a Hampton postcode, 127 opposed the school. Only 17 were in favour. &amp;ldquo;Hampton Water is a very diverse community,&amp;rdquo; said Tracy Butler, a resident who campaigned against the school. &amp;ldquo;We have lots of different faiths; we also have residents of no faith at all.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The reasons behind the approval have never been made clear. &amp;ldquo;The Department of Education have on multiple occasions . . . refused to provide any information about how they assess these proposals,&amp;rdquo; says Alastair Lichten, co-ordinator of No More Faith Schools. As such, it is difficult to tell how far St John Henry Newman, or JHN, is symptomatic of a wider trend. Even so, a pressing question remains: why has the UK government supported a new wave of faith schools, permitting them to open in parts of the country whose inhabitants they may not represent?&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Anger in Hampton Water is likely to have been compounded by the way the school was funded. Ten per cent of the capital costs were raised through a charge on local facilities, levied by the council on developers and passed on to purchasers. This means that, in buying a property in the housing development, residents will have helped to pay for the school, despite not knowing what type it would be.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;This could happen anywhere, so that young families moving to a new housing development in England might end up paying for a faith school their children are not qualified to attend. At JHN, as at other VA schools, the remaining 90 per cent of capital costs, and 100 per cent of running costs, are being funded by the state. In other words, we&amp;rsquo;re all paying for religious privilege.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s true that the Diocese has committed an additional &amp;pound;250,000 to projects at JHN. However, foremost among these are a chapel and &amp;ldquo;a crucifix on the outside wall of the school&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; hardly symbols of inclusivity. According to Lichten, JHN will be &amp;ldquo;the most discriminatory new school that has opened in England in about 10 years.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The government has typically justified faith schools on the grounds that they improve academic results and increase parents&amp;rsquo; choice. In a 2014 Commons debate on Catholic schools, the Education Secretary, Damian Hinds, praised their &amp;ldquo;high performance&amp;rdquo;, which he attributed to their &amp;ldquo;ethos and character&amp;rdquo; (Hinds himself attended a Catholic grammar school). The evidence, however, is less clear. A 2016 report by the Education Policy Institute found that while pupils in state faith schools did do better academically than their peers at non-faith schools, the gap was much smaller when controlling for factors such as socioeconomic background and prior attainment.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Religious groups have certainly latched on to the diversity argument. In the case of JHN, the Diocese said that a new Catholic school would &amp;ldquo;enhance choice and diversity of education provision for parents within the Hampton area&amp;rdquo;. What will actually happen, says Butler, is that the school will end up selecting children from Catholic families living further away in preference to local children from non-Catholic families. As a resident, she sees JHN as &amp;ldquo;a huge missed opportunity for integration&amp;rdquo;. People moved into the area &amp;ldquo;hoping that their children would all be able to go to school together&amp;rdquo;, she says.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Yet the government seems unperturbed, and doesn&amp;rsquo;t even bother to monitor the effectiveness of faith-selective admissions. In response to a Freedom of Information request by the NSS in 2020, the Department for Education (DfE) admitted that it &amp;ldquo;does not hold information on which schools select on the basis of religion as an element of their admissions criteria&amp;rdquo;. They do not seem to be concerned that religious organisations may be using the school system in England to extend their power, largely at the expense of those who do not share their beliefs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The grip of the Church of England&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;It is no coincidence that the organisation to take the greatest advantage of this means of influence is the Church of England, the established church of this country. The C of E is the biggest sponsor of faith schools, and is currently running 4,644 state schools, around three-quarters of which are primary schools. It estimates that around 15 million adults alive today will have attended one of its schools in the course of their education.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;If you ask most people about their experience of attending an Anglican school, a common view is that it &amp;ldquo;didn&amp;rsquo;t do me any harm&amp;rdquo;, or that all it really teaches is &amp;ldquo;being nice to people&amp;rdquo;. There is little doubt that the C of E is, for historical reasons, the best assimilated into mainstream British culture. But by the same token, most of its so-called &amp;ldquo;Christian values&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; faith and piety aside &amp;ndash; are no longer seen as distinctively Christian, but rather as near-universal. Anglicanism in particular does not form part of the identity of most British people, especially in younger age groups: only 1 per cent of 18-to-24 year-olds identify themselves with the creed, according to the NSS.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This seemed to be playing on the mind of Stephen Cottrell, the Archbishop of York, when he urged the General Synod, in a paper presented in June, to adopt &amp;ldquo;a bolder commitment to Christian education and ministry with children, young people and students,&amp;rdquo; emphasising the need for &amp;ldquo;youth evangelism&amp;rdquo;. Clearly it is a question of survival.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The so-called &amp;ldquo;religiosity inspections&amp;rdquo; are a key tool in this drive to proselytise. State-funded faith schools must be inspected by their sponsoring religious body every five years. According to Matthew Hill, a former head teacher who contributed to a recent NSS report on the subject, schools have to show not only that their values are &amp;ldquo;rooted in an exclusively Christian narrative&amp;rdquo;, but that they are working closely with the local church. He has also seen inspectors questioning primary school children, some as young as five, on theology. &amp;ldquo;Some were asked about the Trinitarian nature of God,&amp;rdquo; he said. A 2020 NSS report examined 40 &amp;ldquo;religiosity&amp;rdquo; reports on schools produced by two C of E dioceses in 2019. It found that over half &amp;ldquo;conflated successful [religious education] with promoting or eliciting Christian viewpoints&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Yet in Hill&amp;rsquo;s experience, few parents realise the difference between a religiosity inspection and a standard Ofsted inspection. The inspections thus put enormous pressure on heads to &amp;ldquo;ramp up the evangelism. . . If the school used to be an excellent church school and now it&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;lsquo;requires improvement&amp;rsquo; church school, that&amp;rsquo;s not good PR.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The C of E&amp;rsquo;s involvement in education isn&amp;rsquo;t only confined to the promotion of the Christian faith. In order to protect its own privileges, the organisation seems to feel compelled to defend all religions against the encroachments of secular democracy. This approach has even extended to unregistered faith schools.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Disadvantaging minorities&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;By law, all schools for children aged 5 to 16, both state-funded and independent, must register with the DfE and submit to regular inspections. However, &lt;br /&gt;according to statutory guidance, &amp;ldquo;out-of-school settings&amp;rdquo; that provide cultural, religious and other types of &amp;ldquo;study support&amp;rdquo; only need register as schools if they are operating for at least 18 hours a week, and teach five or more children. Some organisations, including Charedi (ultra-Orthodox Jewish) and fundamentalist Islamic and Christian groups, use this provision to their advantage. While claiming to operate for less than the 18-hour limit, or outside normal hours, they in fact run as full-time religious schools. According to an updated report on unregistered schools published by Ofsted in November 2021, children attending them are &amp;ldquo;at risk because there is no formal external oversight of safeguarding, health and safety or the quality of education provided&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The very secretiveness of these unofficial schools makes it hard to estimate how many there are, let alone the numbers of students. However, recent data from Ofsted showed that 90 out-of-school settings in Britain with a Christian, Jewish or Muslim faith have been investigated for potential illegality over the course of the last five years. There is additional concern that children whose parents claim they are in elective home education (EHE) are actually at unregistered schools, and that this figure has increased since the Covid-19 lockdowns made EHE more common.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Back in 2015, when radicalisation was high on the political agenda, the existence of these schools &amp;ndash; in particular their potential rejection of &amp;ldquo;British values&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; was of sufficient concern for the government to launch a consultation on ways to regulate out-of-school settings where these provided &amp;ldquo;intensive education&amp;rdquo;. However, as reported in the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; &lt;em&gt;Catholic Herald&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; in 2017, Justin Welby, as Archbishop of Canterbury, personally lobbied &amp;ldquo;senior members of the government&amp;rdquo; not to change the law, while Caroline Spelman MP approached the Cabinet on behalf of the Church Commissioners.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The fear of both Anglican and Catholic interests was that a law change would subject Sunday schools and Bible study groups to unwelcome meddling. The lobbying was effective. As the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Catholic Herald&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; put it: &amp;ldquo;Very quickly, and very quietly, the government dropped the idea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Since then, however, the existence of unregistered schools has continued to receive media attention, thanks in part to campaigns by the NSS and Humanists UK. Ofsted inspectors have also made some progress in closing the schools. However, despite promising signs, the government has yet to tighten the law sufficiently to stop them altogether &amp;ndash; and, according to Ofsted figures, there have only been five successful prosecutions. The DfE issued guidance in 2020 on the proper conduct of out-of-school settings, including &lt;span class="s1"&gt;yeshivas&lt;/span&gt; and &lt;span class="s1"&gt;madrasas&lt;/span&gt;, but it is non-statutory and voluntary &amp;ndash; in other words, it is all but useless.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In the meantime, an unknown number of children may still be receiving education solely at unregistered religious schools, and potentially suffering a range of harms, from ideological indoctrination to ignorance of basic life skills, to safety risks and even physical abuse.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;In October last year, for instance, a father and daughter, Arshad and Nadia Ali, were convicted for a second time of running an unregistered Islamic school in south London. Ofsted identified a number of safeguarding failures at Ambassadors High School, as it was known, including a failure to properly vet the adults working with the children, and insufficient fire safety provisions. Inspectors had previously found that &amp;ldquo;the headteacher had no plan or strategy to promote fundamental British values, or encourage respect for other people&amp;rdquo;. It is difficult to imagine how students who attend such institutions will be able to relate to people of different backgrounds with whom they may have to work and live.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Another example is the unregistered schools known to operate in Charedi communities, particularly in the London boroughs of Hackney and Haringey. These communities tend to keep themselves largely isolated from wider society in order to preserve their fundamentalist religious practices. However, their inner workings have been brought to light by the Jewish organisation Nahamu, whose website describes its members as &amp;ldquo;deeply involved in the religious Jewish community&amp;rdquo; but &amp;ldquo;concerned about increasing levels of extremist discourse and obscurantism&amp;rdquo; within it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As Eve Sacks, board member at Nahamu, explains, Charedi schools are &amp;ldquo;almost exclusively for boys over 13&amp;rdquo;. They provide no secular education. &amp;ldquo;Mainly they learn the Talmud and they might also learn the Torah,&amp;rdquo; she says. The boys speak in Yiddish, a vernacular language, and learn to read Biblical Hebrew and Aramaic. The focus is not on writing essays: &amp;ldquo;literally what are they doing is just reading text&amp;rdquo; and receiving lectures from rabbis on how to interpret it, Sacks says. They may be doing this for as much as 12 hours a day, five and a half days a week.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Ironically, the girls &amp;ndash; who are forbidden to learn the Torah &amp;ndash; receive a better education, albeit a limited and segregated one, in independent but registered faith schools.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;One consequence of this system is that the boys grow up barely able to speak English. Sacks has been approached by Charedi men in their twenties who want to go to university but cannot fill in an application form. &amp;ldquo;And I think, my goodness, you were really wronged there.&amp;rdquo; The lack of education in secular subjects in any language means that their choice of profession is very limited.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Abuse of children in faith schools&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Another problem is safeguarding. In 2019, Amanda Spielman, Ofsted Chief Inspector, was tipped off about a pamphlet entitled &amp;ldquo;Encouragement to teachers and guidance for parents&amp;rdquo;. The pamphlet was written in Hebrew and published with the approval of &amp;ldquo;senior rabbinical figures&amp;rdquo; within the Charedi community, some of whom were thought to be serving teachers at unregistered schools. In her evidence to a statutory government enquiry on child protection, Spielman related that much of the pamphlet came across as &amp;ldquo;a manifesto for corporal punishment&amp;rdquo;. Its author states that &amp;ldquo;force&amp;rdquo; should be used on students &amp;ldquo;to knock down the strength of the evil inclination &amp;ndash; to put fear on them &amp;ndash; to make them submissive because submission is the foundation to revoke their own opinion and receive the faith&amp;rdquo;. In one unregistered faith school, inspectors found that isolation and forced standing for long periods were used as sanctions even on &amp;ldquo;young children&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Even when they are told about the issues at unregistered schools, however, public authorities have often been reluctant to intervene, not least because of worries that they will be accused of racism. But this attitude, argues Sacks, is misguided. It is little better than saying that &amp;ldquo;everybody&amp;rsquo;s entitled to get GCSEs unless you&amp;rsquo;re a Charedi Jew&amp;rdquo;. What is truly &amp;ldquo;antisemitic&amp;rdquo; is depriving these children of the opportunity to have a basic secular education.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Despite these problems, it is Sacks&amp;rsquo; impression that &amp;ldquo;a reasonably large percentage of the community&amp;rdquo; are happy with their unofficial system, which aims to turn boys into &amp;ldquo;scholars&amp;rdquo; and girls into &amp;ldquo;good wives and mothers&amp;rdquo;. If, however, parents wish to send their children into a mainstream school, they risk being shunned. &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re excluded from your synagogue and none of your relations talk to you and everybody gossips about you when you&amp;rsquo;re in the street.&amp;rdquo; For the few who choose to leave the community altogether, moving into mainstream British society is very difficult. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like being an immigrant even though it&amp;rsquo;s the country you&amp;rsquo;ve been brought up in.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are no easy answers to the numerous problems posed by faith schools, even those that are registered. A partial solution advocated by the NSS and others would be to remove their right to select students on the basis of their religion. This would at least ensure they are serving their local area. At the same time, continuing to allow for religiously selective independent schools, but all the while giving Ofsted real powers to regulate them and requiring them to follow a basic secular curriculum, would at least provide some protection for students&amp;rsquo; autonomy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It may be that, as the C of E and other advocates of faith schools argue, going to such a school, in addition to satisfying religious parents, does not inevitably harm a child or prevent him or her from making friends with children from families of other cultural and philosophical persuasions. There may even be meaningful reasons why some faith schools, at least well-established ones, can provide a higher quality of education than non-faith schools. However, these arguments have to be weighed against the benefits of integrating children into wider British society and exposing them to new ideas in the most impressionable part of their lives. There also remains the question of whether it is appropriate for religious organisations to be wielding so much power behind the scenes through their influence over the school system.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Ultimately, it is difficult to see how the knotty problem of faith schools will ever be disentangled as long as politicians and public authorities continue to defer to religion and shrink from scrutinising minority groups. In the balancing act between the rights of parents and children, which every state has to make, deference to religious interests almost inevitably favours parents, whose minds are made up, over children, who have yet to discover things.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;Children are children,&amp;rdquo; says Terri Haynes, a Peterborough councillor and teacher. &amp;ldquo;They might have Catholic parents, but that doesn&amp;rsquo;t make them Catholic.&amp;rdquo; Yet this is how they are treated by faith schools, with or without their parents&amp;rsquo; consent.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A breakthrough might come with a written national constitution founded on secular principles of universal application. This is something that Britain, unlike France or the US, has never had. Yet unfortunately, this prospect seems increasingly distant in a land of such creaking antiquity. In the long term, though, it is hard to see how separating the education system more clearly from religious interests could fail to benefit those whom it ought, above all, to serve: the students.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5944/faith-in-education#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Another day, another lecture</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/30/another-day-another-lecture/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bRt6Keoh6Sc" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66102</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T02:02:15Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-31T02:02:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Genetics"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Study: Artificial Sweeteners and Cancer? Don’t Panic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/study-artificial-sweeteners-and-cancer-dont-panic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Well, it’s a day ending in “y” so it must be time for another study to grab mainstream media headlines proclaiming that something you love causes cancer. Let’s spin the wheel and see what …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=5yDSLcCdDWQ:RnZUOq_ghcc:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131412</id>
    <published>2022-03-29T22:03:36Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-29T22:03:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>"We're bringing philosophy into British culture"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Hilary-Lawson1.jpg" height="485" alt="Hilary Lawson" width="690" /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Where did the idea for HowTheLightGetsIn festival come from? Why did you feel that the UK needed a philosophy and music festival?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, you know, it wasn't a grand plan. I have had an involvement with philosophy ever since I was an undergraduate. And it seemed to me that philosophy was something of a joke in [British] culture as a whole at the time, more associated with the Monty Python [sketch] the Philosophers&amp;rsquo; Football Match, then with answering any serious questions. And I think many people thought philosophy was just lost in an argument over the meaning of words and indeed was incomprehensible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And that seemed to be a mistake. It seemed to me that philosophy is about the biggest questions in life. It doesn't have to be an arcane, abstruse subject. We're all involved in it whether we like it or not. We're alive, and we have to cope with the strangeness of being alive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So that was really the origin of the idea, I guess. And initially, it was just a few people in a small chapel in Hay-on-Wye. And from the moment that we did that first [event], we got a remarkable response. And so it's just grown in a rather crazy way now. We now have 10 million views online on our site. And I think to some small degree, we have changed the way people think about what philosophy is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Was there anything that surprised you, in terms of what was popular?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[Initially] I thought that perhaps the more technical subjects, about the nature of language and truth, or about, you know, subatomic physics or something, would not be our strongest suit. And we would go for topics that were more easily accessible, more &lt;em&gt;Moral Maze &lt;/em&gt;as it were, that sort of thing. But in fact, it was the most technical subjects that we got most engagement with. And I think the reason for that is not that we were attracting a particularly &amp;ldquo;nerdy&amp;rdquo; audience (although I'm sure we have some very brilliant people in our audience) but that it wasn't being found anywhere else. Those conversations were not found in culture generally, they were talked about in an ivory tower context.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What we found is if we put on these debates about, you know, what is the nature of the world? What is the nature of truth? What is the nature of reality? People loved it, because we were actually talking about the big stuff. And we weren't trying to dumb it down for the audience.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In politics, for example, we are happy to listen to, I don't know, &lt;em&gt;Question Time&lt;/em&gt;, or &lt;em&gt;Newsnight&lt;/em&gt;, about a topic we may know nothing about. But we listen and we quickly get the idea. There are different views, different positions, and we work out what's going on. Well, exactly the same is true for philosophy &amp;hellip; And it&amp;rsquo;s really gripping for people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Philosophical questions should certainly have a universal appeal. But do you also think we're in a historical moment now, when humanity is facing multiple existential crises, where it has a particular role to play?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Absolutely. I think that in the west we have had, for at least a few hundred years, the idea that we were gradually progressing towards a better world &amp;hellip; We were morally better than our predecessors, we were developing a fairer, more equitable society and so forth &amp;hellip; And that started to fall apart in the latter part of the 20th century. Partly as a result of postmodernist type moves in thought &amp;ndash; the recognition that there are many different perspectives and we can't rely on our own &amp;ndash; but also because the simplicity of the idea that science was just discovering everything, and coming to a final answer, looked less and less credible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And so, indeed, philosophy has a key role to play, because we are now in a space where those previous modernist certainties have faded. And to a considerable degree, many people are very lost.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What would you say to the critics of postmodernism who see the tradition as destructive and chaotic, due to its apparent claim that &amp;ldquo;truth does not exist&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, postmodernism certainly made it look as if there was no particular moral outlook, there was no particular theoretical outlook, that it was all a question of the perspective that you had, and people would have different perspectives. And you were just left in a multitude of alternative diverse perspectives. And of course, that, if left at that level, it's fantastically debilitating. How do you choose between them? You just get conflict between the different outlooks and the situation looks intractable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It's not really possible to go back to those simplicities of objectivity that we once had, say, in the British case, in the high point of the Victorian period. We recognise that it is the case that there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; alternative perspectives ... but nevertheless, we have to find a way to move forward.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I would argue is, we have to give up on the idea that our language and our descriptions of the world uncover the truth. That's not, I think, what they're doing. Our descriptions of the world are tools to enable us to intervene in the world. They help us get things done. And of course, we always want a better tool. You know, if you are using a pen, you want to make sure it&amp;rsquo;s a good pen. You might improve the nib, or if it's a ballpoint pen, you want to make it flow a little bit better, whatever it might be. But there's no &lt;em&gt;true&lt;/em&gt; pen. There's no ultimate pen. There is just a better way of intervening in the world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And you determine, I think, a better way to intervene in the world by looking to see how it's working at the moment. How is your theory working? How might it change? How might you be able to improve things? So I think you can give up the idea that we are uncovering the truth of the world and [instead] recognise that different people have different frameworks, which enable them to do different things.&lt;strong&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is that what you meant when you wrote &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/articles/post-realism-auid-1755"&gt;in an article for the Institute of Art and Ideas&lt;/a&gt; that &amp;ldquo;the abandonment of realism does not entail a chaos of equal alternatives&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. You don&amp;rsquo;t just think, &amp;ldquo;well, everything is equal&amp;rdquo;. You're trying to make a framework which works better, which achieves outcomes that are more effective and so forth. I think we need to double down on empiricism, looking to see how our theories work. And at the same time, double down on rationality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rationality is really out of out of favour at the moment. It&amp;rsquo;s somehow thought that rationality is embedded in a particular outlook: a western enlightenment, male perspective and so forth. It has been &lt;em&gt;associated&lt;/em&gt; with that, because that's about the idea that it uncovers a single truth &amp;hellip; But I think that we can recognise that the power of the Enlightenment, the power of liberal democratic views, was not about the uncovering of the truth, but it was about uncovering key strategies of improving the way that we think, through empiricism and rationalism. And that's what we need to focus on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But surely there are some facts that can be proven to be true?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;No single claim about the world has been identified, which is unchallengeable &amp;ndash; that is, independent of the context in which the claim is made. I've had numerous arguments with realists about this. I have sought to demonstrate that even in claims like &amp;ldquo;London is the capital of France&amp;rdquo;, you can find a context in which that could be held to be true.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Just imagine: there&amp;rsquo;s an economist talking to a set of bankers in Paris. And he begins by saying, &amp;ldquo;London is the capital of France&amp;rdquo;. And he goes on to show how he thinks that the power of the financial City of London means that it actually controls the economic framework in which Paris is operating. And that would then mean that his claim that &amp;ldquo;London is the capital of France&amp;rdquo; is true. So context is everything.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And I think the mistake that some critics of postmodernism make is to have a theological view about truth. I do think it's theological, really. They see themselves as scientists, they're attached to the idea that they can see how things are. And I am profoundly against that. It's a dangerous view, it makes you arrogant, it makes you think there's only one way of going about things and makes you dismissive of other people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;[At the same time,] I&amp;rsquo;ve spent most of my life criticising postmodernism, because in some forms it's completely incoherent. When it's expressed in the form, &amp;ldquo;there is no truth&amp;rdquo; &lt;span class="TextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0"&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;most of the time, that's incoherent, because that's a claim, which is supposedly a truism, you know: it is true, but there is no truth. Well, you&amp;rsquo;ve got something wrong there, and postmodernism is at risk of those sorts of criticisms. We have to work out how to move forward and create an overall framework that isn't self-contradictory in that way, or results in the chaos that some forms of postmodernism do, without thinking that we can just retreat to a sort of &amp;ldquo;theology of truth&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you make of political actors like Donald Trump and Vladimir Putin, who seem to be using a perverted version of postmodernist relativity to further their own agendas?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I think lots of different things are going on there. On the one hand, I do think that the intellectual culture of the west &lt;span class="TextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0"&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;which became more postmodernist, in many fields &lt;span class="TextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW84431935 BCX0"&gt;&amp;ndash;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; did mean that thinkers like Trump and Putin were able to echo that idea of alternative ways of putting things, in defence of their views. I mean, that postmodern way of looking at things wasn't &lt;em&gt;responsible&lt;/em&gt; for Trump and Putin, and I don&amp;rsquo;t think they both go around studying [deconstructionist philosopher] Derrida, but I think that in an inchoate sort of way it it enabled them to defend their position as an alternative perspective.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I'm going to add something much more controversial, though, in response to that, which is that [Trump and Putin] did also identify something &amp;ndash; which was that the main outlook of the liberal media in the west was largely the same. It had a similar framework and understood the world in a similar sort of way. And it assumed that this outlook was the truth, with a capital "T", and that everybody else was somehow lying if they held a different perspective.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Can you give us an example?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Well, if you look at the recent situation with Putin and Ukraine, you see this in action. So that initially, the response to Putin was &amp;ldquo;Oh, he's obviously deranged&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s not helpful to see the world like this: a person is behaving in a way which doesn't fit with how we see it, so he's obviously mad &amp;hellip; Putin&amp;rsquo;s way of seeing the world, as I understand it, is very much in terms of a Russian nationalist perspective, a Russian imperialist perspective to some extent, and he's wishing to extend Russian power. Now, we might think that's quite wrong. Of course, I think it's totally wrong. We should do everything we can to counter it. But it is not helpful to think, &amp;ldquo;Well, we've covered the truth. And he's just mad.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think it would be helpful for politicians to think more philosophically? To bring us back to the festival, is that something that HowTheLightGetsIn is attempting to do, by including politicians as speakers and guests?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We're always trying to do that. We&amp;rsquo;re trying to bring to bear the bigger questions on whatever the topic is. And that might be political. Obviously, at the moment, we're all very focused on [the Ukraine war]. But I think it applies in every area. So with science, we ask questions around, where are our current theories going? Are we achieving what we want to achieve? And that, in a way, is just bringing philosophy into culture.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about encouraging debate between disciplines?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The silo discipline of a lot of academic subjects means that these bigger questions tend to get overlooked in some form or another &amp;hellip; And that's why our speakers come, you know, all of these world-leading figures &amp;hellip; it's not a marketing exercise to promote your book. It's about talking about ideas. And all of the people we invite are fascinated by ideas. That's what really motivates them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And we also try and encourage a situation where people do genuinely mix. So for example, with our speakers, we don't have separate VIP areas, we encourage them to go out, you know, join the coffee queue like everyone else. You might be standing next to the world's leading scientist in a particular area, or a major politician. It also means that those people are really engaged. And we involve music and comedy and those sorts of things, because it softens all of that status stuff.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I mean, we all have to deal with the fact that, you know, life is a really puzzling thing. We're all going to die sometime. And we don't really understand what the hell's going on &amp;hellip; So [the festival is] providing that space where people can have that conversation &amp;ndash; whether it's on the dance floor, or in a comedy tent, or when they're talking about some technical philosophical point &amp;ndash; they can really engage in the question of what it is to be alive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;More details on HowTheLightGetsIn, the world's largest philosophy and music festival, can be found&lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=HL+Interview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="0"&gt; here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;New Humanist &lt;/em&gt;magazine is a philosophy partner of the festival, and we hope you can join us on 2-5th June on the River Wye in Hay. Along with headliners Yuval Noah Harari, Richard Dawkins, Roger Penrose and Slavoj Žižek, our editor, Samira Shackle, will be chairing an event on "Necessity and Lies".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Readers receive a 20% discount, with the code NEWHUMANIST20. &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=HL+Interview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner" data-auth="NotApplicable" data-linkindex="1"&gt;Advanced tickets&lt;/a&gt; are now on sale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For those of you who can't be with us in person, the festival will also be streaming online during the 2nd-5th June. All the debates and talks from the festival will also be released online in the months after. To access the livestream and video content, go to the Institute of Art and Ideas online platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=HL+Interview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGIHay2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;IAI.TV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5960/were-bringing-philosophy-into-british-culture#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-29T17:20:49Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-29T17:20:49Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Index: A History of the</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5943/index-a-history-of-the#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/index.jpg" height="577" alt="A history of the index" width="375" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Index: a history of the &lt;/strong&gt;(Allen Lane) by Dennis Duncan&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The history of the index, Dennis Duncan tells us, should not be of interest to bookish obsessives alone. Rather, it is one dotted with big personalities and scandals, as well as moral panics that hold contemporary relevance. The first indexes were made in the 13th century by the polymath Robert Grosseteste and Cardinal Hugh of Saint-Cher. In its infancy, the form sparked concerns that it might replace the role of books. The idea might sound ludicrous, but similar fears persist today: if people can find information immediately by &amp;ldquo;Googling&amp;rdquo; (Google is an index, as Duncan reminds us), what use have they for the written word?&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;We learn that the mere existence of the index relies on a number of features we now take for granted. One is the alphabet; another is the manufacturing of books in codex form, rather than scroll; yet another is page numbers. When Duncan tries to make use of a 14th-century index, he notices that it is basically useless. Why? Because scribes making copies of books back then paid little attention to pagination. This made indexes almost redundant; only the index in the book&amp;rsquo;s original version would be faithful. &amp;ldquo;Though indexes had been around for centuries,&amp;rdquo; says Duncan, &amp;ldquo;the printed page number would turbocharge their pervasiveness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;A running theme of the book is the overlapping of the spoken and the written word: one formative development for the index in the 12th century was that, for &amp;ldquo;an increasingly rootless, urban population&amp;rdquo;, there came a greater emphasis on preaching to the wider population. New readers needed new and &amp;ldquo;instantaneous&amp;rdquo; ways into the scriptures.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Another earlier development was the birth of universities in France and England. As indexes are useful to today&amp;rsquo;s students, so they would come to be useful for the often religious students of almost a millennium ago. &amp;ldquo;Disputation, the citing of authorities, the reading-out of commentaries (a format with a now familiar name: the &lt;span class="s1"&gt;lecture&lt;/span&gt;): scholastic learning would favour external demonstration over inner revelation, intellectual agility over endless meditation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;By the 18th century the index was, surprisingly, a subject divisive enough to invite disdain and incite literary bickering. Yet Duncan impresses on us the skill and sheer determination required to involve oneself in the world of indexing. Not only was it once painstakingly manual (like all work with books), but it required &amp;ndash; and requires &amp;ndash; the constant making of decisions about how material can be best categorised for the reader. &amp;ldquo;Its commitment is not to the author but to the reader, and to the arbitrary order of the alphabet,&amp;rdquo; Duncan writes of the index. In a modern age that prioritises the ready availability of information, this is particularly true. Since 2007, he notes, the hashtag has became one of many highly effective improvements in the way we arrange information we want immediate access to.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Often, Duncan indulges a likeable urge to treat this bookish history rather like a novel with protagonists: &amp;ldquo;What is their motivation?&amp;rdquo; he asks of Grosseteste and Saint-Cher. The book&amp;rsquo;s witty title also deserves special applause: &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Index, A History&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s1"&gt;of the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; encapsulates both the subject and tone of Duncan&amp;rsquo;s animated and amusing work. In a similar vein, one interesting avenue the book travels down is the discussion of whether or not fiction too should contain indexes, making reference to John Updike&amp;rsquo;s quip that &amp;ldquo;most biographies are just novels with indexes&amp;rdquo;. Though the reader might dismiss the idea as fanciful, Duncan provides examples of novelists using indexes either sincerely or as a way of subverting the form for laughs. As ever, the book educates and entertains in the same breath.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;As Duncan seeks to impress on the reader, the testament to the sophistication of the index is that we barely notice it, and instead take it for granted. This book ensures that, for a brief while at least, we do not.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5943/index-a-history-of-the#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-28T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-28T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Repeating Something Makes it Sound Truer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/why-repeating-something-makes-it-sound-truer/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Before I begin today’s video, I want to give a shout-out to my Patrons! They make these videos possible, and in exchange they get early ad-free videos, weekly newsletters, monthly Q&amp;A livestreams, and a smart …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131409</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T17:46:48Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T17:46:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are Russians Lying About Their Support for War in Ukraine?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/are-russians-lying-about-their-support-for-war-in-ukraine/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Recently I read that a survey of Russians found that 58% of them supported the country’s invasion of Ukraine. The figure came from a phone survey conducted by Russian researchers (who wish to remain anonymous) …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131406</id>
    <published>2022-03-24T16:42:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-24T16:42:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Many Children Do You Have?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/how-many-children-do-you-have/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So many people have sent me books on how to grieve. I have so many. I’ll tell you in the future about that. Tonight I want to tell you a story of love. When I met one of my stepchildren, we were not close. When I married their father, we were not close. The only …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131405</id>
    <published>2022-03-23T00:35:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-23T00:35:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meet me in the metaverse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5942/meet-me-in-the-metaverse#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="(Ollie Hirst)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/olliehirst_new_humanist_feb_cover.jpg" height="587" alt="Metaverse" width="800" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The metaverse leapt into popular awareness in 2021, in a world all too prepared for virtual sociality thanks to a year and counting of pandemic social distancing and Zoom Christmases. Last April, Epic Games announced $1 billion in investment to build &amp;ldquo;revolutionary&amp;rdquo; connected social experiences. In June, Facebook announced itself as &amp;ldquo;a metaverse company&amp;rdquo;, with 10,000 employees working on virtual reality products and experiences, and by October, it had rebranded itself as Meta, driving a flurry of commentary as people scrambled to work out what that might actually mean.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The word quickly made it into the Oxford English Dictionary, where it&amp;rsquo;s defined as &amp;ldquo;a virtual-reality space in which users can interact with a computer-generated environment and other users&amp;rdquo;. Venture capitalist Matthew Ball, whose &amp;ldquo;Metaverse Primer&amp;rdquo; essays have done a lot to shape thinking around the concept, wrote of it: &amp;ldquo;You can walk into any experience or activity, and potentially address almost any of your needs, from a single starting point or world that&amp;rsquo;s also populated by everyone else you know.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Online video games are probably the easiest way in to imagining the metaverse. They allow for flexibility of interaction (for example, while &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; began as a shooter game, it now tags itself as the place where you can &amp;ldquo;Watch a concert, build an island or fight&amp;rdquo;) as well as scale (&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has over 200 million players). There are also their highly developed internal economies and social organisation &amp;ndash; in &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Second Life&lt;/span&gt;, for instance, users can build houses and open businesses, which contribute to its $600 million economy.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;But the metaverse is potentially more than just a gateway to digital experiences. It crosses over into physical experiences too. Augmented reality, where the so-called IRL (&amp;ldquo;in real life&amp;rdquo;) world is visible alongside digital content, does not require special headsets or fancy glasses. Recall the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Pok&amp;eacute;mon GO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; craze of 2016, where collectible monsters manifested on street corners through the window of an ordinary phone screen. Pop star Ariana Grande has already played concerts in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, outfitted in flying, iridescent shards of virtual glass, complete with glowing white eyes. Perhaps next year you&amp;rsquo;ll attend a concert in full VR while your partner watches it via TikTok Live on their Apple glasses. The future is surely hybrid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Who owns this space is yet to be determined. We might hope for a pluriverse of platforms and experiences that we can explore as we desire, walking between worlds while bringing our identities, social relationships and digital possessions with us. Tech companies, however, seek monopolies. Interoperability will be challenging, requiring more cooperation than the Web 2.0 era of social media ever achieved.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Still, the metaverse does not have to be owned by a single company, whether Zuckerberg&amp;rsquo;s Meta or any other. In October 2021, San Francisco tech opinionator Shaan Puri offered a broader and more persuasive definition: &amp;ldquo;The metaverse is the moment in time where our digital life is worth more to us than our physical life.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s not new, he says, but rather &amp;ldquo;a gradual change that&amp;rsquo;s been happening for 20 years&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The cyberpunk origins of the metaverse&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Gradual then became sudden. The Covid-19 pandemic ruptured social interaction, with the CoMix social contact survey reporting that levels of social interaction plummeted 75 per cent during lockdowns, only recovering to about 50 per cent of pre-pandemic levels during the fairly unrestricted summer of 2020. In December 2021, Britons were averaging 2.7 contacts per day, barely higher than the first lockdown. We have seen a profound retreat to the nuclear family: sex outside a cohabiting relationship was literally illegal for several months, and lifestyle media is awash with talk of &amp;ldquo;pruning friendships&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;As metaverse discussions washed backwards and forwards last year &amp;ndash; at a time when I, living alone, went days without face-to-face social interaction &amp;ndash; I started to wonder whether I was not already living in a virtual world. Twitter, with its dramas and &amp;ldquo;main characters&amp;rdquo;, was a conversation I checked in on so many times a day it became a continuous, collective narrative. Discussions with friends (many of them also &amp;ldquo;extremely online&amp;rdquo;, as the phrase goes) would switch seamlessly between digital and offline events. Zoom calls gave me a daily fix of faces. A direct message turned into a date in VR Chat. I have always perceived my online interactions as real and significant, and during lockdown this proved a saving grace: that time may have been tedious, but I never felt disconnected. Virtual social interaction proved surprisingly sustaining. Worlds are ultimately created in the mind&amp;rsquo;s eye, not on a screen or a graphics chip. Language has had that conjuring power since time immemorial.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The metaverse is not in fact a new idea: the term was coined in 1992 by Neal Stephenson in his cyberpunk novel &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Snow Crash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;When you live in a shithole,&amp;rdquo; he wrote, &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rsquo;s always the Metaverse.&amp;rdquo; Stephenson famously described a virtual world owned and governed by corporations, mirroring the miseries of an anarcho-capitalist security state outside. It&amp;rsquo;s a 90s concept, then. So what can we learn from thinking about it through the actually existing online worlds of that time?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of the MUDs and MOOs of the 1980s and 90s: text-based &amp;ldquo;multi-user dungeons&amp;rdquo;. LambdaMOO was the largest and best-known, with around 10,000 users in 1994 and an architecture based on developer Pavel Curtis&amp;rsquo;s own California home. Players would enter through a space called the Coat Closet, which led on to the Living Room, a hangout and place for conversation (complete with a virtual gossiping cockatoo). Keyboard commands let you move &amp;ndash; left, right, up, down &amp;ndash; and upon entering a new room, a description would load on your screen, suggesting various possibilities for action. You could chat with other people in the room in the standard messaging manner.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;wo books provide a vivid record of life in these virtual worlds: &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;My Tiny Life: Crime and Passion in a Virtual World&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by Julian Dibbell in the US, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;The Cybergypsies: A True Tale of Lust, War, and Betrayal on the Electronic Frontier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Indra Sinha in the UK &amp;ndash; both published in 1999 but centred on events some years earlier.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sinha was an ad man. Tasked with writing copy to sell modems, he decided the first step had to be getting to know the internet, &amp;ldquo;the oases and caravanserais of cyberspace: this bulletin board, that multi-user game&amp;rdquo;. He quickly became hooked, staying up all night on secretive forums and running up phone bills of &amp;pound;700 a month. His marriage grew strained, but Sinha was intoxicated by the people he met: &amp;ldquo;Jarly the hacker, the lovely and lecherous Calypso, Luna the roleplayer who denied she was human&amp;rdquo;, as well as their stories. &amp;ldquo;What stories! seductions, vampings, fleecings, quarrels in cyberspace that turned into real world bomb threats, a feud that began with an online murder which ended up closing down a whole network,&amp;rdquo; he told the era-defining forum The WELL in 1999.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The book is freighted with insight for the potentials of life in the metaverse. Sinha emphasises how this virtual existence keeps bleeding into real life, and he sought to &amp;ldquo;convey the real experience of what it had been like to live in several worlds simultaneously&amp;rdquo; where &amp;ldquo;it was ALL real to me. All equally real, or equally unreal.&amp;rdquo; People keep crossing over, meeting up at parties and activist campaigns or turning up on each other&amp;rsquo;s doorsteps looking nothing like their characters online. Heightening this, Sinha utilises a flat narrative style in which it&amp;rsquo;s not always apparent where action is taking place. Emotions, especially, bleed over too. &amp;ldquo;The first lesson of cyberspace: that although everything around her, including herself, is fantasy, the terror is real.&amp;rdquo; Yet, as one of Sinha&amp;rsquo;s interlocutors tells him, &amp;ldquo;It is always important to draw the distinction between player and character&amp;rdquo;: that is, online life is a performance, and should be read as such.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;"A subset of the human imagination"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Meanwhile, Sinha describes his behaviour &amp;ndash; and that of his fellow travellers &amp;ndash; as an addict might: the telephone line to the modem &amp;ldquo;a hollow vein awaiting a needle&amp;rdquo; that might open up &amp;ldquo;a vast and chaotic world of the imagination&amp;rdquo;. The book&amp;rsquo;s marketing pitched it as a sequel to Thomas de Quincey&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Confessions of An English Opium Eater&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and it knowingly slips into the same traps: even when trying to convey the darkness of these virtual worlds, the phantasmagoria and the seduction remain compelling. Sinha later said in an interview that, ultimately, &amp;ldquo;cyberspace is nothing more or less than a subset of the human imagination&amp;rdquo;. This, to him, is both its blessing and its curse. The human imagination can chart some Stygian currents, and this is something the metaverse (and its governors) must confront.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Julian Dibbell, a technology journalist, gives us another story from these early virtual worlds, prefiguring what&amp;rsquo;s ahead. It is to my mind one of the canonical stories of online community, ethics, and what exactly it means to &amp;ldquo;be&amp;rdquo; on the internet. It&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;A Rape In Cyberspace&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 10pm in LambdaMOO, the text-based California house party. The entire experience is just databases and code, Dibbell reminds us: all of the entities present, &amp;ldquo;rooms, things, characters&amp;rdquo;, are just subprograms that interact &amp;ldquo;according to rules very roughly mimicking the laws of the physical world&amp;rdquo;. That night, a character called Mr Bungle brings a &amp;ldquo;voodoo doll&amp;rdquo; to the party &amp;ndash; a subprogram that attributes actions to other characters that their users did not actually create. They&amp;rsquo;re not entirely &amp;ldquo;kosher&amp;rdquo; in this space, we&amp;rsquo;re told, but they&amp;rsquo;re also often amusing.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;He could have sent a command to print the message &amp;lsquo;Mr._Bungle, smiling a saintly smile, floats angelic near the ceiling of the living room, showering joy and candy kisses down upon the heads of all below&amp;rsquo;,&amp;rdquo; Dibbell writes. Instead, Mr Bungle uses the program to simulate the violent rape and assault of a number of characters in the room, before the others present manage to work out how to disable him.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What has just happened? A few dozen young people, sitting at computer terminals, have seen a sequence of words appear and scroll down their screens. &amp;ldquo;No bodies touched&amp;rdquo;, Dibbell emphasises. Nobody even saw any graphic images. Yet, as the LambdaMOO community come together in the days after to talk through what has happened and what should be done, one of the women affected finds herself writing with &amp;ldquo;posttraumatic tears . . . streaming down her face&amp;rdquo;, which Dibbell takes as &amp;ldquo;a real-life fact that should suffice to prove that the words&amp;rsquo; emotional content was no mere fiction&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not calling for policies, trials, or better jails,&amp;rdquo; another victim later writes. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what I&amp;rsquo;m calling for. Virtual castration, if I could manage it. Mostly, [this type of thing] doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen here. Mostly, perhaps I thought it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t happen to me. Mostly, I trust people to conduct themselves with some veneer of civility. Mostly, I want his ass.&amp;rdquo; Thirty-odd people hash out all the possibilities. Had it merely been some kind of thought experiment, as Mr Bungle later claimed? Or should he be &amp;ldquo;toaded&amp;rdquo;, that is, killed? Through this deliberation, Dibbell writes, the party-goers &amp;ldquo;become, finally, the community so many of them already believed they were&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Viewed 30 years later, this episode may seem curiously utopian. Whatever we might say happened, here is a community taking harassment seriously. Mr Bungle was indeed &amp;ldquo;toaded&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a kind of social death, not just for his avatar but for the man behind it too, expelled from the LambaMOO community. Would gamers do the same today? I&amp;rsquo;m not sure of the answer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dibbell and Sinha were writing at a time when people were pretty confident that the online world wasn&amp;rsquo;t real. In 1993, the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; published Peter Steiner&amp;rsquo;s now famous cartoon, where one hound at a computer quips to another, &amp;ldquo;On the internet, nobody knows you&amp;rsquo;re a dog.&amp;rdquo; Back then, the internet was, as Sinha&amp;rsquo;s subtitle puts it, &amp;ldquo;the electronic frontier&amp;rdquo;, open and lawless. It had not yet been captured by business, and was far from its current enclosure by Big Tech.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Since then we have seen several iterations of this &amp;ldquo;reality&amp;rdquo; debate, which, I would argue, is really a discussion about how we should treat each other in the digital world. Do online actions have consequences, or does the fact they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; mean they&amp;rsquo;re immaterial? In &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Alone Together&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, psychologist Sherry Turkle fretted, &amp;ldquo;Does virtual intimacy degrade our experience of the other kind?&amp;rdquo; She argued that interacting with avatars simulating emotion posed a serious threat to our abilities to relate to one another IRL. Other scholars have explored the ways in which online relationships provide support &amp;ndash; for example, how LGBTQ young people used online communities to find solidarity. Online trolls were seen as tricksters until it became evident that they could cause real harm.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;A decade of digital change at once&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Then the pandemic arrived, and a decade or more of social and digital change happened all at once. Grandma learns how to use an iPad; Zoom&amp;rsquo;s stock price soars; people adjust to working with colleagues they&amp;rsquo;ve never met in the flesh. Finally, the idea of making any kind of neat online/offline, real/unreal distinction is put to bed as the fool&amp;rsquo;s errand it always was.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In his new book &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Reality+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, released in January, philosopher David J. Chalmers argues that we not only can but increasingly will live a meaningful life in virtual worlds. In an interview with the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;New York Times&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, he notes that &amp;ldquo;most of these basic kinds of things that matter you ought to be able to get in a virtual world&amp;rdquo;, from social relationships to learning, and setting and achieving goals. Being in a simulated environment does not make these experiences somehow &amp;ldquo;unreal&amp;rdquo; or insignificant, he argues: they may not be wholly the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; as IRL, while some experiences &amp;ndash; from awe at nature to the joys of embodiment &amp;ndash; are &amp;ldquo;a century&amp;rdquo; away from being replicated, or may never be. But, he told the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; Times&lt;/span&gt;, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s clear to me that virtual worlds have a lot to offer,&amp;rdquo; although &amp;ldquo;this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make them a panacea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The metaverse remains an apparition of speculation and hype, scepticism and hope. Technologically, the space is wide open, and some capabilities will not be fully realised for decades. Yet I wonder whether we&amp;rsquo;re talking about it now not only out of fascination with what&amp;rsquo;s next, but as a means of understanding the present day &amp;ndash; and the fact that the IRL and the virtual have already merged. Public life is profoundly shaped by the online &amp;ndash; politics, for example, is governed by WhatsApp groups and Twitter posting, and MPs use their time in parliament as a chance to create viral video moments. And vice versa: &amp;ldquo;Virtual space has to be understood as an embodied space in which actual-life selves, practices, and norms continue to exist,&amp;rdquo; the philosophers Katleen Gabriels and Marjolein Lanzing argue. This is why the &amp;ldquo;Bungle Affair&amp;rdquo; felt so violent for those involved, even though nothing ever physically happened.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rather than a discrete &amp;ldquo;place&amp;rdquo; that you may enter and exit from, it might be more helpful to imagine the metaverse as a persistent digital layer of reality. And as with the rollout of the internet in the first place, you won&amp;rsquo;t fully recognise what it is, until you realise you&amp;rsquo;re engulfed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5942/meet-me-in-the-metaverse#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T11:56:38Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T11:56:38Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What happened to British fair play?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5940/what-happened-to-british-fair-play#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Richmond Road in Bradford (Tim Green / Wikimedia Commons)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Welcome_to_Bradford__8027402174_.jpg" height="887" alt="Welcome to Bradford" width="1330" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;"I&amp;rsquo;m 40 and still regarded as a youth.&amp;rdquo; It was the early summer of 1995, and a local community worker of Pakistani-British heritage was showing me around the rough and sloping ground of a local youth cricket club in Bradford, West Yorkshire, run without any support from official sports bodies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d come up to make a special report for BBC News in the aftermath of the Manningham Riots, a short but intense period of youth rioting provoked by alleged police brutality in Bradford, which hosts the largest population of people of Pakistani heritage of any city in England. I was there to try to understand the roots of the violence, which had taken the nation by surprise. The un-level playing field proved a handy metaphor for how two generations of young British Asians were being failed by both indifference from the civic authorities at large and the conservative social strictures of their own community.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Twenty-five years later, after watching 30-year-old Azeem Rafiq testify before a Commons select committee in October 2021 about the spirit-breaking racism he&amp;rsquo;d endured for years, I remembered that encounter. The teen cricket prodigy, who grew up in Barnsley, 30 miles from Bradford, had captained England&amp;rsquo;s under-15s and became Yorkshire&amp;rsquo;s youngest ever captain.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Yorkshire County Cricket Club&amp;rsquo;s leadership stayed in denial until sponsors pulled out. Enemies then signed letters slandering Rafiq&amp;rsquo;s character and dredged up years-old tweets of antisemitic comments he had made (for which he showed full contrition and met Jewish organisations to make amends), thereby undermining the veracity of his own trauma. How could so little have changed?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the years I have come to realise that Bradford and its environs are emblematic of the UK&amp;rsquo;s wider social crises and broken promises. As a journalist from London, my 1995 post-riot visit offered a limited glimpse into how traditional political racial solidarity had been splintered by social and religious division. The book burnings of &lt;em&gt;The Satanic Verses&lt;/em&gt; in 1989 had been the first shock. Who were these people burning books for &amp;ldquo;blasphemy&amp;rdquo;? When I went back after the 2001 Bradford riots, this time for Channel 4 News, a white social worker informed me I was being &amp;ldquo;racist&amp;rdquo; for asking about forced marriage.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I met a female social worker who had previously been part of the domestic violence support group Southall Black Sisters and recently moved to the city. She told me she had attended a meeting where self-appointed male community leaders had demanded that all complaints of domestic violence be referred to them to be dealt with. The police would have agreed, she said, if she hadn&amp;rsquo;t been there to object.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Bradford was one of several English towns where in the past decade British Asian sexual grooming gangs have been convicted of abusing teenage girls. My own encounters in the city seemed evidence of a widespread culture of denial and misogyny, within council services and the police as much as in the community: a culture that had allowed abusers to prosper from Rochdale and Rotherham in Yorkshire to Telford and Oxford.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;There is more, however, to Bradford. As a member of the advisory board for the city&amp;rsquo;s National Science and Media Museum I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen in love with its grand Victorian buildings and the buzz of its brutalist Oastler market, selling food from across the globe. There&amp;rsquo;s a distinctive attitude and pride, while its citizens come up again and again with their own solutions to help tackle poverty and underachievement.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was hopeful when, in 2021, Channel 4 opened a new programming hub in Leeds as part of their commitment to the Leeds/Bradford area. What Bradford &amp;ndash; Britain&amp;rsquo;s ninth largest city &amp;ndash; desperately needed was proper transport infrastructure to make the most of it. But when HS2 was scaled back late last year, these plans were abandoned. Residents will continue to rely on an often-disrupted connection to Leeds, limiting opportunities and job prospects.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Azeem Rafiq should have been in his prime years on the England team. Instead, this sportsman has gone through the trauma of reliving the abuse and taunts before an audience. As if it defines him. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t. He&amp;rsquo;s a hero.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;If you want to know if politicians&amp;rsquo; pledges of levelling up are kept, watch Bradford and its nearby towns. They&amp;rsquo;ve seen too many broken promises over the past 25 years. When we finally invest properly in its infrastructure and treat its talented sons and daughters with the respect and care they deserve, we&amp;rsquo;ll know the truth about that much-claimed British value of fair play.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5940/what-happened-to-british-fair-play#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T08:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intolerance of Inquiry, Failures of Imagination</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/intolerance-of-inquiry-failures-of-imagination/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! A few days ago, Raif Badawi walked out of his prison cell.  A progressive Saudi writer, Badawi was arrested in 2012 on charges of “insulting Islam” and apostasy for daring to question religion and criticize the Saudi Arabian government through his website. The Center for Inquiry (CFI) …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978231</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VIDEO: Paul Offit on Medical Risk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/video-paul-offit-on-medical-risk/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We live in an unprecedented age of medical marvels, but success never comes free. In his third appearance on Skeptical Inquirer Presents, renowned virologist Paul Offit discussed the ideas behind his new book You Bet Your Life, explaining that the path to each medical advancement is paved with failures and risk.  “I wrote this book knowing …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978225</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dreaming of Mars and the Aliens Who Aren’t There</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/dreaming-of-mars-and-the-aliens-who-arent-there/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no evidence that Earth has ever been visited by extraterrestrials, yet many people are firmly convinced that aliens are among us. A team of researchers at California State University, Fresno, led by psychologist Matthew J. Sharps, set out to understand the psychological traits that influence a person’s beliefs about alien visitations and abductions. …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978223</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Raif Badawi Released from Prison</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/raif-badawi-released-from-prison/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Friday, March 11, global human rights activist Ensaf Haidar made a stunning announcement: her husband Raif Badawi, imprisoned in Saudi Arabia since 2012, had been released. In 2014, Badawi was found guilty of “insulting Islam” and given an egregious sentence: seven years in prison, which was soon increased to ten; a ten-year travel ban …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978218</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:12:05Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:12:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Carl Sagan’s Call to Enlightenment</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/carl-sagans-call-to-enlightenment/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Astronomer Carl Sagan left an inspiring legacy, sharing his love of science through his bestselling books, scientific work, and his groundbreaking series Cosmos. Robyn E. Blumner, executive director of the Richard Dawkins Foundation for Reason &amp; Science, reminds us that Sagan’s legacy and his passion for reason and discovery are also carried on by a magazine …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978214</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:10:08Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:10:08Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-container-2 wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-container-1 wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
