<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-03-11T22:34:19Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Russia has wacky conspiracy theorists, too?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/11/russia-has-wacky-conspiracy-theorists-too/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;If you spread kooky nonsensical ideas, you&amp;#8217;re likely to be infected with them too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Russian Defense Ministry: &amp;quot;&amp;#8230; the United States is training migratory birds to migrate from Ukraine to Russia and distribute bacteriological weapons&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One question. African or European? &lt;a href="https://t.co/XKJTJVNhLP"&gt;pic.twitter.com/XKJTJVNhLP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Howard Altman (@haltman) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/haltman/status/1502033752284872711?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 10, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m having a tough time pitying them now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If you spread kooky nonsensical ideas, you’re likely to be infected with them too. Russian Defense Ministry: "… the United States is training migratory birds to migrate from Ukraine to Russia and distribute bacteriological weapons" One question. African or European? pic.twitter.com/XKJTJVNhLP — Howard Altman (@haltman) March 10, 2022 I’m having a tough time pitying them […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=65913</id>
    <published>2022-03-11T17:10:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T17:10:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Damn homeopathy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/11/damn-homeopathy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Here’s a one-minute horror story, and a novel (to me) <a href="https://twitter.com/DoctorPallaviIn/status/1502137714073690114">rationalization for quackery</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy-500x615.png" alt="" width="500" height="615" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-65911" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy-500x615.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy-122x150.png 122w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy-244x300.png 244w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/homeopathy.png 589w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>The patient thinks that it is <em>good</em> that her breast lump has erupted into a bleeding, rotting mass, because that’s a sign that the homeopathic treatments were working, rather than failing. Yikes.</p>
<p>P.S. Important: in the name of all that is holy, do not Google “fungating”. It is not a portmanteau of “fun” and “gating” — the derivation is from “fungal”, and you do not want to see a breast with a fungating mass. It is horrifying to consider that so many people in human history have died of this ghastly disease.</p>
<p>And that is a multi-millennial horror story.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here’s a one-minute horror story, and a novel (to me) rationalization for quackery. The patient thinks that it is good that her breast lump has erupted into a bleeding, rotting mass, because that’s a sign that the homeopathic treatments were working, rather than failing. Yikes. P.S. Important: in the name of all that is holy, […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=65910</id>
    <published>2022-03-11T15:56:31Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T15:56:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It’s “SPRING” BREAK!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/11/its-spring-break/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I get a whole week off! I’ll use that time to catch up on grading and get a few lectures ahead, of course. It’s not like I’m going to be frolicking in the sunshine.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring-500x667.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="667" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-65908" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring-500x667.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring-113x150.jpg 113w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring-225x300.jpg 225w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/spring.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>-17°C right now. I wasn’t wearing enough layers this morning and really felt it.</p>
<p>We are going to do one thing fun, though: we’re driving east today, stopping for a brief while in St Cloud to visit Eldest Son, then off to Wisconsin to visit Youngest Granddaughter for a day. I may overdose on cuteness for the weekend.</p>
<p>Oldest Boy is adorable. Granddaughter is pretty sweet, too.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I get a whole week off! I’ll use that time to catch up on grading and get a few lectures ahead, of course. It’s not like I’m going to be frolicking in the sunshine. -17°C right now. I wasn’t wearing enough layers this morning and really felt it. We are going to do one thing […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=65907</id>
    <published>2022-03-11T15:31:24Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T15:31:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>PowerPoint is a tool for blaming faculty</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/11/powerpoint-is-a-tool-for-blaming-faculty/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">It’s true. <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/how-to-reverse-declining-history-major-enrollment-numbers-which-are-all-the-facultys-fault">It’s never the administration’s fault, always the faculty</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown-500x308.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="308" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-65904" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown-500x308.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown-150x92.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown-300x185.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/enrollmentsdown-768x473.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>That last line is too true. I suspect many mathematics professors feel that their discipline has been relegated to working as a service that gives basic training to the “sexier”, more popular majors, like chemistry, biology, and computer science. I hope this satire doesn’t give any administration the idea of merging math with accounting to save money. Quick, let them know that the mathematicians are all playing around with Greek letters and don’t know anything about arithmetic!</p>
<p>Oh, wait, let’s not forget, McSweeney’s is poking fun at the dismissal of <em>history</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong-500x308.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="308" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-65905" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong-500x308.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong-150x92.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong-300x185.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/whatarefacultydoingwrong-768x473.jpeg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>That is all correct. The Tulsa Massacre is depressing, and the English Civil Wars? Go ahead, ask any American who won it, and they won’t have a clue. They won’t even be able to name which side was which.</p>
<p>I have suddenly realized that the PowerPoint slides I use for genetics are also incredibly bland. Am I going to have to worry about my job? Please don’t merge biology with health services!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It’s true. It’s never the administration’s fault, always the faculty. That last line is too true. I suspect many mathematics professors feel that their discipline has been relegated to working as a service that gives basic training to the “sexier”, more popular majors, like chemistry, biology, and computer science. I hope this satire doesn’t give […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=65903</id>
    <published>2022-03-11T14:43:15Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T14:43:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Humor"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don’t forget the pandemic, you all!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/11/dont-forget-the-pandemic-you-all/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard-150x84.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="84" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-65901" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard-150x84.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard-300x169.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard-768x432.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard-500x281.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/graveyard.jpeg 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I know it’s easy to do — so many distractions! And the powers-that-be are eager for you to cast all caution to the winds! — but this is an ongoing, world-changing catastrophe. So here’s <a href="https://www.medpagetoday.com/infectiousdisease/covid19/97610">a refresher</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>The global COVID-19 death toll may be three times higher than official tallies suggest, according to a systematic analysis of excess mortality during the pandemic.</p>
<p>From Jan. 1, 2020 to Dec. 31, 2021, global deaths directly attributed to COVID-19 reached 5.9 million, yet estimates put excess deaths during this period at a staggering 18.2 million (95% uncertainty interval [UI] 17.9-19.6), Haidong Wang, PhD, of the University of Washington in Seattle, and the COVID-19 Excess Mortality Collaborators reported in The Lancet.</p>
<p>India had the highest number of excess deaths (4.07 million, 95% UI 3.71-4.36), an estimated eight times higher than its 489,000 reported COVID-19 deaths, which was followed by the U.S. (1.13 million, 95% UI 1.08-1.18), where the official count reached 824,000 by the end of 2021.</p></blockquote>
<p>Just remember, human beings, we can deal with more than one problem at once. It’s hard, but problems don’t disappear when a new one rises up.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I know it’s easy to do — so many distractions! And the powers-that-be are eager for you to cast all caution to the winds! — but this is an ongoing, world-changing catastrophe. So here’s a refresher. The global COVID-19 death toll may be three times higher than official tallies suggest, according to a systematic analysis […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=65900</id>
    <published>2022-03-11T14:04:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-11T14:04:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No child left behind</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5931/no-child-left-behind#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Parents fret that Covid-19 has created a generation of lost children. This needs to be corrected (Alamy Stock Photo)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2B17YBWs.jpg" height="836" alt="Two people hugging" width="1175" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Covid-19 spread across the world in 2020, millions of young people were taken out of school. Referred to as a &amp;ldquo;lost generation&amp;rdquo;, it is often assumed that these children will struggle, if not ultimately fail, to catch up on the days, weeks and months of education they could not access. The anxiety for themselves, their parents and their educators is animated by a fear that they have been damaged already, perhaps irreparably, and that their lives will be blighted forever. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But we know from the latest research into child and adolescent development that a young person&amp;rsquo;s ability to catch up should never be considered beyond reach. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t only hold true for education. Across the globe, &amp;ldquo;Catch Up&amp;rdquo; is a technical term applied to a much more fundamental process: the restoration of height, weight and cognition that has been lost as a result of malnutrition. We know from this process that young humans are extraordinarily resilient. With adequate care and support, they have a good chance of regaining what they have lost. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take much, as long as an essential first ingredient is present: the knowledge that children can recover from setbacks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The evolving science of nutrition&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The science of nutrition is relatively new. The first vitamin, B1, was isolated and chemically defined in 1926. By the 1950s, all the remaining essential micronutrients had been identified and synthesised. It was a transformation in our understanding of malnutrition. Starving children weren&amp;rsquo;t just lacking food, they were missing these minuscule but essential micronutrients. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Those of us with the luxury to do so get our iron, iodine and Vitamin A &amp;ndash; the three micronutrients that are vital preventatives of malnutrition &amp;ndash; from the regular food we buy at supermarkets. They enable our bodies to produce enzymes, hormones and other chemicals, and thereby create the messaging system that actually tells our cells to grow or develop or change. It is micronutrients that make us what we will eventually become, but many around the world struggle to access them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The best indication that micronutrients are absent from a child&amp;rsquo;s diet for long periods is stunting (when a child is too short for their age) and wasting (when a child is too thin for their age). A child may feel full from macronutrients (proteins, fats and carbohydrates), but if there are no micronutrients then their cells aren&amp;rsquo;t getting the messages to keep growing towards adulthood. So instead they go into a kind of cellular power conservation survival mode, ready for when the micronutrient going eventually gets better. This process is known as &amp;ldquo;thrifty growth&amp;rdquo;. The child&amp;rsquo;s energy is diverted towards basic survival: keeping their brain and lungs functioning optimally for as long as possible. Less energy, therefore, goes where it should, and their bones stop lengthening as a result. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But nothing can be thrifty for ever. Eventually energy runs out, and malnutrition starts to affect a child&amp;rsquo;s cognitive and behavioural development. Malnourished children have less energy to walk to school, and less ability to concentrate when they get there. It is therefore not only once-in-a-lifetime pandemics that keep children out of school; for many children living in conditions of war and famine, myriad factors combine to stop them from accessing education. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To date, the easiest way to restore micronutrients is to add them to what are called fortificant food premixes, or to provide them as concentrated supplements in the form of iodised salt, iron tablets and syrups, and Vitamin A capsules. But we are also taking our understanding of the role of micronutrients in new and wonderful directions. Through precise selective breeding, agri-nutritionists have created whole new families of potatoes and sweet potatoes that are &amp;ldquo;nutri-dense&amp;rdquo;, which means they grow with the highest possible pro-Vitamin A and enhanced iron content. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These crops aren&amp;rsquo;t only designed to combat malnutrition; they can also help us to meet the challenges of the climate crisis. Ensuring that what we grow has the maximum nutritional value will become increasingly important as the climate changes. This new class of vegetables is drought tolerant and doesn&amp;rsquo;t mind poor soil, which makes them easy to farm in the world&amp;rsquo;s increasingly hot and dry places, where children are already more likely to need micronutrient supplements.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;No more thrifty growth&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But correcting malnutrition is also a question of timing. Scientists often talk about &amp;ldquo;the first thousand days&amp;rdquo; of a child&amp;rsquo;s life as being the most important for interventions. All micronutrient supplements are best at generating Catch Up when the little human taking them is &amp;ndash; or should be &amp;ndash; undergoing a growth spurt. Supplements should therefore be given in the earliest years of life, when their cells should be fizzing with activity and potential. Across the world, studies show that malnourished children up to the age of three who receive micronutrient supplementation begin to grow again. Perhaps they won&amp;rsquo;t be quite as tall as the international height standard for their region, but nevertheless, they can be put onto the right track. And it means much more than merely taller children with longer legs. It means the messages generated by micronutrients are getting to the right places, stimulating the cell growth and development that are also needed for cognitive development. No more thrift. Children that have fallen behind catch up, both mentally and physically.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The &amp;ldquo;thousand days&amp;rdquo; window is extremely important. But we have recently begun to recognise that there is another crucial window of opportunity. Humans have two significant growth spurt periods in their life: one in the first thousand days; the other during adolescence, when puberty occurs. This second growth spurt is every bit as vital to our adult development as the first one. Humans get about 25 per cent of their eventual height during their teenage years, and like those first thousand days, we rely on the chemical messaging of the micronutrient system to get this rapid growth phase in our development done. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The need for energy and micronutrients will never be higher than it is in adolescence. This is the point when the micronutrients should be messaging the hormones to tell the brain to develop voluntary-control mechanisms and executive function: the means whereby people get to choose their behaviours, understand their choices, make plans and see them through. If the messages don&amp;rsquo;t get through, it isn&amp;rsquo;t just leg length that is profoundly limited. Cognitive development is every bit as likely as bone length to be stunted and eventually wasted. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Adolescents, however, don&amp;rsquo;t receive enough attention, despite the possibilities presented for their Catch Up. In fact, studies from across the world are starting to come in that show that when micronutrient supplementing measures are applied to malnourished adolescents, Catch Up happens much more quickly, significantly and observably than it does in the toddler cohort. Restoring the right amount of nutritious food to teenagers means they do what they are meant to do, and grow to become healthy adults. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So why don&amp;rsquo;t we see more programmes and funding directed at teenagers in need, particularly as such interventions are reasonably affordable? It seems that the science is being held back by our prejudices. It&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to fund science on adolescents because society is wary of vaguely threatening young male teenagers living in difficult places where conflict drives their hunger. Their rough skin and narrowed eyes, full of fear and aggression, don&amp;rsquo;t make for good photographs in funding applications. For no good reason, it is often assumed that it&amp;rsquo;s too late to restore what has been lost to these vulnerable young men who are no longer children but have become a frightening, potentially dangerous population. Instead, the round, tear-filled eyes of the hungry toddler, cradled in its mother&amp;rsquo;s arms, gets all the oxygen in the funding room, and most of the money. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is a huge wasted opportunity &amp;ndash; for girls as well as boys. Thus far, everything we know about the potential of adolescent Catch Up comes from studying groups in developed nations: young people who are malnourished for a range of reasons other than conflict or famine, including patients who are congenitally deficient in hormones, who have coeliac disease, or whose bones have been stunted by conditions such as cerebral palsy. Whatever the reason for what is technically termed &amp;ldquo;affluent stunting&amp;rdquo;, micronutrient restoration produces Catch Up in these adolescents, steadily and permanently. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be difficult to adapt this research to create an infrastructure to enable adolescent Catch Up all over the non-affluent world, and it&amp;rsquo;s likely to result in better fed teenagers who make more thoughtful decisions about the rest of their lives. The Lancet&amp;rsquo;s launch in November of a series on adolescent nutrition, acknowledging that the field is &amp;ldquo;overlooked in policy and investment&amp;rdquo;, is a welcome development, but much more needs to be done. The essential first step, of course, would be accepting that these teenagers are worthy of the effort.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The fundamental value of nurture&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is another major area upon which we could improve, and that is prevention. Everyone agrees that prevention is better than cure. Ending world hunger would be excellent, but in the meantime what can be done to delay the point at which hunger becomes malnutrition and thrift becomes loss? The answer is perhaps unexpected, but even more hopeful than the progress with micronutrient-generated Catch Up. This is because it is something we already do well, across the world and relatively cheaply: we vaccinate. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Vaccinations are so very helpful in achieving Catch Up because malnutrition is not just about not enough good food. It also happens because our immune systems, for some evolutionary reason, are not part of the thrifty growth system. When a child&amp;rsquo;s physiology begins to conserve energy, the immune system is immediately diminished, leaving them vulnerable. So the hungry child gets infections everywhere, but especially in the gut, where they cascade catastrophically, starving the child from inside as well as out. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This quickly becomes a vicious cycle. Even when micronutrient levels are restored with supplements, the energy that should be resuming growth patterns stays fighting the effects of infection. The result: no Catch Up, just a slow diversion of resources into a cycle of hunger and sickness. In a vaccinated child, however, the chemical messages aren&amp;rsquo;t wasted fighting infections, but go where they are needed to generate positive growth and development.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not only do vaccinations help break the malnutrition-immune dysfunction cycle, they also fill in the immunity gap. This is because vaccinations can generate what are technically called &amp;ldquo;beneficial non-specific effects&amp;rdquo;. It means that a BCG shot, for instance, given against TB or leprosy, also strengthens the whole immune response in each child that receives it, and therefore gives better overall resistance to disease. Another example is the measles vaccine, which gives the same fortificant power to the overall developing immune system, as well as no more measles. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not all vaccinations have this ability. The pneumonia vaccine, for example, simply does what it says on the vial. And the BCG vaccination has to be given as early in the first thousand days as possible in order to achieve its best effects. If it&amp;rsquo;s done right, a vaccinated child has higher haemoglobin levels than an unvaccinated child and is therefore less likely to need iron supplements. This is because vaccinations have ensured that at least one of its micronutrients is doing just fine, getting the important messages to wherever in the body they are needed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t yet know if something similar happens with teenage vaccinations. But that&amp;rsquo;s only because we haven&amp;rsquo;t looked yet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One more thing. When a child is taken for their vaccination, we can see a process at work that is as fundamental to achieving proper nutrition in its widest possible sense as feeding is. A vaccinated child is a nurtured child. If the child is held and comforted during the process, their tears wiped away and their paper record card carefully kept until next time, then they are receiving nurturing care. Nurturing generates cognitive stimulation, just as micronutrients do. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A child that isn&amp;rsquo;t nurtured isn&amp;rsquo;t only less likely to be vaccinated. If no one reads them a story at a regular bedtime or ensures they are warm, comfortable and able to dream their way through untroubled nights, then they may never be able to read a story all the way to the end for themselves. Even if they can walk to school they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to do much when they get there. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This holds for teenagers too. If no one listens to the aspirations of an adolescent, and if they aren&amp;rsquo;t encouraged to stay in school for as long as possible, then even if their bellies are full they too will be held back and eventually fall behind. Literacy is as a good marker as vaccination status as to whether or not a child or adolescent is receiving the essential ingredients of nurturing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Healthcare by other means&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet for all the work being done to increase vaccinations, and despite a 70 per cent drop worldwide in vaccine-preventable deaths since 2000, there are reckoned to be 20 million children who are under-vaccinated, which means they may have received no or only some of their vaccinations. It&amp;rsquo;s not because of funding shortages. Vaccines are efficient and inexpensive, and vaccinators are never short on energy and courage. But vaccinations stall in particular regions in the world because of political instability, poor communications and community dysfunction &amp;ndash; for all sorts of reasons that don&amp;rsquo;t need more science for resolution, just better human activity and wider peace. In the meantime, the gap remains.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A good place to start bridging the gap would be through the sustainable development goals (SDGs) set by the UN for realisation in 2030. We should make a new goal, specifically aimed at optimising current vaccination strategy systems so that every young person may have an optimised immune system. That is a good place to start, because vaccinations are healthcare systems by other means, easy and cheap to establish. This new SDG could probably be brought in ahead of schedule because it only needs a bit more science, some improved communications and logistics and &amp;ndash; perhaps the most significant challenge of all &amp;ndash; for us to set aside our prejudices about who is deserving of our care and attention, of our best and most expensive research efforts. If we have two chances per human to optimise immune systems and therefore generate Catch Up, then we should take them both, and let no one fall behind. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are no lost generations, just the ones we prefer not to see. Catch Up, wherever you look for it, depends on human beings doing things we already know how to do, and doing them as well as they can possibly be done for every single child and adolescent who needs them. Young people themselves &amp;ndash; with their remarkable resilience and ability to survive &amp;ndash; will do most of the rest, given just a little of the right support.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5931/no-child-left-behind#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-10T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-10T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Race for Tomorrow and We Have a Dream</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5929/book-review-race-for-tomorrow-and-we-have-a-dream#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="18-year-old activist Mya-Rose Craig undertakes the most northerly ever climate strike, in the Arctic (Daniella Zalcman / Greenpeace)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/GP1SUDBB_High_resS.jpg" height="1041" alt="18-year-old activist Mya-Rose Craig undertakes the most northerly ever climate strike, in the Arctic" width="1562" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Climate change primers are not an easy task. How can our civilisation&amp;rsquo;s greatest challenge be rendered in a digestible form that doesn&amp;rsquo;t utterly depress its readers but rather compels them past the first chapter? Enter two new works by Simon Mundy and Mya-Rose Craig. Both refuse to get bogged down in either dystopian futures or endless statistics, choosing instead to focus on the stories of people across the world whose daily experiences of environmental change, along with their efforts to tackle it, can help us to make sense of this mind-boggling situation.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the last 15 years as an environmental campaigner, I&amp;rsquo;ve seen the different ways we&amp;rsquo;ve tried, and often failed, to convey the magnitude of the problem. We&amp;rsquo;ve taken turns focusing on economic cost, lives lost, or worsening manifestations like the recent floods and droughts. We tried sneaking climate more indirectly into communications around issues like fuel poverty and air pollution. Now, thankfully, it feels as though we are finally putting the emergency back where it needs to be: front and centre. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;Race for Tomorrow&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;We Have a Dream &lt;/em&gt;are part of this trend, which recognises that there is no one single answer to the catastrophe. To write a book about what Mundy describes as &amp;ldquo;by far the biggest story of the century&amp;rdquo;, to &amp;ldquo;avoid getting lost in the sprawling mass of information, with a subject that touches every part of the planet&amp;rdquo;, both authors have opted to highlight multiple narratives from across the world. Craig&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;We Have a Dream&lt;/em&gt;, written primarily for young people to inspire them into action, focuses on raising up the voices of young Indigenous people and people of colour. Mundy, who writes for those taking their first foray into the complexity of the issue, journeys across the world interviewing fascinating people playing very different roles in the fight against climate change. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Adapting to our new reality is a feature of any book now being written about climate change. But as Mundy says when visiting Venice to report on its new ocean barrier developed to protect the city from rising seas, &amp;ldquo;the barrier is less a promise of a new future than a gigantic symbol of all that has gone wrong in the past&amp;rdquo;. He recalls the climate scientists arriving on Maldivian atolls to chart when a village will disappear, not if. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In &lt;em&gt;We Have a Dream&lt;/em&gt;, young activist Litokne Kabua tells us how nearly two thirds of the homes in his Marshall Islands community have washed away after extreme weather events and the degradation of coral reefs that protect the islands from storm waves. Adaptation alone will never be enough to safeguard the most vulnerable, who have had no hand in creating this mess &amp;ndash; and both books thankfully still choose mitigation of climate change&amp;rsquo;s worst impacts as their focus.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Lawyers and activists vs. the fossil fuel companies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;I am always pleasantly surprised when reading books about the environment to come across a statistic that grabs my attention, and Mundy doesn&amp;rsquo;t disappoint. I had to put the book down and take a deep breath after learning that mountain glaciers are retreating by 10,000 tonnes per second. Woven into his journey are a number of such facts, before he moves on to another story from an entirely different perspective. It is a pace that occasionally risks sacrificing complexity. Yet on the whole he captures many of the trade-offs, conflicts and double standards at play in the fight for climate action. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The chapter on Bangladesh manages this especially well. It explores the conflict between Sheikh Hasina&amp;rsquo;s much lauded climate rhetoric on the world stage and her despotism at home. The culprits of this crisis, however, enter a little late. Fossil fuel companies make their first appearance about halfway through the book, via the incredible story of the Filipino lawyers and activists challenging Shell. Yet their role is intrinsic to every single story Mundy tells. Similarly, we have to wait until the final section for the entry of the US and China, despite their fundamental role in destroying the environment and in developing the climate adaptation infrastructure he visits across the globe. But if the villains take a while to appear, the rallying call of those fighting them features throughout &amp;ndash; and there is no equivocation about the need for climate justice.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The increasingly popular call for rich countries to take responsibility forces us to confront the reality that, just as climate change is linked to other planetary tipping points, such as biodiversity loss, it also cannot be isolated from systemic injustices and global inequalities. The very premise of Craig&amp;rsquo;s book highlights this fact, choosing only activists who, like the author, are people of colour and/or who represent Indigenous communities. Unsurprisingly for a book with intersectionality at its heart, its focus is rarely exclusively on climate: addressing rights for Indigenous communities living through frighteningly rapid change in the Arctic, efforts to conserve wildlife in Bangladesh, and the challenges of air pollution in Singapore. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The stories in &lt;em&gt;We Have a Dream&lt;/em&gt; implicitly remind us that climate change is a threat multiplier: it makes other problems worse, and by what magnitude is very hard to predict. What we know is that inequality, conflict and resulting mass migration can be worsened by climate change, while some environmental threats, like interference with the nitrogen cycle, can also compound it. As an inspiring activist herself (I worked with Craig when one of Greenpeace&amp;rsquo;s ships took her to the Arctic for the most northerly ever climate strike), she streamlines the information most likely to spur action in her readers. The stories she promotes &amp;ndash; each accompanied by vibrant, beautiful illustrations by Sabrena Khadija &amp;ndash; follow the same format. We are introduced to 30 inspiring individuals: their backstories, dreams for the future, and the moment they first realised environmental activism was for them. For a younger reader, the book might well prove transformative. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As primers for quite different audiences, neither work attempts to be exhaustive in its scope. With climate change, such a task is virtually impossible. Instead, I was left at the end of each book wanting more, and therein lies their success. In fact, it would be hard to finish either as a newcomer to the subject, or to climate activism, and not immediately go out to try and learn more. And that is exactly what these authors want to happen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5929/book-review-race-for-tomorrow-and-we-have-a-dream#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-07T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-07T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Trans Children and the 8th Corporal Act of Mercy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/trans-children-and-the-8th-corporal-act-of-mercy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am about to write about religion on the Skepchick site. Seriously, the other redhead in this joint should kick me out while she still can. I am a Catholic. On the Skepchicks. If you keep reading, it’s at your own spiritual peril. You have been warned. I have come to call this time of …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=9_K4eX9q3ns:rVgI8zu7nM8:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131391</id>
    <published>2022-03-07T05:51:44Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-07T05:51:44Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>An Update on Sanity, Ukraine, and the Loss of a Child…</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/an-update-on-sanity-ukraine-and-the-loss-of-a-child/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been one month since Little I died. If you feel compelled, you can donate to the things he loved in life. What follows, is heartache. On Friday at 1:50 pm I sat in my office looking at my calendar and realized I physically could not move from my chair. I wanted to go …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=8ukMRnS0c3c:mB2uS6y7p30:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131389</id>
    <published>2022-03-06T12:19:30Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-06T12:19:30Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>"With Havana Syndrome, the US government has spent five years chasing ghosts"</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5939/with-havana-syndrome-the-us-government-has-spent-five-years-chasing-ghosts#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img title="A US flag on the dashboard of a car in Havana, Cuba (H. L. Tam / Flickr)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-03-03-at-10.51.31.jpg" height="954" alt="US flag Cuba" width="1330" /&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Robert W. Baloh and Robert E. Bartholomew published &amp;ldquo;Havana Syndrome: Mass Psychogenic Illness and the Real Story Behind the Embassy Mystery and Hysteria&amp;rdquo; (Springer) in March 2020. Bartholomew is Honorary Senior Lecturer in the Department of Psychological Medicine at the University of Auckland in New Zealand, and Baloh is a distinguished professor at the David Geffen School of Medicine at University of California, Los Angeles. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Your book makes the argument that so-called &amp;ldquo;Havana syndrome&amp;rdquo;, whereby US officials and others claim to be victims of mysterious sonic or &amp;ldquo;pulsed energy&amp;rdquo; attacks by Cuba, is in fact nothing more than a mass psychogenic illness &amp;ndash; a form of mass hysteria in which symptoms are experienced as if they were real. What makes you so sure of this? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; There is not a shred of credible evidence that there ever were attacks. After five years, no weapon has been found and there is not a single intelligence intercept suggesting there was a weapon. While the US military has researched the use of acoustical and microwave weapons, they have not been able to develop a practical device due to the laws of physics. There is a big difference between researching something and developing a practical weapon.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What therefore do you make of US claims that these &amp;ldquo;attacks&amp;rdquo; have produced, among others, brain damage?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; The claims of brain damage, changes to white matter [nerve fibres found in the deep tissue of the brain] and hearing loss are the product of inaccurate reporting. In December 2017, information was leaked to the media about a study that was being conducted on US Embassy patients which showed mysterious white matter tract changes in their brains. Media outlets around the world reported on the strange &amp;ldquo;brain anomalies&amp;rdquo;. Then, in February 2018, the study appeared in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of the American Medical Association&lt;/em&gt;. Yet only three of the patients exhibited white matter tract changes, which is the same distribution you would expect to find in a normal population because white matter changes are common in everything from depression to migraines to normal ageing.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Then there were the reports of brain damage after the publication of a 2019 study in the same journal. Again, the story made headlines, with many media outlets reporting on the &amp;ldquo;brain damage&amp;rdquo; suffered by the diplomats. However, brain anomalies are not the same as brain damage. While they did find anomalies, it is not unusual to find minor anomalies in small patient cohorts due to individual variation, given they can be caused by exposure to long-term stress.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As for reports of hearing loss, that never happened either. In 2018, the results of a study on US diplomats who were reportedly suffering from Havana Syndrome were leaked. The media was soon reporting that one-third of the patients in the study were experiencing hearing loss. However, when the study was published that December, only two patients had hearing loss, and in both cases, it had occurred &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; they were even posted to Cuba. The remainder thought they had hearing loss, but when given a standard hearing test, it proved to be unfounded.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The head of one US association that represents current and former diplomats and foreign aid workers recently stated that victims have suffered &amp;ldquo;real trauma and real injury&amp;rdquo;. If it were indeed psychological, how could the consequences be so severe? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew: &lt;/strong&gt;Mass psychogenic illness symptoms are as real as any other medical condition, but their origin is non-organic. It is not just &amp;ldquo;all in their heads&amp;rdquo;. They are experiencing real symptoms and both Professor Baloh and I are sympathetic to their suffering. But telling them they have brain damage only exacerbates their condition.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh&lt;/strong&gt;: The key difference is that there is no evidence of brain injury or brain damage. MRI scans of the brain have been normal and there are no neurological abnormalities on examination. The non-specific test abnormalities that have been reported are commonly seen in patients with stress-related neurological disorders such as anxiety and post-traumatic stress disorder.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There have now been some 1,000 cases of Havana Syndrome reported worldwide. How is it able to spread across geographies in the way it has? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh&lt;/strong&gt;: In fact this is strong support for a diagnosis of psychogenic illness. Diplomatic and state department officials were warned to be on the outlook for symptoms and to immediately report them. This caused them to focus and ruminate on routine body symptoms that nearly everyone experiences. They developed negative expectations, called the &amp;ldquo;nocebo effect&amp;rdquo;, and by attending to the symptoms, the symptoms were amplified and required less activation for conscious awareness.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; Like all outbreaks of mass psychogenic illness, you need to understand the context. You need to go back to patient zero. It began in a small unit of CIA officers in Havana in late 2016. For weeks they had been hearing mysterious sounds &amp;ndash; then one day one of them presented to the US Embassy clinic with a headache and ear pain, and a theory emerged that they were being harassed by a new acoustical weapon. The story then spread through the small CIA unit, and not long after, to the US and Canadian embassies which had a close relationship and were sharing information. The sonic attack hypothesis may seem like an odd assumption at first, but you have to put yourself in their shoes. The notion that they were harassed seemed plausible because there is a long history of Cuban agents harassing diplomats. For instance, during the Cold War, agents would sneak into their houses while they slept and rearrange furniture, leave cigarette butts on their kitchen table and open all the windows so the house would become filled with mosquitos. The diplomats who were sent to the new Embassy in Havana in 2015 had been briefed on this.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;However, there&amp;rsquo;s an old saying: &amp;ldquo;When you hear the sounds of hoofbeats in the night, first think horses not zebras.&amp;rdquo; The doctors in the US State Department went for the most exotic hypothesis early on &amp;ndash; they were searching for unicorns when they should have stuck to more mundane explanations. Of the first 21 victims in Cuba, eight recorded their &amp;ldquo;attacks&amp;rdquo;, and a panel of scientists later concluded that the sounds aligned closely with the mating call of the Indies short-tailed cricket [an insect local to Cuba]!&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;One alleged cause of &amp;ldquo;Havana Syndrome&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; sound waves &amp;ndash; has been seen before in instances of mass psychogenic illness. Can you explain the brief life of &amp;ldquo;acoustic shock&amp;rdquo; in the early days of telephones? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh:&lt;/strong&gt; Acoustic shock, which is discussed in detail in our book, has many parallels with Havana Syndrome. In the early days of telephones, people developed a wide spectrum of symptoms including headache, dizziness, tinnitus and brain fog after hearing a brief disturbing sound on a telephone. Typically, the sound, if recorded, was not that impressive. The condition was initially called an &amp;ldquo;ear concussion&amp;rdquo; even though there was no evidence of ear damage.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;History is littered with stories of such mass hysterias: the dancing manias of the Middle Ages; the laughter epidemic in Tanzania in 1962; mass fainting at a school in Blackburn, England in 1965. What makes us susceptible to them? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; In a word: plausibility. There is an old saying: &amp;ldquo;Talk of the devil and he is bound to appear.&amp;rdquo; In Salem in 1692, a belief in the devil altered the perceptual sets of the local residents whose worldview included the reality of witches and demons. In Salem, when the cry of &amp;ldquo;Witch!&amp;rdquo; went up, believers went searching for evidence to confirm it. If someone visited and you fell sick soon after, it was evidence of witchcraft. It&amp;rsquo;s not that dissimilar to Havana Syndrome because many of the symptoms are so vague as to be experienced by nearly everyone on the planet in any given week: fatigue, difficulty concentrating, forgetfulness, insomnia, dizziness, confusion, disorientation, ear pressure and pain.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh:&lt;/strong&gt; Although the human brain is a remarkable organ, it has &amp;ldquo;design flaws&amp;rdquo; that make it vulnerable to suggestion and manipulation. Advertisers and politicians routinely take advantage of these flaws to influence our behaviour with regards to purchases and voting. These design flaws can be traced to both nature and nurture. Many of our emotions and behaviours are ingrained in the primitive deep brain modules encoded by genes that evolved over millions of years of evolution. We are susceptible to irrational fears that can change the chemistry and physiology of our brain and body, leading to a wide range of symptoms.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;US government officials don&amp;rsquo;t exactly fit the typical profile of victims of mass hysteria, who are often either young or not informed by western science and medicine. What conditions in their line of work might have produced it? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh: &lt;/strong&gt;First, these are common misperceptions about victims of mass psychogenic illness, in part due to &amp;ldquo;historical baggage&amp;rdquo; associated with the word &amp;ldquo;hysteria&amp;rdquo;. Mass psychogenic illness can affect anyone regardless of age, gender or level of education. It often begins in close-knit groups living in stressful situations and is amplified by politics and cultural beliefs.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; We do not claim that victims of psychogenic illness are &amp;ldquo;crazy&amp;rdquo;, mentally ill or are psychologically weak. It is a collective stress response that is based on a belief. We all have beliefs, and therefore everyone is potentially susceptible. That includes highly trained and well-educated intelligence officers.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;While CIA agents appear to have been over-represented as victims, that is readily explainable. In Havana, intelligence agents were viewed as the first targets and intelligence officers around the world were warned that they might be next, thus resulting in agents being hyperaware of their health and creating a self-fulfilling prophecy. It is important to remember that not every victim is experiencing mass psychogenic illness. Many are simply redefining an array of common and uncommon health conditions under a new label: &amp;ldquo;Havana Syndrome&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why might the US government be so resistant to accepting that this could be the work of something other than a hostile state? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; I believe that embarrassment is a big factor. It is embarrassing to think that they have spent five years chasing ghosts, and in the process, wasted tens of millions of taxpayer dollars investigating claims of an imaginary secret weapon that turned out to be the mating calls of crickets.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh: &lt;/strong&gt;They have also backed themselves into a corner, having strongly supported the notion of an attack by a hostile state from the very onset. Some politicians have demanded retaliation even though we have no idea who to retaliate against. Other politicians have specifically used the foreign attack theory to further their agenda against Cuba. Furthermore, &amp;ldquo;victims&amp;rsquo; groups&amp;rdquo; have powerful political allies and they refuse to even consider the possibility of psychogenic illness. Even mentioning the term can lead to immediate sanctioning.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are a range of potentially serious outcomes &amp;ndash; both political and scientific &amp;ndash; that arise from this. In what ways could it prove consequential beyond just being a matter of intrigue? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Baloh: &lt;/strong&gt;Obvious political consequences are the breakdown in relations with Cuba and possible future actions against other countries despite the lack of evidence of an &amp;ldquo;attack&amp;rdquo;. With regards to the &amp;ldquo;victims&amp;rdquo; of the proposed attacks, telling them that they have brain damage caused by some type of mysterious weapon is a prescription for a life with chronic debilitating symptoms. Their symptoms are real but they need to be reassured that they do not have permanent brain damage and that they can be treated and get well.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Robert Bartholomew:&lt;/strong&gt; The real danger that this case poses is to highlight the potential for politics to become mixed with science. The implications are enormous, from vaccination uptake to global warming. The effectiveness of vaccines and the reality of global warming are settled science, but in the social media and fake news age, misinformation abounds.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5939/with-havana-syndrome-the-us-government-has-spent-five-years-chasing-ghosts#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-04T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-04T04:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What the Science Says About Trans Teens on Puberty Blockers (CW: Self-Harm)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/what-the-science-says-about-trans-teens-on-puberty-blockers-cw-self-harm/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Last month Ken Paxton, the current Attorney General of Texas, published a nonbinding opinion that parents who provide their trans kids with science-based medical care should be investigated for child abuse. This was quickly …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=GrOtOM2dr0M:LUb_IA5ChIc:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131385</id>
    <published>2022-03-04T00:24:45Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-04T00:24:45Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>White fright in America</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5928/white-fright-in-america#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="The Jan 6 2021 Capitol Hill mob (Flickr/Tyler Merbler)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2021_storming_of_the_United_States_Capitol_09__cropped_.jpg" height="545" alt="The Jan 6 2021 Capitol Hill mob" width="800" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Ever since 6 January 2021, when a pro-Trump mob stormed the US Capitol, pundits have busily questioned who exactly were the people who engineered what many consider to be one of the darkest moments in US political history. The photos of the mob offered little clarity: one man wore horns and animal fur, others wore militia uniforms; still others looked as if they&amp;rsquo;d breezed in off the streets. Speculation tended to take the place of hard data.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;University of Chicago researchers have now given a clearer view of the profile of participants, and it complicates traditional assumptions of the nature and make-up of far-right movements. They were largely middle-class, and included doctors, CEOs and other white-collar professionals. In other words, they came from the mainstream of US society, not from an aggrieved economic fringe.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The research, published in &lt;em&gt;Foreign Policy&lt;/em&gt; magazine in January, also shows that for all the diversity of backgrounds, one anxiety united most of those present: that of an ascendent non-white majority. More than half of the 716 people arrested or charged for the insurrection, the report said, &amp;ldquo;come from counties [in the US] where the white share of the population is declining fastest&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Their fears align with a conspiracy theory known as the Great Replacement, popularised a decade ago by Renaud Camus. Camus was a former darling of the French left, a prolific gay writer whose earlier work was feted by Allen Ginsberg, Roland Barthes and others, but who, by the late 1990s, had come to see evidence of &amp;ldquo;ethnic and civilisational substitution&amp;rdquo; underway in western countries. One day, in rural southern France, he saw the &amp;ldquo;replacement&amp;rdquo; materialise before him. &amp;ldquo;You would go to a fountain, six or seven centuries old, and there were all these North African women with veils!&amp;rdquo; he told the New Yorker in 2017. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;His ideas already had an audience in France &amp;ndash; far-right leader Marine Le Pen had asked in 2011: &amp;ldquo;How could we be satisfied to see our adversaries continue their work of moral and economic ruin of the country, to let it be taken over by an organised replacement of our population?&amp;rdquo; But they were quickly taken up by white supremacists elsewhere who saw demographic shifts in the US and Europe as proof of a catastrophic upending of supposedly age-old hierarchies. Trump played heavily into this fear with his so-called &amp;ldquo;Muslim ban&amp;rdquo; (Camus believes that white Europeans are under particular threat from Muslims). &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The urge to protect a national white majority has led to other regressive ideas. Alain de Benoist, who founded the New Right in France in the 1960s, is credited with birthing the identitarian movement via his promotion of an isolationist interpretation of diversity &amp;ndash; that in order for supposedly discrete cultures to not become homogenised into non-existence, French people should stay in one country, Algerians in another, and so on. Identitarianism has come to be seen as the acceptable face of white supremacy, not just in France, but in the UK, the US and elsewhere.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The precise grip that Great Replacement theory holds on American voters isn&amp;rsquo;t clear. We do know that much support for Trump was propelled by powerful fears, imagined or not, that the United States many knew is disappearing. This evidently hasn&amp;rsquo;t gone away: one US poll in January put support for Trump at 51 per cent (most polls however put it between 30 and 45 per cent). If he does run for office in 2024, he&amp;rsquo;ll surely play to those fears once more. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Warnings of a &amp;ldquo;white genocide&amp;rdquo;, the supposed end-result of the Great Replacement, are of course preposterous. Yet three-quarters of the 6 January 2021 insurrectionists believed that the Democratic Party is playing a central role in the &amp;ldquo;replacement&amp;rdquo; of white Americans. One might pass them off as an extreme interest group, but as the latest research shows, the profile of radical political movements in the US is changing, as it is elsewhere, and some previously fringe ideas are no longer so fringe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the Witness section of our New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5928/white-fright-in-america#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-03T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-03T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Study: Political Opponents are More Stupid than Evil</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/study-political-opponents-are-more-stupid-than-evil/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Last year, one week after Donald Trump convinced hundreds of Republicans to storm the US Capitol to find and lynch Mike Pence – sorry, sometimes I say a sentence and my brain just breaks …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=U8nxaxqTymg:qTgYJQA6YTA:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131383</id>
    <published>2022-03-02T16:32:01Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-02T16:32:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Michael Ignatieff and the redemptive power of consolation</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5935/michael-ignatieff-and-the-redemptive-power-of-consolation#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Marcus Tullius Cicero, who wrote Consolatio in 45 BC (&amp;Ouml;sterreichische Nationalbibliothek - Austrian National Library)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Screenshot-2022-02-24-at-12.46.13.jpg" height="907" alt="Cicero" width="1149" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is something &amp;ldquo;anti-Descartian&amp;rdquo; about consolation: I feel, therefore I am. While we all think more or less the same (there are many people and few ideas), when I stub my toe, only I feel the pain. Even more significant, when my heart breaks, it&amp;rsquo;s only my world that crumbles. &amp;ldquo;The basis of the self is not thought,&amp;rdquo; wrote Czech novelist Milan Kundera, &amp;ldquo;but suffering,&amp;rdquo; which he considered the &amp;ldquo;most fundamental of feelings&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fundamental or not, suffering alone cannot dictate our state of being. Equally important is how we cope with grief and misery, how we console ourselves and grow and learn. Through that redemptive process, consolation has immeasurably shaped art, politics and religion. Giving form to that immeasurability was the task Canadian author and historian Michael Ignatieff set himself in his latest book, &lt;em&gt;On Consolation&lt;/em&gt;. Looking at 17 historical figures, from the prophet Job to Abraham Lincoln to the 20th century doctor Cicely Saunders, he draws a beautifully clear map of how the search for consolation has evolved throughout the centuries and come to define the worth of human life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In late 2021 I visited Ignatieff at his loaned flat in Vienna&amp;rsquo;s stately Josefstadt district. Snug in his study, Ignatieff easily assumed the role of the boffin, holding court over a cluttered desk dominated by a sepia globe, the walls behind him hung with esoteric artwork and an antique map of Venice. His own books occupied almost an entire shelf of that bookcase, their topics a wide variety of philosophic subjects: pain, honour, human rights, morality, and empire. But it could be said the search for solace has been his longest pursuit, forming a solid basis for some of his best work, from 1985&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Needs of Strangers&lt;/em&gt;, through 1987&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Russian Album&lt;/em&gt;, to 2017&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;The Ordinary Virtues&lt;/em&gt;. His prior enquiries prepared him well, and make &lt;em&gt;On Consolation&lt;/em&gt; a thorough examination of how the sentiment we know as consolation came about, and how it has changed over time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Of the book&amp;rsquo;s germ, Ignatieff recalled a choral performance of the Psalms staged in Utrecht. &amp;ldquo;I began to wonder why a non-believer like me would be moved and comforted and possibly consoled by religious language,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;That sent me to look at the Psalms in detail, and the Hebrew Bible, and Saint Paul, and on and on.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That was before the Covid-19 pandemic, and his preoccupation with consolation seemed strange to friends and family, who assumed some tragedy had befallen him. It hadn&amp;rsquo;t, though he admitted to being drawn to moments of &amp;ldquo;real loss, real bewildering, disabling loss&amp;hellip;the moments that flatten you.&amp;rdquo; He paused, as though realising it sounded somewhat desperate, adding, &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m a depressive character, and I don&amp;rsquo;t wish to imply so. Life is pretty damn good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a strong vein of positivity that runs through the book. Consolation might imply a dour topic, and there are moments of desperation in the book&amp;mdash;imprisonment, death, sickness. But consolation is more accurately an act of hope and confidence, a definitive act of pulling oneself out of sadness. Ignatieff isn&amp;rsquo;t pedalling any feel-good remedies, and makes it clear early on that suffering isn&amp;rsquo;t something that can be avoided, let alone cured, even as society treats it as &amp;ldquo;an illness from which we need to recover&amp;rdquo;. One has a sense, speaking to Ignatieff, that he has become what Kundera called &lt;em&gt;homo sentimentalis&lt;/em&gt;, someone who has raised feelings&amp;mdash;even negative ones&amp;mdash;to a category of value. &amp;ldquo;Comfort is transitory,&amp;rdquo; he writes. &amp;ldquo;Consolation is enduring.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On Consolation&lt;/em&gt; threads together the revelations and wisdom of Marcus Aurelius, David Hume, Mahler, and others. &amp;ldquo;I began to see those connections, the most obvious one being Boethius, who faced death at the hands of the Barbarian king, inspiring Dante, who was similarly in exile in the same city, who then, in turn, inspired Primo Levi in Auschwitz.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While Ignatieff holds up art as a timeless tenant of consolation, the book is also concerned with the limits of everyday language. &amp;ldquo;Words,&amp;rdquo; he writes, &amp;ldquo;just fall apart.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I think we&amp;rsquo;ve all experienced that when we try to console someone who is heartbroken,&amp;rdquo; Ignatieff said. &amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s no generic loss, there&amp;rsquo;s only loss for you and loss for me. And that means empathy is crucial to consolation. But anyone who tries to console finds this is where words break down, where silence descends over a room.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Over and over again in these chapters, people are reflecting on the limits of words. Cicero writes these letters consoling other people &amp;ndash; &lt;em&gt;Consolatio&lt;/em&gt; [a philosophical work by Cicero] is [part of] a positive genre in the Roman stoic tradition &amp;ndash; and then he loses his daughter. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the most distressing moments in life, and it&amp;rsquo;s where empathy comes to its limits, where words come to their limits, where meaning comes to its limits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The limits of what others can provide is one of the clearest messages of the book, and put me in mind of the difference between &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t know what to say&amp;rdquo; and the crueller &amp;ldquo;What do you want me to say?&amp;rdquo; We are, Ignatieff suggests, caught between our desire to be comforted by others, and the necessity of consoling ourselves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The figures in &lt;em&gt;On Consolation&lt;/em&gt; exist at pivot points in history, when the promise of a divine afterlife was found wanting. Their works of writing, art, and music have pushed the western world towards secularism and an age when religion has yielded most of its power to foretell a better future to science and politics. But given our current governmental and climatic crises, are science and politics too gloomy to provide the consolation once afforded by religious faith?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t believe the Armageddon narrative,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;Not only do I not believe it, I think it&amp;rsquo;s pernicious and disabling. It&amp;rsquo;s not uncommon to hear our species described as a virus, as a parasite, and a plague upon the earth. I like the human race. Who else is going to fix this?&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s a note he found to be struck again and again throughout history, that the essential element of consolation is hope.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I wondered how the project has changed his outlook on humanity, and the future. He fell silent for a long moment, then said &amp;ldquo;The whole project made me much more hostile to ideology and political faith itself than I ever thought I would be. It made me much more pragmatic &amp;ndash; let&amp;rsquo;s go with what works, and cut the talk.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Before we parted, I asked if he had any advice for those seeking consolation today. His face bore an expression like pain, his eyebrows, still dark where his hair has lightened to grey, tilting together and one cheek pulling into a half-smile. &amp;ldquo;You have to have patience with yourself. You have to give yourself a break sometimes. You can&amp;rsquo;t think yourself out of certain holes. You can&amp;rsquo;t write yourself out of certain holes. You can&amp;rsquo;t play yourself out of certain pits. You just have to let time do its work, and you have to have faith that you&amp;rsquo;ll get through it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5935/michael-ignatieff-and-the-redemptive-power-of-consolation#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-02T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-02T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MARCH 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/open-discussion-march-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978157</id>
    <published>2022-03-01T12:33:07Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-01T12:33:07Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Misinformation &amp; Propaganda as Russia Invades Ukraine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/02/misinformation-propaganda-as-russia-invades-ukraine/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Well, season 2,022 of Earth has taken quite the turn from “global pandemic” to “land war in Europe” as Vladmir Putin did the thing that most experts agreed would be extremely stupid, and invaded …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=mIHRGX4Kjq0:7Xlu096gVdM:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131367</id>
    <published>2022-02-28T21:54:18Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-28T21:54:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Paines, Pinkers, and Critical Thinkers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/02/paines-pinkers-and-critical-thinkers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! If you’re reading this, you’re probably a grownup. Whether we are speaking to our own supporters or reaching out to new audiences, most of our communications are naturally aimed at adults. But the work to advance a society based on reason and science must begin with fostering critical thinking …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978110</id>
    <published>2022-02-16T16:56:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-16T16:56:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism"/>
    <category term="Education"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VIDEO: Outwit the Universe with Steven Pinker</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/02/video-outwit-the-universe-with-steven-pinker/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2020, the Center for Inquiry launched Skeptical Inquirer Presents, a free series of live online talks from leading experts in science and skepticism, and in 2022, it’s going stronger than ever. Three events have already been held this year, with talks from skeptic activist Susan Gerbic, virologist Paul Offit, and, in the episode that …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978104</id>
    <published>2022-02-16T16:46:59Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-16T16:46:59Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It’s Alive!!!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/02/its-alive/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What does it mean to be alive? Does life have a clear definition? On the Point of Inquiry podcast, New York Times science writer Carl Zimmer joined host Jim Underdown to discuss Zimmer’s new book, Life’s Edge: The Search for What It Means to Be Alive. Can we clearly define what it means to be alive? Scientists have been struggling …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978099</id>
    <published>2022-02-16T16:42:45Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-16T16:42:45Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Taking Homeopathy to Court</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/02/taking-homeopathy-to-court/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last month, the Center for Inquiry reached a major milestone in its groundbreaking consumer-protection lawsuits against retail giants Walmart and CVS. CFI is suing these corporations over their deceptive sale and marketing of homeopathic products under the Consumer Protection laws of the District of Columbia, and on January 13, CFI Legal Director Nick Little presented …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978095</id>
    <published>2022-02-16T16:41:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-02-16T16:41:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" alt="71K22hD8AqL" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750 750w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1500 1500w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-container-2 wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-container-1 wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Magic Award</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our first award focused on performers who use magic tricks to improve the lives of others, including work with disadvantaged groups, hospital patients, and schools. The judges selected two great winners: Megan Swann (who presents a magic show that promotes environmental issues) and Breathe Magic (who support children with hemiplegia by helping them to learn tricks that improve physical and psychological wellbeing).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This year, the award will provide £2,000 to support a new and innovative project that promotes the art of magic. This might, for example, include developing a live or virtual performance, writing a magic-related book or essay, creating a podcast, devising a new form of illusion or presentation, or undertaking research into the history of magic. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Applicants need to be over 18 years old and currently residing in the UK, and nominations will close at 5pm (GMT) on 20th February 2021.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To enter, please head over to &lt;a href="https://goodthinkingsociety.org/projects/the-good-magic-awards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"&gt;The Good Thinking Society&lt;/a&gt; now! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards. Our first award focused… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Good Magic Award</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12851</id>
    <published>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
