<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email></email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-03-25T23:33:37Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>You knew it was going to come down to this</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/25/you-knew-it-was-going-to-come-down-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice-300x242.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="242" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-66055" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice-300x242.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice-150x121.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice-768x621.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice-500x404.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/mybodymychoice.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Goddamn Texas Republicans. <a href="https://www.star-telegram.com/opinion/bud-kennedy/article259670215.html">Now they’re saying it out loud</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Should Texas punish abortions by putting teenage girls and women to death? Or not? That’s the current debate in the Republican Party of Texas, where outlawing abortion is no longer a question of “if” or “when” but a question of whether to kill women for getting one.</p></blockquote>
<p>They’re trying to pass <a href="https://www.texastribune.org/2021/03/09/texas-legislature-abortion-criminalize-death-penalty/">a heinous bill</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>A Texas lawmaker has filed a bill that would abolish and criminalize abortions, leaving women and physicians who perform the procedure to face criminal charges that could carry the death penalty.</p>
<p>The legislation, filed Tuesday by state Rep. Bryan Slaton, does not include exceptions for rape or incest. It does exempt ectopic pregnancies that seriously threaten the life of the woman “when a reasonable alternative to save the lives of both the mother and the unborn child is unavailable.”</p>
<p>“It is time for Texas to protect the natural right to life for the tiniest and most innocent Texans, and this bill does just that,” Slaton said. “It’s time Republicans make it clear that we actually think abortion is murder. … Unborn children are dying at a faster rate in Texas than COVID patients, but Texas isn’t taking the abortion crisis seriously.”</p></blockquote>
<p>The only abortion crisis is that these assholes want to ban it. Would you be surprised to learn that this same representative wants to <a href="https://www.dallasnews.com/news/politics/2021/03/27/push-is-on-in-texas-house-by-gop-member-to-remove-mask-mandate-relax-covid-restrictions/">roll back <em>all</em> of the pandemic prevention measures in the state</a>? He thinks no one is dying of COVID, but that more “unborn children” (there is no such thing) are dying than…zero.</p>
<p>This bozo is eager to start killing adult women, though. Gotta get the body count up somehow.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Goddamn Texas Republicans. Now they’re saying it out loud. Should Texas punish abortions by putting teenage girls and women to death? Or not? That’s the current debate in the Republican Party of Texas, where outlawing abortion is no longer a question of “if” or “when” but a question of whether to kill women for getting […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66054</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T22:03:44Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T22:03:44Z</updated>
    <category term="Abortion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why Repeating Something Makes it Sound Truer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/why-repeating-something-makes-it-sound-truer/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Before I begin today’s video, I want to give a shout-out to my Patrons! They make these videos possible, and in exchange they get early ad-free videos, weekly newsletters, monthly Q&amp;A livestreams, and a smart …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=DQSdzrnYLRg:jddMvDTzNp0:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131409</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T17:46:48Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T17:46:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How about if we just call it “The Homophobic Space Telescope”?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/25/how-about-if-we-just-call-it-the-homophobic-space-telescope/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div id="attachment_66052" style="width: 160px" class="wp-caption alignright"&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" class="size-thumbnail wp-image-66052" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst-150x150.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst-300x300.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst-500x500.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/renamejwst.jpg 620w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;p class="wp-caption-text"&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/64153800"&gt;#RenameJWST&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p class="lead"&gt;I learned three disappointing things about NASA today. There&amp;#8217;s been an ongoing kerfuffle over the &lt;em&gt;name&lt;/em&gt; of the James Webb Space Telescope, because Webb presided over a remarkably homophobic culture at the agency. Now &lt;a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-00845-6"&gt;internal documents about the debate over naming it have been revealed&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Internal NASA documents obtained by Nature reveal fresh details about the agency’s investigation last year into whether to rename its flagship James Webb Space Telescope (JWST). A group of astronomers had led a community petition to change the name, alleging that the telescope’s namesake, former NASA chief James Webb, had been complicit in the persecution and firing of gay and lesbian federal employees during his career in the US government in the 1950s and 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I already knew all that. Those aren&amp;#8217;t the new disappointments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One was that this problem goes all the way back to 1969, when a judge ruled on a firing case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Although the documents reveal that key decisions were made in meetings and not over e-mail, they still show agency officials wrestling with how to investigate the allegations and control public messaging over the controversy. As early as April 2021, an external researcher flagged wording from the 1969 court ruling to NASA officials. It came in the case of Clifford Norton, who had appealed against being fired from NASA for “immoral, indecent, and disgraceful conduct”. In the decision, the chief judge wrote that the person who had fired Norton had said that he was a good employee and asked whether there was a way to keep him on. Whomever he consulted in the personnel office told him that it was a “custom within the agency” to fire people for “homosexual conduct”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I think you will find this paragraph to be troubling,” wrote the external researcher to Eric Smith, the JWST’s programme scientist at NASA in Washington DC. “‘A custom within the agency’ sounds pretty bad.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Troubling? You think? The NASA personnel office considered it customary to fire anyone exposed as gay? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s old news, you say. What isn&amp;#8217;t old is how the modern agency carried out their investigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;NASA staff stated that it would only be a problem if they found evidence that Webb was &amp;quot;overtly anti-gay&amp;quot;. At one point, there was an informal survey to take the temperature of the astronomy community on the name change, which consisted of calling ~10 faculty who are not LGBTQ+&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Dr. Lucianne Walkowicz (@RocketToLulu) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/RocketToLulu/status/1507380601799778308?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;March 25, 2022&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second disappointment is that they contacted 10 straight astronomers who said discrimination against gay people wasn&amp;#8217;t a problem, and that was part of their ultimate decision to bury the controversy. Does anyone else see a problem with their methodology?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then the third surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revelations about NASA’s decision regarding the JWST come at a time of increasing concern over the way the agency handles issues of identity. Earlier this month, employees at the agency’s Goddard Space Flight Center in Greenbelt, Maryland, were told that they would no longer be able to include pronouns, such as she/her or they/them, in their display names in agency computer systems. After the move was discussed on Reddit and the astronomy community reacted negatively on other social platforms, NASA put out a statement that employees could continue to include pronouns in their e-mail signature blocks.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How authoritarian of them. So this month the administrators were openly transphobic, while pretending that oh no, they were never ever homophobic? I don&amp;#8217;t think I believe them, especially since they tried to hide their findings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I learned three disappointing things about NASA today. There’s been an ongoing kerfuffle over the name of the James Webb Space Telescope, because Webb presided over a remarkably homophobic culture at the agency. Now internal documents about the debate over naming it have been revealed. Internal NASA documents obtained by Nature reveal fresh details about […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66051</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T16:05:59Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T16:05:59Z</updated>
    <category term="Feminism, Gender, and Equality"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I never thought I’d sympathize with a church</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/25/i-never-thought-id-sympathize-with-a-church/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">This is an <a href="https://freaktography.com/abandoned-indigenous-church-and-burial-ground/">amazing photo series of an abandoned church in Ontario</a>, documenting its decay over a decade. I feel ya, church.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch-500x495.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="495" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-66049" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch-500x495.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch-150x150.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch-300x297.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch-768x760.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/abandonedchurch.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>It’s got the appearance of an apocalyptically sudden departure — there’s an old open bible in the pulpit, with a pair of reading glasses casually left on top. It’s like one day they were holding services, and the next day every one was gone, never to return. </p>
<p>Also interesting how it falls: it starts with a little water leak in the roof, leading to mold and rot spreading across the ceiling, and then one winter, ka-boom, the roof caves in. </p>
<p>It’s reminding me that maintenance is important. Little problems lead to big problems lead to complete system collapse, so tend to those little problems as you go.</p>
<p>(Speaking of which — this was a bad winter for me, with annoying tendinitis issues basically crippling me for months. I got these new shoes with a good fit and great ankle support two weeks ago, and it’s almost miraculous how much better I feel, walking around fairly freely now with barely a twinge. Appreciate your mobility while you’ve got it, it’s awful when a little problem messes you up. Get good shoes. Patch those roof leaks.)</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is an amazing photo series of an abandoned church in Ontario, documenting its decay over a decade. I feel ya, church. It’s got the appearance of an apocalyptically sudden departure — there’s an old open bible in the pulpit, with a pair of reading glasses casually left on top. It’s like one day they […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66048</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T15:34:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T15:34:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Joanne! You have a friend!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/25/joanne-you-have-a-friend/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;I&amp;#8217;m sure JK Rowling is thrilled to pieces to have such a prominent ally, &lt;a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/politics/politics-news/putin-compares-russia-jk-rowling-cancel-culture-rant-1326643/"&gt;a world leader no less, who appreciates her so much and even finds kinship with her&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Vladimir Putin is pretty upset that the United States and other Western nations have taken issue with him invading Ukraine and killing thousands of people. The murderous authoritarian took a page from the American right wing to air his grievances on Friday, comparing retaliation against the war to “cancel culture.” He even likened Russia to Harry Potter author J.K. Rowling, who has been widely criticized for expressing anti-trans sentiment — but still, lest we must remind you, continues to publish books and make millions of dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They canceled [J.K.] Rowling recently, the children’s author,” Putin said after complaining that the Red Army doesn’t get enough credit for defeating fascism in World War II. “Her books are published all over the world, just because she didn’t satisfy the demands of gender rights.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hWaoxn0vqNY" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She&amp;#8217;s canceled, just like Putin! Still rolling in the dough, still on the lips of every intolerant authoritarian, but &amp;#8220;canceled&amp;#8221;, whatever that means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Putin went on to compare Western nations “canceling” Russian “writers and books” to Nazis burning books 90 years ago. He did not mention reports that Russians are literally burning Ukrainian books, or the nation’s state-run media and longstanding suppression of free speech. He went on to claim there is “no place for ethnic intolerance” in Russia, where “cultural diversity is the pride of our society.” Putin did not mention that the Russian government has been trying to snuff out LGBTQ rights for years, most recently in a lawsuit arguing that an LGBTQ rights group is engaging in activity that goes against “traditional values.”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Man, if Putin said he admired me, I&amp;#8217;d be scrambling to disavow it (and rushing to take a shower) and would be seriously reconsidering my life. I wonder what kind of rambling screed Rowling is going to write about this? I halfway expect that she will graciously thank him and express her appreciation. I hope she&amp;#8217;s not that far gone.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’m sure JK Rowling is thrilled to pieces to have such a prominent ally, a world leader no less, who appreciates her so much and even finds kinship with her. Vladimir Putin is pretty upset that the United States and other Western nations have taken issue with him invading Ukraine and killing thousands of people. […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66046</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T14:53:37Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T14:53:37Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Friday Cephalopod: Babies are so cute</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/03/25/friday-cephalopod-babies-are-so-cute-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><div id="attachment_66044" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna-500x500.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="500" class="size-large wp-image-66044" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna-500x500.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/03/euprymna.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.mathieurenard.eu/research.html">Mathieu Renard</a></p></div>
</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=66043</id>
    <published>2022-03-25T14:29:02Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-25T14:29:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Cephalopods"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are Russians Lying About Their Support for War in Ukraine?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/are-russians-lying-about-their-support-for-war-in-ukraine/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Recently I read that a survey of Russians found that 58% of them supported the country’s invasion of Ukraine. The figure came from a phone survey conducted by Russian researchers (who wish to remain anonymous) …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=UxqJDYZhNPo:HUupmkMS7YU:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131406</id>
    <published>2022-03-24T16:42:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-24T16:42:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How Many Children Do You Have?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/how-many-children-do-you-have/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So many people have sent me books on how to grieve. I have so many. I’ll tell you in the future about that. Tonight I want to tell you a story of love. When I met one of my stepchildren, we were not close. When I married their father, we were not close. The only …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=YkBPqNFmikU:BbMkF058djE:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131405</id>
    <published>2022-03-23T00:35:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-23T00:35:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Two Kids, Time Off, and the Prison of Condolences</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/two-kids-time-off-and-the-prison-of-condolences/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’m an academic mom. I’m on my menace hours. What do I mean by menace hours? It’s a term I used to use with my son for the time in the middle of the night when it’s quiet and you get your real things done. This weekend made me completely re-evaluate what this time means. …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=fqs1OZfDHeI:gqQ1a81-niI:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Isis the Scientist</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131401</id>
    <published>2022-03-22T09:24:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-22T09:24:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do We Prefer Nature Walks Because of Fractals?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/03/do-we-prefer-nature-walks-because-of-fractals/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Well, it happened again: I saw a new science paper that sounded interesting, started reading, and fell down a rabbit hole. The subject this time? Fractals. It all started with this press release I …<div class="feedflare">
<a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:yIl2AUoC8zA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=yIl2AUoC8zA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:dnMXMwOfBR0"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=dnMXMwOfBR0" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:F7zBnMyn0Lo"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:F7zBnMyn0Lo" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:7Q72WNTAKBA"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=7Q72WNTAKBA" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:V_sGLiPBpWU"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:V_sGLiPBpWU" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:qj6IDK7rITs"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?d=qj6IDK7rITs" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:gIN9vFwOqvQ"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:gIN9vFwOqvQ" border="0"/></a> <a href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?a=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:D7DqB2pKExk"><img src="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~ff/Skepchick?i=wsvbHxciOis:BTyfJoDFUhk:D7DqB2pKExk" border="0"/></a>
</div></div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131397</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T18:39:44Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T18:39:44Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meet me in the metaverse</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5942/meet-me-in-the-metaverse#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="(Ollie Hirst)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/olliehirst_new_humanist_feb_cover.jpg" height="587" alt="Metaverse" width="800" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The metaverse leapt into popular awareness in 2021, in a world all too prepared for virtual sociality thanks to a year and counting of pandemic social distancing and Zoom Christmases. Last April, Epic Games announced $1 billion in investment to build &amp;ldquo;revolutionary&amp;rdquo; connected social experiences. In June, Facebook announced itself as &amp;ldquo;a metaverse company&amp;rdquo;, with 10,000 employees working on virtual reality products and experiences, and by October, it had rebranded itself as Meta, driving a flurry of commentary as people scrambled to work out what that might actually mean.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The word quickly made it into the Oxford English Dictionary, where it&amp;rsquo;s defined as &amp;ldquo;a virtual-reality space in which users can interact with a computer-generated environment and other users&amp;rdquo;. Venture capitalist Matthew Ball, whose &amp;ldquo;Metaverse Primer&amp;rdquo; essays have done a lot to shape thinking around the concept, wrote of it: &amp;ldquo;You can walk into any experience or activity, and potentially address almost any of your needs, from a single starting point or world that&amp;rsquo;s also populated by everyone else you know.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Online video games are probably the easiest way in to imagining the metaverse. They allow for flexibility of interaction (for example, while &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; began as a shooter game, it now tags itself as the place where you can &amp;ldquo;Watch a concert, build an island or fight&amp;rdquo;) as well as scale (&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; has over 200 million players). There are also their highly developed internal economies and social organisation &amp;ndash; in &lt;span class="s1"&gt;Second Life&lt;/span&gt;, for instance, users can build houses and open businesses, which contribute to its $600 million economy.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;But the metaverse is potentially more than just a gateway to digital experiences. It crosses over into physical experiences too. Augmented reality, where the so-called IRL (&amp;ldquo;in real life&amp;rdquo;) world is visible alongside digital content, does not require special headsets or fancy glasses. Recall the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Pok&amp;eacute;mon GO&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; craze of 2016, where collectible monsters manifested on street corners through the window of an ordinary phone screen. Pop star Ariana Grande has already played concerts in &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Fortnite&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, outfitted in flying, iridescent shards of virtual glass, complete with glowing white eyes. Perhaps next year you&amp;rsquo;ll attend a concert in full VR while your partner watches it via TikTok Live on their Apple glasses. The future is surely hybrid.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Who owns this space is yet to be determined. We might hope for a pluriverse of platforms and experiences that we can explore as we desire, walking between worlds while bringing our identities, social relationships and digital possessions with us. Tech companies, however, seek monopolies. Interoperability will be challenging, requiring more cooperation than the Web 2.0 era of social media ever achieved.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Still, the metaverse does not have to be owned by a single company, whether Zuckerberg&amp;rsquo;s Meta or any other. In October 2021, San Francisco tech opinionator Shaan Puri offered a broader and more persuasive definition: &amp;ldquo;The metaverse is the moment in time where our digital life is worth more to us than our physical life.&amp;rdquo; It&amp;rsquo;s not new, he says, but rather &amp;ldquo;a gradual change that&amp;rsquo;s been happening for 20 years&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The cyberpunk origins of the metaverse&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Gradual then became sudden. The Covid-19 pandemic ruptured social interaction, with the CoMix social contact survey reporting that levels of social interaction plummeted 75 per cent during lockdowns, only recovering to about 50 per cent of pre-pandemic levels during the fairly unrestricted summer of 2020. In December 2021, Britons were averaging 2.7 contacts per day, barely higher than the first lockdown. We have seen a profound retreat to the nuclear family: sex outside a cohabiting relationship was literally illegal for several months, and lifestyle media is awash with talk of &amp;ldquo;pruning friendships&amp;rdquo;.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;As metaverse discussions washed backwards and forwards last year &amp;ndash; at a time when I, living alone, went days without face-to-face social interaction &amp;ndash; I started to wonder whether I was not already living in a virtual world. Twitter, with its dramas and &amp;ldquo;main characters&amp;rdquo;, was a conversation I checked in on so many times a day it became a continuous, collective narrative. Discussions with friends (many of them also &amp;ldquo;extremely online&amp;rdquo;, as the phrase goes) would switch seamlessly between digital and offline events. Zoom calls gave me a daily fix of faces. A direct message turned into a date in VR Chat. I have always perceived my online interactions as real and significant, and during lockdown this proved a saving grace: that time may have been tedious, but I never felt disconnected. Virtual social interaction proved surprisingly sustaining. Worlds are ultimately created in the mind&amp;rsquo;s eye, not on a screen or a graphics chip. Language has had that conjuring power since time immemorial.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The metaverse is not in fact a new idea: the term was coined in 1992 by Neal Stephenson in his cyberpunk novel &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Snow Crash&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. &amp;ldquo;When you live in a shithole,&amp;rdquo; he wrote, &amp;ldquo;there&amp;rsquo;s always the Metaverse.&amp;rdquo; Stephenson famously described a virtual world owned and governed by corporations, mirroring the miseries of an anarcho-capitalist security state outside. It&amp;rsquo;s a 90s concept, then. So what can we learn from thinking about it through the actually existing online worlds of that time?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m thinking of the MUDs and MOOs of the 1980s and 90s: text-based &amp;ldquo;multi-user dungeons&amp;rdquo;. LambdaMOO was the largest and best-known, with around 10,000 users in 1994 and an architecture based on developer Pavel Curtis&amp;rsquo;s own California home. Players would enter through a space called the Coat Closet, which led on to the Living Room, a hangout and place for conversation (complete with a virtual gossiping cockatoo). Keyboard commands let you move &amp;ndash; left, right, up, down &amp;ndash; and upon entering a new room, a description would load on your screen, suggesting various possibilities for action. You could chat with other people in the room in the standard messaging manner.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;wo books provide a vivid record of life in these virtual worlds: &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;My Tiny Life: Crime and Passion in a Virtual World&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; by Julian Dibbell in the US, and &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;The Cybergypsies: A True Tale of Lust, War, and Betrayal on the Electronic Frontier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, by Indra Sinha in the UK &amp;ndash; both published in 1999 but centred on events some years earlier.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Sinha was an ad man. Tasked with writing copy to sell modems, he decided the first step had to be getting to know the internet, &amp;ldquo;the oases and caravanserais of cyberspace: this bulletin board, that multi-user game&amp;rdquo;. He quickly became hooked, staying up all night on secretive forums and running up phone bills of &amp;pound;700 a month. His marriage grew strained, but Sinha was intoxicated by the people he met: &amp;ldquo;Jarly the hacker, the lovely and lecherous Calypso, Luna the roleplayer who denied she was human&amp;rdquo;, as well as their stories. &amp;ldquo;What stories! seductions, vampings, fleecings, quarrels in cyberspace that turned into real world bomb threats, a feud that began with an online murder which ended up closing down a whole network,&amp;rdquo; he told the era-defining forum The WELL in 1999.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;The book is freighted with insight for the potentials of life in the metaverse. Sinha emphasises how this virtual existence keeps bleeding into real life, and he sought to &amp;ldquo;convey the real experience of what it had been like to live in several worlds simultaneously&amp;rdquo; where &amp;ldquo;it was ALL real to me. All equally real, or equally unreal.&amp;rdquo; People keep crossing over, meeting up at parties and activist campaigns or turning up on each other&amp;rsquo;s doorsteps looking nothing like their characters online. Heightening this, Sinha utilises a flat narrative style in which it&amp;rsquo;s not always apparent where action is taking place. Emotions, especially, bleed over too. &amp;ldquo;The first lesson of cyberspace: that although everything around her, including herself, is fantasy, the terror is real.&amp;rdquo; Yet, as one of Sinha&amp;rsquo;s interlocutors tells him, &amp;ldquo;It is always important to draw the distinction between player and character&amp;rdquo;: that is, online life is a performance, and should be read as such.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;"A subset of the human imagination"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Meanwhile, Sinha describes his behaviour &amp;ndash; and that of his fellow travellers &amp;ndash; as an addict might: the telephone line to the modem &amp;ldquo;a hollow vein awaiting a needle&amp;rdquo; that might open up &amp;ldquo;a vast and chaotic world of the imagination&amp;rdquo;. The book&amp;rsquo;s marketing pitched it as a sequel to Thomas de Quincey&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Confessions of An English Opium Eater&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and it knowingly slips into the same traps: even when trying to convey the darkness of these virtual worlds, the phantasmagoria and the seduction remain compelling. Sinha later said in an interview that, ultimately, &amp;ldquo;cyberspace is nothing more or less than a subset of the human imagination&amp;rdquo;. This, to him, is both its blessing and its curse. The human imagination can chart some Stygian currents, and this is something the metaverse (and its governors) must confront.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Julian Dibbell, a technology journalist, gives us another story from these early virtual worlds, prefiguring what&amp;rsquo;s ahead. It is to my mind one of the canonical stories of online community, ethics, and what exactly it means to &amp;ldquo;be&amp;rdquo; on the internet. It&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;A Rape In Cyberspace&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s 10pm in LambdaMOO, the text-based California house party. The entire experience is just databases and code, Dibbell reminds us: all of the entities present, &amp;ldquo;rooms, things, characters&amp;rdquo;, are just subprograms that interact &amp;ldquo;according to rules very roughly mimicking the laws of the physical world&amp;rdquo;. That night, a character called Mr Bungle brings a &amp;ldquo;voodoo doll&amp;rdquo; to the party &amp;ndash; a subprogram that attributes actions to other characters that their users did not actually create. They&amp;rsquo;re not entirely &amp;ldquo;kosher&amp;rdquo; in this space, we&amp;rsquo;re told, but they&amp;rsquo;re also often amusing.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;ldquo;He could have sent a command to print the message &amp;lsquo;Mr._Bungle, smiling a saintly smile, floats angelic near the ceiling of the living room, showering joy and candy kisses down upon the heads of all below&amp;rsquo;,&amp;rdquo; Dibbell writes. Instead, Mr Bungle uses the program to simulate the violent rape and assault of a number of characters in the room, before the others present manage to work out how to disable him.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What has just happened? A few dozen young people, sitting at computer terminals, have seen a sequence of words appear and scroll down their screens. &amp;ldquo;No bodies touched&amp;rdquo;, Dibbell emphasises. Nobody even saw any graphic images. Yet, as the LambdaMOO community come together in the days after to talk through what has happened and what should be done, one of the women affected finds herself writing with &amp;ldquo;posttraumatic tears . . . streaming down her face&amp;rdquo;, which Dibbell takes as &amp;ldquo;a real-life fact that should suffice to prove that the words&amp;rsquo; emotional content was no mere fiction&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not calling for policies, trials, or better jails,&amp;rdquo; another victim later writes. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure what I&amp;rsquo;m calling for. Virtual castration, if I could manage it. Mostly, [this type of thing] doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen here. Mostly, perhaps I thought it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t happen to me. Mostly, I trust people to conduct themselves with some veneer of civility. Mostly, I want his ass.&amp;rdquo; Thirty-odd people hash out all the possibilities. Had it merely been some kind of thought experiment, as Mr Bungle later claimed? Or should he be &amp;ldquo;toaded&amp;rdquo;, that is, killed? Through this deliberation, Dibbell writes, the party-goers &amp;ldquo;become, finally, the community so many of them already believed they were&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Viewed 30 years later, this episode may seem curiously utopian. Whatever we might say happened, here is a community taking harassment seriously. Mr Bungle was indeed &amp;ldquo;toaded&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; a kind of social death, not just for his avatar but for the man behind it too, expelled from the LambaMOO community. Would gamers do the same today? I&amp;rsquo;m not sure of the answer.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Dibbell and Sinha were writing at a time when people were pretty confident that the online world wasn&amp;rsquo;t real. In 1993, the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; &lt;em&gt;New Yorker&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt; published Peter Steiner&amp;rsquo;s now famous cartoon, where one hound at a computer quips to another, &amp;ldquo;On the internet, nobody knows you&amp;rsquo;re a dog.&amp;rdquo; Back then, the internet was, as Sinha&amp;rsquo;s subtitle puts it, &amp;ldquo;the electronic frontier&amp;rdquo;, open and lawless. It had not yet been captured by business, and was far from its current enclosure by Big Tech.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Since then we have seen several iterations of this &amp;ldquo;reality&amp;rdquo; debate, which, I would argue, is really a discussion about how we should treat each other in the digital world. Do online actions have consequences, or does the fact they&amp;rsquo;re &amp;ldquo;virtual&amp;rdquo; mean they&amp;rsquo;re immaterial? In &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Alone Together&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, psychologist Sherry Turkle fretted, &amp;ldquo;Does virtual intimacy degrade our experience of the other kind?&amp;rdquo; She argued that interacting with avatars simulating emotion posed a serious threat to our abilities to relate to one another IRL. Other scholars have explored the ways in which online relationships provide support &amp;ndash; for example, how LGBTQ young people used online communities to find solidarity. Online trolls were seen as tricksters until it became evident that they could cause real harm.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;A decade of digital change at once&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Then the pandemic arrived, and a decade or more of social and digital change happened all at once. Grandma learns how to use an iPad; Zoom&amp;rsquo;s stock price soars; people adjust to working with colleagues they&amp;rsquo;ve never met in the flesh. Finally, the idea of making any kind of neat online/offline, real/unreal distinction is put to bed as the fool&amp;rsquo;s errand it always was.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In his new book &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;Reality+&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, released in January, philosopher David J. Chalmers argues that we not only can but increasingly will live a meaningful life in virtual worlds. In an interview with the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;New York Times&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, he notes that &amp;ldquo;most of these basic kinds of things that matter you ought to be able to get in a virtual world&amp;rdquo;, from social relationships to learning, and setting and achieving goals. Being in a simulated environment does not make these experiences somehow &amp;ldquo;unreal&amp;rdquo; or insignificant, he argues: they may not be wholly the &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;same&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; as IRL, while some experiences &amp;ndash; from awe at nature to the joys of embodiment &amp;ndash; are &amp;ldquo;a century&amp;rdquo; away from being replicated, or may never be. But, he told the&lt;span class="s1"&gt; Times&lt;/span&gt;, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s clear to me that virtual worlds have a lot to offer,&amp;rdquo; although &amp;ldquo;this doesn&amp;rsquo;t make them a panacea.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The metaverse remains an apparition of speculation and hype, scepticism and hope. Technologically, the space is wide open, and some capabilities will not be fully realised for decades. Yet I wonder whether we&amp;rsquo;re talking about it now not only out of fascination with what&amp;rsquo;s next, but as a means of understanding the present day &amp;ndash; and the fact that the IRL and the virtual have already merged. Public life is profoundly shaped by the online &amp;ndash; politics, for example, is governed by WhatsApp groups and Twitter posting, and MPs use their time in parliament as a chance to create viral video moments. And vice versa: &amp;ldquo;Virtual space has to be understood as an embodied space in which actual-life selves, practices, and norms continue to exist,&amp;rdquo; the philosophers Katleen Gabriels and Marjolein Lanzing argue. This is why the &amp;ldquo;Bungle Affair&amp;rdquo; felt so violent for those involved, even though nothing ever physically happened.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Rather than a discrete &amp;ldquo;place&amp;rdquo; that you may enter and exit from, it might be more helpful to imagine the metaverse as a persistent digital layer of reality. And as with the rollout of the internet in the first place, you won&amp;rsquo;t fully recognise what it is, until you realise you&amp;rsquo;re engulfed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5942/meet-me-in-the-metaverse#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T11:56:38Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T11:56:38Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What happened to British fair play?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5940/what-happened-to-british-fair-play#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Richmond Road in Bradford (Tim Green / Wikimedia Commons)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Welcome_to_Bradford__8027402174_.jpg" height="887" alt="Welcome to Bradford" width="1330" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;"I&amp;rsquo;m 40 and still regarded as a youth.&amp;rdquo; It was the early summer of 1995, and a local community worker of Pakistani-British heritage was showing me around the rough and sloping ground of a local youth cricket club in Bradford, West Yorkshire, run without any support from official sports bodies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d come up to make a special report for BBC News in the aftermath of the Manningham Riots, a short but intense period of youth rioting provoked by alleged police brutality in Bradford, which hosts the largest population of people of Pakistani heritage of any city in England. I was there to try to understand the roots of the violence, which had taken the nation by surprise. The un-level playing field proved a handy metaphor for how two generations of young British Asians were being failed by both indifference from the civic authorities at large and the conservative social strictures of their own community.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Twenty-five years later, after watching 30-year-old Azeem Rafiq testify before a Commons select committee in October 2021 about the spirit-breaking racism he&amp;rsquo;d endured for years, I remembered that encounter. The teen cricket prodigy, who grew up in Barnsley, 30 miles from Bradford, had captained England&amp;rsquo;s under-15s and became Yorkshire&amp;rsquo;s youngest ever captain.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Yorkshire County Cricket Club&amp;rsquo;s leadership stayed in denial until sponsors pulled out. Enemies then signed letters slandering Rafiq&amp;rsquo;s character and dredged up years-old tweets of antisemitic comments he had made (for which he showed full contrition and met Jewish organisations to make amends), thereby undermining the veracity of his own trauma. How could so little have changed?&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Over the years I have come to realise that Bradford and its environs are emblematic of the UK&amp;rsquo;s wider social crises and broken promises. As a journalist from London, my 1995 post-riot visit offered a limited glimpse into how traditional political racial solidarity had been splintered by social and religious division. The book burnings of &lt;em&gt;The Satanic Verses&lt;/em&gt; in 1989 had been the first shock. Who were these people burning books for &amp;ldquo;blasphemy&amp;rdquo;? When I went back after the 2001 Bradford riots, this time for Channel 4 News, a white social worker informed me I was being &amp;ldquo;racist&amp;rdquo; for asking about forced marriage.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;I met a female social worker who had previously been part of the domestic violence support group Southall Black Sisters and recently moved to the city. She told me she had attended a meeting where self-appointed male community leaders had demanded that all complaints of domestic violence be referred to them to be dealt with. The police would have agreed, she said, if she hadn&amp;rsquo;t been there to object.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Bradford was one of several English towns where in the past decade British Asian sexual grooming gangs have been convicted of abusing teenage girls. My own encounters in the city seemed evidence of a widespread culture of denial and misogyny, within council services and the police as much as in the community: a culture that had allowed abusers to prosper from Rochdale and Rotherham in Yorkshire to Telford and Oxford.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;There is more, however, to Bradford. As a member of the advisory board for the city&amp;rsquo;s National Science and Media Museum I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen in love with its grand Victorian buildings and the buzz of its brutalist Oastler market, selling food from across the globe. There&amp;rsquo;s a distinctive attitude and pride, while its citizens come up again and again with their own solutions to help tackle poverty and underachievement.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;I was hopeful when, in 2021, Channel 4 opened a new programming hub in Leeds as part of their commitment to the Leeds/Bradford area. What Bradford &amp;ndash; Britain&amp;rsquo;s ninth largest city &amp;ndash; desperately needed was proper transport infrastructure to make the most of it. But when HS2 was scaled back late last year, these plans were abandoned. Residents will continue to rely on an often-disrupted connection to Leeds, limiting opportunities and job prospects.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;Azeem Rafiq should have been in his prime years on the England team. Instead, this sportsman has gone through the trauma of reliving the abuse and taunts before an audience. As if it defines him. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t. He&amp;rsquo;s a hero.&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;If you want to know if politicians&amp;rsquo; pledges of levelling up are kept, watch Bradford and its nearby towns. They&amp;rsquo;ve seen too many broken promises over the past 25 years. When we finally invest properly in its infrastructure and treat its talented sons and daughters with the respect and care they deserve, we&amp;rsquo;ll know the truth about that much-claimed British value of fair play.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5940/what-happened-to-british-fair-play#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-21T08:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-21T08:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Re-imagining the Second World War</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5934/re-imagining-the-second-world-war#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="A portrait of Major Mahomed Akbar Khan by Henry Lamb is hung in the Second World War Gallery at IWM London" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/iwm.jpg" height="981" alt="Hanging a portrait of Major Mahomed Akbar Khan at IWM London" width="1531" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;An unknown Ethiopian artist&amp;rsquo;s impression of the invasion of Abyssinia in 1935 painted on an antelope&amp;rsquo;s hide, a jigsaw puzzle made of Nazi swastikas, and a flat iron pan from the Partition of India in 1947. It&amp;rsquo;s through objects such as these that the Imperial War Museum in London is hoping to offer visitors a bold global look at the Second World War.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;In October the museum opened the doors to its new Second World War and Holocaust galleries after a massive &amp;pound;30.7m reimagining. It&amp;rsquo;s the first major redevelopment of the museum&amp;rsquo;s permanent representation of the Second World War since 1989. A lot has changed. Gone are the hugely popular war &amp;ldquo;experiences&amp;rdquo; of the 1990s, where you could walk through a recreated bombed-out street or trench. Instead, the museum shows the different global environments &amp;ndash; desert, tropics, tundra &amp;ndash; that the war took place in. Experiences of civilians, rather than battles or weaponry, are now front and centre. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Links are made between the War Galleries and the new Holocaust Galleries, both through narrative and a shared exhibition space. But it is the rendering of the Second World War that is a significant departure for IWM. Why was it done now? And does it succeed? &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Every British schoolchild has been taught the stories of Dunkirk and the Battle of Britain. Along with endless repeats of Dad&amp;rsquo;s Army, and the &amp;ldquo;Great Escape&amp;rdquo; sung at football matches, it can seem as if the Second World War is ever-present in British culture. It was weaponised during the 2016 EU referendum by both sides: Nigel Farage invoked the trope of Britain &amp;ldquo;alone&amp;rdquo; fighting the Germans, while the Remain camp argued that the conflict taught us the need for close ties with the continent. At the beginning of the pandemic, then-health minister Matt Hancock went so far as to compare Britain&amp;rsquo;s response to the Covid-19 pandemic with the national resilience shown during the Blitz.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The vital role of museums&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But these takes often have more to do with Britain&amp;rsquo;s culture wars than with historical accuracy. As the last generation that actually survived the war passes away, the role of museums in cutting through the confusion and forging a clearer relationship between the public, the politicians and our national collective memory of the war becomes ever more necessary. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We live in an age of emotion, with a need for personal connection. The stories of more than 100 individuals from 30 different countries are told in the new galleries, part of a wider trend in the museum sector called &amp;ldquo;peopling&amp;rdquo;, where personal lives are given space, along with the more abstract narratives of movements and battles. Take Sam Martinez, for instance. Martinez, whose passport is displayed, was an &amp;ldquo;Axeman&amp;rdquo; from British Honduras (now Belize) who rushed to Glasgow to contribute to the war effort. We learn not just of his bravery but of the prejudice he faced: while invited to dances in Scotland, he would also hear local leaders complain about &amp;ldquo;black foresters starting relationships with Scottish women&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Discovering his story, we empathise with his courage and determination and acknowledge the acute racial tensions of the era &amp;ndash; although the museum stops short of calling this what we would now recognise it as: racism. Still, it&amp;rsquo;s important to remember that racism itself is an evolving historical concept: the racism experienced today is different to racism as it was experienced during the time of the British Empire. What we do see in these stories is an institution tentatively coming to terms with some of the legacies of Britain&amp;rsquo;s imperial past. The new galleries hope to tell a &amp;ldquo;global story&amp;rdquo;. That includes the former British Empire, but it also extends to the Soviet Union, eastern Europe, North Africa and the Mediterranean. Special attention is given to China, as well as the Japanese and Allied campaign in East Asia and the Pacific. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not to say it shies away from representations of the war in Britain. However, it does seek to clarify the facts. One way in which the British story of the war has been warped in the popular imagination is the idea of Britain singlehandedly fighting the Nazis, following the fall of France and much of Europe to German occupation. In reality, Britain was very much not &amp;ldquo;alone&amp;rdquo;, relying heavily on its empire for resources, financial support &amp;ndash; and, of course, troops. In exposing its historical inaccuracy, the Imperial War Museum, London shows how this idea erases the contribution and exploitation of millions of individuals across the globe. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It is the hope of many historians and museum professionals that realigning the narrative in public spaces like the IWM will exact real political change, encouraging the public to recognise when their politicians, and national press, are touting phony historical equivalencies.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The new galleries also want to expand the concept of the Second World War as a &amp;ldquo;Total War&amp;rdquo;, in which the distinction between civilian and combatant is made redundant and entire nations and their populations are mobilised for the war effort. Dr Yasmin Khan, who advised on the new galleries, says: &amp;ldquo;The war touched many parts of the globe far from the usual epicentres or theatres, and impinged on civilian lives in myriad ways: social, economic, political, from food shortages to internment or deforestation. So part of the new approach to the war is to try and understand this total effect, the way that so many aspects of human life were shaped &amp;ndash; often far away from the frontlines, in places we might not immediately associate with the war. This is what I think the new galleries achieve.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Indeed, as IWM curator Kate Clements adds, &amp;ldquo;By drawing comparisons between, for example, the experience of civilians being bombed in Britain, Japan, Germany and China, we are able to demonstrate that although the effects of war were felt to different degrees, in different places and at different times, there was a commonality of experience in the war that collectively bound together those millions that lived through it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Hence the museum does not hold back when showing the horrors of war: visitors will learn that in 1941, two million out of the three million Soviet prisoners held by the Germans died within six months, either through starvation or neglect. Similarly, sexual violence &amp;ndash; an often-underexplored aspect of the war &amp;ndash; is shown through the stories of so-called &amp;ldquo;comfort women&amp;rdquo;, those forced into sexual slavery by the Imperial Japanese Army. Starvation and hunger are explored via the controversial starving of roughly 3 million people in British-controlled Bengal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The "anti-woke" backlash&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, has the IWM succeeded? While generally met with positive reviews, its new galleries have not gone without criticism. A recent review by Peter Hitchens suggested that while impressive, too little was included on how Stalin treated Soviet citizens. Similarly, historian Laurence Rees wrote in the Telegraph: &amp;ldquo;No prominence is given to the horrific crimes Stalin committed during the war against his own people&amp;rdquo;, such as the deportation of entire ethnic groups like the Kalmyks, Crimean Tatars and Chechens.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These critics have a point. After all, the Soviet Union did suffer the highest number of wartime casualties and the stories of those abused and murdered by its regime should be fully told. However, we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t ignore the context of these criticisms. After Labour&amp;rsquo;s Jeremy Corbyn years and amid the rising popularity of left-wing politics among young Brits, there is a hint of moral panic around calls to emphasise communist atrocities in culture and academia: a pertinent example of how the war is still being used as a point of reference for contemporary debate.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Fears over &amp;ldquo;woke&amp;rdquo; or left-wing education have led to calls for new public spaces which provide a counternarrative. This includes a newly proposed museum to communist atrocities, the board members of which include former Conservative MP Owen Paterson and MEP Daniel Hannan. The would-be director of the museum, James Bartholomew, who is also a former Brexit Party candidate, said last year that teachers &amp;ldquo;who, if not Marxist themselves, are left-wing&amp;rdquo; are to blame for a lack of knowledge about communist atrocities.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The same fears over how Britain&amp;rsquo;s past is represented came into play after the National Trust published its report in September 2020 investigating the proven links of some of its properties to the slave trade. The backlash against perceived &amp;ldquo;wokeness&amp;rdquo; led to the foundation of the protest group Restore Trust, which lists amongst its main aims to &amp;ldquo;restore the [National] Trust&amp;rsquo;s original apolitical ethos&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Challenging uncomfortable histories&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The government itself is certainly not shy of engaging in these culture wars. Following concerns over the Black Lives Matter movement and the toppling of statues in the US and the UK, then-culture secretary Oliver Dowden sent a letter in September last year to institutions funded by the Department for Digital, Culture, Media and Sport implying that their funding could be at risk if they removed controversial statues or objects.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Many museums will be watching cautiously. Having lost so much revenue during the pandemic, it would be understandable for some to shy away from taking a bold stance in their representation of the past. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Nevertheless, it is more important now than ever that museums continue to question and challenge uncomfortable histories. They would be doing a disservice to the public if their representations of the past were mediocre, or boring, for the sake of avoiding debate and controversy. As the war generation leave us, being able to interact with authentic material culture from the time is even more important for our ability to resist simplistic culture war debates.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The new galleries at the IWM are not without fault, and invariably miss out histories that do not fit into either their overarching narrative or exhibition space. But their attempt to offer a more global look at the Second World War is admirable, as is their foregrounding of personal stories, along with the complexities of economic, social and military histories. They offer something that is rarely found on the internet, in political rhetoric or in newspaper columns: the nuanced insights generated by the coupling of historical lives and extraordinary objects.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5934/re-imagining-the-second-world-war#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-17T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-17T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Intolerance of Inquiry, Failures of Imagination</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/intolerance-of-inquiry-failures-of-imagination/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! A few days ago, Raif Badawi walked out of his prison cell.  A progressive Saudi writer, Badawi was arrested in 2012 on charges of “insulting Islam” and apostasy for daring to question religion and criticize the Saudi Arabian government through his website. The Center for Inquiry (CFI) …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978231</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:48:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>VIDEO: Paul Offit on Medical Risk</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/video-paul-offit-on-medical-risk/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We live in an unprecedented age of medical marvels, but success never comes free. In his third appearance on Skeptical Inquirer Presents, renowned virologist Paul Offit discussed the ideas behind his new book You Bet Your Life, explaining that the path to each medical advancement is paved with failures and risk.  “I wrote this book knowing …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978225</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:16:21Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dreaming of Mars and the Aliens Who Aren’t There</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/dreaming-of-mars-and-the-aliens-who-arent-there/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is no evidence that Earth has ever been visited by extraterrestrials, yet many people are firmly convinced that aliens are among us. A team of researchers at California State University, Fresno, led by psychologist Matthew J. Sharps, set out to understand the psychological traits that influence a person’s beliefs about alien visitations and abductions. …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978223</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:13:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Raif Badawi Released from Prison</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/raif-badawi-released-from-prison/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Friday, March 11, global human rights activist Ensaf Haidar made a stunning announcement: her husband Raif Badawi, imprisoned in Saudi Arabia since 2012, had been released. In 2014, Badawi was found guilty of “insulting Islam” and given an egregious sentence: seven years in prison, which was soon increased to ten; a ten-year travel ban …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978218</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:12:05Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:12:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Religion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Carl Sagan’s Call to Enlightenment</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/03/carl-sagans-call-to-enlightenment/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Astronomer Carl Sagan left an inspiring legacy, sharing his love of science through his bestselling books, scientific work, and his groundbreaking series Cosmos. Robyn E. Blumner, executive director of the Richard Dawkins Foundation for Reason &amp; Science, reminds us that Sagan’s legacy and his passion for reason and discovery are also carried on by a magazine …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Paul Fidalgo</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978214</id>
    <published>2022-03-16T16:10:08Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-16T16:10:08Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>From Sophocles to "Succession", we've always loved family sagas</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5932/from-sophocles-to-succession-weve-always-loved-family-sagas#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="HBO series &amp;ldquo;The Righteous Gemstones&amp;rdquo; (Ryan Green/HBO)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/cassidy-freeman-danny-mcbride-jim-turner-harley-jane-kozak-tim-baltz-edi-patterson.jpg" height="1041" alt="The Righteous Gemstones" width="1562" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The best moments on television shine for lots of different reasons. They can be heartwarming, tearjerking, shocking &amp;ndash; or, sometimes, so viscerally uncomfortable that they keep replaying in your head long after the episode or even the series is over.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&amp;ldquo;What It Takes&amp;rdquo;, the sixth episode of the third series of the HBO drama &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt;, ends with just such a moment. Logan Roy, ruthless patriarch of both his family and their media empire, has chosen to support a repugnant, near-fascist presidential nominee and is demanding that his children line up for a photograph with this man. His daughter, who has already aired her opposition to the choice and been ignored, is hovering on the sidelines of the photoshoot refusing to get into frame. This is when Logan (played by a magisterial Brian Cox) walks over to her and in a menacing undertone delivers the killer line. &amp;ldquo;Siobhan, are you part of this family or not?&amp;rdquo; For a second, the choice to answer &amp;ldquo;No&amp;rdquo; flickers across her face. Then she knuckles under, lines up and pastes on a smile for the camera. It&amp;rsquo;s a brutal and brief encapsulation of the show&amp;rsquo;s fundamental tension: the three-way fight between morality, loyalty and self-interest. In Succession, the family always wins even as its members lose.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The family saga, of which &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt; is merely the most recent and prominent example, has long been a fundamental component of what is generally known as &amp;ldquo;prestige TV&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the big budget, often American series that have captured the cultural zeitgeist over the past three decades. At the same time stuck-at-home viewers were indulging in the second and third series of &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt;, they were also delving back into the boxsets that they had never had time for before. And many of those are also family sagas of one sort of another, from &lt;em&gt;The Sopranos&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, which in amongst the dragons and the nudity is an epic tale of dynastic alliances and betrayals.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So why are we so hooked on these intergenerational tales of conflict and inheritance? It&amp;rsquo;s partly because a family saga comes with a built-in narrative arc: power and influence must ultimately, no matter how hard ageing members resist, pass down the family tree, because time can only move forward, never back. Then there&amp;rsquo;s the fascination of tracking how different traits and habits are replicated. Logan Roy and his eldest son Kendall are almost never on the same side of any fight, but looking in on their relationship from the outside, the viewer can see that their conflicts are more often because of their similarities than their differences. As subject matter, these tangled fictional genealogies are universally relatable. There might not be any vast media conglomerates or iron thrones to inherit, but we all have families and all families have their tensions. The gravitational pull of the family unit is inescapable: even those who cut all ties still end up defining themselves in opposition to it.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Millennia before the current boom in high-quality television, writers were exploring the potential of this kind of storytelling. The Old Testament is one early example: the so-called &amp;ldquo;succession narrative&amp;rdquo; in the second book of Samuel and the first Book of Kings deals with the family history of the royal house of ancient Israel and the battle to accede to the throne of David. The Ancient Greek dramatists were similarly fascinated by the theatrical potential of lineage and inheritance. Sophocles&amp;rsquo; most famous and enduring plays, &lt;em&gt;Oedipus Rex &lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;Antigone&lt;/em&gt;, both feature protagonists torn between the competing attractions of duty, desire and independence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Austen, Dickens and Galsworthy&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;This obsessive documentation of family conflict was itself inherited by later writers of the western canon. What are the novels of Jane Austen, with their preoccupation with familial relationships and marriage, if not family sagas? Twentieth-century critics frequently chose &lt;em&gt;Bleak House&lt;/em&gt; as the greatest of Charles Dickens&amp;rsquo;s novels. It seems no coincidence that it is his most overtly family-orientated story. By placing a seemingly never-ending Court of Chancery case at the heart of the narrative, Dickens exposed the dark and seedy side of our preoccupation with inheritance. Greed and family do not make for a happy mixture.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Following in Dickens&amp;rsquo;s footsteps in the early 20th century came John Galsworthy. Beginning in 1906, he published a trio of connected novels known collectively as &lt;em&gt;The Forsyte Saga&lt;/em&gt;. Dealing with the lives and property of the titular Forsyte family, these books delicately skewered the upper-middle-class Edwardian snobbishness that had replaced the Victorian priggishness of the previous century. Although Galsworthy was best known for his plays during his own lifetime, it is this trilogy that has survived in popular culture. Unlikely as it may seem, these novels provided an early indication &amp;ndash; right from the beginning of the 20th century &amp;ndash; of how well a family saga could work on television. A black and white BBC adaptation of &lt;em&gt;The Forsyte Saga&lt;/em&gt; in the 1960s was such a roaring success that 18 million people tuned in to watch the final episode, and it made history as the first BBC series to be sold for official broadcast in the Soviet Union.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;What all of these family sagas have in common, from the Book of Kings to &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt;, is the wealth and power of the family in question. When inheritance is a major theme, it follows that there must be something to inherit, and as a result the overwhelming majority of such stories deal with characters who are rich, privileged and sometimes even royal. There are, of course, deviations. Yaa Gyasi&amp;rsquo;s 2016 novel &lt;em&gt;Homegoing&lt;/em&gt; is a family saga that covers the generational fallout from the transatlantic slave trade. Similarly, a recent National Theatre adaptation of several D. H. Lawrence novels, &lt;em&gt;Husbands and Sons&lt;/em&gt;, looked at family dynamics and notions of inheritance in a working-class mining community. But these are the exceptions. Even our tastes in non-fictional family sagas tend towards the wealthy and famous, as seen in the way that tabloids delight in the exploits of celebrity offspring or extended family groups.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Part of what makes &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt; worth watching is that same frisson of reality versus fiction. It&amp;rsquo;s impossible not to notice the parallels between Logan Roy, his media companies and his three warring children and Rupert Murdoch, his media companies and his four children from his first two marriages, all of whom have at one time or another held senior positions in his businesses.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Dysfunctionality on the small screen&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The entertainment industry in general and television in particular are very good at latching on to a successful format and replicating it, as different studios and broadcasters attempt to lure viewers&amp;rsquo; attention in an oversaturated market. Thus the popularity of &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt; is spawning a renaissance of sorts for the family saga on the small screen. &lt;em&gt;The Righteous Gemstones&lt;/em&gt; follows the fortunes of a dysfunctional family of televangelists, and was instantly renewed for a third season. Its tagline &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;serving the lord and themselves&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; could almost be a motto for this whole subgenre. Then there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Monarch&lt;/em&gt;, a multigenerational drama starring Anna Friel and Susan Sarandon, about a country music dynasty called, appropriately enough, the Romans, which promises Roy-style conflict with a different industry as its backdrop.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;On this side of the Atlantic, this year ITV will air the first series of &lt;em&gt;Riches&lt;/em&gt;, which creator Abby Ajayi describes as &amp;ldquo;a love letter to Black London&amp;rdquo;. The six-part series is already attracting comparisons to &lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt; for its focus on a family of Black Londoners squabbling over their wealthy father&amp;rsquo;s business empire after his health begins to fail. And, of course, the world of TV family sagas is not immune to the industry&amp;rsquo;s obsession with reboots, because this is also the year that HBO&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; prequel, &lt;em&gt;House of the Dragon&lt;/em&gt;, will debut. In 2022, television is still very much keeping it in the family.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;Subscribe today&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5932/from-sophocles-to-succession-weve-always-loved-family-sagas#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-14T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-14T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No child left behind</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5931/no-child-left-behind#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Parents fret that Covid-19 has created a generation of lost children. This needs to be corrected (Alamy Stock Photo)" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2B17YBWs.jpg" height="836" alt="Two people hugging" width="1175" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Covid-19 spread across the world in 2020, millions of young people were taken out of school. Referred to as a &amp;ldquo;lost generation&amp;rdquo;, it is often assumed that these children will struggle, if not ultimately fail, to catch up on the days, weeks and months of education they could not access. The anxiety for themselves, their parents and their educators is animated by a fear that they have been damaged already, perhaps irreparably, and that their lives will be blighted forever. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But we know from the latest research into child and adolescent development that a young person&amp;rsquo;s ability to catch up should never be considered beyond reach. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t only hold true for education. Across the globe, &amp;ldquo;Catch Up&amp;rdquo; is a technical term applied to a much more fundamental process: the restoration of height, weight and cognition that has been lost as a result of malnutrition. We know from this process that young humans are extraordinarily resilient. With adequate care and support, they have a good chance of regaining what they have lost. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t take much, as long as an essential first ingredient is present: the knowledge that children can recover from setbacks.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The evolving science of nutrition&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The science of nutrition is relatively new. The first vitamin, B1, was isolated and chemically defined in 1926. By the 1950s, all the remaining essential micronutrients had been identified and synthesised. It was a transformation in our understanding of malnutrition. Starving children weren&amp;rsquo;t just lacking food, they were missing these minuscule but essential micronutrients. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Those of us with the luxury to do so get our iron, iodine and Vitamin A &amp;ndash; the three micronutrients that are vital preventatives of malnutrition &amp;ndash; from the regular food we buy at supermarkets. They enable our bodies to produce enzymes, hormones and other chemicals, and thereby create the messaging system that actually tells our cells to grow or develop or change. It is micronutrients that make us what we will eventually become, but many around the world struggle to access them.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The best indication that micronutrients are absent from a child&amp;rsquo;s diet for long periods is stunting (when a child is too short for their age) and wasting (when a child is too thin for their age). A child may feel full from macronutrients (proteins, fats and carbohydrates), but if there are no micronutrients then their cells aren&amp;rsquo;t getting the messages to keep growing towards adulthood. So instead they go into a kind of cellular power conservation survival mode, ready for when the micronutrient going eventually gets better. This process is known as &amp;ldquo;thrifty growth&amp;rdquo;. The child&amp;rsquo;s energy is diverted towards basic survival: keeping their brain and lungs functioning optimally for as long as possible. Less energy, therefore, goes where it should, and their bones stop lengthening as a result. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;But nothing can be thrifty for ever. Eventually energy runs out, and malnutrition starts to affect a child&amp;rsquo;s cognitive and behavioural development. Malnourished children have less energy to walk to school, and less ability to concentrate when they get there. It is therefore not only once-in-a-lifetime pandemics that keep children out of school; for many children living in conditions of war and famine, myriad factors combine to stop them from accessing education. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;To date, the easiest way to restore micronutrients is to add them to what are called fortificant food premixes, or to provide them as concentrated supplements in the form of iodised salt, iron tablets and syrups, and Vitamin A capsules. But we are also taking our understanding of the role of micronutrients in new and wonderful directions. Through precise selective breeding, agri-nutritionists have created whole new families of potatoes and sweet potatoes that are &amp;ldquo;nutri-dense&amp;rdquo;, which means they grow with the highest possible pro-Vitamin A and enhanced iron content. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;These crops aren&amp;rsquo;t only designed to combat malnutrition; they can also help us to meet the challenges of the climate crisis. Ensuring that what we grow has the maximum nutritional value will become increasingly important as the climate changes. This new class of vegetables is drought tolerant and doesn&amp;rsquo;t mind poor soil, which makes them easy to farm in the world&amp;rsquo;s increasingly hot and dry places, where children are already more likely to need micronutrient supplements.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;No more thrifty growth&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But correcting malnutrition is also a question of timing. Scientists often talk about &amp;ldquo;the first thousand days&amp;rdquo; of a child&amp;rsquo;s life as being the most important for interventions. All micronutrient supplements are best at generating Catch Up when the little human taking them is &amp;ndash; or should be &amp;ndash; undergoing a growth spurt. Supplements should therefore be given in the earliest years of life, when their cells should be fizzing with activity and potential. Across the world, studies show that malnourished children up to the age of three who receive micronutrient supplementation begin to grow again. Perhaps they won&amp;rsquo;t be quite as tall as the international height standard for their region, but nevertheless, they can be put onto the right track. And it means much more than merely taller children with longer legs. It means the messages generated by micronutrients are getting to the right places, stimulating the cell growth and development that are also needed for cognitive development. No more thrift. Children that have fallen behind catch up, both mentally and physically.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The &amp;ldquo;thousand days&amp;rdquo; window is extremely important. But we have recently begun to recognise that there is another crucial window of opportunity. Humans have two significant growth spurt periods in their life: one in the first thousand days; the other during adolescence, when puberty occurs. This second growth spurt is every bit as vital to our adult development as the first one. Humans get about 25 per cent of their eventual height during their teenage years, and like those first thousand days, we rely on the chemical messaging of the micronutrient system to get this rapid growth phase in our development done. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The need for energy and micronutrients will never be higher than it is in adolescence. This is the point when the micronutrients should be messaging the hormones to tell the brain to develop voluntary-control mechanisms and executive function: the means whereby people get to choose their behaviours, understand their choices, make plans and see them through. If the messages don&amp;rsquo;t get through, it isn&amp;rsquo;t just leg length that is profoundly limited. Cognitive development is every bit as likely as bone length to be stunted and eventually wasted. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Adolescents, however, don&amp;rsquo;t receive enough attention, despite the possibilities presented for their Catch Up. In fact, studies from across the world are starting to come in that show that when micronutrient supplementing measures are applied to malnourished adolescents, Catch Up happens much more quickly, significantly and observably than it does in the toddler cohort. Restoring the right amount of nutritious food to teenagers means they do what they are meant to do, and grow to become healthy adults. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;So why don&amp;rsquo;t we see more programmes and funding directed at teenagers in need, particularly as such interventions are reasonably affordable? It seems that the science is being held back by our prejudices. It&amp;rsquo;s very difficult to fund science on adolescents because society is wary of vaguely threatening young male teenagers living in difficult places where conflict drives their hunger. Their rough skin and narrowed eyes, full of fear and aggression, don&amp;rsquo;t make for good photographs in funding applications. For no good reason, it is often assumed that it&amp;rsquo;s too late to restore what has been lost to these vulnerable young men who are no longer children but have become a frightening, potentially dangerous population. Instead, the round, tear-filled eyes of the hungry toddler, cradled in its mother&amp;rsquo;s arms, gets all the oxygen in the funding room, and most of the money. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This is a huge wasted opportunity &amp;ndash; for girls as well as boys. Thus far, everything we know about the potential of adolescent Catch Up comes from studying groups in developed nations: young people who are malnourished for a range of reasons other than conflict or famine, including patients who are congenitally deficient in hormones, who have coeliac disease, or whose bones have been stunted by conditions such as cerebral palsy. Whatever the reason for what is technically termed &amp;ldquo;affluent stunting&amp;rdquo;, micronutrient restoration produces Catch Up in these adolescents, steadily and permanently. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;It wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be difficult to adapt this research to create an infrastructure to enable adolescent Catch Up all over the non-affluent world, and it&amp;rsquo;s likely to result in better fed teenagers who make more thoughtful decisions about the rest of their lives. The Lancet&amp;rsquo;s launch in November of a series on adolescent nutrition, acknowledging that the field is &amp;ldquo;overlooked in policy and investment&amp;rdquo;, is a welcome development, but much more needs to be done. The essential first step, of course, would be accepting that these teenagers are worthy of the effort.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The fundamental value of nurture&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is another major area upon which we could improve, and that is prevention. Everyone agrees that prevention is better than cure. Ending world hunger would be excellent, but in the meantime what can be done to delay the point at which hunger becomes malnutrition and thrift becomes loss? The answer is perhaps unexpected, but even more hopeful than the progress with micronutrient-generated Catch Up. This is because it is something we already do well, across the world and relatively cheaply: we vaccinate. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Vaccinations are so very helpful in achieving Catch Up because malnutrition is not just about not enough good food. It also happens because our immune systems, for some evolutionary reason, are not part of the thrifty growth system. When a child&amp;rsquo;s physiology begins to conserve energy, the immune system is immediately diminished, leaving them vulnerable. So the hungry child gets infections everywhere, but especially in the gut, where they cascade catastrophically, starving the child from inside as well as out. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This quickly becomes a vicious cycle. Even when micronutrient levels are restored with supplements, the energy that should be resuming growth patterns stays fighting the effects of infection. The result: no Catch Up, just a slow diversion of resources into a cycle of hunger and sickness. In a vaccinated child, however, the chemical messages aren&amp;rsquo;t wasted fighting infections, but go where they are needed to generate positive growth and development.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not only do vaccinations help break the malnutrition-immune dysfunction cycle, they also fill in the immunity gap. This is because vaccinations can generate what are technically called &amp;ldquo;beneficial non-specific effects&amp;rdquo;. It means that a BCG shot, for instance, given against TB or leprosy, also strengthens the whole immune response in each child that receives it, and therefore gives better overall resistance to disease. Another example is the measles vaccine, which gives the same fortificant power to the overall developing immune system, as well as no more measles. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Not all vaccinations have this ability. The pneumonia vaccine, for example, simply does what it says on the vial. And the BCG vaccination has to be given as early in the first thousand days as possible in order to achieve its best effects. If it&amp;rsquo;s done right, a vaccinated child has higher haemoglobin levels than an unvaccinated child and is therefore less likely to need iron supplements. This is because vaccinations have ensured that at least one of its micronutrients is doing just fine, getting the important messages to wherever in the body they are needed.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;We don&amp;rsquo;t yet know if something similar happens with teenage vaccinations. But that&amp;rsquo;s only because we haven&amp;rsquo;t looked yet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One more thing. When a child is taken for their vaccination, we can see a process at work that is as fundamental to achieving proper nutrition in its widest possible sense as feeding is. A vaccinated child is a nurtured child. If the child is held and comforted during the process, their tears wiped away and their paper record card carefully kept until next time, then they are receiving nurturing care. Nurturing generates cognitive stimulation, just as micronutrients do. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A child that isn&amp;rsquo;t nurtured isn&amp;rsquo;t only less likely to be vaccinated. If no one reads them a story at a regular bedtime or ensures they are warm, comfortable and able to dream their way through untroubled nights, then they may never be able to read a story all the way to the end for themselves. Even if they can walk to school they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to do much when they get there. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;This holds for teenagers too. If no one listens to the aspirations of an adolescent, and if they aren&amp;rsquo;t encouraged to stay in school for as long as possible, then even if their bellies are full they too will be held back and eventually fall behind. Literacy is as a good marker as vaccination status as to whether or not a child or adolescent is receiving the essential ingredients of nurturing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Healthcare by other means&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet for all the work being done to increase vaccinations, and despite a 70 per cent drop worldwide in vaccine-preventable deaths since 2000, there are reckoned to be 20 million children who are under-vaccinated, which means they may have received no or only some of their vaccinations. It&amp;rsquo;s not because of funding shortages. Vaccines are efficient and inexpensive, and vaccinators are never short on energy and courage. But vaccinations stall in particular regions in the world because of political instability, poor communications and community dysfunction &amp;ndash; for all sorts of reasons that don&amp;rsquo;t need more science for resolution, just better human activity and wider peace. In the meantime, the gap remains.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;A good place to start bridging the gap would be through the sustainable development goals (SDGs) set by the UN for realisation in 2030. We should make a new goal, specifically aimed at optimising current vaccination strategy systems so that every young person may have an optimised immune system. That is a good place to start, because vaccinations are healthcare systems by other means, easy and cheap to establish. This new SDG could probably be brought in ahead of schedule because it only needs a bit more science, some improved communications and logistics and &amp;ndash; perhaps the most significant challenge of all &amp;ndash; for us to set aside our prejudices about who is deserving of our care and attention, of our best and most expensive research efforts. If we have two chances per human to optimise immune systems and therefore generate Catch Up, then we should take them both, and let no one fall behind. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;There are no lost generations, just the ones we prefer not to see. Catch Up, wherever you look for it, depends on human beings doing things we already know how to do, and doing them as well as they can possibly be done for every single child and adolescent who needs them. Young people themselves &amp;ndash; with their remarkable resilience and ability to survive &amp;ndash; will do most of the rest, given just a little of the right support.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/5931/no-child-left-behind#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-03-10T09:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-10T09:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" alt="71K22hD8AqL" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750 750w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1500 1500w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is all about whether it’s possible to predict the future. As ever, it contains 28 full colour pages about magic, mystery and the mind. This issue also has lots of interactive demonstrations and illusions. Mother Shipton predicts your future , Nostradamus uncovers the secret of publishing profitable predictions and Paul The Psychic  Octopus reveals all.Amazing work by Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts.  Enjoy! Available now from <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-issue4-prophecy" target="_blank">Prop Dog</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13171" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/cover4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg" data-orig-size="844,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="cover4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726" alt="" class="wp-image-13171" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=726 726w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=106 106w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=213 213w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/cover4.jpg 844w" sizes="(max-width: 726px) 100vw, 726px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="13173" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/magic-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg" data-orig-size="1072,1092" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="magic" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005" alt="" class="wp-image-13173" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=147 147w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=295 295w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg?w=768 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/09/magic.jpg 1072w" sizes="(max-width: 1005px) 100vw, 1005px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that Issue 4 of our magic comic, Hocus Pocus, is out now. This one is… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/09/16/hocus-pocus/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13168</id>
    <published>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</published>
    <updated>2021-09-16T14:07:15Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="9771" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/explore2/research/papers2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" data-orig-size="2199,1206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="papers2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9771" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg" alt="papers2" width="2199" height="1206" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg 2199w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=82 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=165 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=768&amp;h=421 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2018/04/papers2.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=562 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2199px) 100vw, 2199px"/>I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative.</p>
<p>During the experiment, a group 10 to 11-year-old children completed a creativity test that involved coming up with multiple uses for an everyday object. They were then taught how to perform a simple trick in which they showed someone a cube with different coloured sides, asked the person to secretly choose a colour, and then magically revealed their person’s choice. Finally, they all completed the creativity test a second time. Compared to another group of children who took part in an art lesson, learning the trick significantly boosted the children’s creativity scores.</p>
<p>Magic tricks often involve lateral thinking and we suspect that learning to perform the illusions encouraged children to think outside of the box.  There is a  need to enhance creative thinking from a young age. Learning magic tricks would be a cost effective, practical, and fun way of teachers and parents boosting children’s creativity. Maybe in the future, magic will become part of the school curriculum!</p>
<p>The peer-reviewed work was carried out in collaboration with  Amy Wiles and Professor Caroline Watt (Edinburgh University), and published in the academic journal PeerJ.</p>
<p>You can read the paper for free <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/11289/">here</a>, and a general review on magic and education <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/8747/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have just co-authored a new research paper suggesting that learning to perform magic tricks makes children more creative. During the experiment, a… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/06/new-paper-on-creativity/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW PAPER ON CREATIVITY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13015</id>
    <published>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-06T19:02:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New MAGic BOOK</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="12986" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/cover2-2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1400,1795" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="cover2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-12986 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg" alt="cover2" width="368" height="471" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=368&amp;h=471 368w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=736&amp;h=942 736w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=117&amp;h=150 117w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/cover2-1.jpg?w=234&amp;h=300 234w" sizes="(max-width: 368px) 100vw, 368px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – <strong>David Copperfield’s History of Magic</strong>.<br/><br/><span style="color:var(--color-primary-base);font-family:var(--site-font-body);font-size:revert;">It’s written by David Copperfield, David Britland and myself, with photographs by Homer Liwag.</span></p>
<p>The book presents a personal tour of David’s amazing secret museum of magic in Las Vegas. Containing over 100 full colour photographs, the book takes you on a journey into a clandestine world of psychology, history and magic.  The book is released on October 26th and is now available for pre-order. <br/>USA: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Click here</a><br/>UK: <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/exec/obidos/ASIN/1982112913" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Amazon UK</a></p>


<div class="wp-container-2 wp-block-columns">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:100%;">
<div class="wp-container-1 wp-block-columns alignwide">
<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>



<div class="wp-block-column" style="flex-basis:50%;"/>
</div>
</div>
</div>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12990" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12990" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page1.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="12991" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/page2/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="page2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024" alt="" class="wp-image-12991" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=1024 1024w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=2048 2048w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/05/page2.jpg?w=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"/></a></figure>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have co-authored a new book – David Copperfield’s History of Magic. It’s written… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/05/02/new-book-on-magic-history/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New MAGic BOOK</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12977</id>
    <published>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</published>
    <updated>2021-05-02T20:54:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Good Magic Award</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our first award focused on performers who use magic tricks to improve the lives of others, including work with disadvantaged groups, hospital patients, and schools. The judges selected two great winners: Megan Swann (who presents a magic show that promotes environmental issues) and Breathe Magic (who support children with hemiplegia by helping them to learn tricks that improve physical and psychological wellbeing).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;This year, the award will provide £2,000 to support a new and innovative project that promotes the art of magic. This might, for example, include developing a live or virtual performance, writing a magic-related book or essay, creating a podcast, devising a new form of illusion or presentation, or undertaking research into the history of magic. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Applicants need to be over 18 years old and currently residing in the UK, and nominations will close at 5pm (GMT) on 20th February 2021.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To enter, please head over to &lt;a href="https://goodthinkingsociety.org/projects/the-good-magic-awards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"&gt;The Good Thinking Society&lt;/a&gt; now! &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last year I collaborated with The Good Thinking Society to set up the Good Magic Awards. Our first award focused… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/01/25/good-magic-award-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Good Magic Award</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=12851</id>
    <published>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</published>
    <updated>2021-01-25T12:47:42Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why I went back to school in Higher Ed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/11/went-back-school-higher-ed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/"&gt;yesterday&lt;/a&gt;, I&amp;#8217;ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: &amp;#8220;What the hell Dan? Aren&amp;#8217;t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few reasons I decided to go back to school. but most of them ultimately boil down to one thing: the academic job market. I&amp;#8217;ve been writing about my &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2014/12/28/on-the-market-i-bespoke-courses/"&gt;experiences&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/01/08/on-the-market-ii-digital-footprints/"&gt;looking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/09/on-the-market-iii-byu-doesnt-deserve-my-application-or-yours/"&gt;for&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/09/25/on-the-market-iv-paying-for-the-privilege/"&gt;a&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2015/10/19/on-the-market-v-diversity-statements/"&gt;job&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/01/17/on-the-market-vi-excellence-in-teaching-and-student-evaluations/"&gt;over&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/10/17/on-the-market-vii-job-candidates-are-people-too/"&gt;the last few years&lt;/a&gt;, and after four years and &lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2017/05/05/inexhaustive-list-of-jobs-not-received-with-a-humanities-phd/"&gt;dozens and dozens of applications&lt;/a&gt;, it became very clear that something had to change if I planned on actually getting a job before retirement age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was also getting dangerously close to losing my immigration status in Canada, where I have lived for over twelve years. My three-year postgraduate work visa was set to expire this past summer, and with no employment on the horizon that would satisfy CIC requirements for renewal, going back to school was essentially the only way for me to stay in the country short of marriage (which an immigration lawyer actually suggested).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One would think that earning an advanced postgraduate degree would give someone a leg up in the immigration system, but it turns out this is not always so: immigration nominations for PhD students and graduates come from the individual provinces, and Quebec&amp;#8211;where I studied&amp;#8211;is the only one not to offer them.* And so earning yet another graduate degree in Ontario became the quickest and most straightforward path to finally ending the twelve-year string of short-term temporary visas that have been an omnipresent &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Damocles"&gt;Damoclean sword&lt;/a&gt; for essentially my entire adult life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why Higher Ed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/04/10/universities-should-be-employing-surplus-phds-as-administrative-staff/"&gt;As I&amp;#8217;ve written before&lt;/a&gt;, administration is currently the only growth industry in the sector, and I thought it might be useful to have a professional degree that would help me break into that market. I also do honestly believe that schools would benefit from having more administrators who have first-hand experience with teaching and research, and with actual lived experience as graduate students and academic contract workers. What are the chances, for example, that anyone currently working in a university provost&amp;#8217;s office has ever actually &lt;em&gt;been&lt;/em&gt; an adjunct and knows what it is like? Or has even been a graduate student any time after the 1980s?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I have spent over a decade of my life acquiring and sharpening the tools of critical inquiry, and I think that turning that toolset on higher ed itself is the way I am best qualified to help tackle the many challenges facing the industry. And this goes beyond just literature and research: I have become increasingly interested in helping to actually craft policy that might help to ameliorate some of the problems I&amp;#8217;ve seen and heard about on the ground. This degree is a first step in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;#8212;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*For reasons that I&amp;#8217;m sure are totally unrelated to the fact that most international students in Quebec aren&amp;#8217;t native French-speakers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As I mentioned yesterday, I’ve recently gone back to school for an M.Ed in Higher Education. Regular readers may know that I already have a humanities PhD, which raises a pretty obvious question: “What the hell Dan? Aren’t you done with school? Why collect yet another degree? Seriously what is wrong with you?” There are […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4681</id>
    <published>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-11T13:29:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="higher ed"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="immigration"/>
    <category term="international students"/>
    <category term="job market"/>
    <category term="jobs"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SoD is back in business!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/11/10/sod-is-back-in-business/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to post fairly regularly about my ideas, experiences, and research over the next few semesters. This will include everything from day-to-day experiences in the programme itself to discussions of the existing literature on higher ed to summaries of my own research in the field (and possibly links to full papers for the true masochists among you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the topics I plan to address in the next few weeks, most of which derive from seminar papers I will be writing:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is the Human Capital Model a Myth? Signalling, Credentialism, and Rent-Seeking in Higher Ed&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Idea of a Stoic University (Or: How to Un-coddle the American Mind)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transnational Mobility in the Academic Labour Market for the Humanities&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Graduate School as the Structural Model for the Theory of Emerging Adulthood&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m looking forward to bringing you all along with me on this new journey!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hello everyone! Many apologies for my long absence, but things got a little busy for me when I went back to school (yes, again) to actually officially study Higher Education! The upside for you, dear readers, is that my new studies have provided lots of new grist for the old mill, and I plan to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4680</id>
    <published>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</published>
    <updated>2018-11-10T12:19:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Meta"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>SIU Zero-time Adjunct Follow-up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p style="text-align: center">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme <a href="https://chancellor.siu.edu/messages/04-24-18-university-statement.php">here</a>. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no need to comment further.]</p>
<p>After publishing <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/">my take on the leaked email</a> from SIU Associate Dean Michael Molino yesterday, I read a fair amount of discussion about the issue on social media and faced a little bit of criticism myself for jumping on a viral outrage bandwagon without necessarily having a complete picture of the situation. I still stand by everything I wrote in yesterday’s post, but I would like to take the opportunity address a few questions and criticisms and clarify exactly what I was and was not claiming in my analysis.</p>
<p><strong>Is this email even real? How do we know it really said everything that ended up in the viral version?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, fair enough. This website <em>is </em>called <em>School of Doubt</em>, so a bit of skepticism is always warranted. After this question was raised I reached out to <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com/">Karen Kelsky</a>, who disseminated the most viral version of the email, to ask about its provenance. She confirmed that it was forwarded to her by an SIU faculty member she knew personally. Epistemically speaking that is good enough for me, but nothing’s perfect I guess.</p>
<p><b>Is it really fair to target Molino as an individual because someone leaked an email he wrote? Isn’t this just doxxing that invites harassment?</b></p>
<p>In his capacity as an administrator implementing policy at a state university, Molino is in a position of authority operating in the public trust. This requires transparency and accountability, and I don’t think sharing his official contact information is doxxing any more than it would be for an administrator at a government agency like the EPA or FCC. Furthermore, email communication at public universities is a matter of public record, both for good and for ill (as I have covered <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/05/24/foia-abuse/">previously</a>). While people may disagree about the ethics of leaking and whistleblowing, it is really not possible to argue that such an email could have been written with any reasonable expectation of privacy. But yes, he’s probably going to have a bad time and that sucks.</p>
<p><strong>What if Molino isn’t even ultimately responsible for coming up with the policy?</strong></p>
<p>Well, bluntly, who cares? He is clearly working to implement it. Not to get all Godwinny, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nuremberg_defence">we’ve heard that one before</a>. You can write to the Provost instead if you want. I won’t provide his email but I bet you can find it.</p>
<p><strong>Zero-time adjuncts are not volunteer workers: they are like contractors whose affiliation with the institution does not guarantee them work hours.<br/>
</strong></p>
<p>First off there is a terminology problem here. <strong>Zero-hour </strong>contracts are a kind of labour arrangement, more common in the UK, in which contractors are not guaranteed any specific number of work hours nor are they necessarily required to accept all hours offered. <strong>Zero-time </strong>academic appointments, also known as 0% appointments, are most often used to provide affiliation to scholars or other kinds of people who are employed in other departments or by other organisations. For example, an economist might be tenured faculty at a business school but also have a zero-time appointment in the economics department of the arts faculty of the same school. This person might advise students or otherwise participate in research and service in both departments, but it is understood that the work in their 0% appointment is covered by the pay from their full-time appointment. Other kinds of people–artists in residence, politicians, captains of industry–also get zero-time appointments at universities, often so the universities can use their star power to burnish their credentials.</p>
<p><strong>Even so, zero-time adjuncts would almost certainly be paid for teaching classes if and when they did so. Not to do so would probably be illegal, right?</strong></p>
<p>Okay, here is the crux of the issue. First off, although you can probably read my criticism as implying that zero-time adjuncts would be <em>teaching </em>for free, what I actually said was that they would be <em>working</em> for free. In fact all of the kinds of academic labour I mentioned in yesterday’s post were duties professors undertake <em>in addition to teaching</em>. Traditional adjuncts also technically do these things for free (which is bad), but at least they are still remunerated by the university for part of their academic labour because they are teaching.</p>
<p>So what does it mean when they also don’t get teaching?</p>
<p>Does anyone seriously believe that they will be compensated at a specific and fair hourly rate for time they spend at departmental meetings, on thesis committees, advising and communicating with students, collaborating on research projects, or having other “intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units”? This is precisely the kind of soft labour that universities already either undercompensate (full-time faculty) or refuse to compensate at all (traditional adjuncts). Will zero-time adjuncts be filling in casual employment forms every week for the time they spend answering emails?</p>
<p>Like it or not, “professor” is still a word with a meaning. Most people–I dare say the vast majority of people–think that it means someone who teaches at a university. Even most students don’t <em>really</em> understand the difference between full-time and contingent faculty, because they don’t have much first-hand experience with the non-teaching work that professors do. Or when they do (e.g. academic advising, mentorship, etc.), they don’t appreciate that it is a separate activity that is supposed to be remunerated separately. That’s exactly why I wrote my <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2016/02/03/syllabus-adjunct-clause/">Syllabus Adjunct Clause</a>, which presumably went viral for a reason.</p>
<p>This lack of awareness is why it is so dangerous to allow this precedent. Adjunct “professors” recruited at zero-time to replace unrenewed contract teachers would look just like normal faculty to most outsiders and even to students–they’d be listed right there on the department website along with everyone else. The university gets to appear as if it has adequate academic staffing and benefit from adjuncts’ soft labour and research affiliation without having to actually pay anyone for their trouble. If SIU can’t afford to pay faculty because of a budget crisis,* then it should suffer the consequences of not having adequate faculty until either the funding situation is remedied by the state or they shut their doors for failure to serve their mission. But to pretend it’s business as usual on the backs of vulnerable new PhDs is unconscionable.</p>
<p>*I will leave it up to the reader to decide how serious a budget crisis it must be if the top dozen SIU administrators all earn in excess of $200k per year and well over 200 employees–I stopped counting–earn in excess of $100k (rent must be steep in rural Southern Illinois).</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">[Update to the update: SIU has posted a statement on the programme here. As it essentially confirms my suspicions that it is designed to steal soft academic labour from new PhDs by trading on their institutional loyalty and need for affiliation without paying them for their services, I provide the link here but see no […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4547</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T12:00:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="follow-up"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>And so It Has Come to This</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/23/and-so-it-has-come-to-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://siu.edu/">Southern Illinois University</a> has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never <em>if</em>, but <em>when</em>, and it turns out that <em>when</em> is today.</p>
<p>Yes, friends, the day has finally come that administrators at SIU have finally wrung that very last drop of blood from the stone by deciding to stop paying contingent faculty altogether.</p>
<p>Courtesy of <a href="http://theprofessorisin.com">The Professor Is In</a> on Facebook (emphasis mine):</p>
<blockquote><p>Dear Chairs,</p>
<p>I know you are swamped right now with various requests and annual duties. I apologize for adding to that, but I am here to advocate for something that merits your attention. The Alumni Association has initiated a pilot program involving the College of Science, College of Liberal Arts, and the College of Applied Sciences and Arts,<em><strong> seeking qualified alumni to join the SIU Graduate Faculty in a zero-time (adjunct) status.</strong></em></p>
<p>Candidates for appointment must meet HLC accreditation guidelines for appointment as adjunct professors, and they will generally hold an academic doctorate or other terminal degree as appropriate for the field.</p>
<p><em><strong>These blanket zero-time adjunct graduate faculty appointments are for 3-year periods, and can be renewed. While specific duties of alumni adjuncts will likely vary across academic units, examples include service on graduate student thesis committees, teaching specific graduate or undergraduate lectures in one’s area of expertise, service on departmental or university committees, and collaborations on grant proposals and research projects.</strong></em> Moreover, participating alumni can benefit from intellectual interactions with faculty in their respective units, as well as through collegial networking opportunities with other alumni adjuncts who will come together regularly (either in-person or via the web) to discuss best practices across campus.</p>
<p>The Alumni Association is already working to identify prospective candidates, but it <em><strong>asks for your help in nominating some of your finest former students who are passionate about supporting SIU</strong></em>. Please reach out to your faculty to see if they might nominate a former student who would meet HLC accreditation guidelines for adjunct faculty appointment, which is someone holding a Ph.D., MFA, or other terminal degree. One of the short-comings with our current approach to the doctoral alumni is that the database only includes those with a Ph.D. earned at SIU, but often doesn’t capture SIU graduates with earned doctorates from other institutions. Here are the recommended steps to follow:</p>
<p>· Chairs in collaboration with faculty should consider specific needs/desires of their particular department, and ask how they could best utilize adjunct faculty. For example, many departments are always looking for additional highly qualified members to serve on thesis committees, and to provide individual lectures, seminars, and mentorship activities for both graduate and undergraduate students.</p>
<p>· Based on faculty recommendations, chairs should identify a few good candidates and approach those individuals to see if they are interested. The interested candidate should provide his/her CV (along with a brief letter of interest outlining areas in which they are willing to participate) to the department chair, who can then approach the Graduate Dean for final vetting and approval.</p>
<p>The University hasn’t yet attempted its first alumni adjunct appointment, but this is the general mechanism already in place. Meera would like CoLA to establish a critical mass of nominees before the end of the summer. A goal of at least one (1) nominee per department would get us going.</p>
<p>Thanks,</p>
<p>Michael</p>
<p>—<br/>
MICHAEL R. MOLINO<br/>
Associate Dean for Budget, Personnel, and Research</p>
<p>COLLEGE OF LIBERAL ARTS<br/>
MAIL CODE 4522<br/>
SOUTHERN ILLINOIS UNIVERSITY<br/>
1000 FANER DRIVE<br/>
CARBONDALE, ILLINOIS 62901</p>
<p>mmolino@siu.edu<br/>
P: 618/453-2466<br/>
F: 618/453-3253</p></blockquote>
<p>In case you don’t speak adminstratese, “zero-time” means “unpaid.” Molino has set up an official, university-wide programme encouraging <em>every single department</em> to exploit the precarious labour market for their own graduates by offering them continued status and institutional affiliation in return for working for free.</p>
<p>For those of you outside academia this might seem like such a self-evidently bad deal that you would wonder why on earth anyone would take it.</p>
<p>But that’s exactly the problem: things are already <em>so bad</em> in the academic labour market that adjuncting for free for a few years at your alma mater isn’t even all that much worse than what many new PhDs are already doing, not to mention the fact that academics spend their formative years immersed in a professional culture that not only encourages but <em>demands</em> uncompensated labour (mentoring, research, conferences, publication, peer review) as “service to the discipline” and proof of professional dedication.</p>
<p>At one time this demand was not unreasonable, grounded as it was in a strong social contract whereby full time tenured and tenure-track faculty were compensated for this “extra” work by their home institutions rather than by the academic publishers, conferences, and research projects who were the direct beneficiaries of their research and service labour. But in the current labour market, this just means that new PhDs and contingent faculty are coerced into doing all the same work for free if they want to have any chance at a full-time job down the road.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, things like institutional status and even plain old library privileges are crucial to many new PhDs’ ability even to work for free: most granting agencies require some kind of institutional affiliation from their applicants and subscriptions to academic journals and other resources are ruinously expensive to independent researchers outside traditional institutional settings.</p>
<p>And when many adjuncts already don’t earn anything close to a living wage, <em>is</em> there even much difference between that and nothing at all? In the end, it’s just a few more deliveries for Uber Eats.</p>
<p style="text-align: center">[Ed. note: I posted a follow-up to this post addressing some common questions and criticisms <a href="http://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/24/siu-zero-time-adjunct-follow/">here</a>]</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Illinois University has finally taken the step that we all knew was coming, whether we openly admitted it to ourselves or not. The progression was too obvious, the market forces in question too powerful, for this result to have been anything but inevitable. The question was never if, but when, and it turns out […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4546</id>
    <published>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-24T01:05:34Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="Money"/>
    <category term="academia"/>
    <category term="adjuncts"/>
    <category term="labor"/>
    <category term="labour"/>
    <category term="neoliberalism"/>
    <category term="PhD"/>
    <category term="unpaid internships"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>*Out of Office Response* Re: quick question?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://schoolofdoubt.com/2018/04/19/office-response-re-quick-question/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p>Dear [STUDENT],</p>
<p>Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office.</p>
<p>This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching this course has already fallen well below minimum wage and I cannot answer emails while driving for Uber.</p>
<p>The following questionnaire is designed to help you determine the right place to look for the answer to your question. Please go through it in order until you find the answer to your query. IF and ONLY IF you go through the entire list without finding the answer to your question, please follow the instructions at the end as to where to send your question in order to receive an answer directly.</p>
<p>Let’s begin, shall we?</p>
<p>1. Am I your professor, and are you currently enrolled in my class?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If the answer is NO, please consult your course schedule online to determine which professor you are supposed to be bothering with your inane question.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you have questions about enrollment and registration, please contact the Office of the Registrar, where they receive both fair hourly pay and full benefits in compensation for helping you solve your problems.</p>
<p>2. Is the answer to your question on the course syllabus, which we went over in detail on the first day of class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Questions answered on the syllabus include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When and where does our class meet?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">What assignments do we have and when are they due?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">When are exams and what will be on them?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How many points are deducted from our final grade when we email you questions that are clearly answered on the syllabus?</p>
<p>3. If your question is about a specific assignment, is it answered on the assignment sheet, which we went over in detail in class and which is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">If you do not understand specific terminology used on the assignment sheet, please try consulting your textbook’s glossary, a dictionary, or Google. You may also want to try coming to class, where I teach you what these words mean.</p>
<p>4. Is your question answered on our course FAQ page, which currently lists 127 commonly asked questions and is freely available online 24 hours a day from anywhere in the world?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">You may find it easier to use Ctrl+F and search for specific keywords to navigate this very long document.</p>
<p>5. Is your question unrelated to our class, inappropriate, or just plain unanswerable?</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Such questions might include but are not limited to:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">How much wood a woodchuck can chuck</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">The sound of one hand clapping, trees falling in the woods, or other Zen koans (try <a href="https://books.google.ca/books?id=XB-ICwAAQBAJ&amp;printsec=frontcover#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">this book</a> instead)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px">Whether or not Bernie would have won</p>
<p>6. If you have reached the end of this questionnaire without finding the answer you need, you probably have a valid question. Congratulations!</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px">Please contact your TA for assistance.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear [STUDENT], Thank you for writing me with your question about [COURSE]. I am currently out of the office because I am contingent faculty and do not have an office. This automated response email is intended to help you find the answer to your question on your own, as my average hourly pay for teaching […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Dan</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://schoolofdoubt.com/?p=4541</id>
    <published>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</published>
    <updated>2018-04-19T22:47:46Z</updated>
    <category term="Higher Education"/>
    <category term="comedy"/>
    <category term="email"/>
    <category term="higher education"/>
    <category term="syllabus"/>
    <category term="teaching"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
