<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-02-14T18:32:28Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Shame on Temple University</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/14/shame-on-temple-university/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">The <a href="https://www.tugsa.org/strike">Temple University Graduate Student Association</a> has been on strike for about a month. They’ve been protesting the fact that the university demands full-time work for $19,500 a year, and expects them to live on that in a major city on the East Coast. I lived in Philadelphia 23 years ago, and I can tell you that even then $19,500 would have been starvation wages. I don’t know how they’ve been coping in 2023.</p>
<p>I guess the answer is that they haven’t, and that’s why they’re striking.</p>
<p>Now Temple University, which has always played up their role in serving the working class and poorer communities in the region, has decided to send out a little surprise message to the striking workers.</p>
<blockquote><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote-171x300.jpeg" alt="" width="171" height="300" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-69301" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote-171x300.jpeg 171w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote-86x150.jpeg 86w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote-768x1347.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote-500x877.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/TempleNote.jpeg 1168w" sizes="(max-width: 171px) 100vw, 171px"/></a>As a result of your participation in the TUGSA strike, your tuition remission has been removed for the spring semester. You now owe the full balance listed in TUpay, which is due by Thursday, March 9.<br/>
If your balance is not paid-in-full by the due date, you we be assessed a $100 late payment fee and a financial hold will be placed on your student account. This hold will prevent future registration,</p></blockquote>
<p>Who is running that place nowadays? Some cartoon villain?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Temple University Graduate Student Association has been on strike for about a month. They’ve been protesting the fact that the university demands full-time work for $19,500 a year, and expects them to live on that in a major city on the East Coast. I lived in Philadelphia 23 years ago, and I can tell […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69300</id>
    <published>2023-02-14T17:01:25Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-14T17:01:25Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is there a Silicon Valley philosophy that isn’t just ego and vanity and selfishness?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/14/is-there-a-silicon-valley-philosophy-that-isnt-just-ego-and-vanity-and-selfishness/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;Does this man look 18 to you? How about 30?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/bryanjohnson.jpg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/bryanjohnson-500x670.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="670" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69297" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/bryanjohnson.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/bryanjohnson-112x150.jpg 112w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/bryanjohnson-224x300.jpg 224w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would have guessed he was in his 40s, and would have won a kewpie doll. He&amp;#8217;s 45. His name is Bryan Johnson. He has, however, &lt;a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/z34ay8/bryan-johnson-blueprint-aging-biotech"&gt;set himself the goal of reversing aging&lt;/a&gt; and getting his &amp;#8216;epigenetic age&amp;#8217; down to something absurd, by making his body the subject of an &amp;#8220;experiment&amp;#8221; &amp;#8212; although it is an experiment with no controls, no comparisons of the effectiveness of various treatments, and a subjective criterion of &amp;#8220;perfection,&amp;#8221; which he alone defines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;As of now, Johnson claims that the experiment, which he’s dubbed Project Blueprint, is more concerned with understanding the possibilities of one body—his own—than in creating a replicable system. The journey has led to improved physical health, but the most inarguable effect thus far has been on his physical appearance. He has dropped 60 pounds, and a recent MRI scan found that Johnson was in the 99th percentile for both body fat and muscle concentration—proof, he said, of his achieving “the perfect body ratio.” The muscles everywhere from his shins up to his neck appear to almost protrude out of him, and his skin wraps tightly around his face, which is the point: Johnson puts his skin through regular and painful skin rejuvenation processes, on top of the obligatory application of numerous daily creams. After two years, he claims, his skin is that of a twenty-something and his fitness level is that of an 18-year-old; his body also now runs three degrees cooler than it used to. More than 50 of his biomarkers are also now “perfect,” he has said. He even claims he has been able to stop dying his hair as of three months ago, after making “significant progress reversing gray hair.”  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do twenty-somethings look that shiny and moist? I see a lot of them running around here, and they really don&amp;#8217;t look like middle-aged somethings who just got back from the spa with a miracle gel filling their pores. Is running 3 degrees cooler actually a good thing, or has he just decided that it must be?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s assume, charitably, that he has improved his personal health, since he does look fit. How does he do it? By throwing ridiculous amounts of money at it, of course. He&amp;#8217;s a silicon valley dudebro!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Johnson says that he spends more money on his body than LeBron James. With this sizable budget (more than $2 million a year), he pays for the food he eats (a precise 1,977 calories a day, made up of the world’s most nutritious elements), as well as the 112 to 130 supplemental pills he takes on a daily basis, and the ultrasound machine and other medical-grade machinery he keeps on the second floor of his discrete compound in Venice, Los Angeles, where he and his team of more than 30 doctors, clinicians, and researchers analyze how the 78 organs that make up his body have responded to the latest tweaks to his diet, sleep, and movement.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oooh, &lt;em&gt;precisely&lt;/em&gt; 1977 calories a day…sounds specific and sciencey. Until you learn that he picked that number because that&amp;#8217;s the year he was born, not because there&amp;#8217;s some evidence that that&amp;#8217;s an optimal number. It&amp;#8217;s simply another example of the whims of the privileged rich nincompoops who infest tech culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Extreme as the specifics of his approach might be—this is a man who has a device that tracks his nightly erections—Johnson falls squarely in line with many of his Silicon Valley peers. In recent years, people throughout the technology sector have taken increasingly innovative—and often eccentric—approaches to their personal health and wellness in a pursuit of a longer, happier life. The industry is chock-full of people who, for example, eat five cans of sardines a day or consume nothing but coffee, water, and tea for over a week straight. Former Twitter CEO Jack Dorsey made headlines in 2019, when he announced that he fasted for 22 hours a day and often went days with nothing but water, sparking concerns that the tech sector was “rebranding eating disorders” as wellness. But it was not entirely outside of the norms of an industry that has become taken with “biohacking,” in which one approaches the body as a computer program, to be forever tweaked and optimized. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He doesn&amp;#8217;t really care about the science. None of them do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Existing in a state of perpetual and extreme caloric restriction makes it difficult to fit all the nutrients he needs into his diet. He believes a constant caloric deficit to be “the number one evidence-based health protocol,” though when I later asked specifically what research convinced Johnson to remain in a state of extreme caloric restriction, the only answer I got was “scientific evidence.” Levine, the Altos researcher, said that studies on caloric restriction have led to mixed results and mostly focused on animals. Experiments on mice, for example, have found that while some benefit from restriction, others do not or even experience negative effects. A new study on flatworms out just this month found “no benefits to lifespan” outside of “perfect” environments, as Levine put it. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt; This is an exercise in supernatural thinking. They want to live forever in youthful vigor &amp;#8212; I don&amp;#8217;t blame them for that, I would kinda like that myself &amp;#8212; but in the absence of real evidence, and with the fact that they&amp;#8217;re asking to defy the physical nature of their existence, they just have to make stuff up, or clutch at feeble signs of improvement and imagine that they can amplify that indefinitely. Here goes Bryan Johnson, dreaming that all of his obsessive hypochondria will help him reach his goal of immortality. It won&amp;#8217;t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/NdZHo3xuZvw" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He claims to have the altruistic goal of helping humanity live decades longer, of increasing the time they have to accomplish great things, which is noble of him. I wonder, though, if people would be able to achieve great things if they have to focus so intensely and with such effort and expense on their personal vanity. Is extending life span (which Johnson has not done) really worth it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the male spider. He&amp;#8217;s small relative to the female, who is a ruthless predator with no qualms against cannibalism. Should he expend most of his effort in growth, bulking up and building his strength, trying to match the physical advantages of the female? Or should he be content with being small, fast, and agile, quickly scampering to females at the earliest possible age to take his shot?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can tell you that my spiders have chosen the scamper strategy. If they tried to focus on body building before daring to mate, they&amp;#8217;d find that a scamperer had been there before them. And that the female might eat them anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you prefer human analogies, imagine that Alexander the Great had stayed home in Pella, abstaining from wine, living on a spare diet of pulses, slathering his face with the richest cosmetics. He&amp;#8217;d probably have lived to be as old as Bryan Johnson! He wouldn&amp;#8217;t have had &amp;#8220;the Great&amp;#8221; slapped on his name, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe Alexander the Vain?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Does this man look 18 to you? How about 30? I would have guessed he was in his 40s, and would have won a kewpie doll. He’s 45. His name is Bryan Johnson. He has, however, set himself the goal of reversing aging and getting his ‘epigenetic age’ down to something absurd, by making his […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69296</id>
    <published>2023-02-14T16:26:02Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-14T16:26:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>True Love</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/14/true-love-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">My kind of Valentine’s Day.</p>
<div id="attachment_69294" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove-500x660.png" alt="" width="500" height="660" class="size-large wp-image-69294" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove-500x660.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove-114x150.png 114w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove-227x300.png 227w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/truelove.png 752w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.thefarside.com/2023/02/14/1">The Far Side</a></p></div>
<p>My wife gave me three spiders she caught around the house. Did you get any signs of affection today?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My kind of Valentine’s Day. My wife gave me three spiders she caught around the house. Did you get any signs of affection today?</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69293</id>
    <published>2023-02-14T13:35:41Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-14T13:35:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Creepy Uncle Jordy has some advice about rape</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/14/creepy-uncle-jordy-has-some-advice-about-rape/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan.png"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan-143x150.png" alt="" width="143" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69290" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan-143x150.png 143w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan-287x300.png 287w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan-500x523.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/creepyunclejordan.png 636w" sizes="(max-width: 143px) 100vw, 143px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="lead"&gt;He has sympathy for the idea that rape is not a property crime, but a crime against a person, &lt;em&gt;BUT&lt;/em&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-width="500" data-dnt="true"&gt;
&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Jordan “just asking questions” Peterson ponders if rape being bad cuz it violates women’s consent is a good enough justification. Maybe we should consider how it hurts the women’s male “protectors” &lt;a href="https://t.co/MZZv9kmgBr"&gt;https://t.co/MZZv9kmgBr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Biden’s Gamer Lights (@shitposter1312) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/shitposter1312/status/1625289057084342273?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;February 14, 2023&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, you can say that untrammeled sexual access to a woman is a crime, but it needs to be criminalized in such a way that men still flock to her defense. It&amp;#8217;s not sufficient to have a society where a woman can say &amp;#8220;no&amp;#8221;, you also have to arrange it so that she will have enraged masculine protectors surrounding her.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Continuing this reasoning based entirely on the idea that women are helpless, I don&amp;#8217;t think it&amp;#8217;s sufficient that it&amp;#8217;s against the law to beat up weak old men and steal their money, we have to rally beefcake to defend them when they step out on the street. Likewise, it&amp;#8217;s terrible that birds are preyed upon by cats…we need to put an army of strong young men who are angry on patrol in our parks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the logic of a bully who thinks the solution to everything has to be force, preferably force delivered by some brutish male. Reduce everything to a question of whether a gang of men will support it &amp;#8212; that&amp;#8217;s the way the Proud Boys think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quickly, before they usual mob starts screaming about &amp;#8220;CONTEXT!&amp;#8221; &amp;#8212; that short clip comes from a nauseatingly long (one hour and 45 minutes!) &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rGsZ_HI_q1M"&gt;interview by Louise Perry, a conservative &amp;#8220;feminist&amp;#8221;&lt;/a&gt;. This clip comes from around 1h 30m in the whole thing, and precedes a bit where he explains that &amp;#8220;unsophisticated women&amp;#8221; don&amp;#8217;t say &amp;#8220;no&amp;#8221; soon enough or strongly enough, but hey, he&amp;#8217;s not blaming the victim, he says. If we could fix this, we wouldn&amp;#8217;t have this huge debate about consent on college campuses, he claims.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What debate? I think it&amp;#8217;s settled. Non-consensual sexual assault is bad. No debate necessary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;#8217;t listen to the whole thing. Five minutes of pompous babbling with weird hand gestures is about all I can take.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">He has sympathy for the idea that rape is not a property crime, but a crime against a person, BUT… Jordan “just asking questions” Peterson ponders if rape being bad cuz it violates women’s consent is a good enough justification. Maybe we should consider how it hurts the women’s male “protectors” https://t.co/MZZv9kmgBr — Biden’s Gamer […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69289</id>
    <published>2023-02-14T12:53:08Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-14T12:53:08Z</updated>
    <category term="Feminism, Gender, and Equality"/>
    <category term="Fools, Tools, Kooks, and Goons"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do spiders celebrate Darwin’s birthday?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/13/do-spiders-celebrate-darwins-birthday/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">It was yesterday, in case you forgot.  Over the weekend, the spiders produced two more egg sacs, and they also ate one of my precious males.</p>
<p>To celebrate the fecundity, they all got big fat slow waxworms for breakfast today. They’re all off munching right now.</p>
<p>I tried to tell them that they ought to get romancing for Valentine’s Day, too.</p>
<p>I’d show you a picture of a big fat slow waxworm getting eaten by a very happy spider, but I’ve been avoiding horrifying you all with those closeup images of my beautiful charges. You can find the carnage on my <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/78633014">Patreon</a> or <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/ConE-h6rxUO/">Instagram</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It was yesterday, in case you forgot. Over the weekend, the spiders produced two more egg sacs, and they also ate one of my precious males. To celebrate the fecundity, they all got big fat slow waxworms for breakfast today. They’re all off munching right now. I tried to tell them that they ought to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69287</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T17:21:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T17:21:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Spiders"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New hope for less controversial Alzheimer’s drug</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6075/new-hope-for-less-controversial-alzheimers-drug#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;img title="Histopathology of amyloid plaque in Alzheimer's disease" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Histopathology_of_amyloid_plaque_in_Alzheimer_s_disease.jpeg" height="576" alt="Amyloid plaque in Alzheimer's disease" width="780"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In 2021 the drug Aducanumab became the first new treatment for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease (AD) to be approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 20 years. But it was surrounded by serious questions over the design, analysis, efficacy and safety of the underlying trials, as well as the conduct of the FDA itself (see &lt;em&gt;New Humanist &lt;/em&gt;Autumn 2021).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Like many drugs in the pipeline, Aducanumab targets build-ups of the beta-amyloid protein, known as &amp;ldquo;plaque&amp;rdquo;, in the brain. The hypothesis is that this plaque collects between neurons and disrupts their normal function, playing a causal role in the development of AD. Whilst the theory has been the basis of decades of research, scientists remain divided over its validity. The controversy surrounding Aducanumab&amp;rsquo;s approval did little to settle the debate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Then, in late 2022, a clinical trial reported significant results in targeting the &amp;ldquo;brain plaque&amp;rdquo; so central to this hypothesis. A new compound, Lecanemab, was again approved under an accelerated procedure by the FDA. However, the results of the trial, published in the &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, have largely been received with greater hope and confidence than the Aducanumab debacle. They appear to provide evidence for the first time of both significant reductions in plaque and, crucially, a slowing in the rate of decline in cognition by 27 per cent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;We are yet to find out who might benefit. Treatment with the drug requires two weekly transfusions and will cost over $25,000 per patient per year in the US. In the UK, medical regulators are yet to announce their timeline for considering Lecanemab (they never gave the green light to Aducanumab).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Excitement has also been muted among researchers due to concerns over adverse events. The drug has only been trialled, so far, in early-stage AD patients and some experts say it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely to help those who are further down the line. However, there is still cause for optimism. If Lecanemab is approved, it would be the first time a drug is made available to AD sufferers that targets the cause of the disease, rather than the symptoms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;This article is a preview from our New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6075/new-hope-for-less-controversial-alzheimers-drug#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:47:23Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:47:23Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tracking the anti-abortion backlash</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6078/tracking-the-anti-abortion-backlash#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="'40 Days for Life' campaign outside the British Pregnancy Advisory Service (BPAS) offices, London." src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Bedford_Square_anti-abortion_protestors.jpeg" height="865" alt="'40 Days for Life' outside the British Pregnancy Advisory Service (BPAS) offices, London." width="1472"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The image of religious protesters outside an abortion clinic &amp;ndash; holding candles and praying, or shouting at young women while brandishing gruesome posters &amp;ndash; conjures a particular place. We think of the United States. Not everyone knows that this kind of scene also plays out in the UK. Efforts are now being made to protect British women seeking to exercise their reproductive rights. This has created a backlash from anti-abortion protestors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Buffer zones are areas outside clinics providing abortion, implemented to prevent women from being abused and harassed on their way in and out. In Northern Ireland, a bill to make it a criminal offence to protest within 150 metres of any clinic is currently passing through parliament. In December, the UK&amp;rsquo;s Supreme Court ruled that while the bill did restrict protesters&amp;rsquo; rights, these restrictions were justified.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The court acknowledged that the case was &amp;ldquo;highly sensitive&amp;rdquo; but stated that the women accessing abortion services &amp;ldquo;have a reasonable expectation of being able to do so without being confronted by protest activity designed to challenge and diminish their autonomy and undermine their resolve.&amp;rdquo; It took into account that clinic staff could also be intimidated, harassed and abused. Legislation is also now passing through parliaments in England and Wales, and is being considered in Scotland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The president of the American anti-abortion campaigning group 40 Days for Life responded to the Supreme Court ruling with a video promising immediate action. This is a US-based group, but it is active in Northern Ireland and Scotland. In September 2022, the group organised a six-week &amp;ldquo;prayer vigil&amp;rdquo; targeting clinics in Edinburgh, Glasgow, Aberdeen, Dundee and Falkirk. It is just one of several anti-abortion groups who strongly oppose buffer zones, framing it as a free speech issue.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The first legally enforced buffer zone in the UK was created in 2018 in the west London area of Ealing. Soon after this, the government rejected calls for nationwide buffer zones in England and Wales. Since then, 50 clinics have been targeted by anti-abortion protesters in England and Wales, according to the British Pregnancy Advisory Service (BPAS). But there are presently only five buffer zones in England, including in Bournemouth, where the director of anti-abortion group March for Life Isabel Vaughan-Spruce was arrested outside a clinic in December.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Clare Murphy, BPAS chief executive, said: &amp;ldquo;Anti-choice groups routinely follow women and healthcare professionals as they enter and leave clinics, display graphic banners of dismembered foetuses, and tell women that if they terminate a pregnancy, they risk breast cancer and long-term mental illness.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The level of resistance and organisation from anti-abortion groups indicates that even if the new laws go through, and more buffer zones are created, this will not be the end of the fight. It&amp;rsquo;s one that we must win.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;This piece is a preview from our New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6078/tracking-the-anti-abortion-backlash#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:46:58Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:46:58Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Policing the internet</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6079/policing-the-internet#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Internet_Security_Padlock_for_VPN___Online_Privacy.jpeg" height="334" alt="Internet security padlock" width="418"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;br&gt;How to make the internet safe has been the subject of fraught debate in Britain for years. What might sound at first like a set of clear goals around the protection of children and prevention of crime quickly becomes entangled in questions around responsibility and what counts as &amp;ldquo;harmful content&amp;rdquo;. As&lt;em&gt; New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; goes to print, the Online Safety Bill is passing through the House of Lords: a piece of legislation that has become so complex and bloated that it risks sneaking through changes that threaten our privacy and freedom of speech.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The bill would hold tech firms accountable for carrying harmful content such as revenge pornography or child sex abuse material, or selling illegal drugs or weapons. CEOs of online platforms like Facebook or TikTok could be fined, or even jailed, for failing in their duty of care.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;This all sounds like progress, particularly as the key aim is to keep children safe online. The fly in the ointment is the argument that, if tech companies are to be responsible for hosting content, they must be able to access it. This isn&amp;rsquo;t such an issue for search engines like Google, but what about messaging services? A clause in the bill has mandated that tech companies provide the ability to scan end-to-end encrypted messaging for child sex abuse material, so that it can be reported to authorities. But those concerned with privacy have raised the alarm about the risk of eroding encryption.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;We all feel that the only person reading our message should be its intended recipient. Popular messaging services like WhatsApp advertise themselves on this basis &amp;ndash; but not all end-to-end encrypted services are equally secure. Clearly, putting in a backdoor is likely to weaken these protections further, and could be used well beyond its intended scope.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;There is also a risk that the bill will erode freedom of expression. Worryingly, an amendment has been introduced that, in the words of culture secretary Michelle Donelan, prohibits &amp;ldquo;posting videos of people crossing the channel which shows that activity in a positive light&amp;rdquo;. This is a far cry from the original intention of the legislation. A photograph of a family in their lifejackets will not be the thing that persuades someone to flee conflict or persecution. Meanwhile, it could have a chilling effect on NGOs, and hamper the essential gathering of footage and information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The internet is a fluid and rapidly evolving space, intimately bound up with our lives. And while legislation might be overdue, that&amp;rsquo;s no reason to rush through law that has unintended consequences. Safety online is vital, but it&amp;rsquo;s just as important that we get it right.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is a preview from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here. &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6079/policing-the-internet#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:46:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:46:36Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How to move an object from a distance</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6074/how-to-move-an-object-from-a-distance#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="An artist's visualisation of sound waves" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Visualization_of_Sound_Waves_-_10_of_10.jpeg" height="808" alt="Visualisation of sound waves" width="1596"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;For &lt;em&gt;Star Wars &lt;/em&gt;super-fans, spring is a special time of year. The fourth of May is Star Wars Day, aka &amp;ldquo;May the fourth be with you&amp;rdquo;, a play on the franchise&amp;rsquo;s well-known phrase &amp;ldquo;may the Force be with you&amp;rdquo;. The Force is a mysterious entity within the Star Wars Universe that Jedi harness to give them special powers, including the ability to move and levitate objects from a distance. But apart from being the answer to the pub quiz question &amp;ldquo;What links &lt;em&gt;Star Wars, Matilda&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Stranger Things&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;rdquo;, telekinetic powers only exist in science fiction.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;And yet, we have recently mastered the art of manipulating objects without touching them. How? By using light and sound waves. When these waves bounce from the surface of an object, a little bit of the momentum of the wave is transferred to the object. This change in momentum, occurring over a short time-period, manifests as a force. And if the force is larger than any other forces acting on the object, like gravity or friction for example, then the object will move in the direction of the momentum shift.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;This effect is easily achieved for tiny objects similar in size to the wavelength of the wave being used &amp;ndash; millimetres for sound and nanometers for light. Any bigger than that and the effect is a mere tickle on the surface. That is, unless you do something special to the surface that guides and concentrates the momentum shift in a particular direction so that the force becomes controllable and significant.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;A group from the University of Minnesota has done just that, by using metamaterials that have very specific, sub-millimetre patterns etched into the surface to manipulate and steer the sound waves as they interact. Their experiment, published recently in&lt;em&gt; Nature Communications&lt;/em&gt;, involved a 7cm-long piece of 3D-printed plastic, designed to incorporate a pattern of shallow grooves along one edge. Sure enough, the team was able to move the object sideways and, remarkably, pull it back towards the source of the sound.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;By optimising and scaling up this approach, the team is hoping to apply it to contactless control in robotics.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is a preview from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6074/how-to-move-an-object-from-a-distance#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:45:37Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:45:37Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>One step closer to easy green energy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6076/one-step-closer-to-easy-green-energy#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Burning hydrogen produces nothing more polluting than water vapour." src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/water.jpeg" height="1063" alt="Burning hydrogen produces water vapour." width="1596"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;Hydrogen has long been touted as a potentially revolutionary green source of energy. Burning the gas produces nothing more polluting than water vapour, and making it is trivially easy. Just hook up some electrodes to an electric current, then dunk them in water. Try it with a nine-volt battery and a couple of wires and you&amp;rsquo;ll soon see bubbles of hydrogen forming on one wire and oxygen on the other. Given that the chemistry is so simple, and we have access to literally oceans of raw materials, why haven&amp;rsquo;t we already transitioned to a hydrogen economy? &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Unfortunately, unless your water is incredibly pure, you will initiate a load of other wholly undesirable chemical reactions. This means direct electrolysis of sea water is unfeasible. You could desalinate the water first, but this requires more energy than would be obtained from burning the hydrogen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Thankfully, a team from Nanjing Tech University, China have recently solved this problem by combining the evaporation and electrolysis steps inside a single reactor. The reactor consists of two chambers &amp;ndash; one with sea water, the other with salt-free water and the electrodes. Separating the chambers are a pair of waterproof breathable membranes (much like those in your waterproof jacket) with gas trapped between them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Potassium hydroxide is added to the water in the inner chamber until it is at a higher concentration than the salt in the sea water. This means the water will diffuse from the sea water chamber to the higher concentration chamber within. But the only way it can move from one chamber to the other is via the gas-filled gap between the membranes. Liquid water can&amp;rsquo;t make it through, but water vapour can &amp;ndash; leaving the salt behind. The clean water can then be safely split into hydrogen and oxygen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The team have already extensively tested the system, producing over a million litres of hydrogen gas in just a few months. With cheap hydrogen production now within our sights, we can think about how to use it for transport, heavy industries and to heat our homes. We are one step closer to a source of green energy that is also easy and practical.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is a preview from our New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6076/one-step-closer-to-easy-green-energy#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:45:17Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:45:17Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION FEBRUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/open-discussion-february-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978493</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JANUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/01/open-discussion-january-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978482</id>
    <published>2023-01-01T10:47:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-01T10:47:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>BOOK CLUB 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/01/book-club-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the 2023 follow-on from the 2022 BOOK CLUB thread, which is now closed, though you can easily refer back to earlier discussions by clicking on the link. BOOK CLUB 2023 has been created to provide a dedicated space for the discussion of books. Pretty much any kind of book – it doesn’t have …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978479</id>
    <published>2023-01-01T10:40:58Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-01T10:40:58Z</updated>
    <category term="Featured"/>
    <category term="Special Topic"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Secular Rescue – Saving Freedom, Saving Lives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/12/secular-rescue-saving-freedom-saving-lives/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supporter, December 10 is recognized around the world as Human Rights Day. The theme this year is “Dignity, Freedom, and Justice for All.” Those are wonderful ideals, enjoyed by far too few across the globe. Secular Rescue works to improve (and often to save) the lives of atheists and nonbelievers living in places that would …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978469</id>
    <published>2022-12-12T14:57:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-12T14:57:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
