<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-02-27T12:39:18Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Florida, again</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/26/florida-again/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students-150x115.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="115" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69415" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students-150x115.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students-300x231.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students-500x384.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/florida-students.jpeg 700w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Now they’re planning to destroy higher ed in the state by putting <a href="https://www.tampabay.com/news/education/2023/02/23/florida-bill-would-end-diversity-programs-ban-majors-shift-power-universities/">everything in the hands of the governor and his appointed cronies</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>A bill filed this week in the Florida House would turn many of Gov. Ron DeSantis’ wide-ranging ideas on higher education into law by limiting diversity efforts, vastly expanding the powers of university boards and altering course offerings.</p>
<p>House Bill 999, filed by Rep. Alex Andrade, R-Pensacola, proposes leaving all faculty hiring to boards of trustees, allowing a faculty member’s tenure to be reviewed “at any time,” and removing majors or minors in subjects like critical race theory and gender studies. It would also prohibit spending on activities that promote diversity, equity and inclusion and create new general education requirements.</p></blockquote>
<p>You want to read the whole bill? <a href="https://www.flsenate.gov/Session/Bill/2023/999/BillText/Filed/PDF">Here it is</a>.</p>
<p>My sympathies to my colleagues in Florida. This is a terrible time to be looking for a new job — colleges everywhere are struggling — but do you really want Chris Rufo deciding whether to fire you or not?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Now they’re planning to destroy higher ed in the state by putting everything in the hands of the governor and his appointed cronies. A bill filed this week in the Florida House would turn many of Gov. Ron DeSantis’ wide-ranging ideas on higher education into law by limiting diversity efforts, vastly expanding the powers of […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69414</id>
    <published>2023-02-26T16:00:40Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-26T16:00:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Academics"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Wow, Florida…</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/26/wow-florida/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I’m sorry, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/brucelee/2023/02/24/lee-county-florida-republican-party-passes-resolution-to-ban-covid-19-vaccines/?sh=5816f01536dc">Florida is a joke</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>If the Lee County Republican Party has their way, the state of Florida will be banning the use of Covid-19 vaccines. Yes, you heard that correctly. Based on a majority vote, the Party has passed a so-called “Ban the jab” resolution that will now go to the desk of Florida Governor Ron DeSantis (R) for his consideration. And why does the Party want such a ban? Well, <a href="https://winknews.com/2023/02/21/ban-the-jab-proposed-resolution-vote-tuesday-evening/">an article for WINK News by Michael Hudak and Taylor Wirtz</a> quoted Joe Sansone, the guy who drafted the resolution, as saying, “The Lee County Republican Party is going to be on the vanguard of this campaign to stop the genocide because we have foreign non-governmental entities that are unleashing biological weapons on the American people.”</p></blockquote>
<p>This Sansone clown is a “psychotherapist” who clearly knows nothing about biology. He claims the vaccine is a “bioweapon”, and he has the ear of the governor. Do you think DeSantis will refuse to sign his insane declaration?</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda-500x326.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="326" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69412" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda-500x326.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda-150x98.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda-300x195.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda-768x500.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/sansone-agenda.jpg 1565w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Sansone is pretty far out there.</p>
<blockquote><p>The WINK article also included another quote from Sansone that really seemed to embrace some conspiracy theory claims: “If you got this shot, you go home and hug your pregnant wife—she can have a miscarriage through skin contact.” Wait, so now, you’ve got to start worrying about hugging people who have gotten Covid-19 vaccines? How exactly is that supposed to work scientifically? Did Sansone provide any peer-reviewed scientific studies to support his assertion? Most likely not, because good luck trying to find any peer-reviewed scientific studies to support such an assertion.</p></blockquote>
<p>Don’t worry, though, he has been <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/therapists/joseph-sansone-bonita-springs-fl/426823">verified by Psychology Today</a>, so you can trust him. PT would never publish a wackaloon, right? (Actually, I feel like Psychology Today is the Florida of pop-sci magazines.)</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Joseph Sansone, M.S., PhD, LMHC, CCMHC, is the author of Bioplasticity: Hypnosis Mind Body Healing. A psychotherapist specializing in clinical hypnosis, Joseph was trained in advanced clinical hypnosis at the Academy of Professional Hypnosis in 1997. Dr. Sansone has a B.A. in psychology, a M.S. in clinical mental health counseling, and a PhD in psychology. Joseph has spent much of his life as an entrepreneur and enjoys facilitating self-actualization. Joseph Sansone is a licensed mental health counselor as well as a board certified clinical mental health counselor. Dr. Sansone is also a member of the National Guild of Hypnotists.</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’m sorry, Florida is a joke. If the Lee County Republican Party has their way, the state of Florida will be banning the use of Covid-19 vaccines. Yes, you heard that correctly. Based on a majority vote, the Party has passed a so-called “Ban the jab” resolution that will now go to the desk of […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69411</id>
    <published>2023-02-26T13:42:39Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-26T13:42:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Bad science"/>
    <category term="Fools, Tools, Kooks, and Goons"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hmmm, I was right?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/25/hmmm-i-was-right/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/dilbert-gravestone.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/dilbert-gravestone-150x113.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="113" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69409" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/dilbert-gravestone-150x113.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/dilbert-gravestone.jpeg 250w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I said we should <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/24/cancel-scott-adams/">cancel Scott Adams</a>, and gosh, look what happened: people spoke up all across the country, and <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2023/02/25/scott-adams-dilbert-canceled/">Scott Adams was canceled</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Newspapers across the United States have pulled Scott Adams’s long-running “Dilbert” comic strip after the cartoonist called Black Americans a “hate group” and said White people should “get the hell away from” them.</p></blockquote>
<p>I guess it’s easy to be a prophet when you predict the obvious stuff.</p>
<p>One could argue that this means Adams will be whining indignantly about injustice and those damned libs some more, but that’s fine, he has free speech, he can complain all he wants, I simply won’t be hearing about it and can take some satisfaction in the fact that he won’t be making as much money off his bigotry anymore.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I said we should cancel Scott Adams, and gosh, look what happened: people spoke up all across the country, and Scott Adams was canceled. Newspapers across the United States have pulled Scott Adams’s long-running “Dilbert” comic strip after the cartoonist called Black Americans a “hate group” and said White people should “get the hell away […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69408</id>
    <published>2023-02-25T22:33:57Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-25T22:33:57Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Probably touched by an angel</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/25/probably-touched-by-an-angel/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Asbury University is a small Christian college in Kentucky with a reputation for promoting these <a href="https://news.yahoo.com/asbury-university-revival-explained-153135027.html">weird cultish revival meetings</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>What started as a standard chapel service on Feb. 8 quickly ballooned into something much larger than anyone could have anticipated. “The first day we had a very ordinary service, I would call it unremarkable,” university President Dr. Kevin Brown told NBC News. But by nightfall, students began returning to the auditorium, joining the group of those that stuck around after the initial mass. More followed, and more, and more, until the chapel was overflowing with students eager to join their peers in prayer. For the next 12 days, the ever-growing congregation worshipped around the clock, as word of the movement meanwhile spread like wildfire on social media, encouraging thousands of pious hopefuls to trek to Asbury and join what many participants had dubbed a “revival.”</p></blockquote>
<p>It did go in <a href="https://kentuckylantern.com/briefs/someone-who-attended-the-large-spiritual-revival-at-asbury-university-has-measles/">a direction nobody anticipated</a>. Hallelujah! Praise Jesus!</p>
<blockquote><p>Someone who attended the “large spiritual revival” at Asbury University on Feb. 18 has measles, the Kentucky Cabinet for Health and Family Services announced Friday night. </p>
<p>“Anyone who attended the revival on Feb. 18 may have been exposed to measles,” Dr. Steven Stack, commissioner of the Kentucky Department for Public Health, said in a statement. “Attendees who are unvaccinated are encouraged to quarantine for 21 days and to seek immunization with the measles vaccine, which is safe and effective.”</p></blockquote>
<p>The Lord works in mysterious ways.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles-500x461.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="461" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69406" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles-500x461.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles-150x138.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles-300x277.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/measles.jpeg 605w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Asbury University is a small Christian college in Kentucky with a reputation for promoting these weird cultish revival meetings. What started as a standard chapel service on Feb. 8 quickly ballooned into something much larger than anyone could have anticipated. “The first day we had a very ordinary service, I would call it unremarkable,” university […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69405</id>
    <published>2023-02-25T13:30:23Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-25T13:30:23Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A peek into the fantasies of a creationist</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/02/25/a-peek-into-the-fantasies-of-a-creationist/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">In case you ever wondered what kind of schlock a creationist would churn out if they decided to write fiction, I give you…<a href="https://www.smashwords.com/books/view/1176422"><q><i>Mythic Evolution</i></q></a>, a collection of short stories written by Miguel Atkinson.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>Finally the mysteries of evolution may be revealed! Short stories on evolution collected to enjoy! From the World’s Greatest Evolutionist appearing to solve every mystery of evolution to the raw power of the Lightning Evolutionist, the world of evolution may never be the same!</p></blockquote>
<p>I know, you’re curious, but like me, you don’t want to pay $3.99 to read any of these glorious works of creative writing. Fortunately, he provides a free sample, which I include below the fold, which simultaneously will satisfy your curiosity about the content and will cure you of any desire to read further. But first, I’ll tell you what I found interesting about it.</p>
<p>Here is the cover to the book.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution-500x707.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="707" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69403" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution-500x707.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution-106x150.jpg 106w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution-212x300.jpg 212w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/02/mythic-evolution-768x1086.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Even conservative Christians know that sex sells! The orientation of the image is a bit odd, and I found myself wondering why this woman is wearing her lab safety goggles around her thigh.</p>
<p>Then the sample story is about…a debate at a science conference. Creationists certainly have a skewed perspective on what science involves, don’t they? In this story, his mystery man scientist — who is wearing a lab coat and safety goggles, of course — presents his dazzling theory. Or rather, what a creationist thinks would be a typical scientific explanation.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>…humans like bananas even though they are not native to their locality. Here we see humans remember their ape-like diet. Humans love bananas and apes love bananas. I call it, theory of evolutionary flavor!!! Haha! Why? Therefore evolution.</p></blockquote>
<p>Then the creationist, Dr. Roman Sigfried, who is going to <q>end the lies of evolution</q> with a presentation of his evidence, reveals his rebuttal: photos of <q>human footprints and human bones on top of dinosaur tracks</q>. Atkinson has all the power of his imagination to conjure up a persuasive example, and he falls back on a debate that rehashes the Paluxy River footprints. It’s been done. It didn’t work.</p>
<p>The excerpt ends shortly after the evolutionist threatens to <q>kill</q> his opponent, so I guess we’ll never know how the big debate is resolved. I promise you won’t enjoy the full force of his muddled writing and twisted logic and limited imagination, but here’s the unadorned writing sample if you wish to torture yourself.</p>
<p><span id="more-69402"/></p>
<blockquote class="creationist">
<p>Months before when the man who shocked the world first appeared.</p>
<p>They were in a large crowd at a small science conference. A small debate of two notable men. Dr. Roman Sigfried, a leader in denouncing evolution hoaxes like the flying pig pictures awhile back. And Dr. Martin Apel who cancelled suddenly!</p>
<p>Although this was a small get together, it garnered more attention as Dr. Sigfried was basically saying it was the end of evolution once he presented. This caused a few local news crews to stop by but the buzz wasn’t like a concert or anything. Still, the turnout was higher than recent years and many professionals as well as people of varied experience showed up for the debate and presentation.</p>
<p>“It’s time we end the lies of evolution. After my presentation of the evidence, I suspect everyone will finally realize it was dead on arrival,” the doctor said to the blonde newswoman.</p>
<p>The newswoman ran down the hall to the other doctor to get a comment as well. “I have come to reveal my latest research not indulge in fantasy like Dr. Roman. Stay tuned!” the mystery substitute said as they both moved to the stage. The podiums were ready as well as the massive screen for their displaying evidence.</p>
<p>The university had scheduled a debate on evolution and creation for over a month. Unfortunately, the evolutionist had cancelled. No doubt in fear of his opponent who had won several thus far. Rather than cancel the whole event, a substitute had been chosen due to his eagerness. A complete unknown with little in credentials. Yet, he stood boldly in his white coat with safety goggles atop his head as if he had just finished some experiment!</p>
<p>The Creation advocate stood up in a dark suit at his podium. The audience bought snacks as they prepared for a break from the usual school events. “My opponent Dr. Apel was too busy to make it. I don’t blame him. The last time we spoke, he was trying to convince me evolution was real because he had lower back pain!” Dr. Roman said with a smile. They laughed.</p>
<p>“As if that was proof that he used to walk on four legs? I mean, what kind of proof is he thinking of? That man ‘evolved’ from hippo? I have never met our substitute but I hope you won’t be using Dr. Apel’s arguments,” Dr. Roman said as he gestured to him.</p>
<p>The man in the lab coat gladly spoke up.</p>
<p>“I too have heard this foolish idea. People say lower back pain proves evolution. I think we all see the faulty logic in that. Anyone can hurt their back or twist it even whilst sleeping. It’s much more logical to say humans like bananas even though they are not native to their locality. Here we see humans remember their ape-like diet. Humans love bananas and apes love bananas. I call it, theory of evolutionary flavor!!! Haha! Why? Therefore evolution.” the man declared before the stunned audience.</p>
<p>“Well, of course bananas are delicious! But still!” Dr. Roman said as he continued on his evidence tearing into evolution. The crowd was half pleased and half angry.</p>
<p>Dr. Roman went into his presentation in depth. The screen flashed with photos of the footprints.</p>
<p>“Now, these human footprints and human bones on top of dinosaur tracks clearly undo the idea of billions of years! It is utter nonsense and the time to let go, no, the time to destroy the lies is here!” Dr. Roman shouted to applause. But the evolutionists were furious!</p>
<p>“I’m going to kill this fucker,” the evolutionist mumbled to himself.</p>
<p>He turned to his opponent happily. “Well?” Dr. Roman said.</p>
<p>“Are you finished? Yes, well, I suppose that is a nice transition point for me, thank you. As Dr. Roman just put it, it is impossible for humans to live at this time,” the unknown man said from his podium.</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In case you ever wondered what kind of schlock a creationist would churn out if they decided to write fiction, I give you…Mythic Evolution, a collection of short stories written by Miguel Atkinson. Finally the mysteries of evolution may be revealed! Short stories on evolution collected to enjoy! From the World’s Greatest Evolutionist appearing to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69402</id>
    <published>2023-02-25T11:59:40Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-25T11:59:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Creationism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: The Age of the Strongman</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6085/book-review-the-age-of-the-strongman#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/ageofstrongman.jpg" height="697" alt="The Age of the Strongman by Gideon Rachman" width="462"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;The Age of the Strongman&lt;/strong&gt; (Bodley Head) by Gideon Rachman&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The rivalry between democracy and autocracy promises to define much of this century. The Age of the Strongman by the Financial Times&amp;rsquo; chief foreign affairs commentator Gideon Rachman attempts to explain how we got here. The central thrust is that, since the 1990s, the rise of a certain type of leader has become the key feature of &amp;ldquo;the most sustained global assault on liberal democracy since the 1930s&amp;rdquo;. By profiling 14 current-day leaders with authoritarian tendencies &amp;ndash; from central Europe to South America to the Philippines &amp;ndash; Rachman hopes to provide &amp;ldquo;political liberals&amp;rdquo; with an &amp;ldquo;understanding of what they are dealing with&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rachman begins with an outline of the &amp;ldquo;playbook&amp;rdquo; that has propelled strongmen into power. A common tactic is populist nationalism, which paints the strongman as a national saviour, pitting an ethnically and/or religiously defined nation against outside threats such as minority groups, migrants or a shadowy elite. In power, the erosion of civil liberties is a natural consequence. Rachman reminds us how strongmen have subjugated ethnic and religious communities in their countries. Whilst China&amp;rsquo;s Xi detains Uyghurs in &amp;ldquo;re-education&amp;rdquo; camps, Narendra Modi has effectively stripped millions of Muslims of their Indian citizenship. Independent institutions and organisations are neutered. While some strongmen, like Viktor Orb&amp;aacute;n, are known for hollowing out their country&amp;rsquo;s independent media, others, like Vladimir Putin, preside over countries where journalists regularly turn up dead.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Rachman refuses to explain the rise of this authoritarianism through the talents of strongmen alone, nor does he assert that certain countries are predisposed to this rule. Chapters on Boris Johnson and Donald Trump dispel the myth that the west is impervious to democratic decline. Instead, Rachman argues that the success of strongmen is a &amp;ldquo;symptom of the crisis of liberalism&amp;rdquo;, which has economic, political and diplomatic dimensions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Driving this crisis, according to Rachman, is an &amp;ldquo;overconfidence in the power of liberal ideas born from &amp;lsquo;victory&amp;rsquo; in the Cold War&amp;rdquo;. This prevented politicians and commentators from judging the true character of strongmen early in their careers. Rachman includes himself in this, going so far as to quote from one of his past articles that celebrated Modi&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;thrilling&amp;rdquo; rise. The free market&amp;rsquo;s most ardent defenders have since had to reckon with the compatibility of the system with authoritarianism.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But despite beginning what promises to be a meaningful critique of the liberal world order, Rachman never quite gets down to it. Instead, he regresses into clich&amp;eacute;. His acknowledgement of the ills of globalisation is descriptive at best. The term &amp;ldquo;neoliberalism&amp;rdquo; is dismissed as an invention of the populist left, as if it wasn&amp;rsquo;t the object of serious academic enquiry. Meanwhile, strongman critiques of the liberal world order go unexplored. Grievances against US foreign policy, Nato and the EU &amp;ndash; some of which may be justified &amp;ndash; are dismissed. It is unclear what Rachman has learnt from reckoning with post-Cold War politics.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This reversion to type is finalised in the book&amp;rsquo;s conclusion, where the strongman is dismissed as a short-lived fad, and we are told to trust the US to lead a new &amp;ldquo;human-rights based world order&amp;rdquo;. Rachman fails to take seriously the US&amp;rsquo; vulnerability to a Trump-like resurgence, or the grisly legacy of its foreign intervention since the Second World War. In the end, his pages are haunted by the same liberal overconfidence he finds complicit in the rise of the strongman. To strengthen liberalism against rising authoritarianism requires tougher questions of its historical record; perhaps even a consideration about the case for reinvention, something Rachman firmly rules out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6085/book-review-the-age-of-the-strongman#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-22T12:47:58Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-22T12:47:58Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Better, faster, stronger: New Humanist spring 2023 out now</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6080/better-faster-stronger-new-humanist-spring-2023-out-now#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2302-01-Cover.jpg" height="1994" alt="New Humanist spring 2023 cover" width="1596"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The spring 2023 issue of New Humanist is on sale now! &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt; to the print edition for as little as &amp;pound;27 a year. You can also &lt;a href="/supportus"&gt;buy a single copy&lt;/a&gt; for just &amp;pound;7.45. Available in all good newsagents.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h1&gt;Better, faster, stronger&lt;/h1&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The fountain of youth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peter Ward&lt;/strong&gt; on the longevity fanatics experimenting with gene therapy. Is there any value to this unregulated research?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;In 2015, at the age of 44, Parrish flew to Bogot&amp;aacute;, Columbia, to receive dozens of experimental gene therapy injections, with the goal of turning back her biological clock. By that time, she had founded her own company, BioViva. For her first public appearance as CEO, she had chosen to address the immortalist group People Unlimited, where she told a receptive crowd that she wanted to cure ageing, and do it fast enough that they could all benefit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;What dreams may come&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;In our obsession with getting more sleep, we are overlooking the strange mysteries of night terrors and other parasomnias, writes Diletta De Cristofaro&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;Vernon&amp;rsquo;s reflections on Dracula, the protagonist of Bram Stoker&amp;rsquo;s 1897 novel, note that he causes paralysis, somnambulism and night terrors in his victims. He was not just a vampire, she concludes, but &amp;ldquo;every parasomnia combined in the figure of a folkloric monster&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;The temple of the body &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;Weightlifters were once seen as freaks &amp;ndash; but now the fitness industry has taken over the world. Peter Salmon asks, how did we get here?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;In Christianity we are born with sin and spend our lives trying to repay that debt. In capitalism we must keep earning to stop our financial debt growing. This moral imperative is analogous with the prevalent framing of fitness today as an endless and unresolvable quest: one can always be fitter, and not pursuing this goal is a failing to oneself and to society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;Q&amp;amp;A: Anna Lembke&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;The program director of the Stanford Addiction Medicine Fellowship talks to &lt;strong&gt;J.P. O'Malley&lt;/strong&gt; about how to create a healthy pleasure-pain balance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;What I have seen over two decades of clinical work is parents who have assiduously insulated their children not just from painful experiences, but really any kind of challenging experiences. This means that children haven&amp;rsquo;t had the opportunity to build up the mental strength they need to live in the real world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The spring 2023 issue of New Humanist is on sale now! &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt; for as little as &amp;pound;10 a year.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Also in this issue:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2302-38-41-Jain-_1_.jpg" height="1064" alt="Indian widows are standing up for their rights" width="1596"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;ul&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sanket Jain &lt;/strong&gt;meets the women fighting back against India&amp;rsquo;s regressive widowhood traditions&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jen Stout&lt;/strong&gt; reports from Ukraine, where she joins the search for a missing writer taken by Russian forces.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;Sometimes voters get it wrong. &lt;strong&gt;Eliane Glaser &lt;/strong&gt;asks why we find this so hard to admit.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Euan Lawson&lt;/strong&gt; makes the case for drug consumption rooms, to tackle the UK's scandalously high rates of drug-related death.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Samira Ahmed &lt;/strong&gt;dives into the new trend for witch-lit. Is it all hocus-pocus? &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;It's 70 years since two men declared they had cracked DNA. &lt;strong&gt;Mark Lorch&lt;/strong&gt; pays tribute to the female scientists whose contributions were overlooked.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marie Le Conte&lt;/strong&gt; plays the surprise hit &lt;em&gt;Hades. &lt;/em&gt;Why are gamers addicted to dying, again and again?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;Bob Dylan has no intention of ageing gracefully, as &lt;strong&gt;Yo Zushi &lt;/strong&gt;discovers from the singer's latest work.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li class="p1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;J.R. Patterson&lt;/strong&gt; on the philosophy of travel and what we can learn today from&lt;em&gt; Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/li&gt; &lt;li&gt;PLUS: Columns from &lt;strong&gt;Michael Rosen&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Laurie Taylor&lt;/strong&gt;, book reviews, poems, cryptic crossword and &lt;strong&gt;Chris Maslanka&lt;/strong&gt;'s quiz&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ul&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Humanist is published four times a year by the Rationalist Association, a 136-year-old charity promoting reason and free enquiry. We're a quarterly magazine of culture, ideas, science and philosophy. To make a deeper commitment to our work, why not &lt;a href="/subscribe/billing"&gt;become a member&lt;/a&gt; of the Rationalist Association?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6080/better-faster-stronger-new-humanist-spring-2023-out-now#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-16T11:03:37Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-16T11:03:37Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hunting for Vakulenko</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6083/hunting-for-vakulenko#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Mass graves in Izium, Ukraine" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2K1D0CX.jpg" height="667" alt="Mass graves in Izium, Ukraine." width="1000"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;It was a beautiful, fresh October day in the pine forest near Izium, eastern Ukraine, when I walked among the empty graves, avoiding the discarded plastic gowns and gloves &amp;ndash; the Russian army trash. The sandy ground, once a place for picnics, was marred by gaping holes, splintered coffins, makeshift markers and spooled police tape. 447 people had been exhumed here.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Ahead and behind me, Ukrainian writers &amp;ndash; from Kyiv, Kharkiv, Lviv and elsewhere &amp;ndash; also lost for words, were moving slowly through the carnage. They had come, a &lt;br&gt;busload of them, to the recently liberated areas east of Kharkiv, looking for news of their colleague Volodymyr Vakulenko. Looking for grave 319, and hoping that the rumours were true, that he was never there.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;He was a very special man,&amp;rdquo; his friend Maksym Bespalov told me, then immediately corrected himself. &amp;ldquo;He is a very special man. Idealistic.&amp;rdquo; They&amp;rsquo;d met more than a decade ago &amp;ndash; Volodymyr was hugely active in the literary scene, publishing almanacs and magazines, getting published himself and winning awards for his books and poetry, organising festivals and encouraging younger writers. He turned to children&amp;rsquo;s books after the birth of his son. Maksym tells me Volodymyr &amp;ldquo;tries to be everywhere, involved in everything. A little bit crazy, perhaps. But we like him because he is him.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;What are his ideals, I asked Maksym. Without hesitation, he replied: &amp;ldquo;For all of the good versus all of the bad&amp;rdquo;. Volodymyr was an idealist; an outspoken, strident patriot who didn&amp;rsquo;t just write about the Ukrainian struggle but put himself on the line during the revolution of 2014.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Those who loved and admired Volodymyr &amp;ndash; and there are many &amp;ndash; had hopes he was in a Russian prison, awaiting trial. &amp;ldquo;We all understand the most truthful version is that he is dead,&amp;rdquo; Maksym said bluntly. &amp;ldquo;But when we speak about Volodya, we always say that we hope he&amp;rsquo;s still alive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;It was a hope shared by Olena Ihnatenko, the writer&amp;rsquo;s mother. Our next stop, once we&amp;rsquo;d made it through half-destroyed Izium and down cratered roads to the village of Kapytolivka, was Olena&amp;rsquo;s flat. She lives with her husband Vasyl and, now, Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s son Vitalik, who has autism and cannot speak. Volodymyr had hoped that the fact he was Vitalik&amp;rsquo;s sole guardian would mean the soldiers would leave him alone. He was wrong.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;Abducting a civilian&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;We all crammed into the flat and sat on the floor around Olena and Vasyl, like schoolchildren being told a story. They described the bombardment, the month in a cellar, the freezing cold and near-starvation. Then the troops arriving in the bombers&amp;rsquo; wake. Volodymyr, who had been living with Vitalik and his own father elsewhere in the village, apparently ran out when the soldiers came, and shouted, &amp;ldquo;The rashists are here!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Rashist&amp;rdquo; is a neat portmanteau of Russian, racist and fascist that provokes ire in Russian soldiers: it expresses the widely-held Ukrainian view that Russians are now little different to Hitler&amp;rsquo;s forces, which also invaded at 4am, 81 years earlier. It was in keeping with Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s stubborn, proud and undaunted character that he would shout this as the invaders arrived. It was also incredibly dangerous.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Vasyl, with pure white hair and bushy eyebrows, seems a kind, gentle old man; as he speaks to us he is calming Vitalik, stroking his shoulder and murmuring to him. Vitalik is rocking, agitated, staring at the strangers. He knows what&amp;rsquo;s going on, his grandmother insists &amp;ndash; just can&amp;rsquo;t express himself. The idea of this highly strung, nervous boy being seized by troops is almost incomprehensible. But on 22 March, that&amp;rsquo;s what happened.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Where&amp;rsquo;s your nationalist?&amp;rdquo; a soldier nicknamed &amp;ldquo;Bes&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Demon&amp;rdquo;, had demanded of Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s elderly father. His men turned the house upside down looking for pro-Ukrainian literature. Volodymyr, sensibly, had hidden the flags he&amp;rsquo;d kept from his time on the Maidan &amp;ndash; Ukraine&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Revolution of Dignity&amp;rdquo;, which overthrew corrupt ruler Viktor Yanukovych in 2014.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Both Volodymyr and Vitalik were taken to a nearby &amp;ldquo;special department&amp;rdquo; for a few hours, where Volodymyr was beaten, then both were returned home. Olena thinks it was probably a mistake that they took Vitalik. But Volodymyr knew they&amp;rsquo;d be back for him. It was at this point he took a shovel and dug a hole under the cherry tree in his father&amp;rsquo;s garden. He buried the notebook in which he&amp;rsquo;d been describing their life under occupation.&amp;ldquo;Give it to our guys [as everyone calls the Ukrainian Armed Forces] when they come,&amp;rdquo; he told his father.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;A little later the soldiers returned, grabbed the writer while he was cooking on an open fire in the garden, and threw him into a bus on which they&amp;rsquo;d daubed their infamous invasion symbol, the latin letter &amp;ldquo;Z&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;The torture of not knowing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;For Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s ex-wife, Vitalik&amp;rsquo;s mother Iryna Novitska, the lack of information was unbearable. She lives in central Ukraine and had begged him, as everyone had, to get out while he still could. Their last communication was on 7 March when he&amp;rsquo;d called to say troops had entered the village. Then a message, later that night: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve wiped my phone contacts&amp;rdquo;, to protect their identities from the soldiers, in case he was picked up.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The mobile networks were knocked out, one by one. Silence. Kapytolivka, like all the other villages and towns the Russians occupied, was swallowed up. It just disappeared into an information blackout for six long months. Relatives in free Ukraine had no idea if their loved ones in the occupied territories were hungry or fed, wounded or safe, imprisoned, scared . . . dead. Meanwhile, those inside the &amp;ldquo;dark zone&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t know what had become of the rest of the country. Propaganda from Moscow told them lies: Kharkiv has fallen, Kyiv has fallen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In the occupied towns, troops &amp;ndash; both from Russia and conscripts from the so-called &amp;ldquo;republics&amp;rdquo; of Donetsk and Luhansk &amp;ndash; roamed the streets, drunk and dangerous, searching men for &amp;ldquo;patriotic&amp;rdquo; tattoos, and taking them to torture cells, ten of which were later found in Izium alone. Informers were apparently active in the village. Volodomyr&amp;rsquo;s family suspect this is how he was picked up. Long before the invasion, he had predicted that the neighbours would turn him in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Throughout the spring and summer, 71-year-old Olena, struggling with the lack of food, medicine, gas, water and electricity, traipsed back and forth to checkpoints and distant military commanders&amp;rsquo; offices, searching for information about her son, and pleading with the Russians to let him go. The couple made written statements to the new &amp;ldquo;authorities&amp;rdquo;; detailed descriptions of Volodymyr and his arrest. The men promised they weren&amp;rsquo;t holding him; scoffed at the very suggestion. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re not Nazis!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Some rumours reached her; that her Vovka was in Russia, awaiting trial. Or in a prison in occupied Donetsk. After the region was liberated in September, there was a terrible confusion over the mass grave lists: &amp;ldquo;Vakulenko&amp;rdquo; from Kapytolivka was listed. But no date of death was given, and authorities said it was a woman&amp;rsquo;s body in that pit. Could it have been a mistake? &amp;ldquo;I am living on hope,&amp;rdquo; Olena told me, that day in October. &amp;ldquo;I have to. He&amp;rsquo;s my only son.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;The Executed Renaissance&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The idea that a children&amp;rsquo;s writer can be murdered because he believed in his own country is so absurd, so appalling, that you want to find another version of events to believe in. But actually, none of the writers I was with seemed surprised by what had likely happened to Volodymyr. Horrified, deeply angry, but not surprised. The killing of writers and artists, of creative people who shape a national culture, is nothing new in the grim history of Ukrainian&amp;ndash;Russian relations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Back in Kharkiv with the writers, I stayed one cold and eerie night in a building that stands as testament to Russia&amp;rsquo;s repeated attempts to wipe out Ukrainian cultural life: the House of the Word, or Slovo. Built in the late 1920s, it contained high-end apartments that accommodated Ukrainian writers and intellectuals. They were prized by the state in the brief period when Kharkiv was capital of Soviet Ukraine and had a flourishing literary scene. But then came the 1930s. The very idea of Ukrainian culture became anathema. In the countryside, Stalin killed millions with man-made famine, and in Kharkiv&amp;rsquo;s Slovo he killed the poets, playwrights and novelists. I lay awake in the dark listening to intermittent air-raid sirens and thinking of the night-time knocks from NKVD officers which preceded the execution of 33 of this building&amp;rsquo;s residents. But their senseless deaths &amp;ndash; many in a camp in northwest Russia &amp;ndash; did not prevent this group, known as the Executed Renaissance, from having a lasting influence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Victoria Amelina is their cultural descendant: a writer who vividly describes life, who is actively engaged in that old, old struggle to build a sovereign, free Ukraine. It was she who dug up Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s notebook in September, shortly after the Russians had fled Kapytolivka. She was in the area to document war crimes with an NGO. It took a few minutes of digging to find the little parcel. The day made a lasting, deep impression on her. &amp;ldquo;When you&amp;rsquo;re digging up the diary of a kidnapped writer from under a cherry tree, well &amp;ndash; you feel you&amp;rsquo;re somewhere in the 30s, when our writers were shot. Or in the 40s, under Nazi occupation,&amp;rdquo; she told a TV news crew covering the story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Victoria [who was interviewed in the Summer 2022 &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt;] kept a little acorn from the garden that day, a physical memory, and was still carrying it in her pocket when we spoke in November. &amp;ldquo;You know they took literature from his room?&amp;rdquo; she asked me. &amp;ldquo;Books with blue and yellow, or the trident [the Ukrainian national symbol]. They took some as proof of his being Ukrainian, they equal this with &amp;lsquo;Nazi&amp;rsquo;. This is how genocidal logic works.&amp;rdquo; With the family&amp;rsquo;s permission she handed the diary to the Kharkiv Literary Museum for safekeeping. &amp;ldquo;The museum has manuscripts of writers from the Executed Renaissance period; it&amp;rsquo;s symbolic.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;When I go to the museum, on a cold November day marked by power blackouts and snowfall, the curator, wearing white cotton gloves, gently pulls back the tissue paper and shows me the densely scrawled text, in black and red biro, scored out in places and spilling over into the margins. The very last line Volodymyr wrote in the diary he buried &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;I believe in victory!&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; is the same line I hear across Ukraine, day after day, week after week, as the war grinds on and people cling to their faith in their armed forces to drive out the occupier. Belief &amp;ndash; hope &amp;ndash; is non-negotiable. You must keep it, in order to keep going in the face of horror and terror.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;But hope can be terrible too. After the bodies from the mass graves were exhumed and taken to Kharkiv for analysis in September, the family were told to wait for DNA results. Olena still felt her son was alive. Nobody released from Izium&amp;rsquo;s many torture basements had seen Volodya that whole time. Perhaps he&amp;rsquo;d gone to prison?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In mid-November, while in Donbas reporting near the front line, I got a message from Iryna Novitska, Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s ex-wife. &amp;ldquo;Hope has turned to darkness,&amp;rdquo; she said simply. A photograph had emerged: gruesome, awful and irrefutably depicting Volodymyr before he was buried. Olena had seen it. It was all over.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Ukrainian journalists found the man who took the picture &amp;ndash; a local, tasked with collecting bodies and burying them in the pine forest during the occupation. He&amp;rsquo;d taken photos so relatives could identify the bodies later. Volodymyr&amp;rsquo;s body had not been taken from a morgue or basement but from a spot by the side of the road where he may have lain for weeks. The body had bullet holes in the stomach and chest, from a Soviet-era &amp;ldquo;Makarov&amp;rdquo; pistol.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Echoes of the past&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;The next day I took a detour on the way back to Kharkiv, to see Olena one last time. She was heartbroken and furious, thinking back to those long months walking, exhausted, round the checkpoints for information. She recalled a meeting in April with a Russian commander, how he looked at the wall behind her, not meeting her gaze: &amp;ldquo;He said, &amp;lsquo;We&amp;rsquo;re looking, there&amp;rsquo;s no information&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; and I knew then that he knew everything,&amp;rdquo; she said, shaking with anger. &amp;ldquo;Where my son was, what happened to him, everything. There was not the slightest point &amp;ndash; everyone knew, but no one was going to say.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Vitalik&amp;rsquo;s cartoons were playing in the background, and he was laughing at the TV. She hadn&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to tell him yet. He and Volodymyr were joined at the hip. It pained her that this boy was left without a father. She won&amp;rsquo;t be able to cope with his 24-hour-care for ever. Volodymyr used to joke with his mother that he&amp;rsquo;d live a long life, always taking care of Vitalik, going to a nursing home together in old age so they could be together for ever.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Oh and what have you done,&amp;rdquo; she cried suddenly, berating her son. &amp;ldquo;What have you done, oh God, oh my God.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;As a writer, his ex-wife Iryna said, Volodymyr &amp;ldquo;tried to say something in a way that no one had said before&amp;rdquo;. He loved the unusual, the amazing, the unique; his interests were wide-ranging, and though his heart and soul were in the Ukrainian fight, he made common cause with other people living under the shadow of Moscow&amp;rsquo;s empire: the Crimean Tatars, Armenians, Ichkerians, Belarussians.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The investigation into who shot him and why will go on, as will countless others; a long slow reckoning that will never provide all the answers. But the soldiers who took Volodymyr were clear: it was his &amp;ldquo;nationalism&amp;rdquo; that made him guilty. So many stories like this have been uncovered, of Russian soldiers convinced by propaganda back home that Ukraine is a nest of Nazis. Stripping people and ransacking houses for &amp;ldquo;evidence&amp;rdquo; like blue and yellow ribbons, trident tattoos, books in their own language.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Too often in this war, the echoes of the past are deafening: not just of the atrocities committed by the Nazis, but of Stalin&amp;rsquo;s terror the decade before that. We, in recent years, comfortably consigned all that to history, at least in Europe. The mass executions and jackbooted soldiers, the columns of tanks and sadistic torturers, informants and brave resisters, existed in a black-and-white era.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;To the Ukrainian woman digging up a diary of a disappeared children&amp;rsquo;s writer, just a few miles away from the heavy stench of mass graves, it is not history. Victoria Amelina thinks she knows why it&amp;rsquo;s happened again: there was never any reckoning for the Soviet Union&amp;rsquo;s crimes in Ukraine. And certainly no reckoning for what she calls the &amp;ldquo;annihilation of an entire generation of Ukrainian culture&amp;rdquo; in the 1930s: the execution of all those writers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;As there were blacklists then, there are blacklists now, she concluded. Activists, influencers, people to be removed first. The Russians [according to Ukrainian authorities] came with 45,000 body bags. &amp;ldquo;But they expected to win the war in three days,&amp;rdquo; Victoria said. &amp;ldquo;So those thousands of body bags were for whom? For me, I guess, and everyone else like me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6083/hunting-for-vakulenko#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-15T15:48:05Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-15T15:48:05Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Youthsick blues</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6081/youthsick-blues#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Bob Dylan on his Never Ending Tour" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/EBJ281.jpg" height="1075" alt="Bob Dylan does not intend to age gracefully" width="1596"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;br&gt;In a footnote to his essay &amp;ldquo;The Uncanny&amp;rdquo;, Sigmund Freud recounted what might today be called a &amp;ldquo;senior moment&amp;rdquo;. Sitting one night in a private train compartment, he suddenly sensed the presence of an &amp;ldquo;elderly gentleman in a dressing gown and a travelling cap&amp;rdquo;. The intruder wasn&amp;rsquo;t a ghost &amp;ndash; we&amp;rsquo;re talking Freud here, not Jung &amp;ndash; but he was a spooky and unwelcome apparition nonetheless, and the psychoanalyst &amp;ldquo;thoroughly disliked&amp;rdquo; his appearance. So he decided to tell this stranger to scram but, when he looked again, he realised that there was no one there. His adversary was nothing more than his &amp;ldquo;own reflection in the looking glass&amp;rdquo;. Doh!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Among the indignities of growing old is a feeling of disconnection between the eternal self of the mind and the physical self in decline . . . I think. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t know for sure because I&amp;rsquo;m only 41 &amp;ndash; a similar age to when the Jewish-born Bob Dylan recorded the unfocused yet daring &lt;em&gt;Shot of Love&lt;/em&gt;, his third largely Christian-themed album, back in 1981. If early middle age is still a time of peering around the bend to see what&amp;rsquo;s coming next, the slide towards old age is one of self-examination and settling accounts. Or so I gather from Dylan, who spent his forties in the 1980s promiscuously experimenting with world-views and audio production styles that were at odds with those of his first creative peak in the mid-1960s, only to drift back towards familiar ways and influences in the 1990s, then find mastery once again around the turn of the new millennium as a living museum-cum-R&amp;amp;D lab of traditional American musical forms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Now 81, Dylan is as vital an artist as he ever was &amp;ndash; indeed, more so &amp;ndash; as listening to his most recent collection of songs, &lt;em&gt;Rough and Rowdy Ways&lt;/em&gt; (2020), and reading his new book, &lt;em&gt;The Philosophy of Modern Song&lt;/em&gt;, a collection of essays about 66 pop, blues and country tunes, should make abundantly clear. He is rock&amp;rsquo;s world-bending Prospero, in full command of a tempest of his own making, not its rain-soaked Lear.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Yet the everyday tragedy of ageing is inescapable in his work. It&amp;rsquo;s apparently something that you can&amp;rsquo;t transcend even if you&amp;rsquo;re a Grammy-hoarding, Academy Award-winning Nobel laureate with a Pulitzer to boot and a body of work that will outlive us all. &amp;ldquo;How can a 17-year-old like me suddenly be 81?&amp;rdquo; the biologist Lewis Wolpert once asked. I wonder if Dylan asks himself this, too. Does he ever catch sight of an elderly gentleman in a dressing gown and a travelling cap in the dark windows of his tour bus and thoroughly dislike what he sees?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Not that it matters very much in the end. &amp;ldquo;Knowing a singer&amp;rsquo;s life story doesn&amp;rsquo;t particularly help your understanding of a song,&amp;rdquo; Dylan writes in his new book, and that&amp;rsquo;s true of a singer&amp;rsquo;s entire body of work, too. A preoccupation with the dying of the light, however, would explain why Dylan has raved with such exhilarating force at close of day, and why he has taken on a hard-bitten, film-noir-gangster-cum-bluesman persona that sticks two fingers up at those who seek autobiographical authenticity in his work, while offending many of his fans with its luridly macho provocations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;This is the misogynistic Dylan who, in a wild exegesis of the Eagles&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;Witchy Woman&amp;rdquo;, indulges his fascination for &amp;ldquo;the progressive woman &amp;ndash; youthful, whimsical, and grotesque&amp;rdquo;. He&amp;rsquo;s the American psycho who fantasises about torturing to death a &amp;ldquo;hot-blooded sex starved wench&amp;rdquo;, ventriloquising the protagonist of Elvis Costello&amp;rsquo;s 1978 song &amp;ldquo;Pump It Up&amp;rdquo;. For the &lt;em&gt;Los Angeles Times&lt;/em&gt; journalist Jody Rosen, such passages diminish &lt;em&gt;The Philosophy&lt;/em&gt; by evoking an image of its author as a reactionary &amp;ldquo;elderly uncle who bulk-emails links to Fox News segments&amp;rdquo;. In the &lt;em&gt;New Statesman&lt;/em&gt;, Jude Rogers asks whether Dylan &amp;ldquo;included these rants because he enjoys the idea of staying provocative&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; but she understandably finds some of it &amp;ldquo;gut-churning&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Upon first reading, I took all this to be of a piece with the folk- and blues-derived ultraviolence of late-period Dylan songs such as &amp;ldquo;Tin Angel&amp;rdquo;, a story of an adulterous wife that seems modelled equally on the traditional &amp;ldquo;Black Jack Davy&amp;rdquo; and Nick Cave&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Murder Ballads&lt;/em&gt;. For more than a decade now, Dylan has revelled in violence that mostly involves women &amp;ndash; perpetrated by them, inflicted upon them or at least attributed to them in some way. In &amp;ldquo;Nettie Moore&amp;rdquo;, a ballad of regret recorded in 2006, we glimpse Frankie from the folk song &amp;ldquo;Frankie and Albert&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; who murdered her cheating partner in a crime of passion &amp;ndash; merrily &amp;ldquo;raising hell&amp;rdquo;; in the 2000 barnstormer &amp;ldquo;Things Have Changed&amp;rdquo;, a woman with &amp;ldquo;assassin&amp;rsquo;s eyes&amp;rdquo; sits on the protagonist&amp;rsquo;s lap. The femme fatales in his songs are liable to draw first blood and give as good as they get. It&amp;rsquo;s a Robert Johnson-inspired world-view, best summed up by the mournfully sung line &amp;ldquo;There ain&amp;rsquo;t no limit to the amount of trouble women bring,&amp;rdquo; from 2001&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Sugar Baby&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;As troubling as such sentiments might be, these are genre trappings whose primary function is to elicit a raw emotional response. We&amp;rsquo;re not encouraged to take these lines as gospel, to be agreed with and followed, just as Johnny Cash didn&amp;rsquo;t expect us to go out and shoot a man in Reno just to watch him die. The title of Dylan&amp;rsquo;s new book suggests that his project is to impart a philosophy but it was probably chosen ironically, since anyone familiar with his work knows that its power lies in its irreconcilable contradictions. In his essay on Costello&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Pump It Up&amp;rdquo;, he explains, &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s what a song makes you feel about your own life that&amp;rsquo;s important.&amp;rdquo; That&amp;rsquo;s why, I think, his work has always contained multitudes, why very little of it makes the literal, unified sense that compositions by more conventionally wordy songwriters (such as Leonard Cohen) do.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;You can, of course, look at it all biographically. In 1978, Dylan recounted in a &lt;em&gt;Rolling Stone&lt;/em&gt; interview how he had spent his 34th birthday at a gypsy festival in France, where he met the &amp;ldquo;king of the Gypsies&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;&amp;ldquo;He&amp;rsquo;d had a heart attack before I&amp;rsquo;d come home to see him. All his wives and children had left . . . They smell death and they leave. That&amp;rsquo;s what happens in life. And I was very affected by seeing that.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;So, Dylan has long associated old age with a loss of potency, and his fetishisation of violence might be a cartoonish response to that &amp;ndash; much like in all those action movies about elderly ex-secret agents with a particular set of skills and a barely concealed glee at whooping young butts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Even if that&amp;rsquo;s true, however, there&amp;rsquo;s clearly a lot more going on in both his recent songs and &lt;em&gt;The Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;. In those lines about the Eagles&amp;rsquo; &amp;ldquo;Witchy Woman&amp;rdquo;, he slips on a Maga hat and bemoans &amp;ldquo;the progressive woman&amp;rdquo;, invokes the antisemitic trope of &amp;ldquo;the woman from the global village of nowhere&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; an odd thing to do for a guy who was raised Jewish &amp;ndash; and suggests that the only response is to &amp;ldquo;put on the skin of a lion&amp;rdquo;, echoing Mussolini&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;It is better to live one day as a lion than 100 years as a sheep&amp;rdquo;. A few lines later, however, he describes people who hold such views in the most withering terms: &amp;ldquo;Now you&amp;rsquo;re a self-admiring, unchivalrous fellow with an evil nature.&amp;rdquo; If you nodded along to the woman-hating paranoia, you&amp;rsquo;ll realise pretty soon that the joke&amp;rsquo;s on you.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Here is the trickster who threw fictional characters and even Sharon Stone into &lt;em&gt;Rolling Thunder Revue&lt;/em&gt;, his 2019 collaboration with Martin Scorsese that looks like a documentary but is, as its subtitle makes clear, just another &amp;ldquo;Bob Dylan Story&amp;rdquo;. Make of all this what you will, because he offers no unequivocal answers. That, I think, is the point: to make listeners and readers witness the unfolding of their own thought, rather than try to analyse him like an amateur Freud in search of second-hand truths. As he once sang, long ago: trust yourself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6081/youthsick-blues#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-15T15:47:54Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-15T15:47:54Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New hope for less controversial Alzheimer’s drug</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6075/new-hope-for-less-controversial-alzheimers-drug#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;img title="Histopathology of amyloid plaque in Alzheimer's disease" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Histopathology_of_amyloid_plaque_in_Alzheimer_s_disease.jpeg" height="576" alt="Amyloid plaque in Alzheimer's disease" width="780"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In 2021 the drug Aducanumab became the first new treatment for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s Disease (AD) to be approved by the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) in 20 years. But it was surrounded by serious questions over the design, analysis, efficacy and safety of the underlying trials, as well as the conduct of the FDA itself (see &lt;em&gt;New Humanist &lt;/em&gt;Autumn 2021).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Like many drugs in the pipeline, Aducanumab targets build-ups of the beta-amyloid protein, known as &amp;ldquo;plaque&amp;rdquo;, in the brain. The hypothesis is that this plaque collects between neurons and disrupts their normal function, playing a causal role in the development of AD. Whilst the theory has been the basis of decades of research, scientists remain divided over its validity. The controversy surrounding Aducanumab&amp;rsquo;s approval did little to settle the debate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Then, in late 2022, a clinical trial reported significant results in targeting the &amp;ldquo;brain plaque&amp;rdquo; so central to this hypothesis. A new compound, Lecanemab, was again approved under an accelerated procedure by the FDA. However, the results of the trial, published in the &lt;em&gt;New England Journal of Medicine&lt;/em&gt;, have largely been received with greater hope and confidence than the Aducanumab debacle. They appear to provide evidence for the first time of both significant reductions in plaque and, crucially, a slowing in the rate of decline in cognition by 27 per cent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;We are yet to find out who might benefit. Treatment with the drug requires two weekly transfusions and will cost over $25,000 per patient per year in the US. In the UK, medical regulators are yet to announce their timeline for considering Lecanemab (they never gave the green light to Aducanumab).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Excitement has also been muted among researchers due to concerns over adverse events. The drug has only been trialled, so far, in early-stage AD patients and some experts say it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely to help those who are further down the line. However, there is still cause for optimism. If Lecanemab is approved, it would be the first time a drug is made available to AD sufferers that targets the cause of the disease, rather than the symptoms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;This article is a preview from our New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6075/new-hope-for-less-controversial-alzheimers-drug#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-02-13T09:47:23Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-13T09:47:23Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION FEBRUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/open-discussion-february-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978493</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JANUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/01/open-discussion-january-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978482</id>
    <published>2023-01-01T10:47:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-01T10:47:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>BOOK CLUB 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/01/book-club-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the 2023 follow-on from the 2022 BOOK CLUB thread, which is now closed, though you can easily refer back to earlier discussions by clicking on the link. BOOK CLUB 2023 has been created to provide a dedicated space for the discussion of books. Pretty much any kind of book – it doesn’t have …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978479</id>
    <published>2023-01-01T10:40:58Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-01T10:40:58Z</updated>
    <category term="Featured"/>
    <category term="Special Topic"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Secular Rescue – Saving Freedom, Saving Lives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/12/secular-rescue-saving-freedom-saving-lives/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supporter, December 10 is recognized around the world as Human Rights Day. The theme this year is “Dignity, Freedom, and Justice for All.” Those are wonderful ideals, enjoyed by far too few across the globe. Secular Rescue works to improve (and often to save) the lives of atheists and nonbelievers living in places that would …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978469</id>
    <published>2022-12-12T14:57:27Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-12T14:57:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
