<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-04-04T07:28:46Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Another good article on sociogenomics</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/03/another-good-article-on-sociogenomics/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/sociogenomics-is-eugenics.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/sociogenomics-is-eugenics-150x86.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="86" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69730" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/sociogenomics-is-eugenics-150x86.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/sociogenomics-is-eugenics-300x172.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/sociogenomics-is-eugenics.jpeg 474w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Do you want to know <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2018/10/23/139420/sociogenomics-is-opening-a-new-door-to-eugenics/">how sociogenomics works</a>? Here you go.</p>
<blockquote><p>If this is “the science,” the science is weird. We’re used to thinking of science as incrementally seeking causal explanations for natural phenomena by testing a series of hypotheses. Just as important, good science tries as hard as it can to disprove the working hypotheses.</p>
<p>Sociogenomics has no experiments, no null hypotheses to accept or reject, no deductions from the data to general principles. Nor is it a historical science, like geology or evolutionary biology, that draws on a long-running record for evidence.</p>
<p>Sociogenomics is inductive rather than deductive. Data is collected first, without a prior hypothesis, from longitudinal studies like the Framingham Heart Study, twin studies, and other sources of information—such as direct-to-consumer DNA companies like 23andMe that collect biographical and biometric as well as genetic data on all their clients.</p>
<p>Algorithms then chew up the data and spit out correlations between the trait of interest and tiny variations in the DNA, called SNPs (for single-­nucleotide polymorphisms). Finally, sociogenomicists do the thing most scientists do at the outset: they draw inferences and make predictions, primarily about an individual’s future behavior.</p>
<p>Sociogenomics is not concerned with causation in the sense that most of us think of it, but with correlation. The DNA data often comes in the form of genome-wide association studies (GWASs), a means of comparing genomes and linking variations of SNPs. Sociogenomics algorithms ask: are there patterns of SNPs that correlate with a trait, be it high intelligence or homosexuality or a love of gambling?</p>
<p>Yes—almost always. The number of possible combinations of SNPs is so large that finding associations with any given trait is practically inevitable.</p></blockquote>
<p>I’m not just being mean when I say it’s garbage science. “Chewing up data and spitting out correlations,” especially when correlations are ubiquitous, is not a productive approach to much of anything.</p>
<p>Where will it take us? That’s easy to see.</p>
<blockquote><p>Advocates of sociogenomics envision a prospect that not everyone will find entirely benevolent: health “report cards,” based on your genome and handed out at birth, that predict your risk of various diseases and propensity for different behaviors. In the new social sciences, sociologists will examine the genetic component of educational attainment and wealth, while economists will envision genetic “risk scores” for spending, saving, and investment behavior.</p>
<p>Without strong regulation, these scores could be used in school and job applications and in calculating health insurance premiums. Your genome is the ultimate preexisting condition.</p></blockquote>
<p>There’s precedent. The article mentions how Simon Binet invented the IQ test as a tool to identify and help students who were lagging in school…and then within decades discovered “that people were being sterilized for scoring too low”. I know that if I’d been assigned a genetic “risk score” with my family history, I and my brothers and sisters would have been doing manual labor for our short lives.</p>
<p>Also, I still want to know how this pseudonymous eugenics research program with it’s 15 new hires of “young, often charismatic scientists” is getting funded. Following the money would be a good idea here.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you want to know how sociogenomics works? Here you go. If this is “the science,” the science is weird. We’re used to thinking of science as incrementally seeking causal explanations for natural phenomena by testing a series of hypotheses. Just as important, good science tries as hard as it can to disprove the working […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69729</id>
    <published>2023-04-03T21:57:16Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-03T21:57:16Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Truth, but funny</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/03/truth-but-funny/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Trudy and Doug (of Oglaf fame) post amusing sketches on their <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/rollerskates-80952882">Patreon</a> sometimes. This one is high art, it made me laugh and cry at the same time.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/welcome-to-the-gig-economy.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/welcome-to-the-gig-economy.png" alt="" width="434" height="471" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-69727" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/welcome-to-the-gig-economy.png 434w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/welcome-to-the-gig-economy-138x150.png 138w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/welcome-to-the-gig-economy-276x300.png 276w" sizes="(max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trudy and Doug (of Oglaf fame) post amusing sketches on their Patreon sometimes. This one is high art, it made me laugh and cry at the same time.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69726</id>
    <published>2023-04-03T14:03:03Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-03T14:03:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Art, Culture, and Humor"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I think I’ll avoid the news for a few days</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/03/i-think-ill-avoid-the-news-for-a-few-days/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Trump is supposed to be ‘arrested’ tomorrow (which probably means he shows up at a courthouse, is photographed mercilessly while treated with great deference, then retires to a luxurious hotel room to scribble on Truth Social about his martyrdom). Nothing much of substance will happen, but all the networks will be full of false piety and claims that this is an exceptional and significant event, which it isn’t. And of course all the morons will be raging with their battery of flimsy rationalizations.</p>
<div id="attachment_69724" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology-500x468.png" alt="" width="500" height="468" class="size-large wp-image-69724" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology-500x468.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology-150x140.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology-300x281.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology-768x719.png 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/psychopathology.png 915w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2023/3/27/2160196/-Cartoon-The-persecution-of-Donald-John-Trump">Tom Tomorrow</a></p></div>
<p>Sadly, all our news sources will take these excuses very, very seriously and parrot them continuously. Which is why I’ll be ignoring the news for a few days. I hope no catastrophes that might affect me happen! Zombies, please stay dead until next week, maybe. We’re getting another blizzard tomorrow so you’re not going to be getting around very well anyway.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trump is supposed to be ‘arrested’ tomorrow (which probably means he shows up at a courthouse, is photographed mercilessly while treated with great deference, then retires to a luxurious hotel room to scribble on Truth Social about his martyrdom). Nothing much of substance will happen, but all the networks will be full of false piety […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69723</id>
    <published>2023-04-03T13:43:09Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-03T13:43:09Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What the heck is sociogenomics?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/03/what-the-heck-is-sociogenomics/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I was asked recently about “sociogenomics,” and I had to stop and think because I was unfamiliar with the word. At a guess, I thought it would about looking for correlations between genes and socioeconomic groups, ethnicities, and races using tools like genome wide association studies and polygenic scores — you know, <i>Bell Curve</i> shit. To me, it sounded ominous and catastrophically bad, something that would shift into plain old eugenics and evolve into Nazi shit. But what do I know? I had to go look it up. I was just guessing.</p>
<p>Guess what? <a href="https://www.sociogenome.org/">I guessed right</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Sociogenome is the comprehensive study of the role of genes and gene-environment (GxE) interaction on reproductive behaviour. Until now, social science research has focussed on socio-environmental explanations, largely neglecting the role of genes.</p>
<p>Drawing from recent unprecedented advances in molecular genetics we examine whether there is a genetic component to reproductive outcomes, including age at first birth, number of children and infertility and their interaction with the social environment.</p></blockquote>
<p>Uh-oh. They’re just going to take modern genetic techniques and apply them to sociology. But these techniques will not give them the answers they want! They’ll reveal rough correlations, but they won’t untangle genetics and environmental factors — they can’t. This is a problem that has been <a href="https://www.cairn-int.info/journal-population-2022-2-page-181.htm">pointed out to behavioral genetics researchers for years</a>, and they just go sailing on ahead.</p>
<blockquote><p>In the past decade and a half, sociologists and demographers have sought to integrate genetic data into their empirical analyses. To do so, they have drawn on recently developed high-throughput sequencing and genotyping technologies, which allow the entire genome to be mapped. They also follow in the line of a research specialty, behavioural genetics, which rose to prominence in the 1970s. This area, which focused notably on the genetic determination of intelligence, attracted severe criticisms, including among demographers (Jacquard, 1978; Vetta and Courgeau, 2003; Courgeau, 2017). However, these criticisms do not always seem to have been heard, and the emergence of new data and techniques has given rise to new problems, as indicated by calls for caution from learned societies in human genetics (Société française de génétique humaine, 2010; Risch, 2016; Société française de génétique humaine, 2018).</p></blockquote>
<p>Let’s look at an example of a sociogenomics study that was <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/researchers-want-to-link-your-genes-and-incomeshould-they/">summarized in Wired</a>. It does not reassure me.</p>
<blockquote><p>The UK BioBank is the single largest public genetic repository in the world, with samples of the genetic blueprints of half a million Brits standing by for scientific study. But when David Hill, a statistical geneticist at the University of Edinburgh, went poring through that data, he wasn’t looking for a cure for cancer or deeper insights into the biology of aging. Nothing like that. He was trying to figure out why some people make more money than others.</p></blockquote>
<p>I hadn’t thought of that. They’re going to tap into modern behavioral databases, like all that information Facebook has about you, in addition to biological databases, and they’re going to try to weave the two of them into some kind of story. I’ve never been impressed by that.</p>
<blockquote><p>Along with a team of European collaborators, Hill sifted through the UK Biobank data to find about 286,000 participants who had answered a survey question about household income. Using that information they conducted something called a Genome Wide Association Study, where they looked at 18 million places in the genome to see which ones matched up with higher paychecks. They uncovered about 30, which account for 7.4 percent of household income variation across the United Kingdom. (For some context, another way of viewing the results is to say that <strong>92.6 percent of a person’s income is explained by factors other than genetics</strong>.) Hill noticed that many of the genetic differences overlapped with areas known to be associated with intelligence, based on some of his prior work, and when he mapped them out they were largely expressed in the brain.</p>
<p>His team then used these regions to compute a polygenic score, a genetic calculation that predicts a person’s odds of reaching a certain outcome—of, say, developing diabetes or earning six figures. It didn’t perform particularly well, correctly forecasting only 2.5 percent of the differences in income in an independent sample of Scots. “Your DNA will not print you money,” says Hill. But he’s relieved to have found some small effect. “If you’re born with a predisposi­tion for certain traits or abilities, and none of them counted in any way, shape, or form towards your income, then you’d have a profoundly unfair society, in my opinion,” he says.</p></blockquote>
<p>Thanks, I hate it. So he started with the information about a quarter of a million people, went fishing for any correlation at all, and found a tiny percentage of the genetic variation might account for a tiny fraction of the variation in income, because of course they’re zeroing in on money. It looks like noise to me; I’d want to know haw they accounted for the fact that a great deal of wealth is inherited, so you’d expect to see some common traits threaded through lines of wealth. Trust fund babies are going to share genes with mommy and daddy, even if they have nothing to do with the source of their money.</p>
<p>Further, even their weak correlation hasn’t found a genetic basis for wealth. Genes aren’t pure entities that can be isolated in this way and tied to phenotype — everything is polygenic and pleiotropic, and absolutely dependent on the environment for their expression. No wonder I didn’t know what sociogenomics is — if I encountered it in a science journal, I’d glance at the abstract, gag, and turn the page.</p>
<p>Then I figured it out: sociogenomics is nothing but the new label slapped on Kathryn Paige Harden’s behavioral genetics, which I figured out a long time ago was garbage science. <a href="https://www.genderscilab.org/blog/how-to-be-an-anti-eugenicist">Here’s a solid critique of Harden’s ideas</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>In her recent sociogenomics manifesto The Genetic Lottery, Kathryn Paige Harden sets out to rescue behavior genetics from the spectres of racism and eugenics. Sociogenomics, like behavior genetics, studies the possible role of genes in explaining complex human social behaviors. Critics have charged this area of study with fueling biological determinist theories of human social inequality.  </p>
<p>Harden purports to offer a refreshing take on this old debate because she claims that such critics are blind to the role that genetics play in the very thing they aim to secure: social equality. She argues that, in fact, we must use genetic information to promote truly egalitarian social policy. Styling herself after 20th century anti-racist geneticists such as Theodosius Dobzhansky, Harden offers the new sociogenomics as an explicitly anti-eugenic synthesis of genetics and equality.</p>
<p>Harden is right that the legacies of eugenics haunt behavior genetics. The field’s findings have been used to argue that biological differences between social groups explain social inequality and to undermine the possibility of egalitarian interventions. Human behavior genetics and its successor, sociogenomics, have thrived on controversy about the alleged biological relationship between race and IQ and the alleged futility of educational interventions in closing achievement gaps. Harden’s particular focus—the notion that biology can explain population differences in educational attainment and cognitive performance—has been a pillar of eugenic discourse and white supremacist ideology. But Harden believes that it is possible to “[reclaim] genetic science from the legacy of eugenics, realigning it with egalitarian aims.” Harden’s “new synthesis,” she argues, is not only different from eugenics, but self-consciously anti-eugenic. </p>
<p>Harden draws an analogy between her critics’ “genome blindness” (her term for the failure to “see” genetic causes) and color blindness (the failure to “see” race). Just as color blindness undermines antiracism because it fails to grapple with the effects of racism, Harden argues that genome-blindness threatens egalitarian aims because it fails to grapple with genetic causes of inequality. But this analogy breaks down when the entanglement of behavior genetics with eugenics is taken seriously. Resisting eugenics depends on an understanding not of how genes work, but of how eugenics works.  Anti-eugenic science demands an expansive and nuanced understanding of how eugenic thought developed. In this essay, we show that Harden’s account of eugenics seriously undermines her claim to rescue behavior genetics from its clutches.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yeah. Harden is really unconvincing. Somehow, while claiming to be an anti-eugenicist, she embraces the modern genetic determinists and spurns the people who have been showing for decades that genes and environment are inseparable.</p>
<blockquote><p>Harden’s failure to engage with critics of behavioral genetics, often from the political left, veers between simple omissions and outright misrepresentation. This treatment is in stark contrast to how she treats biological determinists on the political right. The work of Charles Murray, the co-author of The Bell Curve, which claimed that differences in IQ scores between the rich and poor were genetic, and whose research aligns neatly with Harden’s, is described as mostly true and his political implications are lightly challenged. The most prominent critic of behavioral genetics, Richard Lewontin, gets much rougher treatment.</p>
<p>In one of the three cases in which Harden bothers to mention Lewontin’s decades-long engagement with behavioral genetics, she gets it wrong, claiming that Lewontin merely said that heritability is useless because it is specific to a particular population at a particular time. In reality, Lewontin showed why the statistical foundation of heritability analyses means it is unable to truly separate genetic and environmental effects. Contra Harden’s characterization of her opponents, Lewontin recognized genetic factors as a cause of phenotypes; however, he stressed their effects cannot be independent of environmental factors and the dynamics of development.</p></blockquote>
<p>Called it. Told you this was going to be some <i>Bell Curve</i> shit.</p>
<p>What really clinches for me that this is something more than a few fringe scholars coming up with fancy titles for the junk science they are doing, though, is this surprise. <a href="https://bga.org/sociogenomics-cluster-hire-at-purdue-university/">Purdue is making a massive investment in creating a sociogenomics department from scratch</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Together the College of Liberal Arts and the College of Science at Purdue University seek applications for multiple scholars in Sociogenomics, including existing groups of investigators, to assemble a new world-leading cohort of approximately 15 faculty. The positions include tenure-track Assistant, Associate, and Professor ranks. </p>
<p>A relatively new field, Sociogenomics encompasses theoretical and methodological approaches across the social, behavioral, and genetic sciences including those with an emphasis on computation. It explores the roles of genetics in social and behavior outcomes, as well as how genetics interact with the environment and social forces. Purdue is strongly committed to establishing a pre-eminent center in this emerging area including hiring a substantive cohort of scholars. We are especially interested in fostering collaborative linkages across the core fields of this discipline, here at Purdue and more broadly. This search is open to leading scholars in any area relevant to the advancement of Sociogenomics, and we are especially interested in candidates who draw from and contribute to research in the social science disciplines, biological sciences, the computational and data sciences, statistics, or other related disciplines. We anticipate joint appointments across departments where appropriate, with tenure homes flexible and negotiated at the time of hire.</p></blockquote>
<p>That is remarkable. Right now, universities everywhere are struggling, thanks to the pressures of the pandemic and political neglect, yet somehow, Purdue has magically come up with the money and the will to create <em>15 faculty positions</em> in this “relatively new field.” This is not how it works. You start with a small team of qualified people in the area, see how successful they are at grants and papers, and how well the students respond to their courses. Then you build around that solid core and grow the department. Also, you typically start with some well-established discipline that you know has a good track record.</p>
<p>Just flash, boom, creating a substantial department out of whole cloth, hiring new people and assembling them into some kind of framework, is what you do when you’ve got some wealthy sugar daddy, a billionaire or two or some corporation that thinks there are profits to be made. And doing it with some vague discipline that is only a few years old — unthinkable. In the absence of a need, this has to be the product of someone with an agenda, probably an unsavory agenda, pushing buckets of money at a university that will happily accept it.</p>
<p>The thing is, ideas that promote the belief that the very rich have earned their money by virtue of their superior biology are ridiculously popular with the people who have an excess of money to donate.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes-500x246.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="246" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69721" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes-500x246.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes-150x74.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes-300x147.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes-768x377.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/trump-has-great-genes.jpeg 1290w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I was asked recently about “sociogenomics,” and I had to stop and think because I was unfamiliar with the word. At a guess, I thought it would about looking for correlations between genes and socioeconomic groups, ethnicities, and races using tools like genome wide association studies and polygenic scores — you know, Bell Curve shit. […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69720</id>
    <published>2023-04-03T13:26:28Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-03T13:26:28Z</updated>
    <category term="Bad science"/>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I’m not lurking, really</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/02/im-not-lurking-really/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I’ve been in my office all day, talking to no one. Instead, I’ve graded two sets of lab reports, prepared two lectures for tomorrow, and am nearly done grading an exam. There are a few million things I’d rather do today, but at least I’ve cleared that annoying pile of work.</p>
<p>If I’m a good boy and get some more done in time, I’m going to the <a href="https://morristheatre.net/blog/">movie theater</a> tonight — I hear that the Dungeons &amp; Dragons movie is entertaining…but I also see that it’s 2 hours and 14 minutes long. It’s fluff! It shouldn’t be that long!</p>
<p>I also shouldn’t be spending my whole weekend working, either.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’ve been in my office all day, talking to no one. Instead, I’ve graded two sets of lab reports, prepared two lectures for tomorrow, and am nearly done grading an exam. There are a few million things I’d rather do today, but at least I’ve cleared that annoying pile of work. If I’m a good […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69718</id>
    <published>2023-04-02T20:09:51Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-02T20:09:51Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/open-discussion-april-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978526</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A festival of big ideas</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6097/a-festival-of-big-ideas#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img title="HTLGI festival will return to the banks of the River Wye this May bank holiday" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/festival-grounds-with-festival-signsmall.jpeg" height="1181" alt="HTLGI festival will return to the banks of the River Wye this May" width="1774"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HowTheLightGetsIn&lt;/em&gt; has now firmly established itself as the most exciting philosophy festival in Europe. Bringing together ground-breaking thinkers from various fields of expertise and walks of life, there are usually intellectual surprises instore &amp;ndash; if you're lucky, maybe even a revelation or two. Hilary Lawson, who calls himself a post-postmodern philosopher, founded HTLGI in 2008 in order to bring "philosophy into British culture". Since then, it has developed into a delight for the mind &amp;ndash; while not neglecting the pleasures of the body (and, of course, delving into the boundaries between mind and body, and questioning whether such boundaries really exist.) There is music and comedy, as well as talks and panel debates. And a Ferris wheel, in case you feel the need to gain a completely different perspective.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 26-29 May, the last bank holiday of the month, the &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;festival will return to Hay-on-Wye&lt;/a&gt;. The historic book town is &lt;em&gt;just about &lt;/em&gt;in Wales &amp;ndash; it gets its name from the River Wye, which for much of its length forms the border between England and Wales. The town is charming, and hosts, at the same time, the Hay Literary Festival, so if you're feeling exceptionally avid, it's possible to do both.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The festival has always dug into the big ideas. One of the many positive effects of bringing together scientists with politicians, activists, intellectuals and creative people of all stripes, is that the debates tend to push against boundaries. It's hard for an evolutionary biologist, for example, to get stuck on the particulars, when they're in conversation with a playwright or a moral philosopher. This year, however, they've made this natural tendency into an explicit theme, "Error and Renaissance".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Lawson put it &lt;a href="https://www.theweek.co.uk/arts-life/culture/music/957551/howthelightgetsin-london-philosophy-and-music-on-hampstead-heath"&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt;, the purpose is to "come together to try and identify the fundamental errors that we have made in our theories, the organisation of society and in world affairs &amp;ndash; all while looking to new forms of thought and action to rebuild afresh.&amp;rdquo; Some of the big names already announced &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/programme?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;in the programme&lt;/a&gt; include philosopher Daniel Dennett, presidential advisor Fiona Hill, string-theorist Brian Greene and geneticist G&amp;uuml;neş Taylor. Readers of &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; might also be interested in checking out Michael Shermer, who has spent his career popularising scepticism as a method to search for truth, or the prominent voice for Christian humanism, Nick Spencer. It's a chance to hear voices we both agree, and disagree with.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; is also sponsoring a debate, "The Best and Worst of All Possible Worlds", so if you do come to the festival, please stop and say hello. The panel will debate whether alternate worlds exist, and also whether the concept can be useful for thinking about &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; world, casting light on deep puzzles of language and reality. Philosopher of physics Paul Horwich, theoretical physicist Tasneem Zehra Husain and philosopher Ben Burgis will debate the continued attraction of many worlds theory, chaired by our Editor, Niki Seth-Smith.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a festival partner, we are offering a 20 per cent discount on tickets to all of our readers, with the code NEWHUMANIST23. Don't miss out on tickets &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; And for those of you who can't be with us in person, all the debates and talks from the festival will gradually be released online, on the Institute of Art and Ideas platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;IAI.TV.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6097/a-festival-of-big-ideas#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-30T13:27:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-30T13:27:01Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The moral duty to pump iron</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6096/the-moral-duty-to-pump-iron#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Eugen Sandow, founder of the Sandow system" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Sandow.jpg" height="768" alt="Eugen Sandow" width="1199"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When the Irish &amp;ldquo;physical culturalist&amp;rdquo; F. A. Hornibrook wrote The Culture of the Abdomen in 1924, he was confident that he had conclusively identified the source of much of industrialised society&amp;rsquo;s problems: chronic constipation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Between the trained athlete and the sedentary bookworm lies a great gulf across which age eventually throws a bridge where both meet in middle life, both burdened with enfeebled bodies, adipose deposits, pendulous bellies, constipated bowels and impaired mental activity... the ponderous speech of the portly magnate finds its echoes in the intestinal rumblings of his ponderous paunch, and awed ignorance acclaims wind for wisdom.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Calling it &amp;ldquo;the white man&amp;rsquo;s burden&amp;rdquo;, in chapters such as &amp;ldquo;Sewage System of the Body&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Buttock Contraction&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Eating and Evacuation&amp;rdquo;, Hornibrook advocated a series of measures to promote good stool cultivation, appreciation and, most importantly, expulsion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some recommendations relate to diet &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;in paraffin, taken in tablespoonful doses three-quarters of an hour before a meal, we have a useful ally in the conflict with constipation&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; while others are to do with the vital moment of unburdening. Hornibrook argues that the modern water closet, in failing to replicate the squatting posture of &amp;ldquo;the native&amp;rdquo; (whose stools are &amp;ldquo;soft, pultaceous and easily passed&amp;rdquo; as opposed to civilised man&amp;rsquo;s, which are &amp;ldquo;almost as hard as old putty, and very dry&amp;rdquo;), needs urgent adaptation to make it more conducive to stool delivery. Failing this, the individual can place a wooden platform eight inches high in front of the toilet, on which the feet can rest during the act of defecation, thus approximating the squat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hornibrook &amp;ndash; whose followers included H. G. Wells and Arnold Bennett &amp;ndash; simultaneously promoted physical fitness based on native dancing rituals. The Culture of the Abdomen has helpful pictures of &amp;ldquo;modern man&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the native&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the posture, attitude, dignity and buttocks of the former being compared unfavourably with the latter&amp;rsquo;s. The book ends with a series of suggested exercises and aids to health including, somewhat randomly, golf. Remember, says Hornibrook, &amp;ldquo;A short belt is a long life-line.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Battle of the Systems&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hornibrook&amp;rsquo;s work grew out of what has become known to historians as the &amp;ldquo;Battle of the Systems&amp;rdquo;, a 19th-century clash between various types of physical regime for the promotion of wellbeing. With its roots in European military practices, and fuelled by an increasingly consumerist society both there and in the US, the various systems promoted different physical regimes, often combining them with dietary and &amp;ldquo;lifestyle&amp;rdquo; advice. Between 1848 &amp;ndash; that Year of Revolutions in Europe &amp;ndash; through to the 1930s, newspapers and magazines promoted schemes for improving one&amp;rsquo;s physical health.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beginning with the Turner movement &amp;ndash; a gymnastic scheme imported to the US by Germans fleeing the 1848 revolution &amp;ndash; the Battle of the Systems came to include the Czech Sokol movement (&amp;ldquo;a strong mind in a sound body&amp;rdquo;); the Swedish System, which concentrated on calisthenics, breathing and massage; and Muscular Christianity, which sought to combine spiritual and physical health as a bulwark against what many believed to be a decrease in manliness caused by excessive Puritanism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Promoted by sections of the Church, Muscular Christianity&amp;rsquo;s version of Christ was the one that &amp;ldquo;came not to send peace, but a sword&amp;rdquo;. As one convert, Theodore Roosevelt, put it, in a truly Christian society &amp;ldquo;there is only a very circumscribed sphere of usefulness for the timid good man.&amp;rdquo; That many of these systems sprang from military training is no coincidence. Sokol argued that one should think deeply about Czech nationalism while lifting weights, while in the UK at the beginning of the 20th century, Muscular Christianity became part of the myth of how the British Empire was created and maintained. The true Brit had a Bible in one hand and a rifle in the other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it was the Sandow system, named for its founder Eugen Sandow, and based on weightlifting, which had convinced Hornibrook of the benefits of physical fitness, having allowed him to reshape his body until he was known, in his own telling, as &amp;ldquo;Brawnibrook&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Gym freaks&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sandow was born Jewish, the son of a German and a Russian. He began using weights at the age of ten. Briefly a circus strongman, he is credited with organising the world&amp;rsquo;s first bodybuilding competition at London&amp;rsquo;s Royal Albert Hall in 1901 (his fellow judge was Arthur Conan Doyle). At the turn of the century, Thomas Edison filmed him performing one of his &amp;ldquo;muscle display performances&amp;rdquo; and he was later designated special instructor in physical culture to King George V.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Natalia Mehlman Petrzela points out in her new book, Fit Nation: The Gains and Pains of America&amp;rsquo;s Exercise Obsession (University of Chicago), despite the advocacy of F. A. Hornibrook and his like, when Sandow made his first tour of the United States, extreme physical health and exaggerated musculature were things to be ogled at, rather than aspired to. Audiences would gather to marvel at what were, in some senses, still freaks. Weightlifting and going to gymnasiums were not only niche activities, but were regarded with a certain amount of scorn.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fast forward a hundred years and Hornibrook and Sandow would be astonished at the centrality of many of their theories &amp;ndash; if not their systems &amp;ndash; in western public discourse. We find ourselves in a new Battle of the Systems, with a bewildering array of techniques supposedly aimed at making all of us fitter, happier and more productive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The global wellness economy was valued at US$4.4 trillion in 2020 &amp;ndash; an astonishing 5.1 per cent of all global output. In the US, gyms are now a $40 billion industry. But despite the massive revenue generated, as Petrzela points out, fewer than 20 per cent of Americans actually work out consistently, a similar figure to the UK. In addition, over 73 per cent of Americans are classed as overweight, 42 per cent of them obese. According to a 2022 UK government report, three-quarters of the British population are overweight, and 28 per cent of them obese. The latter group includes one in seven children under the age of five. For all the talk of our fitness obsession, it seems as much honoured in the breach as in the observance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What one can discern, however, is how closely fitness and capitalism cleave together. If the Battle of the Systems grew from military training, it was no less a product of the Industrial Revolution. The working of the human body gradually became analogous to the working of the new machines which had begun to replace it. Initially, in the early 19th century, there was some upper-class distaste for both sweat and muscle. Both were seen as working class, and even in Sandow&amp;rsquo;s day, part of the thrill of attending his performances lay in slumming it momentarily, and gawping at the bestial displays of these strange somatic creatures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A moral debt&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Increasingly, however, as the middle class emerged, the idea of both individual and societal productivity became more and more prevalent. Somewhere along the way, we developed the idea that to be unproductive is a sin. Physical fitness was no longer an end in itself &amp;ndash; it became, and remains, a moral issue. As endless government campaigns and TV shows tell us, to be unfit is to be bad: a strain on the health service, a burden to society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Muscular Christianity is instructive here. Tracing its origins, somewhat spuriously, back to the apostle Paul, the movement argued that man &amp;ndash; always &amp;ldquo;man&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; had become too civilised, too effete and too intellectual. This was a moral failure as much as a physical one. In fact, one could not separate the two. Just as Hornibrook bemoaned the corpulent, flatulent &amp;ldquo;magnate&amp;rdquo;, proponents of Muscular Christianity argued that the degeneracy of the human body leads to moral degeneracy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As David Graeber argued in his 2011 book Debt: The First 5,000 Years, one of the reasons Christianity and capitalism work so well together is their shared belief that debt is fundamental and ultimately unresolvable. In Christianity we are born with sin and spend our lives trying to repay that debt. In capitalism we must keep earning to stop our financial debt growing. This moral imperative is analogous with the prevalent framing of fitness today as an endless and unresolvable quest: one can always be fitter, and not pursuing this goal is a failing to oneself and to society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To be fit is a personal responsibility &amp;ndash; and therefore it is irresponsible not to be so. The underpinning idea of debt can be seen in the fact that public health campaigns are so often framed in financial terms. &amp;ldquo;Obesity costs the taxpayer &amp;ndash; those who earn enough to pay tax &amp;ndash; x amount&amp;rdquo; and so on, implying that the fit and rich are having to pay for the poor to sit around and get fat. In the UK, as the NHS collapses through chronic underfunding, the scourge of obesity is often held up as a drain on the public purse. Of course, one might argue that it is in fact a healthier middle and upper class, which lives longer, that causes the biggest drain, but this is seldom canvassed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The temple of the body&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The human body shaped by today&amp;rsquo;s hyper-capitalist work regime may not be the only product of this kind of thinking. But if we were designing people who would best fit what capitalism wants, then a set of beings who run on coffee and are fitter than humans in the past would not be far off the mark. Perhaps the dramatic fall in alcohol consumption among younger people in recent years is the result of a partial internalisation of the moral requirement to be useful and productive. (As the French philosopher Georges Bataille noted in his 1949 book The Accursed Share, in a capitalist society, leisure, uselessness and luxury are increasingly only the domain of the upper classes, and are seen as sinful for working people.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Petrzela notes: &amp;ldquo;Fitness has become a socially acceptable form of conspicuous consumption in a society that celebrates the pursuit of health as practically holy.&amp;rdquo; The body itself has thus become both corporatised and a devotional object &amp;ndash; our temple.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition, even more than in the Battle of the Systems, our current fitness obsession places the emphasis on individual empowerment at, Petrzela notes, the expense of collective solidarity. We are in a competition with others, but also with ourselves. It is part of a &amp;ldquo;culture of narcissism&amp;rdquo; which valorises an imagined freedom we can find &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;a lofty idiom of enlightenment&amp;rdquo; where exercise is &amp;ldquo;something more than bodily cultivation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This has led to some extreme outcomes. The Washington Post in 2022 ran a series of articles about deaths in the bodybuilding industry, caused by athletes pursuing ever more unnatural physiques. With steroids freely available, both male and female bodybuilders build themselves up to a point where, as one coach put it, the young Arnold Schwarzenegger would not even be able to compete, let alone win. It has led to a new form of body dysmorphia in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM): &amp;ldquo;bigorexia&amp;rdquo;, where there is no such thing as big enough. &amp;ldquo;Once you step into a gym, you&amp;rsquo;re forever small&amp;rdquo; sums up the thinking.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some individual empowerment is obviously positive. The relationship between feminism and fitness for instance is complex precisely because some of the gains in personal agency and self-esteem are so great that it is difficult to disentangle them from the negatives to do with, for instance, objectification. But a culture where the self is absolutely sovereign increasingly seems just another of capitalism&amp;rsquo;s false versions of liberty. That &amp;ldquo;the body beautiful&amp;rdquo; has become such an aspiration conforms to an incredibly narrow definition of liberty. Like Eugen Sandow a century ago, we are suddenly all engaged in &amp;ldquo;muscle display performances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The business of the body&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;On an individual level, we all basically know how to be healthy, and have for a long time: eat plenty of fruit and veg, stay active, don&amp;rsquo;t drink or smoke and get plenty of sleep. But the countless iterations of this story, emphasising new and different ways to approach the &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo;, force us to set up a plan &amp;ndash; a corporate system of selfhood. We then micromanage as though our body were a business, which we have to run at maximum yield. Our fitness journals become individual profit and loss statements.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, as Fit Nation points out, despite the pursuit of individual health being seen as practically holy, it has not in fact become a &amp;ldquo;public good&amp;rdquo;. In the US, 80 per cent of the population live in what she terms &amp;ldquo;fitness deserts&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; defined as &amp;ldquo;an area without a public park in a half-mile radius&amp;rdquo;. Additional factors such as higher pollution in deprived areas, as well as inadequate street lighting, also lead to a bias in favour of the wealthy when it comes to achieving the &amp;ldquo;freedom&amp;rdquo; that fitness vaunts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The pursuit of fitness requires both time and money. Witness the 2018 Mayo Clinic study which found that playing tennis could add 9.7 years to your lifespan. That those who play tennis tend to be older, richer and already healthier than the general population was not considered. Obesity rates in both the US and the UK are highest among people lacking time and money. Leaving aside the merits or demerits of fitness for a moment, what is notable here is that despite clear structural factors, this is still seen as a moral failing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For Petrzela, who is not only a professor of history but a fitness instructor, access to fitness is therefore a social justice issue. One cannot make fitness an issue of personal responsibility and then not enable equal access.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It does not,&amp;rdquo; Hornibrook wrote in 1924, &amp;ldquo;add to the enjoyment of life to carry round superfluous flesh. It does not add to the enjoyment of life to have stuffed up bowels. It does not add to the enjoyment of life to have a sagging abdomen and atrophied muscles.&amp;rdquo; No one can really argue with that. But nor does it add to the enjoyment of life to make the pursuit of physical health yet another moral quest, which is more often than not a moral failure and another unfulfilled debt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Graeber put it, there is no better way to make things seem moral &amp;ldquo;than by reframing them in the language of debt &amp;ndash; above all, because it immediately makes it seem that it&amp;rsquo;s the victim who&amp;rsquo;s doing something wrong.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6096/the-moral-duty-to-pump-iron#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-30T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-30T05:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Still Pictures by Janet Malcolm</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6095/book-review-still-pictures-by-janet-malcolm#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="New York in the 1940s" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/GCS-New-York.jpg" height="679" alt="New York's Grand Central Station in the 1940s" width="694"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still Pictures: On photography and memory &lt;/strong&gt;(Granta) by Janet Malcolm&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In postwar New York, after escaping Nazi-occupied Prague in 1939, Janet Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s mother Joan was having dinner in an American household. When time for seconds came, Joan declined. In bourgeois Prague, this was a charade known as nutcen&amp;iacute;, and the host would insist until you relented. &amp;ldquo;But here &amp;lsquo;No, thank you&amp;rsquo; was taken to mean just that, and the platter of delicious American food was whisked away before my mother&amp;rsquo;s sad eyes,&amp;rdquo; Malcolm writes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anecdote captures a key theme of Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s autobiography-of-sorts: the alienating experience of being an &amp;eacute;migr&amp;eacute; in a strange land, your personality changed, working out where you fit. Malcolm was four when she boarded one of the last civilian boats from Europe before the war. With the aid of photographs, diaries and letters she weaves an episodic story of her family in their new country: growing up in a Czech community in Manhattan, and the years preceding her career as an acclaimed author and journalist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Malcolm passed away in 2021 at the age of 86. Her last work is also her first of memoir, after a long career stretching the boundaries of nonfiction. Her book The Silent Woman, a biography of Sylvia Plath, called into question the entire voyeuristic project of biographies. In Forty-One False Starts, about the artist David Salle, she wrote in a disjointed form that merged with Salle&amp;rsquo;s collage-like paintings. The Journalist and the Murderer has become a staple in journalism courses for its biting insights into fraught reporter-subject relationships. Whatever Malcolm wrote about, one obituary said, &amp;ldquo;Her real subject was often the writing process itself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This book sees Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s probing gaze pointed at her own life. She describes a classroom crush, who did not return her affections. &amp;ldquo;I was part of the background of ordinary girls, who secretly loved and, unbeknownst to ourselves, were grateful for the safety of not being loved in return,&amp;rdquo; she writes. She analyses what it means to appear a &amp;ldquo;charming&amp;rdquo; person, to flatter and show attention. &amp;ldquo;When I ask someone a question &amp;ndash; either in life or in work &amp;ndash; I often don&amp;rsquo;t listen to the answer. I am not really interested. (The use of a tape recorder during interviews permits me to counteract this obvious disqualification for my job.)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The strongest sections question memoir itself. Our lives are &amp;ldquo;like photographic negatives&amp;rdquo;, she writes, but only a few are developed into photographs and become our memories. She resists this urge to narrativise life from what sticks out of the fog of time. Her father Joseph &amp;ldquo;loved opera, birds, mushrooms, wildflowers, poetry, baseball... My mind is filled with lovely plotless memories of him.&amp;rdquo; She warns autobiographers against using memories that seem to have a plot &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;conflict, resentment, blame, self-justification&amp;rdquo;. These little flashes make us rethink the reading of all memoir.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s relationship to her mother forms the book&amp;rsquo;s emotional core. She looks back &amp;ldquo;ashamed and mortified&amp;rdquo; at her distant young self, unable to give Joan the love she craved. Her mother would spiral into depression when Malcolm left letters unanswered or replied in glib jokes. &amp;ldquo;How could I have been so cruel and callow?&amp;rdquo; she reflects.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Reading Still Pictures, I searched to pinpoint why the book feels so surprising. Some part is no doubt that, in 2010, Malcolm wrote of abandoning autobiography, arguing against its reliance on spotty memory. &amp;ldquo;If an autobiography is to be even minimally readable,&amp;rdquo; she wrote, the autobiographer &amp;ldquo;must not be afraid to invent. Above all he must invent himself.&amp;rdquo; As a journalist she found this repellent. Yet 13 years later, here the book is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Perhaps hardest to pin down is the question of motive. Malcolm flies past a variety of topics without landing on any definitely. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to know who exactly the book is for. Those interested in memory&amp;rsquo;s slipperiness? At times. Those who escaped persecution to begin life anew? For sections, yes. Fans seeking the person behind her journalism? If so, they&amp;rsquo;re bound to be disappointed (she remains private, leaves too many mysteries unsolved; an affair is mentioned, unexplained, then quickly shuffled offstage). The collection seems to lack a coherence that, if Malcolm herself were reviewing it, she&amp;rsquo;d no doubt spot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But this may have been her intention all along. Rather than circling around a central theme, like planets orbiting the sun, this engaging little book is more a series of flashing asteroids. And this is a more accurate description of how memory operates than the polished autobiographies in many bookstores. Yet again, Malcolm matches form to function. She gives us shooting stars &amp;ndash; burning brightly in all directions before fizzing out before our eyes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6095/book-review-still-pictures-by-janet-malcolm#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-28T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-28T04:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The one rule that binds them all</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6094/the-one-rule-that-binds-them-all#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Start by imagining a billiard table with a ball travelling across it in a straight line" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/marcelo-leal-6UeBe2HqziA-unsplash.jpg" height="1229" alt="A billiards table" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For centuries, electricity and magnetism had everyone baffled. In the 19th century, Michael Faraday not only discovered new phenomena but summarised all that was already known in his three-volume Experimental Researches in Electricity. It enabled the great physicist James Clerk Maxwell to distill everything down to 20 equations in 1861-1862. A couple of decades later, this was reduced to four by the physicist and mathematician Oliver Heaviside.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Maxwell&amp;rsquo;s equations are considered to be the high-point of 19th-century physics. They contain the seeds of the revolutions that took place in the 20th century in the fields of both relativity and quantum theory. However, what Maxwell did not realise was that the bewildering array of electrical and magnetic phenomena he had summarised was no more than a consequence of one remarkably simple principle: &amp;ldquo;local gauge invariance&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Picture a billiard table and a billiard ball travelling across it in a straight line. Now imagine that the table is raised by a metre, or two metres, or by any height whatsoever. The ball will continue to follow the same trajectory. In physics, the height of the billiard table is an example of a &amp;ldquo;gauge&amp;rdquo; and the fact that it can be changed without altering the physics is a &amp;ldquo;gauge symmetry&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 1918, the German mathematician Emmy Noether discovered that an unavoidable consequence of every such &amp;ldquo;global&amp;rdquo; symmetry is a &amp;ldquo;conservation law&amp;rdquo;. So, for instance, the fact that the outcome of an experiment will be the same if it is carried out today or tomorrow &amp;ndash; that is, that it obeys &amp;ldquo;time translational symmetry&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; leads to the &amp;ldquo;conservation of energy&amp;rdquo;, one of the cornerstones of physics, which dictates that energy can neither be created nor destroyed, merely transformed from one type to another.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it turns out that in a Universe in which the cosmic speed limit &amp;ndash; set by Einstein &amp;ndash; is the speed of light, it is impossible to lift all parts of a billiard table simultaneously. Imagine, for instance, the billiard table is ten light years across. The best that can be done is to raise one end and watch a hummock propagate across the table at the speed of light, reaching the far end ten years later. It would be reasonable to expect the laws of motion to remain the same everywhere in the billiard-table Universe and for the ball to continue following a straight-line path. However, this would be possible only if a force were introduced at every location to compensate for the undulation. This is the key thing: maintaining local gauge symmetry requires the existence of a force.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, physicists discovered that a particle like an electron is described by a &amp;ldquo;wave function&amp;rdquo;, which propagates according to the Schr&amp;ouml;dinger equation. The probability of finding the particle at any location is given by the square of the &amp;ldquo;amplitude&amp;rdquo; of the wave at that location. But, crucially, the probability does not depend on where the wave happens to be in its undulating pattern. This &amp;ldquo;phase&amp;rdquo; is the gauge, and changing it everywhere by the same amount merely moves the peaks and troughs of the wave along, but does not change anything observable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So what happens if we insist that not only global but local gauge symmetry is maintained &amp;ndash; that is, that the probability is not changed by altering the phase of the electron wave function by a different amount at each location in space and time? Remember, from the billiard table example, that this requires the existence of a force. So, what is the force that is needed? Remarkably, it is precisely the electromagnetic force described by Maxwell.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are four fundamental forces that glue together the particles of matter and make the Universe possible. And, amazingly, three of those have been shown to exist only to maintain local gauge symmetry. In fact, 2023 marks 40 years since this was proved for nature&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;weak&amp;rdquo; force, which is responsible for radioactivity. The proof was the discovery in 1983 of the particles that &amp;ldquo;carry&amp;rdquo; the weak force &amp;ndash; the W and Z bosons &amp;ndash; for which Carlo Rubbia and Simon van der Meer won the Nobel Prize.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In all the chaos of the world, it is easy to lose sight of how amazingly far we humans have come. We are a species of puny apes that arose on an African plain a mere blink of an eye ago in geological time. Yet we have discovered the genetic secret of life, made footprints in the Moon&amp;rsquo;s Sea of Tranquility and discovered the principle that makes everything &amp;ndash; the stars and galaxies and us &amp;ndash; possible. Of course, we are left with the mystery of why nature is so obsessed by enforcing local gauge symmetry. What is the significance of the &amp;ldquo;one rule that binds them all&amp;rdquo;?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6094/the-one-rule-that-binds-them-all#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-23T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-23T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why are we still obsessed with witches?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6093/why-are-we-still-obsessed-with-witches#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="'How far are these books mere fantasies?'" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/petr-sidorov-GESOWH4YLRI-unsplash.jpg" height="1182" alt="Tarot cards" width="1773"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been spending these dark winter nights immersing myself in so-called &amp;ldquo;witch lit&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; reading four of the many new books about witches published in the last year or so. My generation of 20-somethings enjoyed our fair share of feminist necromancy, with the TV show Buffy the Vampire Slayer and hit films like The Craft coming out in the mid-90s. I wanted to know what the current trend for witchy novels and non-fiction revealed about the tastes and dreams of today&amp;rsquo;s young women. How far are these books mere fantasies &amp;ndash; wrapped up in social media-fuelled new age mumbo jumbo about tarot readings and manifestations &amp;ndash; and how far are they grounded in genuine engagement with historical misogyny and patriarchal superstition?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a change from traditional Gothic imagery, I noticed that some of these books are packaged in bright candy-coloured covers; acid pink in the case of Weyward, Emilia Hart&amp;rsquo;s much-heralded debut novel. Following three generations of English women in one family &amp;ndash; in a 17th-century witch trial, the 1940s and the modern day &amp;ndash; it does a good job of grappling with the idea that patriarchy and misogyny endure, even if they change their masks. But although I liked the idea of women having an animal affinity with the natural world of insects and reptiles, the novel has the fundamental problem of imagining witchcraft at some level, however benign, to be real.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Kirsty Logan&amp;rsquo;s Now She is Witch takes a more metaphysical approach, with echoes of the fantasy world of Game of Thrones or The Lord of the Rings, yet it is more satisfyingly realistic. Set in an impressionistic and non-specific Nordic mediaeval Europe, the heroine Lux navigates a theocratic Christian land of witch-burnings, exorcisms, controlling priests and superstitious warrior kings, where the only certainty is that women will be blamed for all wrongs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Logan&amp;rsquo;s evocation of woman-hating perhaps draws on a growing popular knowledge of Scotland&amp;rsquo;s disturbing record of witch-hunting in the 16th and 17th centuries, powered by King James I&amp;rsquo;s (James VI of Scotland) obsession with them and his book Daemonologie. Scotland executed at least 2,500 people &amp;ndash; overwhelmingly women &amp;ndash; for alleged witchcraft. This was proportionally more than anywhere else in Europe and America. Scotland&amp;rsquo;s First Minister Nicola Sturgeon made a formal apology for the murders in March last year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The King of Denmark and Norway even imported Scottish witchfinders &amp;ndash; a fact I learned reading Anya Bergman&amp;rsquo;s impressive historically researched novel The Witches of Vardo, about the torture and murder of women there in the 1662-3 witch trials. The book evokes the superstitious madness of that era, with peasant women from fishing villages on the wild coast blamed for conjuring up storms that downed ships with valuable cargoes. Bergman emphasises the persecution of the Sami native people of the region, incorporating their own legends and ideas of healing into a story that inspired me to find out more about the real events. And, controversially, she imagines a sympathetic interpretation of the role of a real female figure, Anna Rhodius, demonised in historical accounts for her part in the convictions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Against all this fiction, I also read a factual account of witch hunts that reads with the fluency of a novel. With all this interest in witch-lit, perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s no coincidence that The Ruin of All Witches: Life and Death in the New World, published in 2021, came back onto the UK bestseller charts in January. Historian Malcolm Gaskill tells the full story of a 1651 witch hunt in Springfield, Connecticut &amp;ndash; from first accusation to trial and verdict. This was 40 years before the Salem trials.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Crucially, Gaskill writes to make us see the world as those early Puritans saw it; how their own psychological fears, of financial ruin, of neighbours, of Native Americans and the hostile elements, could seed the first accusations of witchcraft through how they interpreted their dreams: &amp;ldquo;The minds of sleeping colonists were transported to a place where the wilderness met the invisible realm and received supernatural revelations encoded as symbols of civility and savagery: angels and serpents. Here the devil turned fantasy into fact and made witches of the weak.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gaskill&amp;rsquo;s book cover is even in the same acid pink as Hart&amp;rsquo;s Weyward. The latter, like the other novels I&amp;rsquo;ve discussed, is fantasy. But, to their credit, all are rooted in this generation&amp;rsquo;s advanced awareness of real-life patriarchy, and the desire of these young women to connect to the historical misogyny endured by their ancestors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6093/why-are-we-still-obsessed-with-witches#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-21T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-21T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Be Tongue-Tied</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/science-cannot-be-tongue-tied/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It might be funny, if it weren’t so worrisome. Recent weeks have seen some absurd new instances of science beset by would-be censors operating under the banner of “inclusion.” Examples are many, and they come from all over the globe. We’ll look at an ongoing controversy in …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978517</id>
    <published>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MARCH 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/open-discussion-march-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978514</id>
    <published>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION FEBRUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/open-discussion-february-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978493</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
