<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-10-25T06:43:39Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Horrifying pedophile enabler Hovind exposed</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/24/horrifying-pedophile-enabler-hovind-exposed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;If ever you wanted a review of Kent Hovind&amp;#8217;s more recent behavior (no, you don&amp;#8217;t), here it is.  If you ever doubted that Hovind was a horrible person &amp;#8212; well, why would you be here? &amp;#8212; this will straighten you out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/D75Uv9_gTo8" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If ever you wanted a review of Kent Hovind’s more recent behavior (no, you don’t), here it is. If you ever doubted that Hovind was a horrible person — well, why would you be here? — this will straighten you out.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68289</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T21:52:55Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T21:52:55Z</updated>
    <category term="Creationism"/>
    <category term="Crime"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Things you never knew about water</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/24/things-you-never-knew-about-water/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I think I poisoned my brain on Sunday reading these <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/23/who-the-heck-is-gilbert-ling/">claims about different phases of water</a>. Or, at least, I poisoned my Google algorithms because now this crap keeps gurgling up.</p>
<p>Here’s one that’s so over-the-top it was almost amusing, except that it’s <a href="https://thewellnessenterprise.com/dr-gerald-pollack/" rel="nofollow">a commercial site using ludicrous claims about biology to sell miracle water</a>.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>Dr. Gerald Pollack is a biomedical engineering research scientist from the University of Washington that discovered a new state of water beyond liquid, solid and vapor. H3O2, sometimes called gel water, structured water or exclusion zone water (EZ water), is in between a solid and a liquid. An extra hydrogen molecule and an extra oxygen molecule make it silkier than H2O. This matters because that 70 – 90% you’ve heard about in your body is actually H3O2. That’s why water doesn’t come gushing out of you like a hose if you get a cut. Your cells are full of the thicker, H3O2. </p></blockquote>
<p>Oooh, silkier. How do they measure that? Also cool that they think I’d turn into a firehose if I only contained normal water.</p>
<blockquote class="creationist"><p>Water in nature is naturally structured even though you can’t see any form in it. At a molecular level, under a microscope water has shapes that are organized in geometric patterns. Spring water, waterfalls and glaciers are structured. And the water in fruits and vegetables is naturally structured. What Dr. Gerald Pollack has revealed to us is that if we want to get our bodies into alignment with nature and health, we need to be thinking about hydration with structured water.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yes. Put water under a microscope and you’ll be able to see the geometric patterns. I guess it’s supposed to look like this:</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/h3o2.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/h3o2.jpeg" alt="" width="474" height="176" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-68287" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/h3o2.jpeg 474w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/h3o2-150x56.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/h3o2-300x111.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 474px) 100vw, 474px"/></a></p>
<p>If your water looks nothing like that, you can buy a tube full of quartz crystals that will structure your tap water for the low, low, low price of only $1799.</p>
<p>Man, this is an <em>amazing</em> racket.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I think I poisoned my brain on Sunday reading these claims about different phases of water. Or, at least, I poisoned my Google algorithms because now this crap keeps gurgling up. Here’s one that’s so over-the-top it was almost amusing, except that it’s a commercial site using ludicrous claims about biology to sell miracle water. […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68286</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T15:31:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T15:31:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No One Has (or Should Have) a “Right to Sex”</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/10/no-one-has-or-should-have-a-right-to-sex/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Let’s talk about sex! Oh, but not in, like, a fun and sexy way. I mean in a way that will involve scientific research, bad takes on Twitter, and Latin phrases like post hoc …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131734</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T15:02:36Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T15:02:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Is this really the best way to illustrate world population?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/24/is-this-really-the-best-way-to-illustrate-world-population/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">This chart is very pretty and colorful, but all it’s really doing is plotting a single variable, population size, against the arbitrary names of political subunits. It’s hard to read and difficult to extract any information about relationships from it. I think the creators need to go back and re-read (or read for the first time?) <a href="https://amzn.to/3DqXNHN">Edward Tufte</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy-500x773.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="773" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-68284" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy-500x773.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy-97x150.jpg 97w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy-194x300.jpg 194w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy-768x1187.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/world-population-at-8-billion-copy.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>This is what you get when someone is told to make some visual candy that really pops, rather than to transform <em>information</em> into a visual medium. My eyes are simultaneously stimulated and offended.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This chart is very pretty and colorful, but all it’s really doing is plotting a single variable, population size, against the arbitrary names of political subunits. It’s hard to read and difficult to extract any information about relationships from it. I think the creators need to go back and re-read (or read for the first […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68283</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T14:47:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T14:47:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>One way to be Less Wrong is to avoid faulty premises</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/24/one-way-to-be-less-wrong-is-to-avoid-faulty-premises/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel-150x58.png" alt="" width="150" height="58" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-68281" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel-150x58.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel-300x116.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel-500x194.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/lingmodel.png 667w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">While I was digging into the question of <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/23/who-the-heck-is-gilbert-ling/">who this Gilbert Ling character was</a>, I ran into lots of sources that didn’t make the final cut. Unfortunately, most of those sources were from fringe or unsavory places — I did check my collection of textbooks, too, and nowhere does he get any mention. So it’s down into the sewers after all! Like this <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/7GSy4kofTBaXcPWXi/thermodynamics-of-intelligence-and-cognitive-enhancement">article on Less Wrong</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Association-Induction hypothesis formulated by Gilbert Ling is an alternate view of cell function, which suggests a distinct functional role of energy within the cell. I won’t review it in detail here, but you can find an easy to understand and comprehensive introduction to this hypothesis in the book “Cells, Gels and the Engines of Life” by Gerald H. Pollack. This idea has a long history with considerable experimental evidence, which is too extensive to review in this article.</p></blockquote>
<p>No, it has a 70 year history all centered on the long-winded writings of a single crackpot. There is no experimental evidence for any of it other than the willful distortions of one Gilbert Ling. Pollack is utterly batty, and not a credible source.</p>
<p>Worse still, this guy is using Ling’s theories as a starting point for discussing how we can use this information to potentially increase IQ.</p>
<blockquote><p>So this suggests a ‘systems biology’ approach to cognitive enhancement. It’s necessary to consider how metabolism is regulated, and what substrates it requires. To raise intelligence in a safe and effective way, all of these substrates must have increased availability to the neuron, in appropriate ratios.</p>
<p>I am always leery of drawing analogies between brains and computers but this approach to cognitive enhancement is very loosely analogous to over-clocking a CPU. Over-clocking requires raising both the clock rate, and the energy availability (voltage). In the case of the brain, the effective ‘clock rate’ is controlled by hormones (primarily triiodothyronine aka T3), and energy availability is provided by glucose and other nutrients.</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh god. Nerds discussing overly simplistic analogies between brains and computers always makes me leery, too, so just stop already. Especially when your ‘over-clocking’ idea is built on a bogus model of cellular metabolism that has been known to be wrong for the entirety of its “long history”.</p>
<p>I know I started this by dissing the Less Wrong forum, but I will say that, to their credit, most of the commenters were tearing that article apart.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While I was digging into the question of who this Gilbert Ling character was, I ran into lots of sources that didn’t make the final cut. Unfortunately, most of those sources were from fringe or unsavory places — I did check my collection of textbooks, too, and nowhere does he get any mention. So it’s […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68280</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T12:58:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T12:58:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>You’re probably as tired of hearing about Sviggum as I am</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/10/24/youre-probably-as-tired-of-hearing-about-sviggum-as-i-am/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/MorrisMission.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/MorrisMission-145x150.jpg" alt="" width="145" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-68278" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/MorrisMission-145x150.jpg 145w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/MorrisMission-290x300.jpg 290w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/10/MorrisMission.jpg 411w" sizes="(max-width: 145px) 100vw, 145px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">At least this <a href="https://www.minnpost.com/opinion-pieces/2022/10/isolation-and-feelings-of-being-unwanted-confront-students-of-color-at-too-diverse-university-of-minnesota-morris/">article focuses on the perspective of the students</a> — they’re pissed off. But hey, I recognized a bunch of the students they highlighted!</p>
<p>I also think one student made a particularly good point. Paradoxically, with great diversity comes great isolation.</p>
<blockquote><p>Mercedese Young Man said she often feels alone on the campus and in the western Minnesota town.</p>
<p>“I feel isolated,” said Young Man, who is in her first semester at Morris. “Before (Sviggum) said all of that I was going to my counselors and telling them I was having a hard time adjusting to being here.”</p>
<p>Young Man, who sat for nearly an hour by herself in the school café seating area, said she transferred to Morris because of its supposed diversity, but she said that’s not the case. Officially Morris can boast of a robustly diverse population – 41% students of color, of that 32% Native American of a total student population of 1,068 – but Young Man disputed those numbers.</p>
<p>“There are just a handful of Native students here and all from separate tribes,” said Young Man, who is from Oglala, South Dakota. “In several of my classes I’m the only person … maybe one other … person of color.”</p></blockquote>
<p>The raw statistics tends to lump all these students into one mass — “students of color” and “Native American” — but they all see themselves as something far more specific. I’ve known students who are Navajo and Delaware, as well as the regional Lakota and Dakota peoples. There are also Hmong and Somali and Nigerian and Latino and Filipino students here, and just sweeping them into a pile and calling them our diverse brown students is insulting and inadequate.</p>
<p>Bugger Sviggum, we should just listen to the students and follow their suggestions.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To the point of UMN Morris’ declining enrollment, Strukel and Kadlec may have unintentionally offered up a marketing campaign for the university.<br/>
“We’re unique here because we’re so separated from the fast-paced world. Here it’s who’s around you; that’s who you got,” said Kadlec. “There’s no Target or Walmart here to take my money so I’m forced to be here on campus with my friends; and that’s not bad at all.”</p>
</blockquote>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At least this article focuses on the perspective of the students — they’re pissed off. But hey, I recognized a bunch of the students they highlighted! I also think one student made a particularly good point. Paradoxically, with great diversity comes great isolation. Mercedese Young Man said she often feels alone on the campus and […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68277</id>
    <published>2022-10-24T12:34:41Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-24T12:34:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>No, Ebola is NOT Airborne!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/10/no-ebola-is-not-airborne/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Look, we all went through a pretty traumatic time in 2020 through…today, so it’s understandable if you see things that immediately put you back in February of 2020 and so you start crying and buying …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131732</id>
    <published>2022-10-21T15:18:12Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-21T15:18:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A stranger in your own land</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6033/a-stranger-in-your-own-land#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/MC1K9N.jpg" height="668" alt="Children run through an Italian square" width="1000" /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Exiles: Three Island Journeys (Faber &amp;amp; Faber) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;by William Atkins&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motherlands: In Search of Our Inherited Cities (Bloomsbury Publishing) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;by Amaryllis Gacioppo &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In 1688, Johannes Hofer, a 19-year-old medical student from Berne, observed a condition that medicine had yet to define. Symptoms of this &amp;ldquo;melancholy delirium&amp;rdquo; might include fever, disturbed sleep, palpitations, loss of appetite and anxiety. The Germans had a word for it: &lt;em&gt;heimweh&lt;/em&gt; or &amp;ldquo;home-woe&amp;rdquo;. But Hofer coined a new medical term from the Greek &lt;em&gt;nostos&lt;/em&gt;, meaning a homecoming, and &lt;em&gt;algos&lt;/em&gt;, denoting pain. He called it nostalgia: an unassuageable grief for a lost homeland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;The meaning of nostalgia may have changed, but two original and remarkable new books explore how Hofer&amp;rsquo;s insight might resonate today in an age of mass migration and resurgent nationalism. Both dig deep into difficult questions around identity and belonging.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Exiles: Three Island Journeys&lt;/em&gt; by William Atkins takes as its starting point the lives of three late 19th-century political exiles, each a figure of resistance and change. The French CommunardLouise Michel was transported to the Pacific island of New Caledonia. Dinuzulu kaCetshwayo, a Zulu king, was exiled by the British to St Helena in the South Atlantic. And the Jewish Ukrainian revolutionary Lev Shternberg was sent to Sakhalin Island, off the coast of Siberia, by Tsarist Russia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Atkins&amp;rsquo; primary interest is in how his subjects adapted to these ruptures in their lives. &amp;ldquo;The thought of the distance kills us,&amp;rdquo; one of Michel&amp;rsquo;s fellow Communard exiles said. In later life, Shternberg taught ethnography in St Petersburg. His students described him as a man &amp;ldquo;charred by some internal burning&amp;rdquo;. Another exiled Communard &amp;ldquo;died of grief at receiving no news from home&amp;rdquo;. To be so unmoored was a kind of death-in-life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;But you couldn&amp;rsquo;t go back, even when you did, in fact, go back. For Dinuzulu, who adopted European clothing and manners during his eight years on St Helena, this was literally true. The defeated kingdom he left behind was broken up by the British, and he returned no longer a king, but as the governor of what was essentially a vassal territory, fractured by conflict and imperial taxation. And yet the land and its people were the source of his identity: &amp;ldquo;the closer to his land he was allowed to be, the more powerful he grew,&amp;rdquo; Atkins writes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Atkins visited the places he writes about. He searches for the traces his subjects left on the spaces they inhabited. But he is also exploring other kinds of exile and fracture, in particular the legacies of empire on these island prisons: the traumas that exiles and subject peoples might share. The indigenous Kanak of New Caledonia are still struggling today to free their country from French dominion. Atkins&amp;rsquo; arrival coincides with a fractious independence vote, which the Kanak lost. He quotes the Kanak &lt;br /&gt;independence campaigner Jean-Marie Tjibaou: &amp;ldquo;The hardest thing is to stay alive and feel like a stranger in your own land.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;***&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;Imperial Europe transported immense numbers to its penal colonies. The British empire dispatched some 376,000, Tsarist Russia nearly two million. &lt;em&gt;Exiles&lt;/em&gt;, then, is an intimate account of an epic phenomenon. Amaryllis Gacioppo&amp;rsquo;s concern in &lt;em&gt;Motherlands: In Search of Our Inherited Cities &lt;/em&gt;is more directly personal. Her starting point is the legacy of four generations of matrilineal migration within her family &amp;ndash; in the 1920s from Turin to Benghazi, then part of Italian colonial Libya; from Benghazi to Palermo by way of Rome in the 1940s; from Palermo to the Sydney suburbs two decades later; and, for Gacioppo herself, a recent move from Australia, her place of birth, to Italy, a country that has both always and never been home to her.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;As Gacioppo traces these stories of displacement from city to city she explores wider ideas about dislocation and belonging. She recreates daily familial journeys and routines, trying to &amp;ldquo;trigger a kind of temporal magic . . . [accessing] powers of memory or meaning or association&amp;rdquo;. She is particularly interested in photographs and maps. A map of Allied bomb damage to Rome pales before the reality of a satellite photograph; but in colonial Benghazi it is the great-grandparents&amp;rsquo; photos that seem unreal.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Turin, Nietzsche said, is &amp;ldquo;the first place where I am possible&amp;rdquo;. If the goal of all migration is to find such a place, what of countries that make migrant lives impossible? In Rome, Gacioppo meets a woman campaigning for the rights of 1.5 million young Italians without citizenship, many of whom arrived in their infancy. They call themselves &amp;ldquo;ghosts by law&amp;rdquo;, denied a connection to their homeland&amp;rsquo;s past, along with the certainty of a settled future.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Gacioppo writes eloquently about the alienating dislocation of the &lt;em&gt;unheimlich&lt;/em&gt; (literally, the unhomely) &amp;ndash; what she calls &amp;ldquo;a dispersal of the self, a confused state of inner unmooring&amp;rdquo;. At the other end of the extreme, she visits the former SS headquarters in Rome, now a museum. In the cells, scratched into the walls, are the messages of the soon-to-be-tortured, soon-to-be-dead. &amp;ldquo;Love Italy&amp;rdquo;, one reads. &amp;ldquo;Those who die for the homeland live for eternity&amp;rdquo;, reads another. What is this idea of home, of place, that &lt;br /&gt;belonging to it is more powerful than death?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Mobility &amp;ndash; migration, exile, colonisation &amp;ndash; has always been part of the human condition. And the most meaningful kinds of belonging have nothing to do with borders or governments. &amp;ldquo;[A] relationship to the land as a basis of cultural identity is one that echoes the beliefs and religions of native peoples all over the world,&amp;rdquo; Gacioppo writes. But roots can also regrow. When Louise Michel returned to France from exile, she smuggled five cats out with her. They were, she said, &amp;ldquo;something alive left from home&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Both of these complex, thoughtful and deeply moving books also look towards the larger idea that, as Gacioppo writes, &amp;ldquo;With each step forward into the future, something is lost, and this loss, the void created by it, travels with us. It is there to remind us that there is no such thing as returning.&amp;rdquo; That is, the griefs of time, of separation, of mortality are another exile from which there is no return. If a true homecoming is impossible and this greater kind of exile haunts us all, who amongst us remains unbroken?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist autumn 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6033/a-stranger-in-your-own-land#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-10-21T12:29:31Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-21T12:29:31Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Flying spaghetti monsters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6031/flying-spaghetti-monsters#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Pastafarians gather for a &amp;ldquo;stand-in&amp;rdquo; in Turin, 2015" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2EX5WMW.jpg" height="1000" alt="Pastafarians gather for a &amp;ldquo;stand-in&amp;rdquo; in Turin in 2015" width="1500" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;One day in 2016, Derk Venema, a Dutch academic specialising in legal philosophy, was browsing the internet for examples of &amp;ldquo;philosophically interesting questions about religious freedom&amp;rdquo; to show his students. He came across the perfect case: a &amp;ldquo;Pastafarian&amp;rdquo;, or self-designated member of the Church of the Flying Spaghetti Monster (FSM), was challenging the authorities for rejecting his driving licence photograph, in which he wore a colander on his head.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Venema took a few students to watch the case before the local Chamber of Commerce. &amp;ldquo;It was one of the most hilarious things I have ever witnessed,&amp;rdquo; he says. Math&amp;eacute; Coolen, the applicant, &amp;ldquo;played his role excellently. Even the Commissioner was having a tough time not laughing.&amp;rdquo; But when he spoke to Coolen afterwards, Venema realised that he was &amp;ldquo;also very serious about the underlying questions, the questions about when and how administrative bodies get to decide what is a religion and what is not, and who gets to enjoy religious privileges and who doesn&amp;rsquo;t.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;One of the students who accompanied Venema on his trip was Mienke de Wilde. She was so impressed by the case that she decided to become a Pastafarian herself. The next time she applied for a driving licence, she submitted a photo of herself wearing a colander. Her application was rejected. She appealed, claiming that Pastafarianism was a religion and her right to manifest it was protected under the European Convention on Human Rights. Venema took on her case and Coolen&amp;rsquo;s; ultimately, it was de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s alone that went all the way to the Dutch Administrative Court and then the European Court of Human Rights (ECtHR). The court handed down judgment on 9 November last year. But before examining their conclusions, it is worth taking a step back to the origins of this strange &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;The Gospel of the Flying Spaghetti Monster&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;In 2005, the Kansas School Board was considering whether to teach the theory of intelligent design alongside evolution. Bobby Henderson, a physics graduate from Oregon, wrote a now famous letter in which he claimed to believe that a &amp;ldquo;Flying Spaghetti Monster&amp;rdquo; created the world, and demanded that his theory be given equal time with the other two. He also claimed that &amp;ldquo;global warming . . . and other natural disasters are a direct effect of the shrinking numbers of pirates since the 1800s.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Henderson had written the letter as satire. In doing so, however, he unexpectedly generated a meme. The internet was in its early days of cavalier freedom. Facebook had been founded the previous year and Twitter would be the next; chain emails were still a thing. At the same time, &amp;ldquo;New Atheism&amp;rdquo; was on the rise. Sam Harris had published &lt;em&gt;The End of Faith&lt;/em&gt; in 2004, and contributions by Richard Dawkins, Daniel Dennett and Christopher Hitchens would soon follow. (Dennett later featured in the FSM documentary &lt;em&gt;I, Pastafari.&lt;/em&gt;) It was fashionable among the godless youth to put &amp;ldquo;Jedi&amp;rdquo; as their religion on the UK census; 176,632 people did so in 2011. Parody was the flavour of the day. Pastafarianism went viral, and publishers rushed to sign Henderson up for a book contract.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The result was &lt;em&gt;The Gospel of the Flying Spaghetti Monster&lt;/em&gt;, published by Villard less than six months before Dawkins&amp;rsquo; &lt;em&gt;The God Delusion&lt;/em&gt;. The&lt;em&gt; Gospel&lt;/em&gt; according to Henderson is a picaresque series of pseudo-scientific rants, accompanied by diagrams and mock-formal logic, on topics from &amp;ldquo;the need for alternative theories&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;a history of heretics&amp;rdquo;. It is clearly designed to parody the attempts of evangelical Christians to co-opt science into supporting their literalist interpretation of the Bible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;As a work of literature or philosophy, the &lt;em&gt;Gospel&lt;/em&gt; has its limitations. In the words of Kathleen McEvoy, an Australian judge: &amp;ldquo;At best the texts present ordinary moral admonitions and mundane articulations of principles of conduct present in the texts of most other established religions.&amp;rdquo; Henderson himself, drawing a comparison with traditional scriptures, wrote that &amp;ldquo;this book will stand up to any of the others &amp;ndash; at least in terms of strict plausibility if not literary finesse and retributive beheadings and disembowelments.&amp;rdquo; The book reportedly sold over 100,000 copies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Meanwhile, the memes of Pastafarianism have multiplied. A crucial moment in the Church&amp;rsquo;s history came in 2011 in Austria, when Niko Alm was permitted to wear a colander in his driving licence photo &amp;ndash; although only after a visit from a public health officer to check that he was sane. The police, who issued the licence, stated that &amp;ldquo;the photo was not approved on religious grounds. The only criterion for photos in driving licence applications is that the whole face must be visible.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;This deftly sidestepped the underlying issue &amp;ndash; but Alm&amp;rsquo;s success led to a string of similar attempts around the world, including de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s. Different authorities have responded in their own ways. In some places, often the more religious ones, the colander has been permitted, from the Czech Republic to Utah; in Poland, the Church of the FSM has been allowed to register as an official religion. In Belgium and Ireland, the colander has not made it through. In England in 2015, the DVLA rejected a colander photo by Ian Harris, described by the &lt;em&gt;Mail Online &lt;/em&gt;as &amp;ldquo;an eccentric man&amp;rdquo;, because headgear was only &amp;ldquo;permissible on religious or medical grounds&amp;rdquo;. In Adelaide, Australia, Guy Albon had his guns confiscated after he submitted a colander photo for his licence, out of fears for his &amp;ldquo;mental competency&amp;rdquo;. More seriously, the Pastafarian Mikhail Iosilevich was issued his licence in Russia &amp;ndash; but was later arrested on the political charge of &amp;ldquo;cooperating with an undesirable organisation&amp;rdquo;. In May, he was sentenced to 20 months in prison and ordered to pay civil damages roughly equivalent to &amp;pound;1500.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Is Pastafarianism a religion?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Wearing the colander can be interpreted as a protest against the legal exemptions and privileges readily granted to adherents of all the major world religions. The Dutch authorities, like the DVLA, would have permitted a turban, skull cap or nun&amp;rsquo;s veil in ID photos as long as the face remained clear. De Wilde&amp;rsquo;s case is the first and, so far, the only time that the European Court has considered whether Pastafarianism is a &amp;ldquo;religion or belief&amp;rdquo; worthy of protection in human rights law.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The result of de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s challenge, however, was the same in both Holland and Strasbourg: rejection. On the evidence, the Dutch courts found, and the European judges accepted, that she genuinely did wear a colander at all times when outside. (A black plastic colander which she likens to a &amp;ldquo;bowler hat&amp;rdquo; and wears at a rakish angle; she has a different one for cooking pasta.) But they could not accept that her beliefs constituted a &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;De Wilde argued that her beliefs were protected under Article 9 of the Convention on Human Rights, which states that, subject to various limitations:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience and religion; this right includes freedom to change his religion or belief and freedom, either alone or in community with others and in public or private, to manifest his religion or belief, in worship, teaching, practice and observance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;A regional court refused de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s appeal on the grounds that wearing the colander was not mandatory in Pastafarianism. This argument was rejected on further appeal by the Administrative Jurisdiction of the Council of State, Holland&amp;rsquo;s highest appeal court, because the case law of the ECtHR had previously held that the manifestation of a religion does not have to be mandatory to be protected.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Instead, both the Administrative Court and the ECtHR rejected the claim that Pastafarianism could amount to a religion. Consequently, however much de Wilde wore her colander, it did not count as a religious act. The thorny path by which they reached this conclusion reveals the difficulties that arise when courts of law are asked to decide metaphysical questions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you read an anthology on the concept of religion, you get hundreds of different definitions,&amp;rdquo; says Paul Cliteur, Emeritus Professor of Jurisprudence at Leiden University. These go back to Cicero in the first century BC, who defined religion as &amp;ldquo;reverence for the gods&amp;rdquo;. It is unsurprising, Cliteur argues, that &amp;ldquo;a bunch of judges assembled in the European Court&amp;rdquo; should find it a tough nut to crack: &amp;ldquo;they are not religious scholars, they are not philosophers, they are not involved.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Through its case law, the ECtHR has developed a test for &amp;ldquo;religion or belief&amp;rdquo; under Article 9: to qualify, the relevant belief must have obtained &amp;ldquo;a certain level of cogency, seriousness, cohesion and importance&amp;rdquo;. In de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s case, the judges quoted the reasoning of the Dutch Administrative Court, and then briefly reiterated it, to conclude that Pastafarianism failed to meet the requisite standards of &amp;ldquo;seriousness and cohesion&amp;rdquo;. The movement was designed to &amp;ldquo;parody&amp;rdquo; established religions in order to criticise the &amp;ldquo;influence and privileged position afforded to [them] . . . in some contemporary societies&amp;rdquo;; as such, it could not be a religion itself. Or, as the Dutch court put it, the &amp;ldquo;satirical element&amp;rdquo; was &amp;ldquo;so dominant&amp;rdquo; that the European Court&amp;rsquo;s test could not be met.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;In the court&amp;rsquo;s view, Pastafarianism was not serious; examples were drawn from Henderson&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Gospel&lt;/em&gt;, including his &amp;ldquo;Eight I&amp;rsquo;d Really Rather You Didn&amp;rsquo;ts&amp;rdquo;, which parodied the Ten Commandments. Nor was it sufficiently cohesive; the court took as its example the pirates-and-global-warming theory. The court was equally dismissive of de Wilde&amp;rsquo;s argument that her own &amp;ldquo;individual version&amp;rdquo; of Pastafarianism could be serious and cohesive, even if the movement as a whole was not; her explanations, it held, were too &amp;ldquo;general and abstract&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;There is clearly force in the view that a humorous parody of something cannot itself be that thing. If the law is required to define concepts like &amp;ldquo;religion or belief&amp;rdquo;, then there must be limiting cases. Henderson&amp;rsquo;s monster started as a sarcastic attack on the teaching of creationism. Its claims are outrageous and entirely unbelievable: that is the point. Wearing a colander or a pirate hat for an ID photo is ridiculous. The purpose of doing so is to question the idea that some forms of headgear are allowed, but not others, on the basis of unprovable dogma.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p4"&gt;Freedom of religion, or freedom of thought?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Yet there are difficulties with the courts&amp;rsquo; reasoning if Pastafarianism is compared with other belief systems &amp;ndash; and, like all parody, it is designed to be compared. Seriousness, for one, is not as straightforward a criterion as it appears. Take Mormonism, says Venema: it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;hilarious&amp;rdquo;. Indeed, to non-believers, the Book of Mormon reads like a parody of the Bible. If Pastafarianism is zany, it reflects the zaniness of established religions. As Henderson writes, &amp;ldquo;every time an &amp;lsquo;official&amp;rsquo; ruling is made against our Church it illustrates how absurd the whole idea is of the state defining what is a legitimate religious organisation.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The European Court&amp;rsquo;s reasoning also betrays the extent to which, in judicial considerations of Article 9, the paradigm case is religion, and other beliefs are only extensions of that. The court concluded that Pastafarianism &amp;ldquo;seeks the same privileges for itself [as for established religions] with a view to propagating its message.&amp;rdquo; That is what it would do if it were a &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; religion, or a sham religion trying to gain money from its supporters. Yet De Wilde told me that she would be happy to remove the colander for her ID photo, as long as others did. &amp;ldquo;We just want to be treated equally.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;There are many undercurrents in the Dutch courts&amp;rsquo; resistance to Pastafarianism. One, argues Venema, is the civil servant&amp;rsquo;s instinctive fear of mockery. &amp;ldquo;We even discovered that there was a lot of communication by city administrations with the Ministry for the Interior. They were advised to deny all these applications by people who wore spaghetti strainers on their heads.&amp;rdquo; As a result of this and the Dutch judgments, says de Wilde, the authorities have effectively discouraged any more Pastafarians from applying.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;A similar attitude was evinced by a Qu&amp;eacute;b&amp;eacute;cois judge in another Pastafarian case in 2015. In the judge&amp;rsquo;s view, the applicant, Isabelle Narayana, who wanted to wear a pirate hat in her ID photo, was treating &amp;ldquo;in a banal manner the fundamental rights and liberties protected by the [Canadian human rights] charters, to the point of rendering them insignificant.&amp;rdquo; He said her claim was &amp;ldquo;an immense farce that aims to mock religions&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Tanya Watkins, self-appointed Captain of the Church of the FSM in Australia, met with similar treatment when she applied to register it as a religious organisation. The judge, Kathleen McEvoy, considered that the scriptures of Pastafarianism were &amp;ldquo;parodic texts, developed and expressed for the purpose of mocking and satirising established religions, holding them up to ridicule and suggesting they are worthless and meaningless&amp;rdquo;. She even lambasted them for being &amp;ldquo;racist&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;sexist&amp;rdquo; and likely to be &amp;ldquo;offensive or insulting&amp;rdquo; to (real) religions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The implication of such judgments is that there is something nefarious about mocking religions in this way &amp;ndash; perhaps due to a sense, in secular countries like Australia, the Netherlands and the UK, that protecting religious exceptionalism is a way of protecting minorities. Yet it is a sad state of affairs when the courts shrink from engaging with the question at the heart of the matter: whether the starting point in human rights law should be religion &amp;ndash; cogent, serious and important &amp;ndash; or whether it should be the freedom to think, believe or withhold belief, and act. If the latter (the secular starting-point), then there would be no need for courts to build a hierarchy of beliefs, or to stop Pastafarians from wearing colanders because they were not serious enough.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;For de Wilde, the point of fighting her case, and being deprived of a driving licence for five years in the process, is to achieve &amp;ldquo;equality&amp;rdquo;. In her view, Pastafarianism is &amp;ldquo;not less real than other religions&amp;rdquo;. Watkins agrees: &amp;ldquo;it has all of the same elements any other religion has,&amp;rdquo; and the same inconsistency in its followers&amp;rsquo; interpretations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Depending on your perspective, Pastafarians are either the most undogmatic believers in history, or unbelievers who will go to extreme lengths to protest against religious exceptionalism. &amp;ldquo;In a certain sense,&amp;rdquo; says Cliteur, &amp;ldquo;and I speak as an atheist, Pastafarianism is the ideal religion. If all humanity were Pastafarians &amp;ndash; people with a sense of humour and a relaxed attitude towards their religious convictions &amp;ndash; that would be a tremendous improvement.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Venema, despite his devotion to the Pastafarian cause, has not become an adherent. &amp;ldquo;I have never considered joining any groups or organisations that are founded on a specific idea,&amp;rdquo; he explains. &amp;ldquo;As a philosopher, I want to be free to think and express anything I want . . . Which I could still do as a Pastafarian, of course.&amp;rdquo; There you have it: a religion with no requirements, which is still too restrictive for a freethinking philosopher.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Perhaps it is also a question of taste, and of the symbols people use to express themselves; colanders and cutlasses are not everyone&amp;rsquo;s cup of tea. Not that Pastafarians are required to wear them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist autumn 2022 edition. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6031/flying-spaghetti-monsters#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-10-21T12:28:59Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-21T12:28:59Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dr. Oz Killed Puppies FOR SCIENCE?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/10/dr-oz-killed-puppies-for-science/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Important breaking news from a week or two ago: DR OZ IS A PUPPY KILLER. Dr. Mehmet Oz, a shambling golem formed from piles of hundred dollar bills Oprah found in her couch cushions, was …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131729</id>
    <published>2022-10-19T15:23:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-19T15:23:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Misinformation Masquerading as Truth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/10/misinformation-masquerading-as-truth/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! This is the time of year when many people are getting ready for Halloween. You may be getting ready for a costume party or stocking up on candy in anticipation of trick-or-treaters at your door. Most of our team is currently in Las Vegas getting ready for …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978437</id>
    <published>2022-10-18T17:15:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-18T17:15:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The pull of our ancient ancestors</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6030/the-pull-of-our-ancient-ancestors#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="The Nine Ladies stone circle, Stanton Moor " src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Nine_Ladies_stone_circle,_Stanton_Moor_-_geograph.org.uk_-_2360408.jpg" height="631" alt="The Nine Ladies of Stanton Moor" width="946" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;Stanton Moor is situated in Derbyshire&amp;rsquo;s beautiful Peak District National Park, in the heart of England. At first glance up here, it&amp;rsquo;s all foxgloves, purple heather and wildflowers. But if you have an archaeologist&amp;rsquo;s eye, like my friend Ian Jackson, you can detect something more deliberately patterned in the rocky formations that stretch out to the horizon in every direction: the outline of a Bronze Age roundhouse, sunken into the rock-strewn moor. The walls are long fallen and weathered away. Ian pointed out the narrow path that leads downwards and suddenly I saw it too. I stepped into the entrance and back through time. I was in someone&amp;rsquo;s home.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re closer to the Bronze Age people than they were to those who built Stonehenge,&amp;rdquo; Ian observed. For a moment I was struck silent with the majesty of that timescale.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;I had come Bronze Age hunting because, like many people it seems, I have recently become fascinated with the pre-Roman peoples of the British Isle. My walk was partly prompted by the British Museum&amp;rsquo;s blockbuster early summer exhibition on Stonehenge, the Neolithic stone circle in Wiltshire. Such stone circles pepper the length and breadth of this island nation. Not far from Stanton Moor is Arbor Low, another Neolithic stone circle at which the stones are now flat on the ground. Historians believe they were deliberately knocked down by medieval people, fuelled by their own superstitions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Stonehenge is a monument that Brits tend to think of as archetypically British. But the exhibition confounded all expectations. A wall mounted with dozens of beautiful stone axe heads from all over Europe revealed, post-Brexit, an almost provocatively counterintuitive picture; Britain connected by a large land bridge to northern Europe, with Stonehenge as the trading and pilgrimage heart of a borderless world. Recent excavations have provided plentiful evidence of trade from further afield &amp;ndash; pottery, jewellery and weapons from the Middle East, North Africa and Asia Minor. More intriguing still were the mysterious carvings of flowing spirals and cups and rings, on giant rocks and boulders found across Europe, from Germany to Scotland.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The British Museum show was fascinating &amp;ndash; but there were some troubling aspects too. The exhibition included skeletons that had been unearthed in graves. One was the skeleton of a woman who was still clutching the outline of her dead baby, a bag of more than a hundred animal teeth buried with them as a spiritual offering. After more than a century of challenge, museums would not, I think, dare to display the human remains of ancient First Nation peoples this way. On the one hand, modern Europeans claim a kinship with these ancient brothers and sisters, and yet we tolerate what could be seen as the desecration of their graves. With their belief systems long lost, they have no one to advocate for them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;And yet there is an honest spiritual craving in our modern behaviour around ancient monuments. Stonehenge is now understood to have been built in line with the natural cycle of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s rotation around the Sun, aligning with sunrise during the solstices. Humanists surely recognise the pull of acknowledging our place in the beautiful but indifferent Solar System.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Iwitnessed this pull in action on that day before the summer solstice when Ian and I walked on Stanton Moor. Not far from where Ian pointed out the outline of ancient homes is a Bronze Age stone circle known as the Nine Ladies. Around it, a tent city had grown up, of young families as much as old hippies, wanting to be part of something bigger than themselves. Such gatherings have been happening all over the country at stone circles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Part of it, I&amp;rsquo;m sure, is that after all the Covid lockdowns, we are still cherishing our right to roam freely and be with others. But there seems to be something else we are craving. It may seem that we know very little about our ancient ancestors. We don&amp;rsquo;t have a good idea of how they looked, and even their bones have mostly vanished. But they have left the most tantalising glimpses: jewellery made of black obsidian; gold torques of such weight and braided beauty it&amp;rsquo;s dazzling to imagine them worn in ritual acts. It&amp;rsquo;s also pleasing to discover that some of the finds in the Stonehenge exhibition suggest women may well have held positions of power in these societies, as shamans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;These were humans living on a minute timescale compared to the weathered rocks of their monuments. Yet their mystery binds them to us. We are drawn to the idea of their transience &amp;ndash; for what did the pandemic do more to reveal than the fragility of our own lives?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist autumn 2022 edition. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6030/the-pull-of-our-ancient-ancestors#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-10-18T12:41:16Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-18T12:41:16Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Work Pray Code</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6029/book-review-work-pray-code#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img title="Buddhist monks at Facebook&amp;rsquo;s headquarters" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/buddhafacebook.jpeg" height="1010" alt="Buddhist monks at Facebook" width="1596" /&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Work Pray Code (Princeton University Press) &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s1"&gt;by Carolyn Chen &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;&amp;ldquo;What happens to us, and what happens to religion, when people worship work?&amp;rdquo; This is the question that occupies sociologist Carolyn Chen in &lt;em&gt;Work Pray Code&lt;/em&gt;, her new book based on in-depth research on Silicon Valley&amp;rsquo;s tech industry. Her answer reveals the book&amp;rsquo;s title (with its suggestion of bounded activities) to be a slight misnomer. For, as Chen discovers, work is not only &amp;ldquo;replacing religion&amp;rdquo; (increasingly omnipresent in employees&amp;rsquo; lives, and the object of faith and devotion); it is infused with spiritual and religious practices geared, ultimately, towards maximum productivity. This is a world where work is not so much distinct from prayer as blurred with it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Chen suggests that Silicon Valley &amp;ndash; ostensibly one of America&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;least religious&amp;rdquo; places &amp;ndash; is not so &amp;ldquo;godless&amp;rdquo; after all. The tech workplace is &amp;ldquo;conscripting&amp;rdquo; religion; borrowing (typically, but not exclusively) from Asian spiritual and religious traditions, such as yoga and meditation, to help employees to become &amp;ldquo;whole&amp;rdquo; and connect to their &amp;ldquo;authentic selves&amp;rdquo;. But the nurturing care and cultivation of employees&amp;rsquo; spiritual lives are not altruistic. Rather, they rest upon the logic that the &amp;ldquo;self-alienated&amp;rdquo; worker operates at sub-optimal capacity. They are also vulnerable to burnout, which is blamed not on overwork, but &amp;ldquo;insufficient self-care&amp;rdquo;. No wonder, then, that employees might seek &amp;ldquo;optimisation&amp;rdquo; through practices including meditation, journaling and even fasting. Chen quotes one CEO who asks his staff to anonymously rate, weekly, aspects of their lives including spirituality. &amp;ldquo;Everyone knows&amp;rdquo;, he explains, &amp;ldquo;that if you&amp;rsquo;re not taking care of yourself, you&amp;rsquo;re not playing for the team.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Chen describes the &amp;ldquo;meditation entrepreneurs&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; including mindfulness teachers, HR executives and the coaches allocated to high-potential staff &amp;ndash; who share the challenge of selling &amp;ldquo;a religious product in a professedly secular workplace&amp;rdquo;. In doing so, they renounce a &amp;ldquo;sacred, separate, Asian, otherworldly, and ethical religious Buddhism&amp;rdquo;, and replace it with one that is &amp;ldquo;universalised, Whitened, scientised, profitable, and efficient&amp;rdquo;. Meditation thus becomes a snackable &amp;ldquo;skill&amp;rdquo; used to aid creativity, flow and focus (alongside empathy, with a view to enabling more &amp;ldquo;user friendly&amp;rdquo; design). Indeed, the practices Chen describes seem so far from actual Buddhism that one wonders whether they can be analysed in terms of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; at all. Chen explains: &amp;ldquo;tech meditators&amp;rdquo; aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;religious&amp;rdquo;, but use &amp;ldquo;religious traditions &amp;ndash; their practices, rituals, and teachings &amp;ndash; as tools or technologies to optimise their work performance&amp;rdquo;, directed towards the &amp;ldquo;religion of work&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Though wonderfully rich in detail, &lt;em&gt;Work Pray Code&lt;/em&gt; is frustrated by its failure to provide, early on, a firm working definition of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo;. This is clarified in an appendix, where Chen suggests that religion &amp;ldquo;in a secular age&amp;rdquo; can be studied not only through &amp;ldquo;religious things&amp;rdquo;, but those things that are also &amp;ldquo;sacred&amp;rdquo; to us and command worship (e.g. work, worshipped through yoga). Still, it leads one to wonder where &amp;ldquo;spirituality&amp;rdquo; ends and &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; and, indeed, cultishness &amp;ndash; begins. Some readers may find Chen&amp;rsquo;s conclusion conservative: though critical of the extent to which work is worshipped, Chen does not challenge work itself; likewise, she criticises &amp;ldquo;religions&amp;rdquo; for not confronting work worship, but leaves religion per se untouched. She suggests, &amp;ldquo;Religious traditions can offer a powerful and distinct set of ethics, communities, and rituals to counter the morally bereft religion of work.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Still, Chen&amp;rsquo;s critique of Silicon Valley&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Techtopia&amp;rdquo; and its impact on the wider social fabric is powerful. She describes how participatory democracy &amp;ndash; indeed, the common good &amp;ndash; suffers when we worship work and disengage from civic life; how public goods become private &amp;ldquo;perks&amp;rdquo; when the tech industry dominates; how so-called &amp;ldquo;wholeness&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the basic stuff of a good life&amp;rdquo; has become the &amp;ldquo;privilege&amp;rdquo; of the highly skilled, while others lack even basic security. Silicon Valley is, she suggests, a bellwether. One need not agree with Chen&amp;rsquo;s framework of &amp;ldquo;religion&amp;rdquo; to see that we must pay attention.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist autumn 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6029/book-review-work-pray-code#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-10-18T12:38:54Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-18T12:38:54Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Rainbow Fentanyl in Halloween Candy???</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/10/rainbow-fentanyl-in-halloween-candy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Transcript: Well, spooky season is here and I could not be happier: I’ve already put up my giant spider and spider web, my fractal skeletons, and my yard flamingulas, and I’m ready to greet my …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131725</id>
    <published>2022-10-13T16:46:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-13T16:46:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Scientists Sued for Criticizing COVID-19 Air Purifiers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://skepchick.org/2022/10/scientists-sued-for-criticizing-covid-19-air-purifiers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This post contains a video, which you can also view here. To support more videos like this, head to patreon.com/rebecca! Almost exactly five years ago, I made a video about air purification. In the blissful year of 2017, the worst thing I could imagine breathing in was wildfire smoke, because I live in the San …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Rebecca Watson</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://skepchick.org/?p=131722</id>
    <published>2022-10-10T15:01:40Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-10T15:01:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Time for a new renaissance?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6034/time-for-a-new-renaissance#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;img title="HowTheLightGetsIn festival aims to bring disciplines together, particularly philosophers and scientists" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/highres_84_6896-1-_1_.jpg" height="1278" alt="HowTheLightGetsIn London" width="1920" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;You know the feeling. You pass the window of a book store, or switch on a political talk show, and are overwhelmed by an irritating sensation of deja vu. Haven&amp;rsquo;t you heard these ideas before? Behind the shiny new designs, aren&amp;rsquo;t these latest non-fiction hardbacks peddling the same basic theories, tweaked to entice a fresh audience? It can be difficult to gauge how our own personal frustration relates to the broader reality. On Sunday, HowTheLightGetsIn London confronted this perception head on. HTLGI is a festival dedicated to "big ideas", bringing together academics, scientists, creatives and "thought leaders" of all stripes. They have more than a vested interest, therefore, in answering the question. Is our intellectual climate in Britain stagnating? If so, how do we encourage new and original thinking?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;The event brought together speakers from the diverse fields of philosophy, theoretical physics and journalism to chew over the dilemma. While the term &amp;ldquo;Renaissance Man&amp;rdquo; didn&amp;rsquo;t pass the lips of any of the speakers (although they might have updated it to &amp;ldquo;Renaissance person&amp;rdquo;), the figure of the free-thinking polymath was a definite spectre in the room. John Ellis, the renowned theoretical particle physicist, called for a more meaningful exchange of ideas and collaboration between disciplines. He pointed out that the experimental techniques he uses to test his ideas within the field of fundamental physics could fruitfully be applied to climate science. While it&amp;rsquo;s possible, he said, to get small pots of money for this kind of work, securing funding for such projects in the longer term is disappointingly difficult.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;"Interdisciplinarity" is a term that is readily bandied about these days, but as the philosopher Sophie Scott-Brown remarked, we "need to pay more attention to what it actually means." She said this could be anything from bringing academics from different departments together to &amp;ldquo;sit around the same table&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;melting down the barriers&amp;rdquo; between disciplines. She is strongly in favour of the latter, envisioning a transformative shift towards a more creative, &amp;ldquo;inquiry-led&amp;rdquo; approach. Taking up John Ellis&amp;rsquo; point, dynamic and complex problems like the climate crisis, or the future of global security, could be tackled with the inventiveness required through putting more emphasis on bringing people together on the basis of what knowledge and skills they might bring to the challenge, whatever their field.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;But this isn't only a question of transforming our approach to learning and research. The trend towards specialisation is tightly linked today with the pressure on universities to adopt business practices and become increasingly self-sufficient, in the light of severe government cuts. The incentive to meet targets, the pressure to secure funding, and the fierce competition for students all serve to create an environment in which, in Scott-Brown's words, ideas are pumped out as "products". Meanwhile, the kind of open-ended inquiry that so often produces new discoveries is hampered by the need to justify the research in advance. &amp;ldquo;Most of my colleagues have to be 99 per cent sure about what they&amp;rsquo;re writing before putting forward a funding application.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;It's interesting that the most concrete idea came from the non-academic on the panel. The journalist David Aaronovitch made an impassioned plea to &amp;ldquo;abolish the A-level&amp;rdquo;, arguing that this would change the culture of learning that runs from school into universities. He claimed that every single British government had done a report on the A-level and found it to be wanting, but that there was a stubborn belief that specialisation is what makes the English system exceptional. He advocated switching to the International Baccalaureate (IB). The United States has the largest number of IB programmes, in both private and state schools, and he suggested that we take some lessons from the American approach, where university degrees are also four years, instead of three, and place more emphasis on students studying a wider breadth of subjects.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Aaronovitch disagreed that our society is suffering from a lack of new big ideas, however. Following the two "isms" of the 20th century (communism and fascism), we now have a distrust of them which is perfectly healthy, he argued. We can see this plainly from the much more recent example of Prime Minister Truss&amp;rsquo; mini-budget, which is deeply &amp;ldquo;ideological&amp;rdquo; and has been a "failure". With big questions like how do we get to net zero, he said, "I'm happy to be more pragmatic."&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;Whether in pursuit of bold new theories, or working on practical solutions, there is hope when it comes to bringing people together. John Ellis praised the inclusion of more women and people of colour in the research community, and the way in which technology was creating a more level playing field when it came to participating in scientific debate. &amp;ldquo;And here I am,&amp;rdquo; he joked, &amp;ldquo;in a philosophy debate, while two other debates are going on about my own field of science.&amp;rdquo; HowTheLightGetsIn is one of the spaces where philosophers and scientists in particular benefit from coming together. &amp;ldquo;This is us forming the new society,&amp;rdquo; Scott-Brown said.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;But the festival happens twice a year, a drop in the ocean. For the spirit of a New Renaissance to take hold, changes would be needed on many levels: cultural, political and economic. It's certain that we need creativity and invention in order to meet the confluence of crises facing Britain today. While our current Prime Minister may indeed have outlined a consistent ideological position, her ideas are explicitly rooted in Thatcherism. It seems likely that a failure to generate new big ideas appropriate to the particular challenges Britain faces today will only lead to a dangerous re-hashing of the old. We know that our intellectual climate is fed by many sources, but the health of the academy, along with our education system as a whole, is surely the bedrock of the edifice. Interdisciplinarity will be key to renewal, but any transformation will need to start by treating universities not as businesses within the higher education market, but as spaces of learning, sharing and discovery.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;More details on HowTheLightGetsIn, the world's largest ideas and music festival, can be found &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/london"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those of you who couldn't be with us in person, all the debates and talks from the festival will gradually be released online in the coming months on the Institute of Art and Ideas online platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=London2022&amp;amp;utm_id=Partner"&gt;IAI.TV&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6034/time-for-a-new-renaissance#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-10-04T10:56:56Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-04T10:56:56Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION OCTOBER 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/10/open-discussion-october-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978431</id>
    <published>2022-10-01T09:44:17Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-01T09:44:17Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Seeds of Freethought Sprouting Around the World</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/09/seeds-of-freethought-sprouting-around-the-world/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! If the study of evolution teaches us anything, it’s that change takes time. Whether it’s the natural evolution of flight or human-made technological advances, it’s a long, complex process that comes from an accumulation of small things, rather than a single quantum leap. There are, however, several …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978421</id>
    <published>2022-09-23T17:08:14Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-23T17:08:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CFI: Secular Rescue – Saving Freedom, Saving Lives</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/09/978409/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supporter, “I’m just waiting for my physical death. I have no one to help me.” This was the plea to Secular Rescue from an ex-Muslim journalist, rights activist, and founder of a civil society group in Afghanistan. When I first learned about this case, Pasoon [an alias] was struggling to survive, living off the remnants …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978409</id>
    <published>2022-09-13T16:19:43Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-13T16:19:43Z</updated>
    <category term="Featured"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION SEPTEMBER 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/09/open-discussion-september-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978405</id>
    <published>2022-09-01T06:51:49Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-01T06:51:49Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
