<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-08-08T12:06:33Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>I am an AI training module</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/08/07/i-am-an-ai-training-module/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen-150x126.png" alt="" width="150" height="126" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70890" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen-150x126.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen-300x252.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen-768x645.png 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen-500x420.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/zoom-screen.png 1060w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I’m trying to plan some alternative teaching options for the Fall, since I might be temporarily incapacitated for a bit — I’m waiting on a call from podiatrist right now, which might define some of my limitations. One of the obvious fall-back strategies would be to do some lectures remotely, since we’re all well-trained on using Zoom nowadays. Except that now I learn <a href="https://www.webpronews.com/zoom-updates-terms-to-use-customer-data-for-ai-training-with-no-opt-out/">Zoom wants to use us</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Zoom has rolled out a controversial update to its terms of service, adding a clause that allows it to use customer data for AI and ML training.</p>
<p>The pertinent clause is quoted below:</p>
<blockquote class="creationist">
<p>You consent to Zoom’s access, use, collection, creation, modification, distribution, processing, sharing, maintenance, and storage of Service Generated Data for any purpose, to the extent and in the manner permitted under applicable Law, including for the purpose of product and service development, marketing, analytics, quality assurance, <strong>machine learning or artificial intelligence (including for the purposes of training and tuning of algorithms and models)</strong>, training, testing, improvement of the Services, Software, or Zoom’s other products, services, and software, or any combination thereof, and as otherwise provided in this Agreement. In furtherance of the foregoing, if, for any reason, there are any rights in such Service Generated Data which do not accrue to Zoom under this Section 10.2 or as otherwise provided in this Agreement, you hereby unconditionally and irrevocably assign and agree to assign to Zoom on your behalf, and you shall cause your End Users to unconditionally and irrevocably assign and agree to assign to Zoom, all right, title, and interest in and to the Service Generated Data, including all Proprietary Rights relating thereto.
</p>
</blockquote>
</blockquote>
<p>Those bastards. This is a sneaky way of violating privacy, confidentiality, and our ownership of classroom content. If they announced that my lectures could be lifted wholesale and sold for use by anyone else, that would be less of a violation than this. They figure they could use a computer proxy to take all that content, massage it, refilter it, and then distribute it without attribution in the guise of AI — no one will be able to blame or credit me as a source, which is an essential part of the way science works.</p>
<p>They’ll also be able to steal my students’ contributions, although mostly they’re all silent black rectangles on the screen. They will chime in with good stuff now and then, though, all of it to be grist for the AI machine.</p>
<p>Also, people use Zoom for business meetings, where real money is at stake. I wonder how they’re going to take to the idea of a digital spy lurking in the background?</p>
<p>Or how about medical consultations? Are those to be AI fodder, too?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’m trying to plan some alternative teaching options for the Fall, since I might be temporarily incapacitated for a bit — I’m waiting on a call from podiatrist right now, which might define some of my limitations. One of the obvious fall-back strategies would be to do some lectures remotely, since we’re all well-trained on […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70889</id>
    <published>2023-08-07T13:52:58Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-07T13:52:58Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Another racist outed, time to follow the threads to his promoters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/08/07/another-racist-outed-time-to-follow-the-threads-to-his-promoters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/Richard_Hanania.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/Richard_Hanania-141x150.png" alt="" width="141" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70883" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/Richard_Hanania-141x150.png 141w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/Richard_Hanania-282x300.png 282w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/Richard_Hanania.png 366w" sizes="(max-width: 141px) 100vw, 141px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I hadn’t heard of this guy, Richard Hanania, until recently — but I sure was familiar with his old pseudonym, Richard Hoste. He was one of the more hateful, obnoxious, stupid racists who was busy stuffing the internet with lies a decade ago. Now I learn, in <a href="https://www.huffpost.com/entry/richard-hanania-white-supremacist-pseudonym-richard-hoste_n_64c93928e4b021e2f295e817">one of the most thorough, devastating journalistic takedowns I’ve ever read</a> that Hoste and Hanania were one and the same, and that he’s broken into the mainstream with the complicity of conservative billionaires.</p>
<blockquote><p>A prominent conservative writer, lionized by Silicon Valley billionaires and a U.S. senator, used a pen name for years to write for white supremacist publications and was a formative voice during the rise of the racist “alt-right,” according to a new HuffPost investigation.</p>
<p>Richard Hanania, a visiting scholar at the University of Texas, used the pen name “Richard Hoste” in the early 2010s to write articles where he identified himself as a “race realist.” He expressed support for eugenics and the forced sterilization of “low IQ” people, who he argued were most often Black. He opposed “miscegenation” and “race-mixing.” And once, while arguing that Black people cannot govern themselves, he cited the neo-Nazi author of “The Turner Diaries,” the infamous novel that celebrates a future race war.</p>
<p>A decade later, writing under his real name, Hanania has ensconced himself in the national mainstream media, writing op-eds in the country’s biggest papers, bending the ears of some of the world’s wealthiest men and lecturing at prestigious universities, all while keeping his past white supremacist writings under wraps.</p></blockquote>
<p>I remember Hoste, because I’ve long kept half an eye on nasty little websites like Taki’s Magazine, The Unz Review, VDARE, the Occidental Observer, and anything linked to the Pioneer Fund. These are the places some of the most openly racist people, like <a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Richard_Spencer">Richard Spencer</a> or <a href="https://rationalwiki.org/wiki/Steve_Sailer">Steve Sailer</a>, let it all hang out nakedly. I’ve always marveled at how they can write such vile, repugnant articles in their safe little hugboxes full of racists, and then walk out in public without shame, even to friendly appreciation from notable academics. It’s one of the tells I recognize for closet racists — <a href="https://www.mcclernan.com/2018/01/steven-pinker-and-steve-sailer.html">people who praise Sailer</a>, for instance, are the kind of slimeballs who read VDARE approvingly, even if they’d never dare to write such things themselves.</p>
<p>Now I’m going to have to add <a href="https://twitter.com/maggiekb1/status/1688512939530358784">“following Richard Hanania” as another marker for the shy racists</a>.</p>
<p>You’re on notice, guys. Scuttle for the kitchen cabinets as fast as you can, the light has been turned on.</p>
<p>Anyway, a major data leak from Disqus has exposed Hanania’s history, and it’s interesting to see how a low-life troll mainstreamed himself and started grabbing attention and money from more respectable venues. First, he dropped the pseudonym and was writing under his real name, Hanania. Then he started writing somewhat less inflammatory, but still crackling with racism, op-eds and articles that he’d submit to big-name sites, where he’d get picked up by sympathetic editors (they’re everywhere). It also helps to cozy up to rich white people, many of whom already share his views.</p>
<blockquote><p>The 37-year-old has been published by The New York Times and The Washington Post. He delivered a lecture to the Yale Federalist Society and was interviewed by the Harvard College Economics Review. He appeared twice on “Tucker Carlson Tonight,” Fox News’ former prime-time juggernaut. He was a recent guest on a podcast hosted by the CEO of Substack, the $650 million publishing platform where Hanania has nearly 20,000 subscribers.</p>
<p>Hanania has his own podcast, too, interviewing the likes of Steven Pinker, the famous Harvard cognitive psychologist, and Marc Andreessen, the billionaire software engineer. Another billionaire, Elon Musk, reads Hanania’s articles and replies approvingly to his tweets. A third billionaire, Peter Thiel, provided a blurb to promote Hanania’s book, “The Origins of Woke,” which HarperCollins plans to publish this September. In October, Hanania is scheduled to deliver a lecture at Stanford.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, rich benefactors, some of whose identities are unknown, have funneled hundreds of thousands of dollars into a think tank run by Hanania. The think tank doles out cash to conservative academics, and produces political studies that are cited across right-wing media.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yes, he has a “think tank,” a term that is long past its past-due date. Hanania’s is called the Center for the Study of Partisanship and Ideology. It’s run out of his house, and mainly seems to be a drop-box for donations that pay his substantial salary. The function of CSPI is…</p>
<blockquote><p>In addition to being a laundering service for handing out money to reactionary academics, it is a paper mill for “studies” that back up reactionary talking points, to be spun into articles and opinion pieces with headlines such as “Social trends causing rapid growth in people identifying as LGBT, report says” (from the ideological astroturfing Sinclair Broadcast Group), “The Lockdowns Weren’t Worth It” (WSJ) and “The new class war is over identity” (Washington Examiner) — the latter being an anti-LGBTQ screed that ended, “My name is Dominic. I’m a trans woman, and my pronouns are me, me, me.”</p></blockquote>
<p>It’s a profitable gig, collecting donations from insufferable rich Republicans and shuffling it into bad publications that pollute the body politic, but there’s no “thinking” involved in a think-tank. But it paid off for Hanania! He could use that illusion of serious scholarship to work his way up the grifter’s ladder.</p>
<blockquote><p>Hanania was making a name for himself. By 2022, he was selected as a visiting scholar at the Salem Center at the University of Texas at Austin. The center — funded through right-wing donors including billionaire Harlan Crow — is led by executive director Carlos Carvalho. “I have no comment,” Carvalho told HuffPost when asked about Hanania.</p>
<p>Hanania was also tapped to be a lecturer for the “Forbidden Courses” program at the University of Austin, the unaccredited school funded by venture capitalists and founded by former New York Times columnist Bari Weiss, now a prominent right-wing influencer herself. The university did not respond to a request for comment about Hanania.</p>
<p>Earlier this year, Hanania spoke to the Yale Federalist Society, the school’s chapter of the conservative legal organization, about what the government has done to “discriminate against whites and men.” The chapter did not respond when asked for comment.</p>
<p>And this October, Hanania is scheduled to teach a seminar at Stanford University’s Graduate School of Business. The school did not respond to HuffPost’s request for comment.</p></blockquote>
<p>He may be dropping a few rungs off that ladder, though. <a href="https://www.semafor.com/newsletter/08/06/2023/new-york-times-is-investigating-its-baghdad-bureau-chief">Bari Weiss has said she didn’t know him and wouldn’t have hired him if she had</a>. Oops.</p>
<blockquote><p>The University of Austin, founded by a group including Bari Weiss in reaction to progressive campus culture and promising freer speech, has drawn a line at the right-wing writer Richard Hanania, after HuffPost revealed that he’d written in favor of eugenics and racism under a pseudonym.</p>
<p>“Richard Hanania has no affiliation with UATX. He was invited once as a speaker. Like many other institutions, we were completely unaware of his pseudonymous, racist writings. Had we known, we would not have invited him,” a spokesman, Hillel Ofek, told Semafor in an email.</p></blockquote>
<p>His invitations to speak at the Federalist Society probably still stand — they eat up the racist white nationalist stuff there. He’s probably going to face some opposition at Stanford, I hope, but you never know. Apologists for hate seem to have infiltrated many higher levels of society. You don’t have to worry about Hanania’s prospects, he was already gearing up to jump to a new grift.</p>
<blockquote><p>Hanania mentioned all of these men [Andreesen, Sacks, Ramaswamy, Thiel] in a June Substack post while describing what he celebrated as the “Tech Right,” a new Silicon Valley-based conservative movement that, among other beliefs, embraces transhumanism and “longtermism.”</p>
<p>The cult of “longtermism” has swept through Silicon Valley in recent years, with Musk and Thiel among its most well-known acolytes. It’s a worldview that often prioritizes the health of future generations of humans — even ones millions of years hence — over people currently living in the here and now, suffering and getting by on planet Earth. (Musk’s goal to colonize Mars, for example, is a longtermist project.)</p>
<p>Its adherents are often obsessed with IQ scores and scientific racism, and the famous computer scientist Timnit Gebru has criticized longtermism as “eugenics under a different name.”</p>
<p>The scholar Émile Torres has also noted that longtermism’s “transhumanist vision of creating a superior new race of ‘posthumans’ is eugenics on steroids,” a recapitulation of 20th-century beliefs that ushered in “a wide range of illiberal policies, including restrictions on immigration, anti-miscegenation laws and forced sterilizations.”</p>
<p>It’s maybe unsurprising, then, that Hanania has emerged as a scribe for this new “Tech Right.” After all, he had years of practice writing about eugenics as Richard Hoste, advocating for precisely those types of policies.</p>
<p>“The maintenance of the quality of the population requires not just a stable population at all levels but the active weeding out of the unfit,” Hoste wrote in 2011 for Counter-Currents, the white supremacist site.</p>
<p>“There is no rational reason,” he wrote, “why eugenics can’t capture the hearts and minds of policy makers the way it did 100 years ago.”</p></blockquote>
<p>New grift, same as the old grift.</p>
<p>The rational reason to reject eugenics is, of course, that we know where it led when it captured “the hearts and minds of policy makers” over a century ago: to suffering and death and a world where an asshole like Hanania can thrive.</p>
<hr/>
<p>P.S. I neglected to mention that another important rung on the racist grift ladder is publishing in Quillette. You will not be surprised to learn that <a href="https://twitter.com/DialecticBio/status/1688539305575370752">Claire Lehman, the creepy mastermind behind Quillette, still supports Hanania</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I hadn’t heard of this guy, Richard Hanania, until recently — but I sure was familiar with his old pseudonym, Richard Hoste. He was one of the more hateful, obnoxious, stupid racists who was busy stuffing the internet with lies a decade ago. Now I learn, in one of the most thorough, devastating journalistic takedowns […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70882</id>
    <published>2023-08-07T13:13:43Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-07T13:13:43Z</updated>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Did you think my personal medical saga was on the mend?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/08/06/did-you-think-my-personal-medical-saga-was-on-the-mend/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/mtn-dew.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/mtn-dew-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70880" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/mtn-dew-150x150.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/mtn-dew-300x300.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/mtn-dew.jpg 474w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Ha ha, fooled you. I’ve been getting steadily worse. My ankle is totally fucked up, my whole foot is swelling like a balloon, and to top it all off, the problems are spreading to my knee. I’ve been reduced to lying immobile hoping some random twitch doesn’t trigger spasms of pain.</p>
<p>Last night was the worst. I’m trying to find a position I can sleep in, rearranging limbs and whimpering pathetically at every twinge, when Mary suggests we go to the ER. “No,” I whined. “I have to man up and deal with this in my manly masculine stupid way. I can’t admit that I can’t deal with this!”</p>
<p>Around 2am I turned to her and said “I can’t deal with this. Take me to the ER, please,” and she did.</p>
<p>So I was shortly stretched out on a table and a nurse was sticking an IV in, and then the Dilaudid flowed. O Sweet Relief! Then another liter or three of blood was extracted to pay for it, and I got lots of blood tests (which came back mostly normal). We’ve got to figure out what was going on, so there were a great many needle sticks as the doctor tried to draw fluids out of my joints, both the ankle and the knee. He succeeded, and slurped about 75mL of Mtn Dew out of me.</p>
<p>If I installed a tap in my knee, I could apparently get free Mtn Dew* at will.</p>
<p>The fluids have all been sent up to a lab in Alexandria. They’re to see if I’ve got an infection, or weird sharp crystals in solution damaging the tissues. He didn’t think it was an infection, and my uric acid results were normal, so he’s just being thorough. It’s time for some thoroughness here.</p>
<p>It’s also time for some pain management. I’m now on NORCON every four hours, for the next 5 days, and prednisone once a day for the same days. I’ve been on this before, and know what to expect: insomnia, diffuse anger at everything, and a wobbly, semi-drunken perspective on the world. So I’ll be ready to blog, in other words.</p>
<p>I’m also aware that I’m getting a few opioid doses here. There have been limits set on their use, and I’ll respect them. These things are scary. I’m just hoping I get an effective treatment <em>before I have to stop taking the potent drugs.</em></p>
<p>I’m meeting a podiatrist tomorrow, and what will then follow is a solid plan of treatment. For now, it looks mainly like wearing the horrible boot and confinement to my house, where Mary will wait on me hand and foot. Maybe I should order a <a href="https://amzn.to/44Y9zF5">little silver bell from Amazon</a>? Yeah, no, I don’t want to take her for granted.</p>
<p>*Warm, flat Mtn Dew that mainly tastes of salt. Maybe PepsiCo should think of a new flavor, <i>Mtn Dew Synovial Goo</i>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ha ha, fooled you. I’ve been getting steadily worse. My ankle is totally fucked up, my whole foot is swelling like a balloon, and to top it all off, the problems are spreading to my knee. I’ve been reduced to lying immobile hoping some random twitch doesn’t trigger spasms of pain. Last night was the […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70879</id>
    <published>2023-08-06T14:45:53Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-06T14:45:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>That’s Texas logic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/08/05/thats-texas-logic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz-150x104.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="104" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70877" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz-150x104.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz-300x208.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz-768x532.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz-500x346.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/library-destroyed-by-the-blitz.jpeg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">A new announcement from <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2023/jul/29/houston-school-district-libraries-book">the Holy Republic of Texas</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The largest school district in Texas announced its libraries will be eliminated and replaced with discipline centers in the new school year.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yep. They’re shutting down the school libraries. And what, you may wonder, is a “discipline center”? It’s where you send the troublemaking students to get them out of your hair.</p>
<blockquote><p>Teachers at these schools will soon have the option to send misbehaving students to these discipline centers, or “team centers’” – designated areas where they will continue to learn remotely.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is getting worse and worse. Now you might be curious about what has prompted this sudden decision to eliminate libraries and turn them into detention camps? It’s Texas, so it could just be cussedness and a love of ignorance. But no, they have a specific excuse.</p>
<blockquote><p>News of the library removals comes after the state announced it would be taking over the district, effective in the 2023-24 school year, due to poor academic performance. Miles was appointed by the the Texas Education Agency in June.</p></blockquote>
<p>That’s Texas logic. You’ve got a school system with poor academic performance, so you step in to improve it by preventing the kids from reading books.</p>
<p>Think it will work?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A new announcement from the Holy Republic of Texas: The largest school district in Texas announced its libraries will be eliminated and replaced with discipline centers in the new school year. Yep. They’re shutting down the school libraries. And what, you may wonder, is a “discipline center”? It’s where you send the troublemaking students to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70876</id>
    <published>2023-08-05T20:51:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-05T20:51:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Jeffrey Epstein’s legacy</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/08/04/jeffrey-epsteins-legacy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black-150x115.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="115" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70873" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black-150x115.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black-300x230.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black-768x588.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black-500x383.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/08/leon-black.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">It lives! So what if Epstein is dead, he was just a symptom of a whole slimy vein of rot.</p>
<p>One of his successors is <a href="https://theintercept.com/2023/08/03/kyrsten-sinema-private-equity-donors-jeffrey-epstein/">Leon Black, another billionaire and good buddy to Jeffrey</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Now Black is back in the headlines, this time accused of raping a 16-year-old girl in the home of Jeffrey Epstein, a serial sex trafficker Black financed with more than $150 million.</p></blockquote>
<p>Is anyone surprised? The poison spreads. It spreads further. It turns out Black and his private equity cronies have bought a politician, Kyrsten Sinema. Are you surprised yet?</p>
<blockquote><p>In 2018, Black and his wife together made a $5,400 donation to Sinema’s campaign, the maximum legal contribution at the time. Three years later, Black was out from the top post at Apollo Global Management, the firm he helped found, after it was revealed that he paid the disgraced financier Epstein more than $150 million for estate planning and tax services. The Senate Finance Committee is currently investigating that payment and whether it involved tax evasion.</p>
<p>During her 2018 bid, Sinema received a smattering of donations from others in the private equity world, including a few dozen senior Blackstone managers, Bain executives, and Goldman Sachs financiers, but she received much more money through the Emily’s List political action committee and from Google employees.</p></blockquote>
<p>This whole story is about tawdry corruption and the oddly insulated world of the very rich. One of the main threads connecting everything, though, is Harvard. Harvard isn’t an educational institution anymore, it’s the prestigious locus of every pretentious wanna-be and nouveaux riche moneybags who wants to buy credibility…and unfortunately, Harvard knows this and is happy to sell out. <a href="https://www.thenation.com/article/society/jeffrey-epstein-harvard-summers/">It’s what they do</a>, and they simultaneously attracted grifters like Epstein and exploited them in a hideous symbiotic relationship.</p>
<blockquote><p>As the steady drip of revelations over the past few months shows, Jeffrey Epstein’s ties to intellectual, cultural, and financial luminaries were much more extensive than previously known. For years after Epstein pleaded guilty in 2008 to soliciting and procuring a minor for prostitution, he socialized with Bill Gates, Woody Allen, Noam Chomsky, Leon Botstein, former Israeli prime minister Ehud Barak, private equity billionaire Leon Black, LinkedIn cofounder Reid Hoffman, CIA director William Burns, and Lawrence Summers.</p>
<p>According to a recent report in The Wall Street Journal, Summers—a former president of Harvard and the current Charles W. Eliot University Professor and director of the Mossavar-Rahmani Center for Business and Government at the Harvard Kennedy School—had more than a dozen meetings scheduled with Epstein from 2013 to 2016. In April 2014, Summers sent Epstein an e-mail seeking “small scale philanthropy advice” regarding his wife, Elisa New, a professor of English at Harvard. “My life will be better if i raise $1m for Lisa,” he wrote. “Mostly it will go to make a pbs series and for teacher training. Ideas?”</p></blockquote>
<p>“Small scale.” She wanted to make videos about poetry, which is nice, but most of us wouldn’t even dream of getting a million dollars for that sort of thing. But if you know a criminal who wants to whitewash his reputation and suck up to a famous university, you can find a way.</p>
<blockquote><p>The Summers-Epstein relationship opens a window into the interlocking of intellectual and financial elites in our era of bloated capital accumulation. The perks and privileges that the superrich can offer make their company and resources hard to resist. Top universities, in turn, entice the tycoon class with a mix of academic prestige, intellectual stimulation, and social legitimation. And no university has more to offer in this regard than Harvard. The school has come to have a mesmerizing effect on the American public, especially its most mercantile tier, for which it is a honeypot.</p></blockquote>
<p>Harvard is going to have a tough time buying their way out of the strikes against their reputation in the last few decades. I know if I had a grandchild applying to callege, I’d strongly discourage them from considering Harvard. I’d consider Harvard on a CV to be a detriment, but then, I’m not a billionaire with ties to the financial industry who thinks schmoozing with other rich people is more important than an actual education.</p>
<p>Right now, I mainly follow news from Harvard for the scandals. <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/harvard-professor-raking-over-1-162755528.html?guccounter=1">Like this one</a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>On June 16, Harvard Business School put one of its most celebrated professors on leave after an internal investigation into accusations that she had falsified her research. Francesca Gino was a popular behavioral scientist who was known for prolific publishing and a schedule packed with speaking gigs and expensive corporate trainings. Harvard paid her over $1 million a year while companies paid tens of thousands more to book her for their private events.</p>
<p>Gino’s record of publishing over 10 journal articles a year, in contrast to the faculty average two or three, seemed too good to be true—and as is now coming to light, it may have been. A four-part investigation by the independent academic watchdog site Data Colada alleges that Gino fabricated some of her high-profile research over at least a decade and as recently as three years ago. It claims to have found at least four times that data in her studies were manipulated. The watchdog believes it is likely that Gino carried out the alleged fraud without assistance from her collaborators.</p></blockquote>
<p>OK, Harvard Business School is kind of the lowest cesspit of a tainted brand, but a professor getting paid a <em>million dollars a year is already suspicious. What, you may wonder, does she study that warrants that kind of salary? She studies dishonesty in business, ironically enough. She’s an advocate for being a rebel and breaking the rules, so you can see already why this would appeal to corporate executives.</em></p>
<p>Anyway, don’t go to Harvard unless you dream of one day being a willing enabler of the extremes of capitalism.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It lives! So what if Epstein is dead, he was just a symptom of a whole slimy vein of rot. One of his successors is Leon Black, another billionaire and good buddy to Jeffrey. Now Black is back in the headlines, this time accused of raping a 16-year-old girl in the home of Jeffrey Epstein, […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70872</id>
    <published>2023-08-04T17:29:13Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-04T17:29:13Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A million Britons are at risk of disenfranchisement at the next general election</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6152/a-million-britons-are-at-risk-of-disenfranchisement-at-the-next-general-election#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/red-dot-Q98X_JVRGS0-unsplash-_1_.jpg" height="1440" alt="Polling station" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The local election in May was the first UK election to implement new regulations that require voters to show a photo ID. Fears that this requirement would prevent some people from voting &amp;ndash; weakening British democracy and risking the disenfranchisement of marginalised groups &amp;ndash; were confirmed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Electoral Commission&amp;rsquo;s full report is expected in September, but its interim report published in June revealed that nearly 14,000 people were denied a vote (the Commission noted that these figures are likely an underestimation). Roughly 0.7 per cent of people were initially turned away from stations for not having an admissible form of identification, such as a passport, driving licence or voter certificate. Most of those people returned later with the correct ID and were able to vote but there were still at least 0.25 per cent who tried to and could not.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What is harder to measure is how many people simply stayed at home on the day because they did not possess the right form of ID, and how many turned back before they reached the ballot-issuing desk &amp;ndash; some polling stations warned people at the entrance about the requirement and the number of voters leaving at this point was not recorded. As a result, we will likely never know the full impact.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Due to electoral rules, it was not possible to collect comprehensive demographic data. But a small survey carried out by the Electoral Commission suggested that &amp;ldquo;some people found it harder than others to show accepted voter ID, including disabled people and the unemployed.&amp;rdquo; This appears to confirm concerns that the new regulations would have the gravest effect on people already marginalised and therefore less likely to have the correct ID, including ethnic minorities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Photo ID has already been required in Northern Ireland for two decades. Toby James, a professor of politics and public policy at the University of East Anglia, told MPs that about 2.3 per cent of the electorate failed to vote in the first Northern Ireland assembly election following the introduction of the requirements as a direct consequence, and that it would be reasonable to expect a similar figure across the UK. If accurate, that will mean the voices of 1.1 million people who want to have a say on our next government will go unheard because of the rule.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The justification for voter ID requirements is that they will prevent people voting in somebody else&amp;rsquo;s name at polling stations &amp;ndash; an offence known as &amp;ldquo;personation&amp;rdquo;. Yet this justification does not stand up to scrutiny. In 2019 there were just two allegations of personation at polling stations that resulted in cautions or convictions, out of 58 million votes cast in the UK that year.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That gives rise to the question of the true motivation. Given the groups most affected, critics see a cynical attempt by the Conservative government to disenfranchise voters who might be less inclined to support them. In an extraordinary statement at the National Conservatism conference in May, former cabinet minister Jacob Rees-Mogg appeared to admit as much &amp;ndash; though he noted that the ploy may have backfired.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Parties that try and gerrymander end up finding their clever scheme comes back to bite them, as, dare I say, we found by insisting on voter ID for elections,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;We found the people who didn&amp;rsquo;t have ID were elderly and they, by and large, voted Conservative, so we made it hard for our own voters and we upset a system that worked perfectly well.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Elections need to be secure, but they also need to be as accessible as possible. At best, the voter ID requirement weakens our democracy without adequate justification. At worst, it is a profoundly undemocratic attempt at voter suppression. Whichever it is, the outcome is the same: Hundreds of thousands of people are at risk of disenfranchisement at the next general election.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;This article is a preview from New Humanist's autumn 2023 issue. Subscribe now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6152/a-million-britons-are-at-risk-of-disenfranchisement-at-the-next-general-election#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-08-03T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-03T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION AUGUST 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/08/open-discussion-august-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978567</id>
    <published>2023-08-01T08:04:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-01T08:04:00Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How industrial farming is destroying the Earth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6150/how-industrial-farming-is-destroying-the-earth#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/PL_RD-1-_1_.jpg" alt="Philip Lymbery feeds pigs"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Philip &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Lymbery&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; is the CEO of Compassion &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;In&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; World Farming&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and a veteran campaigner on animal welfare issues, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;wildlife&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and the environment.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; His &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;books include &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SpellingErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Farmageddon&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;: The True Cost of Cheap Meat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and, most recently,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Si&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;xty Harv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ests Left: How &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;To&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; Reach &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; Nature-Friendly Future&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;, both published by Bloomsbury&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;Y&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;our new book &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;argues that we n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0" data-contrast="none"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;eed to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;move away from industrial farming and towards &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;regenerative &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;farming methods&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt; &amp;ndash; such as rotating crops, minimising the ploughing of soil and using manure and compost instead of fertiliser &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;o&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;enable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt; soil regeneration.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;Why is this &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;so &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW262643341 BCX0"&gt;important?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The food system &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;can&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; go on as it currently is. If we continue with industrial &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;agriculture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; then the very &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;thing&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; we need &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;for the production of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; most of our food &amp;ndash; the soil &amp;ndash; will be gone within a single human lifetime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; [because industrial farming techniques are depleting healthy &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;soils&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; a frightening prospect.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;..&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Industrial agriculture needs to end. It is providing us with an illusion of cheap and plentiful food today but is creating the conditions for&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; catastrophe tomorrow.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why is healthy soil so important?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Soil does three &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;really important&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; things. It not only produces 95 per cent of our food but &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; also pretty much the only thing which stops rainwater from simply running into rivers and back out to sea. It holds &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;rainwater&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; against gravity for our thirsty plants. Healthy soil does that; impoverished soil &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and is susceptible to flash flooding and to drought. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;S&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;oil is also a massive carbon &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;sink. It hol&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ds &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;nearly twice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; as much carbon as there is in the atmos&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;phere. B&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ut the &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;bad news&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; is, beca&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;use o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;f the way &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;we&amp;rsquo;r&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; tr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;eating it, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; releasing that carbon back, making climate chan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ge&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; even worse. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;So&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; if we want to carry on producing food, if we want to harness water for the future and if we want to tackle clima&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;te chan&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ge &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;then &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;there&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; a &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;really &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;straightforward&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; way of doing that, and that is to get behind soil health and move away from industrial agriculture.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Has any good come from&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; the developments of&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; in&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;dustrial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; farming?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Ind&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;us&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;trial agriculture came about&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; in the middle of the last century off the back of the Second World War&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;uge &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;bumper&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; crops&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; that grain became so &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;chea&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;p&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ubiquitous&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; that you m&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ay&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; as well just feed it to &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;animals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;, a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;nd then we started to keep the animals in confinement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;his whole cycle of feeding grain to animals, the animals then convert it to meat, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;milk&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and eggs &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;really inefficiently&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;, so that most of the food value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; in terms of calories and protein is lost in that conversion &amp;ndash; that came about as a space-saving idea, as a way of creating more food. But &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; come at a big &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;price&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; had unintended c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;onsequences.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;..&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; Now that we know about them, we need to deal with them...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;T&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;he great news is that there are life-affirming, beautiful, compassionate solutions at hand to help us get t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;here&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;So&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;[that means] &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;moving from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;industrial&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;agriculture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; to regen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;erative&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; farming and at the same tim&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; reining in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;our&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;diets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;o that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;e&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;not eating &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;h&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;e&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;planet by consuming way too much meat and dairy from farmed animals.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;.. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The way we can do that is by eating more plants and less and better meat, making sure that any meat we do have comes from regen&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;erative&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;o&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;u&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;rces&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The other great news&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; is that the portfolio of alternative proteins is now starting to grow&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &amp;ndash; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; not just plant-based &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;alternatives&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; to meat, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;we&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; also seeing the rise of cultivated meat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; from stem&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;cells grown in a bioreactor. The US Dep&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;artment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; of Agr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;iculture&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; just gave the green light to the production and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;commercial&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; sale of cultivated meat to consumers in &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;America&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;, and what happens in America quickly comes to the UK.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The other form of producing alternative proteins is through precision fermentation. This is programming microbes to produce precise molecules, specific proteins. In this way we really can create new and interesting foods that can satisfy the desire for meat but without the downsides.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Does the answer lie in innovation or going back to the basics?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; both. It &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;has to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; be both, in my view, because &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;yes&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; we do need to go back to the basics of farming... but &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;if we simply try to produce the same amount of meat [as we currently are] with regenerative methods, that will continue to take us over the edge of planetary boundaries. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;So&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; it &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;has to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; be a move to regenerative farming which boosts soil health, brings back biodiversity, satisfies animal welfare, gives us nutritionally better &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;food&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; and creates a sustainable future&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;... but at the same time reduce the amount of meat and dairy from animals that we are as a global society consuming...&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; And I think &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; an easier sell to consumers if you can replace the meat that &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;they&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; currently eating with something that has some level of equivalence.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;What would the shift to regenerative farming mean for the price of food?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;We &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;have to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; remember that food is currently produced in a distorted economic bubble. So-called &amp;ldquo;cheap&amp;rdquo; food is something we pay for three times: The first time at the checkout at the supermarket; the second through our taxes, in subsidising agriculture &amp;ndash; there are&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; billions of pounds a year going to subsidising agriculture, mostly to encourage it down the wrong path; and the third is much more significant financially, &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ou&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;r tax pounds going to clean up the mess to our health and to the environment that&amp;rsquo;s created by the so-called &amp;ldquo;cheap&amp;rdquo; food culture.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;What &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;I think we&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; need to do is to create the economic environment where we do the right thing, where we create a future for our children, we move to regenerative farming, and we make it a policy that decent food, planet-saving nutritional food, should be a basic human right. It &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;shouldn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; be somethi&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;ng that you have to be well off to afford. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Can we produce enough through regenerative farming to feed our growing population?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The answer to that is yes... &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;We currently produce enough food for more than twice the population of the planet. We just waste so much of it ... &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;The amount of grain fed to farmed animals worldwide every year represents enough food to sustain four billion people annually. Much of the food value of that grain is wasted when converted to factory farmed meat, milk and eggs, which represents the biggest single form of food waste on the planet.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Whose responsibility is it to fix this?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;It really needs leadership from the highest level, so here &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;we&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; talking about the United Nations who should be creating a global agreement to move away from industrial agriculture towards regenerative production. Governments absolutely need to create the policy and subsidy regimes that are going to be necessary to shift production and consumption patterns in the way that we need.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; Companies, too, need to come on board... A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;nd we can all seize the power of our plate three times a day by choosing to eat more plants and less and better meat.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;Are there any broader lessons we can take from &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;what we got wrong with industrial farming&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;div class="OutlineElement Ltr SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;We &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun AdvancedProofingIssueV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;have to&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; take a 360&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;degree pers&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;pective. If you look at things just through one lens &amp;ndash; just through climate, just through profit, and so on &amp;ndash; you can solve one problem but create half a dozen others. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun ContextualSpellingAndGrammarErrorV2Themed SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;So&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; we do need to take a holistic view and &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;let&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; not forget that we are part of nature, we rely on nature for the air we breathe, the water we drink and&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; the&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; food we eat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;et&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt; never see ourselves as separa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;te from it.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="Paragraph SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="TextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0" data-contrast="auto"&gt;&lt;span class="NormalTextRun SCXW44446969 BCX0"&gt;&lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;This article is a preview from New Humanist's autumn 2023 issue. Subscribe now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6150/how-industrial-farming-is-destroying-the-earth#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-08-01T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-08-01T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Every year, I forget!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6149/every-year-i-forget#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/newhumanistlaurietoast.jpg" height="687" alt="A cartoon shows Laurie Taylor popping, slightly charred, out of a toaster" width="500"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I dislike anniversaries. With the help of my Filofax I can usually manage to honour the bulk of my friends&amp;rsquo; birthdays &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;Hi Charlotte. Best wishes for your very special day. Gosh doesn&amp;rsquo;t time fly. Do give me a ring next time you&amp;rsquo;re down south&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; but I am frankly unable to pronounce with any degree of certainty upon the length of my present marriage, the exact number of years since my pacemaker was fitted or the precise date when my beloved Liverpool were last declared champions of Europe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, the week before last, when I trooped into Broadcasting House to make another edition of my BBC Radio 4 programme Thinking Allowed, I was energetically confronted by my normally cool producer. Did I know the significance of the episode we were about to make? Not really. Did the year 1998 mean anything to me? Not really. Sorry. Sorry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My producer gave me a slightly sorrowful smile. &amp;ldquo;Laurie, this is our anniversary. Our programme has now been broadcast on Radio 4 for exactly 25 years. So many great memories! Remember the social mobility programme?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;How could I forget? I knew immediately she was talking about the day, 20 years ago, when I was interviewing an expert on social mobility and noticed with alarm that he was sliding from his studio chair. In the hope that he might quickly right himself, I pursued my questioning. &amp;ldquo;Your research indicates an overall decline in social mobility&amp;rdquo;, I said, &amp;ldquo;How might you account for that?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I never got my answer because, with a little whimper, my guest slipped further sideways and then, with a little jerk, fell to the studio floor where he lay motionless amid a tangled mass of studio cables. A frantic producer hissed into my earphones. &amp;ldquo;Laurie. Laurie. Go to your emails.&amp;rdquo; Thankfully the guest was fine and in the pub afterwards we laughed ourselves silly over the incident.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But that happy memory epitomises my problem with all such anniversaries: they rarely have a singular dimension. So while it was certainly great fun to remember the day of the disappearing studio guest, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t relish the incident without also remembering that it occurred at the very time that I was desperately trying to end my unhappy relationship with Sandra, suffering from a rather nasty pubic rash, and had just been told by my dentist that the inside of my mouth resembled a blitzed housing estate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a paradox perfectly captured by Philip Larkin in his poem &amp;ldquo;Reference Back&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Truly, though our element is time,&lt;br&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re not suited to the long perspectives&lt;br&gt;Open at each instant of our lives.&lt;br&gt;They link us to our losses...&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is perhaps one surprising and positive aspect to anniversaries. They can remind us of the road not taken. Nobody captured that benefit with more fervour than my old friend Angela, who, in a tipsy conversation during her 38th wedding anniversary party, confided this insight.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Laurie&amp;rdquo;, she said, glancing across the room to her husband. &amp;ldquo;You know what this anniversary has made me realise? If I had killed Maurice the first time I thought about it, I&amp;rsquo;d have been out of jail by now.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;No such muddled memories ever interfered with my mother&amp;rsquo;s wholesale embrace of anniversaries. During my childhood, I was frequently reminded that I had been named due to the proximity of my birthday to the date of the martyrdom of Saint Laurence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In one respect, Saint Laurence deserved to be honoured. He famously gave all his money away to charity. However, as I later learned, in honouring his anniversary I would also be honouring the date in AD 258 when he was martyred on a red-hot gridiron. As the coals burned into his skin, he had the temerity to give a word of advice to his torturers. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m well done on this side. Turn me over&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For all my horror of anniversaries, I can&amp;rsquo;t stop thinking that this ancient utterance by my namesake might make a rather fine last set of words &amp;ndash; for myself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6149/every-year-i-forget#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-07-27T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-27T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Barbie movie: Is everything worthy of cultural critique?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6151/the-barbie-movie-is-everything-worthy-of-cultural-critique#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Dolls from Barbie's 'Inspiring Women' range. Credit: Mattel" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/barbie-cropped.jpg" height="479" alt="Rosa Parks, Frida Kahlo and Sally Ride in Barbie form, from Mattel's 'Inspiring Women Series'" width="747"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You never really notice how many Japanese tourists there are in central London, do you? They aren&amp;rsquo;t brutish like the Americans, and rarely go around complaining about everything like the French. They just blend into the background, quietly taking photos. But walking from Westminster to Soho in mid-July, on my way to a screening of Greta Gerwig&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt;, they were suddenly unavoidable. The problem was that I couldn&amp;rsquo;t stop thinking about the letters splashed across my chest, written in bright pink, swirly script. &amp;ldquo;Now I am become Death, the destroyer of worlds&amp;rdquo;, the T-shirt screamed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Like a dress that is too tight or heels too high, the shirt seemed like a good idea until I left the house. It was, you see, a &amp;ldquo;Barbenheimer&amp;rdquo; shirt, made to celebrate the fact that &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; was coming out on the same day as Christopher Nolan&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Oppenheimer&lt;/em&gt;, a thriller about the man who led the development of the atomic bomb. The clash of the two movies, with their incongruous combination of themes, was always bound to become a meme. Plans were hatched around the world to go see them one after the other and debates were had on which to see first &amp;ndash; including what anyone could possibly wear to fit with both themes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;All this made me laugh a lot, which is why I headed to the &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; press screening wearing what I did. I thought Greta Gerwig would approve; before she became the pet director of a multinational toy company, she worked on a series of witty indie movies. Every bit of marketing behind &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; made it seem like she was winking at us from behind a bubble gum curtain, hinting that she hadn&amp;rsquo;t lost her edge. The whole thing would be odd and meta and knowingly farcical. Of course she&amp;rsquo;d love &amp;ldquo;Barbenheimer&amp;rdquo;. But walking to the cinema I suddenly became incredibly aware of the fact that I was wearing a T-shirt openly joking about the invention of a bomb that led to the deaths of hundreds of thousands of civilians.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Once in the Cineworld I experienced a different kind of unease. As journalists, we were told to sign an embargo and made to &amp;ldquo;pinky promise&amp;rdquo; not to leak anything by an upbeat woman holding her little finger in the air. Still, we were allowed &amp;ndash; nay, encouraged! &amp;ndash; to post any positive reactions we might have on social media. Large, pink bags of complimentary popcorn were sitting on our laps. What had we got ourselves into?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The lights went out, two hours passed, and by the end I still wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure. For the avoidance of doubt, &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; is a fun movie. It is, at times, laugh-out-loud funny, Ryan Gosling&amp;rsquo;s Ken is hysterically compelling, and the many cameos never fail to delight.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The premise, if you must know, goes like this. Following a perfect day in Barbie Land, where Barbies are doctors and judges and journalists and Nobel Prize winners and presidents, and Kens are just Kens, one Barbie sinks into an existential funk. She sleeps poorly and cannot stop thinking about dying. The soles of her feet, once beautifully arched, are now stubbornly flat. There is cellulite on her thighs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Following a visit to Weird Barbie, a wise old doll who was played with so much that her hips cannot help but fall into the splits, it is concluded that a tear has opened up in the fabric of reality, caused by the connection between our Barbie and the girl playing with her being too strong. In order to stop both worlds coming to ruin, the doll must go to the real world and find out what is going on.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What follows is&amp;hellip;well, it&amp;rsquo;s a lot. At first, Mattel executives appear to be the main antagonists, wishing to put the human-sized doll back in her box. You may be shocked to hear that this doesn&amp;rsquo;t last &amp;ndash; Mattel, after all, ordered and paid for the movie. Instead, the real twist comes when Ken, who followed Barbie on her jaunt, discovers the patriarchy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Men run things in the real world! They have cars and horses! It isn&amp;rsquo;t like Barbie Land, where all they do is sit on the beach and yearn. He returns home before Barbie does and turns it into Kenland. By the time Protagonist Barbie comes back, all hell has got loose. What oh what can she and her human sidekicks do to restore the balance of the universe? You may be able to guess. It&amp;rsquo;s feminism. What else could it possibly be?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In fairness to Gerwig, she doesn&amp;rsquo;t go for the lowest hanging fruit of female empowerment. Barbies aren&amp;rsquo;t freed by being told that they can achieve anything a man can, if only they set their mind to it. Instead, their emancipation comes from a surprisingly irate speech from America Ferrera, playing the real-life mother of a teenage girl.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is impossible to be a woman, she says: the female experience in a patriarchal society is so full of contradictions that no woman can go through it without going mad. We must be assertive without being bossy; we must have money but never ask for it; we must look good but not so good that we draw too much attention to ourselves; we must run things without telling anyone what to do, and so on. In Kenland, as in any other society ruled by men, women can never win. Faced with this maddening realisation, the Barbies short-circuit and return to their old selves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Stripped of their power, the Kens begin lashing out then eventually demure. Running stuff is hard, it turns out! That&amp;rsquo;s what Gosling&amp;rsquo;s Ken tearfully tells Barbie. Because she is not in love with him, she tells him to find out who he is if he is not defined by his relationship with her. In the end, it feels worth noting that few people &amp;ndash; or dolls &amp;ndash; are truly happy, eschewing what would or should have been the conclusion of a more traditional storyline.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In short: the &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; movie really isn&amp;rsquo;t as bad as it could have been, and I should know. I spent two hours chewing on my sweet, low-cal popcorn and scrutinising it. I took notes on the risqu&amp;eacute; jokes and pondered its politics on my walk home.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But then I caught myself wondering what wave of feminism &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; felt closest to and it stopped me in my tracks. I&amp;rsquo;d gone to see a movie about a plastic doll, made by the very people who manufacture that plastic doll. What on earth was I on about?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I wondered if that is what the studio had wanted &amp;ndash; if they&amp;rsquo;d been trying to have their cake and eat it. The &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; movie is pink and saccharine and, yes, enjoyable enough that anyone, teenage or not, can turn it into a fun day out. Its producer and occasional madcap promotional work were intriguing enough that pretentious essayists like me can try to tear it apart and see if there really is anything going on underneath.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we should, though. What if the &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; movie was just that, a bit of harmless entertainment? Must everything have depth? Equally, must all mainstream pop culture be treated as deserving of pointed criticism?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Mass internet culture has flattened everything and now all movies are treated the same &amp;ndash; whether they are fantasy comedies, or heavyweights about the darkest parts of our history. I assumed I wanted to write an in-depth critique of &lt;em&gt;Barbie&lt;/em&gt; because that is what people like me &amp;ldquo;ought&amp;rdquo; to do these days. I wore a T-shirt about a movie in which a man invents a bomb that can kill millions because I thought it was hilarious that it had become tied with a silly movie about girly girls. The meme had become so powerful that there was no meaning left.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It isn&amp;rsquo;t good for us, but it is good for business. People who probably do not care about military history got memed into going to watch a movie about it, and so did people who have no particular interest in children&amp;rsquo;s toys. As far as I&amp;rsquo;m concerned, it&amp;rsquo;s mostly made me want to have an existential crisis, which is ironic because that is what makes Barbie leave Barbie Land and join the real world. Perhaps she was the lucky one. What do you do if nothing feels real in your world, but there is nowhere else you can escape to?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is a preview from the autumn 2023 issue of New Humanist. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe now&lt;/a&gt; to get it delivered to your door in August.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6151/the-barbie-movie-is-everything-worthy-of-cultural-critique#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-07-25T11:04:39Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-25T11:04:39Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why science needs intuition</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6148/why-science-needs-intuition#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Credit: Daniel J Schwarz/Unsplash" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/daniel-j-schwarz-eqzgl9kjvxi-unsplash-sq-small.jpg" height="1368" alt="Hikers on a mountainous path" width="1368"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Imagine you&amp;rsquo;re going for a hike with your friends. At a certain point on your walk, conditions turn for the worse and you realise you are lost. Whose intuition do you trust to get the group to safety? The experienced hiker or the beginner? Of course, you will turn to the former, even if they can&amp;rsquo;t fully explain why they think a certain route is safer than another.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our intuitions guide us every day. It could be as simple as forming an opinion about a new acquaintance. You might have gotten a strange feeling from them, without any discernible cause. Most of us have a vast amount of experience in social contexts &amp;ndash; and so, like the experienced hiker, we often feel justified in trusting our gut when it comes to other people.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But what does it mean, to trust your gut? Historically, intuition has often been viewed as containing an individualised or collective truth, one that emerges from a spiritual or mystical place, disconnected from anything grounded in the material world. This could lead to &amp;ldquo;intuitive&amp;rdquo; actions being seen as good and righteous, or even divinely warranted.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Even today, people often view intuition as something mysterious. Like warm mud bubbling up from a geothermal pool, it emerges from a foreign world, and is therefore often cast as something outside the natural realm. It can be very appealing to view our intuitions in this way, especially when they guide our decisions in a manner that may be convenient to our own self-interest.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But let&amp;rsquo;s return to the group lost on the hike. There&amp;rsquo;s a reason that we trust the experienced hiker. Under the hood they are likely making unconscious evaluations of different variables &amp;ndash; slope, erosion, visibility &amp;ndash; that together might make the difference between a terrible accident and a safe journey home. In a similar way, we are likely to arrive at split-second judgements about other people, through body language, facial expressions, vocal tone and eye contact, that we might not consciously perceive unless they become glaringly obvious.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Less divine inspiration, then, and more a different &lt;em&gt;kind&lt;/em&gt; of thinking.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In modern psychology, intuitive and reflective thinking have been separated and categorised a number of times: implicit vs explicit, heuristic vs systematic, automatic vs controlled, and type 1 and type 2 thinking. Essentially, these types of thinking are contrasted by how much effort we put into making a decision. For intuitive, implicit, heuristic, automatic and type 1 thinking, decisions are made instinctively, where people rely on cues and rapid judgements. Whereas with reflective, explicit, systematic, controlled and type 2 thinking, decisions are made with more conscious effort, where we might weigh positives and negatives, or take the time to evaluate the different options we are choosing from.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We now understand intuition as something that people develop over time, informed by unconscious learning and memory. As we move through the world, only a sliver of what our minds process moves through the medium of our conscious experiences. But our brains are constantly absorbing information, and generating models of the world. You could say that intuition is a way for the wisdom of our subconscious to &amp;ldquo;knock on the door&amp;rdquo; of our waking conscious experience &amp;ndash; pointing us in the right direction, or, at least, in a direction that has served us well before.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;When intuition meets science&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;If intuition were a sort of knowledge that becomes self-evident in the mind&amp;rsquo;s eye, then we would expect little to no variation in the content of people&amp;rsquo;s intuitive knowledge. But this, obviously, is not what we see. Some people might think the statement &amp;ldquo;God exists&amp;rdquo; is intuitively true, for example, while there is no shortage of people who would disagree. (It&amp;rsquo;s also interesting to note that self-defined &amp;ldquo;intuitive thinkers&amp;rdquo; are more likely to believe in God.) What we find intuitive as individuals is deeply shaped by our own nuanced experiences, and the cultural and societal belief systems in which we are embedded.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The phenomenology, or feeling, of intuition has been described by psychologists as involving a sense of coherence in the sensory signals that someone is receiving from the world, mandating a specific course of action when a reasoned path is either absent or impractical: a sense of knowing without knowing how one knows. No doubt, this strange phenomenology has pushed interpretations into spiritual waters, but this disregards the role of lived experiences and norms.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Viewing intuition as a type of skill suggests it is something that can be pragmatically applied in contexts where we have cultivated it, as in the case of the experienced hiker. But one field where intuition might seem out of place is in the practice of science. Scientists are encouraged to remove their assumptions and biases from their theories, and to let the data do the talking. Theories are developed over time, with extensive thought being invested into their limitations and strengths. But can we really discount the role of intuition in science entirely?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Carlo Rovelli, a theoretical physicist working on a theory of quantum gravity, sees intuition as a necessary creative ingredient of the scientific process. With reason and rigour alone, nobody would ever have a good idea, but without them we would never recognise anything useful. In other words, science, for Rovelli, is &amp;ldquo;the simultaneous triumph of intuition and the active limiting of intuition&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rovelli, who is the author of numerous popular science books like &lt;em&gt;The Order of Time&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Seven Brief Lessons on Physics&lt;/em&gt;, also takes intuition seriously when it comes to teaching and communication. He tells me that he tries to cultivate the skill on a daily basis. &amp;ldquo;Every morning I meet my student, we discuss &amp;lsquo;new ideas&amp;rsquo;, or &amp;lsquo;new intuitions&amp;rsquo;; that is, things we think we know but we don&amp;rsquo;t know where the idea came from. But then science is about always remembering that there is nothing we know for sure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sometimes we have to work from &amp;ldquo;feelings&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;hints&amp;rdquo;, he says, because they might give us an indication that we are headed in the right or wrong direction. &amp;ldquo;This is how we think, this is how great scientists think,&amp;rdquo; he adds. &amp;ldquo;Einstein thinks about riding a light ray, [Johannes] Kepler writes about flying through the Solar System. This is using intuition; connecting the dots courageously on the basis of analogies.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Filter, analyse, check&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;It may seem surprising that a scientist like Rovelli takes intuition so seriously. He is working in experimental quantum physics &amp;ndash; a field beyond the parameters of our direct human experience, and on the cutting edge of our understanding. Particles at extremely small scales can act in ways that are alien to our everyday experiences of how objects move and interact with one another and the world. They can spontaneously disappear and reappear, some can share information across vast distances instantaneously, and some can move straight through anything without interacting at all.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the field of quantum physics, therefore, our expectations of how things should and could behave can break down. It might even seem like a warning against giving too much weight to our intuitions when drawing conclusions about the structure of the world. For Rovelli, however, who works with this scale of reality everyday, things have started to become familiar. He&amp;rsquo;s developed an intuitive skill for predicting and describing phenomena at this level. But it has to be a process, of appealing to evidence to check to see if intuitions can really stick.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;So we have to filter, analyse, go back, check, be critical, to filter out the good products of our intuition,&amp;rdquo; Rovelli says. &amp;ldquo;Failing to do so is to be a crackpot, a useless dreamer, it is to lose the way. Humanity has done everything it has precisely because it has navigated smartly between intuition and critical thinking.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;History is filled with examples where a scientist&amp;rsquo;s intuition has taken them beyond the accepted body of knowledge and revolutionised how we understood the world. In his book &lt;em&gt;Helgoland&lt;/em&gt;, Rovelli details the intellectual journey of Werner Heisenberg in his development of quantum theory, a journey that involved stepping outside the confines of accepted thought, and following a hunch of his own.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By focusing on the subatomic quantities of particles that were observable, such as the energy an atom emits when electrons jump, Heisenberg made it possible to build a consistent theory of the atomic world. At the forefronts of human knowledge, such as in the world of quantum physics, a carefully honed sense of intuition can make the difference between a great scientist and a genius.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sara Walker is an astrobiologist from Arizona State University. For the past decade she has been working to uncover &amp;ldquo;laws of life&amp;rdquo; to help guide our search for extraterrestrial life. Recently, Walker has been developing a theory called &amp;ldquo;assembly theory&amp;rdquo;, which aims to describe the conditions where selective processes emerge and abiotic chemistry transitions into chemistry that we might call living.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Essentially, Walker is trying to build a physical theory that can describe the difference between living things and non-living things. She hopes the theory could be used as a barometer in our search for extraterrestrial life, if we encounter life that is vastly different to the types we are familiar with. She also hopes assembly theory could help identify the moment in Earth&amp;rsquo;s deep past where geochemical cycles transitioned into the first living organisms. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Walker, like Rovelli, acknowledges that we have to be careful when it comes to intuition. It&amp;rsquo;s easy to confuse it with &amp;ldquo;common sense&amp;rdquo;, she points out.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We once knew &amp;ldquo;intuitively&amp;rdquo; that the Earth was the centre of the cosmos, and that time moved in a universally linear direction. It&amp;rsquo;s easy for concepts that seem like the natural conclusion to make, based on our understanding of the world at the time, to become &amp;ldquo;deeply rooted in our psyche, and then it becomes hard for us to change the paradigm because we have been taught to accept the world as a certain way.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Jewels and garbage&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;It could be argued, then, that science is the enemy of intuition. Scientists have consistently proven our &amp;ldquo;intuitions&amp;rdquo; about the structure of the physical world to be wrong. But rather than being a mode of thinking that only leads us to drawing false conclusions about reality, intuition can help us when we step out into the unknown, where we don&amp;rsquo;t have observation and theory available to guide our decision making. It can therefore be a corrective force, one that helps us see things in a new light when we are too far down the rabbit hole.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Walker believes that making use of new intuitions is useful, even crucial, when it comes to breaking ground in relatively new fields like her own or Rovelli&amp;rsquo;s. Astrobiologists are involved in speculating about life that could be completely different to Earth-based life, stepping out into a territory that is untethered from previous models. &amp;ldquo;When you are coming up with new concepts to try to figure out fields we don&amp;rsquo;t yet understand, intuition becomes really important to help map out that foreign territory,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s relevant in astrobiology now because astrobiology has leading edge questions that we don&amp;rsquo;t fully understand.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Usually we go off our observations or historical knowledge,&amp;rdquo; she adds, &amp;ldquo;but they are obviously not always accurate. We have had inaccurate models for a long time and the whole point of science is to build a deeper, more powerful model.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While our intuition may stem from our subconscious experience of the world, its intangible nature no doubt plays a crucial role in the unfurling narrative of our attempts to understand ourselves and the world around us. It might be tempting to distance science from intuitive thinking, since our intuitions about the world are so often misguided. To admit that one of our greatest inventions &amp;ndash; the scientific method &amp;ndash; is subject to what might seem like a flash from the dark or a wandering whim could seem like an admission of epistemological frailty. Especially when we are still trying to understand the mysterious nature from which these very whims emerge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But that would be a mischaracterisation of the role that intuition can serve within science. Intuition is what humanises science, and what separates great scientists from the rest. Like the experienced hiker, scientists draw on their intuition like a skill, one that can lead them to new worlds of understanding.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It can seem like a contradiction. The correct use of intuition has been at the heart of many of the great leaps forward in the history of science. But in order for it to be useful, its limits have to be understood. As Rovelli puts it, &amp;ldquo;The point is not to be fooled by intuition. It is our most powerful tool for creativity, but it is often very wrong. It gives us jewels, but only rarely. Most of the time it gives us garbage.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6148/why-science-needs-intuition#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-07-25T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-25T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JULY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/07/open-discussion-july-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978562</id>
    <published>2023-07-01T08:00:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-01T08:00:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We are back!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/06/28/we-are-back/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft is-resized"><img data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" class="wp-image-13712" width="488" height="488" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=488&amp;h=488 488w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=976&amp;h=976 976w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px"/></figure></div>


<p>I am delighted to say that the second series of our On Your Mind podcast has launched today!!</p>



<p>Each week, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will explore aspects of the human psyche, including astrology, how the clothes we wear influence our thoughts, attraction, friendship, dreaming, mind control and much much more.  We will also be joined by some special guests as we attempt to answer all of your questions about psychology. The first series reached No.1 in Apple Podcast’s Science charts, and so we hope that you can join us. </p>



<p>Our first episode looks at creativity and explores how to have good ideas and whether children are more creative than adults. You can listen <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/2txmeCf9U2rj4aAdMLoczK">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to say that the second series of our On Your Mind podcast has launched today!! Each week,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/06/28/we-are-back/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">We are back!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13884</id>
    <published>2023-06-28T16:36:48Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-28T16:36:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Protect Itself. It Needs Our Help.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/06/science-cannot-protect-itself-it-needs-our-help/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It can be easy to take science for granted, to mistakenly believe there is a universal understanding of its importance and agreement about its value and function. Of course, we know that isn’t true. In the new issue of Skeptical Inquirer, Jerry Coyne and Luana Maroja deliver …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978555</id>
    <published>2023-06-27T18:41:11Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-27T18:41:11Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JUNE 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/06/open-discussion-june-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978548</id>
    <published>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/05/open-discussion-may-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978543</id>
    <published>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
