<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-04-11T16:32:26Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>The Renfield protocol</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/11/the-renfield-protocol/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/hoult-as-renfield.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/hoult-as-renfield-127x150.jpeg" alt="" width="127" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69812" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/hoult-as-renfield-127x150.jpeg 127w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/hoult-as-renfield-255x300.jpeg 255w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/hoult-as-renfield.jpeg 310w" sizes="(max-width: 127px) 100vw, 127px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">They don’t tell you about the dirty jobs involved in spider care. Last week, I fed all the adults nice big juicy mealworms, which they promptly killed and then spent several days sucking on their vital fluids. Even when they’re very thorough in their consumption, though, they still leave behind a sack of chitin with organic leftovers inside.</p>
<p>Then it rots.</p>
<p>It rots thoroughly, turning black and soft and turning hairy with fungus. It has a sulfurous reek to it, as well.  Then the spiders turn to me and peremptorily demand, “Renfield! Oh, Renfield! Do clean up the rotting corpses, will you? That’s a good Renfield.”</p>
<p>Renfield is me, if you haven’t figured that out. This morning I got to go through all the cages and pluck out decaying mealworms with a pair of forceps. This is my job. That, and regularly bringing them fresh bodies to turn into rotting corpses. </p>
<p>Oh well. I also got to play with my shiny new camera and take photos of my masters.</p>
<p>You’ll have to go to <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/Cq5rdl6LRV6/">Instagram</a> or <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/81364612">Patreon</a> if you want to see photos. (Hmm, I didn’t do a very good job of promoting those links with all this talk of decaying corpses, did I…)</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">They don’t tell you about the dirty jobs involved in spider care. Last week, I fed all the adults nice big juicy mealworms, which they promptly killed and then spent several days sucking on their vital fluids. Even when they’re very thorough in their consumption, though, they still leave behind a sack of chitin with […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69811</id>
    <published>2023-04-11T15:50:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-11T15:50:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Spiders"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What are they teaching in journalism school nowadays?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/11/what-are-they-teaching-in-journalism-school-nowadays/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Another mass murder by an asshole with a rifle, on a day ending with the letter “y”. But <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/louisville-bank-massacre-suspect-idd-as-ex-varsity-star-connor-sturgeon?ref=scroll">this article</a>! Jesus!</p>
<blockquote><p>The suspect in a Monday morning massacre at a Louisville bank has been identified as a 23-year-old former varsity hoops star and finance grad-turned-banker who livestreamed the horrific attack.</p>
<p>Louisville Police Chief Jacquelyn Gwinn-Villaroel identified the suspect as Connor Sturgeon, who worked at Old National Bank’s downtown Louisville branch.</p>
<p>Gwinn-Villaroel said Sturgeon was livestreaming as he used a rifle to open fire at about 8:38 a.m. in the Old National Bank Building, which houses the bank and a variety of other businesses, killing four people and injuring nine more, including three police officers. Sturgeon was killed after exchanging gunfire with officers, she said, but it’s unclear if he was killed by police or by self-inflicted gunshots.</p></blockquote>
<p>The article briefly mentions the victims by name, but after that, it’s got a more important job to do. It spends <em>22 fucking paragraphs</em> going on and on about what a nice normal guy the <em>killer</em> was. The governor of Kentucky has to tell us what an “incredible friend” he was, they interview old high school friends and buddies from his college fraternity, they reach the depths of banality by getting a quote from the husband of a neighbor.</p>
<blockquote><p>Sturgeon “seemed like a real normal dude, every day he’d wave to me,” Allgeier’s husband, Michael, added.</p></blockquote>
<p>What the fuck? The mass murderer was known to sometimes wave to people? This is news? I learned nothing from it other than that the killer was otherwise a mundane person who lived an ordinary, if privileged, life before going on a shooting rampage. The article says <em>nothing</em> about the victims, short of naming them, and should have been slashed to bits by an editor before publishing.</p>
<p>And it took three ‘reporters’ to cobble together this unquestioning story about a bad man.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/three-reporters.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/three-reporters.png" alt="" width="421" height="263" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-69806" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/three-reporters.png 421w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/three-reporters-150x94.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/three-reporters-300x187.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 421px) 100vw, 421px"/></a></p>
<p>I hope they feel a little bit of shame today.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another mass murder by an asshole with a rifle, on a day ending with the letter “y”. But this article! Jesus! The suspect in a Monday morning massacre at a Louisville bank has been identified as a 23-year-old former varsity hoops star and finance grad-turned-banker who livestreamed the horrific attack. Louisville Police Chief Jacquelyn Gwinn-Villaroel […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69805</id>
    <published>2023-04-11T12:33:52Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-11T12:33:52Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What meritocracy?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/11/what-meritocracy/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Elon Musk is doing a fine job of wrecking the reputation (what there was of it) of rich people. Here’s <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2023/04/10/after-matt-taibbi-leaves-twitter-elon-musk-shadow-bans-all-of-taibbis-tweets-including-the-twitter-files/">his idea of a clever joke</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter-500x837.png" alt="" width="500" height="837" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69801" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter-500x837.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter-90x150.png 90w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter-179x300.png 179w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/titter.png 574w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Juvenile. Stupid. He bought this thing for $44 billion, and now he spends all his time mocking it and literally deprecating it. He threw away over $20 billion so far, and is determined to destroy all the rest.</p>
<p>Worse is what he’s doing to Matt Taibbi. I don’t much care for Taibbi — he’s also juvenile and gullible — but he was defending Musk, incompetently, and was paid by Musk to fire off that damp squib called the “Twitter Files,” but now Musk is cutting off Substack, where Taibbi makes his money, and has gone so far as to ‘shadow ban’ Taibbi on Twitter.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked-500x767.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="767" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69802" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked-500x767.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked-98x150.jpeg 98w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked-195x300.jpeg 195w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/taibbi-blocked.jpeg 649w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Musk is a petty 3 year old child. I browsed his Twitter feed to see what’s going on in his brain, and even his deep thoughts are shallow and trivial. Like this one:</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging-500x274.png" alt="" width="500" height="274" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69803" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging-500x274.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging-150x82.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging-300x164.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/musk-aging.png 585w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Wait, what? Your left arm is the same age as your right, and the two are genetically identical, and typically have similar environmental exposure. How is this an example of precision? How does this tell us that aging can be fixed?</p>
<p>Although…I did once meet a man, a truck driver, whose left arm was ruddy, scaly, and weathered, while his right was pale and smooth. He liked driving with the side window down, and his left arm resting on the door. I guess I’ve cured aging, then — simply stay out of the sun.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Elon Musk is doing a fine job of wrecking the reputation (what there was of it) of rich people. Here’s his idea of a clever joke. Juvenile. Stupid. He bought this thing for $44 billion, and now he spends all his time mocking it and literally deprecating it. He threw away over $20 billion so […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69800</id>
    <published>2023-04-11T11:38:54Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-11T11:38:54Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Texas takes another step into the abyss</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/10/texas-takes-another-step-into-the-abyss/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Daniel Perry was an uber driver who ran a red light, drove into a crowd of Black Lives Matter protesters, and when one of them approached his car carrying an AK-47 (which, stupid and dangerous as it is, is legal in Texas), opened fire with a handgun and killed him. He was found guilty of murder in a jury trial.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.statesman.com/story/news/local/2023/04/08/texas-governor-greg-abbott-will-pardon-daniel-perry-convicted-of-murder-garrett-foster/70095504007/">In Texas</a>. After he threatened to kill someone online.</p>
<blockquote><p>Perry’s defense team argued that he acted in self-defense, but prosecutors contended that Perry instigated what happened. They highlighted a series of social media posts and Facebook messages in which Perry made statements that they said indicated his state of mind, such as he might “kill a few people on my way to work. They are rioting outside my apartment complex.”</p>
<p>A friend responded, “Can you legally do so?” Perry replied, “If they attack me or try to pull me out of my car then yes.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Guess what? The governor wants to free him immediately.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/abbott-perry.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/abbott-perry.png" alt="" width="402" height="600" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-69798" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/abbott-perry.png 402w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/abbott-perry-101x150.png 101w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/abbott-perry-201x300.png 201w" sizes="(max-width: 402px) 100vw, 402px"/></a></p>
<p>Abbott wants an army of undisciplined thugs who will murder people he doesn’t like. It’s the authoritarian mindset.</p>
<blockquote><p>“It’s what happens in Uganda or El Salvador,” said Cofer, a former prosecutor. “Total abrogation of the rule of law. And what’s even worse is that Abbott knows better. He was a smart Texas Supreme Court Justice. He knows this is legally wrong. Profoundly wrong. Pure politics.”</p></blockquote>
<p>But it works! I know I would never consider living in Texas. I won’t even visit the state anymore. Abbott is doing a great job of driving anyone who would oppose him away.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Daniel Perry was an uber driver who ran a red light, drove into a crowd of Black Lives Matter protesters, and when one of them approached his car carrying an AK-47 (which, stupid and dangerous as it is, is legal in Texas), opened fire with a handgun and killed him. He was found guilty of […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69797</id>
    <published>2023-04-10T13:43:14Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-10T13:43:14Z</updated>
    <category term="Crime"/>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Noah was a prevert</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/10/noah-was-a-prevert/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2-150x89.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="89" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-15363" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2-150x89.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2-300x178.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2-500x297.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2014/03/noah-ark2.jpg 610w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I never thought of it from this angle before, but maybe <a href="https://www.mcsweeneys.net/articles/i-am-noah-and-i-need-to-look-at-your-animals-pee-pees">Noah was a devious guy with a bestiality obsession</a>, and he invented that whole flood nonsense as an excuse to check out animals’ genitals. That makes more sense than the book of Genesis, that’s for sure.</p>
<p>It also suggests how we ought to view all those weirdos today who are insisting on laws to check out children’s genitals. There’s no social catastrophe, just a lot of perverts who think they have a cunning excuse.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I never thought of it from this angle before, but maybe Noah was a devious guy with a bestiality obsession, and he invented that whole flood nonsense as an excuse to check out animals’ genitals. That makes more sense than the book of Genesis, that’s for sure. It also suggests how we ought to view […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69795</id>
    <published>2023-04-10T13:18:33Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-10T13:18:33Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Q&amp;A: Anna Lembke on the power of dopamine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6099/qa-anna-lembke-on-the-power-of-dopamine#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Anna_Lembke_office_112-copy.jpg" height="1181" alt="Anna Lembke" width="1771"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anna Lembke is a professor of psychiatry and program director for the Stanford Addiction Medicine Fellowship. Her latest book is &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dopamine is an important neurotransmitter when it comes to motivation, pleasure and reward. What makes it so special? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the final common pathway for all reinforcing substances and behaviours. So, for example, the use of alcohol, and other stimulants, lead directly to the release of dopamine. The more dopamine that&amp;rsquo;s released, and the faster it&amp;rsquo;s released, in this specific circuit [in the brain] called the reward pathway, means it can lead to more addictive behaviour, when it comes to certain substances or activities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But we need it, don&amp;rsquo;t we? Isn&amp;rsquo;t it also involved in memory, attention and the regulation of our body movements? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. It&amp;rsquo;s no coincidence that over many years of evolution the same neurotransmitter that&amp;rsquo;s important for motivation, pleasure and reward is also important for movement, because for most organisms, this has always been linked. In order to get your reward, you have to do the physical work to get there. Even the most primitive worm will release dopamine in response to food in its environment, which allows it to move toward that food. Part of the problem today in modern society is that we humans don&amp;rsquo;t really have to do any work to get our rewards.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You write about the &amp;ldquo;dopamine economy&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;limbic capitalism&amp;rdquo;. Can you explain these terms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m talking here about how the natural end result of successful capitalism is to turn us all into good consumers and addicts. The ultimate consumer, after all, invests all their energy, creativity and resources into getting and consuming their drug of choice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has the internet made us addicted to information? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. In fact, digital media itself is a drug. The smartphone is a modern-day hypodermic syringe. Take, for example, a 10-second TikTok video. As soon as you view it, you&amp;rsquo;re already craving the next clip, because as soon as it ends, you&amp;rsquo;re feeling that comedown. And that drive to want to restore that physiological state is overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we achieve a healthy balance of pleasure and pain?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The best way to stay in balance is to use intoxicants in extreme moderation. And to avoid intoxicants that are super potent. It&amp;rsquo;s also helpful to leave sufficient time in between intoxicants to allow the pleasure-pain balance to restore equilibrium. Exposing our bodies and minds to things that are painful and difficult is also a useful way to regulate our own dopamine production and tilt the balance toward the side of pleasure. Because for every pleasure, we pay a price, and that price is the comedown. Getting our dopamine indirectly, through painful effortful engagement, like, say, taking a cold shower, is helpful, because we pay for our dopamine up front &amp;ndash; as opposed to getting a quick fix of it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You define addiction as &amp;ldquo;the continued and compulsive consumption of a substance or behaviour, despite its harm to self and/or others&amp;rdquo;. How would I know if I&amp;rsquo;m addicted to something?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Addiction is very hard to define because it&amp;rsquo;s a bio-psychosocial disease that is very contextualised, depending upon the time, the place and the culture. It&amp;rsquo;s also a spectrum disorder. It&amp;rsquo;s not a single moment in time, where you cross the line, and now you&amp;rsquo;re addicted. It&amp;rsquo;s a gradual process, characterised by these brain changes, where, over time, the drug essentially stops working. This means the user needs more of it, and more potent forms to get the same effect.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there any way to end this spiral of addiction? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I recommend is a dopamine fast. This involves abstinence from the particular substance or behaviour. This helps reset reward pathways in the brain. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend this for somebody who was at risk of life-threatening alcohol, benzo or opioid withdrawal. Or for someone who had tried repeatedly to stop activities related to addiction on their own, but were unable to because the compulsions were so overwhelming. But for most individuals I treat, it&amp;rsquo;s a good first pass. Typically, during the first 10 to 14 days, they feel worse, because they&amp;rsquo;re experiencing withdrawal when they are in that dopamine-deficit state. But if they can just go long enough, and get over that hump, they find their pleasure-pain balance starts to reregulate itself, and they start to upregulate dopamine and other endogenous feel-good neurotransmitters that have been suppressed. Then by week three or four, they&amp;rsquo;ll report feeling better than they have in a very long time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you make of Gabor Mate&amp;rsquo;s theory that all addiction stems from trauma?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t agree. Trauma can certainly be one of many gateways into addiction. But another reason is simple exposure to the drug, which changes our brain. We can get addicted to things when our lives seem to be perfect. The main point of Dopamine Nation is to show that we&amp;rsquo;re now living in a world that&amp;rsquo;s so saturated with pleasure goods that we&amp;rsquo;re all more vulnerable to the problem of compulsive overuse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But you note that the poor and undereducated, especially those living in rich nations, are more susceptible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;People living in poverty don&amp;rsquo;t have access to the healthier forms of dopamine, which wealthy people do. For example, exposure to being in nature, or gyms, where you can get your dopamine indirectly. People who are unemployed, for instance, have enormous amounts of unstructured time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You argue that we have created &amp;ldquo;oversanitised children&amp;rdquo;. Would tough love from parents better serve their mental health in the long run? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. What I have seen over two decades of clinical work is parents who have assiduously insulated their children not just from painful experiences, but really any kind of challenging experiences. This means that children haven&amp;rsquo;t had the opportunity to build up the mental strength they need to live in the real world. A more effective strategy is to set limits, and boundaries, and give our children real feedback about their strengths and weaknesses, which in the long term will enforce real consequences for transgression.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Might these &amp;ldquo;sanitised children&amp;rdquo; become more predisposed to addiction? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Definitely. If you&amp;rsquo;re not having the experience of your own self efficacy, and your ability to rely on your own fortitude to overcome challenges, that really undermines a sense of competence, and fosters an avoidant coping style, which is really at the heart of many addictions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The use of antidepressants is rising all over the world. Is this a problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We are definitely insulating ourselves from challenging, painful experiences that we need in order to be resilient in the world. One way we are doing that is by overprescribing psychotropics, antidepressants, anxiolytics and hypnotics. That said, I&amp;rsquo;m a psychiatrist. And I regularly prescribe these medicines. In many instances, they are life-saving for people with severe mental illness. But I&amp;rsquo;m concerned about the indiscriminate prescribing of [drugs] like Xanax, which is a highly potent and addictive benzodiazepine. When we take a pill to manage anxiety, we deprive ourselves of the opportunity to learn from that experience, or to conceptualise anxiety as a form of energy. If the anxiety is so overwhelming that it&amp;rsquo;s paralysing, well, that&amp;rsquo;s different. But in many instances, anxiety is energy. And we need to figure out how to manage it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6099/qa-anna-lembke-on-the-power-of-dopamine#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-06T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-06T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>That don't impress me much</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6098/that-dont-impress-me-much#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/NewHumanistLaurieJesusMagician.jpg" height="678" alt="A cartoon depicts Jesus performing a card trick" width="402"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At my Roman Catholic boarding school, it was a requirement to get down on one&amp;rsquo;s knees at bedtime and pray for miracles. There was a good reason for this injunction. Every pupil had been repeatedly told that firm evidence of miracles was the only way in which the school&amp;rsquo;s patron, the Blessed Michael Garico&amp;iuml;ts, could be raised from mere Blessedness into full-blown Sainthood. Three miraculous happenings were required before the Pope could confer such spiritual promotion. The Blessed Michael had so far only managed two such fundamental violations of the natural law. (As I remember, these involved the miraculous restoration to health of an elderly nun, and the transformation of a cauliflower into a bunch of grapes.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alongside these official calls for miracles, there were the numerous miraculous requests made by the school&amp;rsquo;s boarders. Some were purely selfish. Boys routinely prayed for God to intervene in the calculation of their examination marks or in the promotion of their favourite football team. But I also remember regularly going down on my knees to invoke God&amp;rsquo;s help in the reincarnation of a third-former&amp;rsquo;s mother and the furtherance of world peace.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to be able to say that my faith in miracles withered with time, but even at the age of 18 I was still asking my patron saint (Saint Lawrence, who was burned to death over a gridiron in 258 AD) if he would do his level best to bring on Maureen Dobson&amp;rsquo;s period. Thankfully, I was spared the strain of fatherhood at such a tender age.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d also like to be able to say that my current scepticism about miracles was based on some firm philosophical ground, perhaps upon John Stuart Mill&amp;rsquo;s powerful argument that &amp;ldquo;We cannot admit a proposition as a law of nature, and yet believe a fact (a cited miracle) in real contradiction to it. We must disbelieve the alleged fact, or believe that we are mistaken in admitting the supposed law.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it was not Mill &amp;ndash; or such other philosophic sceptics as Auguste Comte, David Hume or Ludwig Feuerbach &amp;ndash; who finally applied the coup de grace to my lingering belief that there might just be &amp;ldquo;more things in heaven and earth&amp;rdquo; than Horatio had dreamt of in his philosophy. It was none other than the American magician David Blaine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Even before I&amp;rsquo;d encountered Blaine and his awesome feats of magic, I&amp;rsquo;d come to regard Jesus&amp;rsquo;s miracles as somewhat lacking &amp;ndash; not only in credibility, but also in invention. Quite frankly, turning water into wine was poor stuff, as was catching a bumper load of fish on the Lake of Gennesaret. Neither could one be unduly impressed by the news that he had turned a group of demons into a herd of pigs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Indeed, when compared to David Blaine&amp;rsquo;s achievements, it has to be said that Christ&amp;rsquo;s inventory of miracles is decidedly second-rate. I don&amp;rsquo;t wish to labour the point, but was Jesus able to hold his breath for 17 minutes, submit to electrocution while standing on top of a pole, or levitate a foot in the air in front of a crowd of New Yorkers? Blaine was buried alive for seven days; Jesus only managed three. Not only did Blaine triumphantly accomplish all these miraculous feats, but they also usually took place in front of passers-by in the streets, people who &amp;ndash; in these irreligious times &amp;ndash; were likely to be far more sceptical than the multitude of God-botherers who inhabited Jerusalem in 27 AD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But although Blaine&amp;rsquo;s magic can startle and fool entire modern-day audiences, there are several websites devoted, with varying degrees of success, to unmasking his deceptions. As far as I am aware, there is no similar site devoted to unmasking the claims of the divine magician. This fact is no doubt indicative of the peculiar manner in which our world allows the truths of science to happily intermingle with the deceits of religion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I recently asked an elderly and rather reclusive philosopher about this apparent paradox. He was reluctant to comment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I pressed him. &amp;ldquo;If you had to choose&amp;rdquo;, I persisted, &amp;ldquo;which of Christ&amp;rsquo;s miracles would you select as the most amazing?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He closed his eyes and thought for a several minutes. &amp;ldquo;Quite simple, really&amp;rdquo;, he said. &amp;ldquo;It was having as many as 12 friends after the age of 30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6098/that-dont-impress-me-much#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-04T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-04T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/open-discussion-april-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978526</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A festival of big ideas</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6097/a-festival-of-big-ideas#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img title="HTLGI festival will return to the banks of the River Wye this May bank holiday" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/festival-grounds-with-festival-signsmall.jpeg" height="1181" alt="HTLGI festival will return to the banks of the River Wye this May" width="1774"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;HowTheLightGetsIn&lt;/em&gt; has now firmly established itself as the most exciting philosophy festival in Europe. Bringing together ground-breaking thinkers from various fields of expertise and walks of life, there are usually intellectual surprises instore &amp;ndash; if you're lucky, maybe even a revelation or two. Hilary Lawson, who calls himself a post-postmodern philosopher, founded HTLGI in 2008 in order to bring "philosophy into British culture". Since then, it has developed into a delight for the mind &amp;ndash; while not neglecting the pleasures of the body (and, of course, delving into the boundaries between mind and body, and questioning whether such boundaries really exist.) There is music and comedy, as well as talks and panel debates. And a Ferris wheel, in case you feel the need to gain a completely different perspective.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 26-29 May, the last bank holiday of the month, the &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;festival will return to Hay-on-Wye&lt;/a&gt;. The historic book town is &lt;em&gt;just about &lt;/em&gt;in Wales &amp;ndash; it gets its name from the River Wye, which for much of its length forms the border between England and Wales. The town is charming, and hosts, at the same time, the Hay Literary Festival, so if you're feeling exceptionally avid, it's possible to do both.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The festival has always dug into the big ideas. One of the many positive effects of bringing together scientists with politicians, activists, intellectuals and creative people of all stripes, is that the debates tend to push against boundaries. It's hard for an evolutionary biologist, for example, to get stuck on the particulars, when they're in conversation with a playwright or a moral philosopher. This year, however, they've made this natural tendency into an explicit theme, "Error and Renaissance".&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Lawson put it &lt;a href="https://www.theweek.co.uk/arts-life/culture/music/957551/howthelightgetsin-london-philosophy-and-music-on-hampstead-heath"&gt;recently&lt;/a&gt;, the purpose is to "come together to try and identify the fundamental errors that we have made in our theories, the organisation of society and in world affairs &amp;ndash; all while looking to new forms of thought and action to rebuild afresh.&amp;rdquo; Some of the big names already announced &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/programme?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;in the programme&lt;/a&gt; include philosopher Daniel Dennett, presidential advisor Fiona Hill, string-theorist Brian Greene and geneticist G&amp;uuml;neş Taylor. Readers of &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; might also be interested in checking out Michael Shermer, who has spent his career popularising scepticism as a method to search for truth, or the prominent voice for Christian humanism, Nick Spencer. It's a chance to hear voices we both agree, and disagree with.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; is also sponsoring a debate, "The Best and Worst of All Possible Worlds", so if you do come to the festival, please stop and say hello. The panel will debate whether alternate worlds exist, and also whether the concept can be useful for thinking about &lt;em&gt;our&lt;/em&gt; world, casting light on deep puzzles of language and reality. Philosopher of physics Paul Horwich, theoretical physicist Tasneem Zehra Husain and philosopher Ben Burgis will debate the continued attraction of many worlds theory, chaired by our Editor, Niki Seth-Smith.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a festival partner, we are offering a 20 per cent discount on tickets to all of our readers, with the code NEWHUMANIST23. Don't miss out on tickets &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; And for those of you who can't be with us in person, all the debates and talks from the festival will gradually be released online, on the Institute of Art and Ideas platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;IAI.TV.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We hope to see you there!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6097/a-festival-of-big-ideas#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-30T13:27:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-30T13:27:01Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The moral duty to pump iron</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6096/the-moral-duty-to-pump-iron#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Eugen Sandow, founder of the Sandow system" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Sandow.jpg" height="768" alt="Eugen Sandow" width="1199"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When the Irish &amp;ldquo;physical culturalist&amp;rdquo; F. A. Hornibrook wrote The Culture of the Abdomen in 1924, he was confident that he had conclusively identified the source of much of industrialised society&amp;rsquo;s problems: chronic constipation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Between the trained athlete and the sedentary bookworm lies a great gulf across which age eventually throws a bridge where both meet in middle life, both burdened with enfeebled bodies, adipose deposits, pendulous bellies, constipated bowels and impaired mental activity... the ponderous speech of the portly magnate finds its echoes in the intestinal rumblings of his ponderous paunch, and awed ignorance acclaims wind for wisdom.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Calling it &amp;ldquo;the white man&amp;rsquo;s burden&amp;rdquo;, in chapters such as &amp;ldquo;Sewage System of the Body&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;Buttock Contraction&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Eating and Evacuation&amp;rdquo;, Hornibrook advocated a series of measures to promote good stool cultivation, appreciation and, most importantly, expulsion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some recommendations relate to diet &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;in paraffin, taken in tablespoonful doses three-quarters of an hour before a meal, we have a useful ally in the conflict with constipation&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; while others are to do with the vital moment of unburdening. Hornibrook argues that the modern water closet, in failing to replicate the squatting posture of &amp;ldquo;the native&amp;rdquo; (whose stools are &amp;ldquo;soft, pultaceous and easily passed&amp;rdquo; as opposed to civilised man&amp;rsquo;s, which are &amp;ldquo;almost as hard as old putty, and very dry&amp;rdquo;), needs urgent adaptation to make it more conducive to stool delivery. Failing this, the individual can place a wooden platform eight inches high in front of the toilet, on which the feet can rest during the act of defecation, thus approximating the squat.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hornibrook &amp;ndash; whose followers included H. G. Wells and Arnold Bennett &amp;ndash; simultaneously promoted physical fitness based on native dancing rituals. The Culture of the Abdomen has helpful pictures of &amp;ldquo;modern man&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the native&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; the posture, attitude, dignity and buttocks of the former being compared unfavourably with the latter&amp;rsquo;s. The book ends with a series of suggested exercises and aids to health including, somewhat randomly, golf. Remember, says Hornibrook, &amp;ldquo;A short belt is a long life-line.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Battle of the Systems&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hornibrook&amp;rsquo;s work grew out of what has become known to historians as the &amp;ldquo;Battle of the Systems&amp;rdquo;, a 19th-century clash between various types of physical regime for the promotion of wellbeing. With its roots in European military practices, and fuelled by an increasingly consumerist society both there and in the US, the various systems promoted different physical regimes, often combining them with dietary and &amp;ldquo;lifestyle&amp;rdquo; advice. Between 1848 &amp;ndash; that Year of Revolutions in Europe &amp;ndash; through to the 1930s, newspapers and magazines promoted schemes for improving one&amp;rsquo;s physical health.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Beginning with the Turner movement &amp;ndash; a gymnastic scheme imported to the US by Germans fleeing the 1848 revolution &amp;ndash; the Battle of the Systems came to include the Czech Sokol movement (&amp;ldquo;a strong mind in a sound body&amp;rdquo;); the Swedish System, which concentrated on calisthenics, breathing and massage; and Muscular Christianity, which sought to combine spiritual and physical health as a bulwark against what many believed to be a decrease in manliness caused by excessive Puritanism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Promoted by sections of the Church, Muscular Christianity&amp;rsquo;s version of Christ was the one that &amp;ldquo;came not to send peace, but a sword&amp;rdquo;. As one convert, Theodore Roosevelt, put it, in a truly Christian society &amp;ldquo;there is only a very circumscribed sphere of usefulness for the timid good man.&amp;rdquo; That many of these systems sprang from military training is no coincidence. Sokol argued that one should think deeply about Czech nationalism while lifting weights, while in the UK at the beginning of the 20th century, Muscular Christianity became part of the myth of how the British Empire was created and maintained. The true Brit had a Bible in one hand and a rifle in the other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it was the Sandow system, named for its founder Eugen Sandow, and based on weightlifting, which had convinced Hornibrook of the benefits of physical fitness, having allowed him to reshape his body until he was known, in his own telling, as &amp;ldquo;Brawnibrook&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Gym freaks&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sandow was born Jewish, the son of a German and a Russian. He began using weights at the age of ten. Briefly a circus strongman, he is credited with organising the world&amp;rsquo;s first bodybuilding competition at London&amp;rsquo;s Royal Albert Hall in 1901 (his fellow judge was Arthur Conan Doyle). At the turn of the century, Thomas Edison filmed him performing one of his &amp;ldquo;muscle display performances&amp;rdquo; and he was later designated special instructor in physical culture to King George V.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Natalia Mehlman Petrzela points out in her new book, Fit Nation: The Gains and Pains of America&amp;rsquo;s Exercise Obsession (University of Chicago), despite the advocacy of F. A. Hornibrook and his like, when Sandow made his first tour of the United States, extreme physical health and exaggerated musculature were things to be ogled at, rather than aspired to. Audiences would gather to marvel at what were, in some senses, still freaks. Weightlifting and going to gymnasiums were not only niche activities, but were regarded with a certain amount of scorn.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fast forward a hundred years and Hornibrook and Sandow would be astonished at the centrality of many of their theories &amp;ndash; if not their systems &amp;ndash; in western public discourse. We find ourselves in a new Battle of the Systems, with a bewildering array of techniques supposedly aimed at making all of us fitter, happier and more productive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The global wellness economy was valued at US$4.4 trillion in 2020 &amp;ndash; an astonishing 5.1 per cent of all global output. In the US, gyms are now a $40 billion industry. But despite the massive revenue generated, as Petrzela points out, fewer than 20 per cent of Americans actually work out consistently, a similar figure to the UK. In addition, over 73 per cent of Americans are classed as overweight, 42 per cent of them obese. According to a 2022 UK government report, three-quarters of the British population are overweight, and 28 per cent of them obese. The latter group includes one in seven children under the age of five. For all the talk of our fitness obsession, it seems as much honoured in the breach as in the observance.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What one can discern, however, is how closely fitness and capitalism cleave together. If the Battle of the Systems grew from military training, it was no less a product of the Industrial Revolution. The working of the human body gradually became analogous to the working of the new machines which had begun to replace it. Initially, in the early 19th century, there was some upper-class distaste for both sweat and muscle. Both were seen as working class, and even in Sandow&amp;rsquo;s day, part of the thrill of attending his performances lay in slumming it momentarily, and gawping at the bestial displays of these strange somatic creatures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A moral debt&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Increasingly, however, as the middle class emerged, the idea of both individual and societal productivity became more and more prevalent. Somewhere along the way, we developed the idea that to be unproductive is a sin. Physical fitness was no longer an end in itself &amp;ndash; it became, and remains, a moral issue. As endless government campaigns and TV shows tell us, to be unfit is to be bad: a strain on the health service, a burden to society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Muscular Christianity is instructive here. Tracing its origins, somewhat spuriously, back to the apostle Paul, the movement argued that man &amp;ndash; always &amp;ldquo;man&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; had become too civilised, too effete and too intellectual. This was a moral failure as much as a physical one. In fact, one could not separate the two. Just as Hornibrook bemoaned the corpulent, flatulent &amp;ldquo;magnate&amp;rdquo;, proponents of Muscular Christianity argued that the degeneracy of the human body leads to moral degeneracy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As David Graeber argued in his 2011 book Debt: The First 5,000 Years, one of the reasons Christianity and capitalism work so well together is their shared belief that debt is fundamental and ultimately unresolvable. In Christianity we are born with sin and spend our lives trying to repay that debt. In capitalism we must keep earning to stop our financial debt growing. This moral imperative is analogous with the prevalent framing of fitness today as an endless and unresolvable quest: one can always be fitter, and not pursuing this goal is a failing to oneself and to society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To be fit is a personal responsibility &amp;ndash; and therefore it is irresponsible not to be so. The underpinning idea of debt can be seen in the fact that public health campaigns are so often framed in financial terms. &amp;ldquo;Obesity costs the taxpayer &amp;ndash; those who earn enough to pay tax &amp;ndash; x amount&amp;rdquo; and so on, implying that the fit and rich are having to pay for the poor to sit around and get fat. In the UK, as the NHS collapses through chronic underfunding, the scourge of obesity is often held up as a drain on the public purse. Of course, one might argue that it is in fact a healthier middle and upper class, which lives longer, that causes the biggest drain, but this is seldom canvassed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The temple of the body&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The human body shaped by today&amp;rsquo;s hyper-capitalist work regime may not be the only product of this kind of thinking. But if we were designing people who would best fit what capitalism wants, then a set of beings who run on coffee and are fitter than humans in the past would not be far off the mark. Perhaps the dramatic fall in alcohol consumption among younger people in recent years is the result of a partial internalisation of the moral requirement to be useful and productive. (As the French philosopher Georges Bataille noted in his 1949 book The Accursed Share, in a capitalist society, leisure, uselessness and luxury are increasingly only the domain of the upper classes, and are seen as sinful for working people.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Petrzela notes: &amp;ldquo;Fitness has become a socially acceptable form of conspicuous consumption in a society that celebrates the pursuit of health as practically holy.&amp;rdquo; The body itself has thus become both corporatised and a devotional object &amp;ndash; our temple.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In addition, even more than in the Battle of the Systems, our current fitness obsession places the emphasis on individual empowerment at, Petrzela notes, the expense of collective solidarity. We are in a competition with others, but also with ourselves. It is part of a &amp;ldquo;culture of narcissism&amp;rdquo; which valorises an imagined freedom we can find &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;a lofty idiom of enlightenment&amp;rdquo; where exercise is &amp;ldquo;something more than bodily cultivation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This has led to some extreme outcomes. The Washington Post in 2022 ran a series of articles about deaths in the bodybuilding industry, caused by athletes pursuing ever more unnatural physiques. With steroids freely available, both male and female bodybuilders build themselves up to a point where, as one coach put it, the young Arnold Schwarzenegger would not even be able to compete, let alone win. It has led to a new form of body dysmorphia in the Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (DSM): &amp;ldquo;bigorexia&amp;rdquo;, where there is no such thing as big enough. &amp;ldquo;Once you step into a gym, you&amp;rsquo;re forever small&amp;rdquo; sums up the thinking.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some individual empowerment is obviously positive. The relationship between feminism and fitness for instance is complex precisely because some of the gains in personal agency and self-esteem are so great that it is difficult to disentangle them from the negatives to do with, for instance, objectification. But a culture where the self is absolutely sovereign increasingly seems just another of capitalism&amp;rsquo;s false versions of liberty. That &amp;ldquo;the body beautiful&amp;rdquo; has become such an aspiration conforms to an incredibly narrow definition of liberty. Like Eugen Sandow a century ago, we are suddenly all engaged in &amp;ldquo;muscle display performances&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The business of the body&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;On an individual level, we all basically know how to be healthy, and have for a long time: eat plenty of fruit and veg, stay active, don&amp;rsquo;t drink or smoke and get plenty of sleep. But the countless iterations of this story, emphasising new and different ways to approach the &amp;ldquo;problem&amp;rdquo;, force us to set up a plan &amp;ndash; a corporate system of selfhood. We then micromanage as though our body were a business, which we have to run at maximum yield. Our fitness journals become individual profit and loss statements.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, as Fit Nation points out, despite the pursuit of individual health being seen as practically holy, it has not in fact become a &amp;ldquo;public good&amp;rdquo;. In the US, 80 per cent of the population live in what she terms &amp;ldquo;fitness deserts&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; defined as &amp;ldquo;an area without a public park in a half-mile radius&amp;rdquo;. Additional factors such as higher pollution in deprived areas, as well as inadequate street lighting, also lead to a bias in favour of the wealthy when it comes to achieving the &amp;ldquo;freedom&amp;rdquo; that fitness vaunts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The pursuit of fitness requires both time and money. Witness the 2018 Mayo Clinic study which found that playing tennis could add 9.7 years to your lifespan. That those who play tennis tend to be older, richer and already healthier than the general population was not considered. Obesity rates in both the US and the UK are highest among people lacking time and money. Leaving aside the merits or demerits of fitness for a moment, what is notable here is that despite clear structural factors, this is still seen as a moral failing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For Petrzela, who is not only a professor of history but a fitness instructor, access to fitness is therefore a social justice issue. One cannot make fitness an issue of personal responsibility and then not enable equal access.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It does not,&amp;rdquo; Hornibrook wrote in 1924, &amp;ldquo;add to the enjoyment of life to carry round superfluous flesh. It does not add to the enjoyment of life to have stuffed up bowels. It does not add to the enjoyment of life to have a sagging abdomen and atrophied muscles.&amp;rdquo; No one can really argue with that. But nor does it add to the enjoyment of life to make the pursuit of physical health yet another moral quest, which is more often than not a moral failure and another unfulfilled debt.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As Graeber put it, there is no better way to make things seem moral &amp;ldquo;than by reframing them in the language of debt &amp;ndash; above all, because it immediately makes it seem that it&amp;rsquo;s the victim who&amp;rsquo;s doing something wrong.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6096/the-moral-duty-to-pump-iron#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-30T05:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-30T05:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Still Pictures by Janet Malcolm</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6095/book-review-still-pictures-by-janet-malcolm#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="New York in the 1940s" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/GCS-New-York.jpg" height="679" alt="New York's Grand Central Station in the 1940s" width="694"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Still Pictures: On photography and memory &lt;/strong&gt;(Granta) by Janet Malcolm&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In postwar New York, after escaping Nazi-occupied Prague in 1939, Janet Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s mother Joan was having dinner in an American household. When time for seconds came, Joan declined. In bourgeois Prague, this was a charade known as nutcen&amp;iacute;, and the host would insist until you relented. &amp;ldquo;But here &amp;lsquo;No, thank you&amp;rsquo; was taken to mean just that, and the platter of delicious American food was whisked away before my mother&amp;rsquo;s sad eyes,&amp;rdquo; Malcolm writes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anecdote captures a key theme of Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s autobiography-of-sorts: the alienating experience of being an &amp;eacute;migr&amp;eacute; in a strange land, your personality changed, working out where you fit. Malcolm was four when she boarded one of the last civilian boats from Europe before the war. With the aid of photographs, diaries and letters she weaves an episodic story of her family in their new country: growing up in a Czech community in Manhattan, and the years preceding her career as an acclaimed author and journalist.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Malcolm passed away in 2021 at the age of 86. Her last work is also her first of memoir, after a long career stretching the boundaries of nonfiction. Her book The Silent Woman, a biography of Sylvia Plath, called into question the entire voyeuristic project of biographies. In Forty-One False Starts, about the artist David Salle, she wrote in a disjointed form that merged with Salle&amp;rsquo;s collage-like paintings. The Journalist and the Murderer has become a staple in journalism courses for its biting insights into fraught reporter-subject relationships. Whatever Malcolm wrote about, one obituary said, &amp;ldquo;Her real subject was often the writing process itself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This book sees Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s probing gaze pointed at her own life. She describes a classroom crush, who did not return her affections. &amp;ldquo;I was part of the background of ordinary girls, who secretly loved and, unbeknownst to ourselves, were grateful for the safety of not being loved in return,&amp;rdquo; she writes. She analyses what it means to appear a &amp;ldquo;charming&amp;rdquo; person, to flatter and show attention. &amp;ldquo;When I ask someone a question &amp;ndash; either in life or in work &amp;ndash; I often don&amp;rsquo;t listen to the answer. I am not really interested. (The use of a tape recorder during interviews permits me to counteract this obvious disqualification for my job.)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The strongest sections question memoir itself. Our lives are &amp;ldquo;like photographic negatives&amp;rdquo;, she writes, but only a few are developed into photographs and become our memories. She resists this urge to narrativise life from what sticks out of the fog of time. Her father Joseph &amp;ldquo;loved opera, birds, mushrooms, wildflowers, poetry, baseball... My mind is filled with lovely plotless memories of him.&amp;rdquo; She warns autobiographers against using memories that seem to have a plot &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;conflict, resentment, blame, self-justification&amp;rdquo;. These little flashes make us rethink the reading of all memoir.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Malcolm&amp;rsquo;s relationship to her mother forms the book&amp;rsquo;s emotional core. She looks back &amp;ldquo;ashamed and mortified&amp;rdquo; at her distant young self, unable to give Joan the love she craved. Her mother would spiral into depression when Malcolm left letters unanswered or replied in glib jokes. &amp;ldquo;How could I have been so cruel and callow?&amp;rdquo; she reflects.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Reading Still Pictures, I searched to pinpoint why the book feels so surprising. Some part is no doubt that, in 2010, Malcolm wrote of abandoning autobiography, arguing against its reliance on spotty memory. &amp;ldquo;If an autobiography is to be even minimally readable,&amp;rdquo; she wrote, the autobiographer &amp;ldquo;must not be afraid to invent. Above all he must invent himself.&amp;rdquo; As a journalist she found this repellent. Yet 13 years later, here the book is.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Perhaps hardest to pin down is the question of motive. Malcolm flies past a variety of topics without landing on any definitely. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to know who exactly the book is for. Those interested in memory&amp;rsquo;s slipperiness? At times. Those who escaped persecution to begin life anew? For sections, yes. Fans seeking the person behind her journalism? If so, they&amp;rsquo;re bound to be disappointed (she remains private, leaves too many mysteries unsolved; an affair is mentioned, unexplained, then quickly shuffled offstage). The collection seems to lack a coherence that, if Malcolm herself were reviewing it, she&amp;rsquo;d no doubt spot.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But this may have been her intention all along. Rather than circling around a central theme, like planets orbiting the sun, this engaging little book is more a series of flashing asteroids. And this is a more accurate description of how memory operates than the polished autobiographies in many bookstores. Yet again, Malcolm matches form to function. She gives us shooting stars &amp;ndash; burning brightly in all directions before fizzing out before our eyes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6095/book-review-still-pictures-by-janet-malcolm#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-03-28T04:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-28T04:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Be Tongue-Tied</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/science-cannot-be-tongue-tied/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It might be funny, if it weren’t so worrisome. Recent weeks have seen some absurd new instances of science beset by would-be censors operating under the banner of “inclusion.” Examples are many, and they come from all over the globe. We’ll look at an ongoing controversy in …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978517</id>
    <published>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MARCH 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/open-discussion-march-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978514</id>
    <published>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION FEBRUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/open-discussion-february-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978493</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
