<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-07-08T06:05:42Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Well, that’s going to ruin the weekend</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/well-thats-going-to-ruin-the-weekend/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/rocky-mountain-oyster-stout.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/rocky-mountain-oyster-stout-150x125.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="125" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70662" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/rocky-mountain-oyster-stout-150x125.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/rocky-mountain-oyster-stout-300x249.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/rocky-mountain-oyster-stout.jpg 413w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">No thank you. <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/fox-news-host-rages-against-plant-based-beer-2021-4?op=1">No meaty beer for me</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Larry Kudlow, a Fox Business host and former Trump economic advisor, raged against the idea of “plant-based beer” on his Friday-night show and falsely claimed that President Joe Biden’s climate plan would require Americans to give up meat.</p>
<p>“Get this: America has to stop eating meat, stop eating poultry, fish, seafood, eggs, dairy, and animal-based fats,” Kudlow said. “OK, you got that? No burgers on July 4. No steaks on the barbie. I’m sure middle America is just going to love that. Can you grill those Brussels sprouts?</p>
<p>“So get ready: You can throw back a plant-based beer with your grilled Brussels sprouts and wave your American flag. Call it July 4 green,” Kudlow said.</p>
<p>“Now, I’m making fun of this because I intend to make fun of it. This kind of thinking is stupid,” he added. “It comes from a bunch of ideological zealots who don’t care one whit about America’s well-being. Not one whit.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>None of his claims are true.</p>
<p>Yes, you can grill Brussels sprouts. They’re quite good.</p>
<p>The big news for him is that <em>all</em> beer is plant- (and fungi-) based. A meat-based beer sounds remarkably unpleasant. If Larry and Kid Rock want to try it, though, I wouldn’t stop them.</p>
<p>Larry Kudlow is a lying moron…a typical Republican, I guess. He said this <em>two years ago</em> — has anyone seen any hint of a steak ban?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No thank you. No meaty beer for me. Larry Kudlow, a Fox Business host and former Trump economic advisor, raged against the idea of “plant-based beer” on his Friday-night show and falsely claimed that President Joe Biden’s climate plan would require Americans to give up meat. “Get this: America has to stop eating meat, stop […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70661</id>
    <published>2023-07-07T23:50:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-07T23:50:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reminder: Atheists exposed!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/reminder-atheists-exposed/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;We&amp;#8217;re having this conversation tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/43hXsUQnKr4" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing the other participants are welcoming is opening the comments to critics and serious questioners &amp;#8212; if you want to disagree (politely!) with a gang of atheists, or dissent vigorously, or promote your goofy beliefs, go ahead. Bring it up in the YouTube chat. We&amp;#8217;ll make some time to address those kinds of comments and questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;#8217;t be chicken. You can bravely march into the snake pit of atheists/evolutionists and get bragging rights by surviving.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’re having this conversation tomorrow. One thing the other participants are welcoming is opening the comments to critics and serious questioners — if you want to disagree (politely!) with a gang of atheists, or dissent vigorously, or promote your goofy beliefs, go ahead. Bring it up in the YouTube chat. We’ll make some time to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70659</id>
    <published>2023-07-07T19:59:38Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-07T19:59:38Z</updated>
    <category term="Atheism and Skepticism"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We don’t have beach reading in the Midwest, lacking in oceans</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/we-dont-have-beach-reading-in-the-midwest-lacking-in-oceans/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Since FDotM mentioned how <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/social-media-confusion/">social media can cut into your book-reading time</a>, I thought I’d say that for me, it isn’t true. I can read a book any time I want, and I do. It is my custom to read for an hour before bed, or sometimes over lunch, and I chew through books pretty fast.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/pistols.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/pistols-94x150.jpg" alt="" width="94" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70655" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/pistols-94x150.jpg 94w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/pistols.jpg 136w" sizes="(max-width: 94px) 100vw, 94px"/></a>Sometimes I pick up trash reads. The latest was one called <a href="https://amzn.to/44x32R8"><i>Pistols: A Deep Sea Thriller</i></a> (hint: you know it’s going to be a throw-away when they need to include the genre in the title; sometimes you can just look at the cover). It’s totally ridiculous. It’s about stomatopods that are exposed to toxic waste and swim around, snipping people in half and cooking them with high intensity sonic bursts. My favorite part was when the scientist character has to explain why they also have toxic slime, and starts babbling about ubiquitination, before he has done any kind of analysis of tissue, or even <em>seen</em> one of the monsters. Cheesy, but sometimes you need something silly.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/galatea.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/galatea-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70656" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/galatea-150x150.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/galatea.jpg 232w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p>I’ve also been on a Madeline Miller kick lately, and that’s definitely not cheesy trash. I recently re-read <a href="https://amzn.to/3raAZbA"><i>The Song of Achilles</i></a>, which was magnificent and nearly made me cry. <a href="https://amzn.to/3PRradb"><i>Circe</i></a> is also really, really good and well worth your while. I’m going on a collecting trip in the old Lake Agassiz lands up north this weekend, and picked up her short story, <a href="https://amzn.to/3XKhAL4"><i>Galatea</i></a> for those moments when I’m not chasing spiders.</p>
<p>See? Being an internet nerd is not incompatible with actively reading for entertainment.</p>
<p>Go ahead. Prove your bookworm cred by telling me all the stuff you read for fun. Don’t be shy, and admit to your popcorn reading as well as your high-brow stuff.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since FDotM mentioned how social media can cut into your book-reading time, I thought I’d say that for me, it isn’t true. I can read a book any time I want, and I do. It is my custom to read for an hour before bed, or sometimes over lunch, and I chew through books pretty […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70654</id>
    <published>2023-07-07T13:35:08Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-07T13:35:08Z</updated>
    <category term="Art, Culture, and Humor"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Wisconsin isn’t a popular site for reality</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/wisconsin-isnt-a-popular-site-for-reality/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">I wish we could vaccinate some people with a heavy dose of reality.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine-300x223.jpeg" alt="" width="300" height="223" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-70652" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine-300x223.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine-150x111.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine-768x570.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine-500x371.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/reality-vaccine.jpeg 779w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p>The state next to mine, Wisconsin, has <a href="https://apnews.com/article/republicans-wisconsin-meningitis-chickenpox-vaccine-mandates-5d0b774f8832e75ab8e40e96f7e583c7">gone insane</a>. The raging anti-vax hysteria </p>
<blockquote><p>The Republican-controlled Wisconsin Legislature on Wednesday voted to stop Democratic Gov. Tony Evers’ administration from requiring seventh graders to be vaccinated against meningitis.</p>
<p>The state Senate and Assembly, with all Republicans in support and Democrats against, voted to block the proposal. There is no current meningitis vaccination requirement for Wisconsin students.</p>
<p>The Legislature’s vote also makes it easier for parents to get an exemption from a chicken pox vaccine requirement that is in place for all K-6 students. Evers’ administration wanted to require parents seeking a chicken pox vaccination exemption to provide proof that their child has previously been infected.</p></blockquote>
<p>WHY? These are well-established, safe vaccines against terrible diseases. They work. But somehow, Republicans have got it in their heads that reasonable evidence-based medicine is bad.</p>
<p>This is getting personal, too. My daughter and son-in-law and my little 4 year old granddaughter all live in Wisconsin, and she’ll be attending Wisconsin public schools in a year. I don’t want her to get chicken pox or meningitis. Of course, I trust her parents to get her vaccinated even in the absence of a public health requirement — it’s all the other kids we have to worry about.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I wish we could vaccinate some people with a heavy dose of reality. The state next to mine, Wisconsin, has gone insane. The raging anti-vax hysteria The Republican-controlled Wisconsin Legislature on Wednesday voted to stop Democratic Gov. Tony Evers’ administration from requiring seventh graders to be vaccinated against meningitis. The state Senate and Assembly, with […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70651</id>
    <published>2023-07-07T12:34:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-07T12:34:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Social media confusion!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/07/07/social-media-confusion/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">There are too many options for social media so far. Twitter is dying of a surfeit of Nazis and an incompetent overlord; Bluesky I haven’t tried, but I don’t trust it, since it’s run by the <em>old</em> overlord, and will probably follow the same trajectory; I’ve been on Mastodon for a while, and am comfortable with it; the new kid on the block is Threads, which is owned by the repulsive Zuckerberg. Let’s see what the First Dog on the Moon has to say about it!</p>
<div id="attachment_70649" style="width: 510px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices-500x864.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="864" class="size-large wp-image-70649" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices-500x864.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices-87x150.jpg 87w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices-174x300.jpg 174w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/07/social-media-choices.jpg 686w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a><p class="wp-caption-text"><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2023/jul/07/twitter-is-burning-bluesky-is-smug-where-is-the-best-place-to-do-your-pathetic-doomscrolling">First Dog on the Moon</a></p></div>
<p>I think the final category, “Owner seeks dominion over the Earth,” is definitive, which means I’ll stick with the distributed community of federated websites that lacks an owner.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are too many options for social media so far. Twitter is dying of a surfeit of Nazis and an incompetent overlord; Bluesky I haven’t tried, but I don’t trust it, since it’s run by the old overlord, and will probably follow the same trajectory; I’ve been on Mastodon for a while, and am comfortable […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70648</id>
    <published>2023-07-07T11:57:51Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-07T11:57:51Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How neo-Nazis are radicalising gamers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6137/how-neo-nazis-are-radicalising-gamers#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Graphics from 'Assassin's Creed: Valhalla'" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/valhalla.jpg" height="540" alt="A graphic from Assassin's Creed: Valhalla shows a Viking-esque warrior walking through a battlefield carrying an axe" width="960"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It might seem contradictory that the most hateful viewpoints are often coupled with a yearning for a return to a romantic, idyllic past. In order for any political movement to survive, its leaders have to tell stories about how they think the world should be. On the far right, it usually goes as follows: our lands were once places of unspoiled, awe-inspiring natural beauty. People lived materially tough but spiritually enriching lives, graced with pristine, entirely white, nuclear families, green spaces and physical and psychological strength. The only thing they had to do to protect their way of life was to defend themselves &amp;ndash; unfailingly, violently &amp;ndash; against outsiders.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And if there isn&amp;rsquo;t a period of history that backs up that narrative, you can just invent one. A prime example of this is the far right&amp;rsquo;s celebration of the Vikings &amp;ndash; inaccurately re-envisioned as a singular white race built on glory and bloodshed, with a visually striking and fearsome aesthetic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Nazi party repeatedly adopted Viking and Nordic symbols to craft a fantasy of the Aryan race; the swastika is based on an ancient, Nordic artefact. As alt-right politics rose to the surface of party politics following the election of Donald Trump to the presidency, Norse-age symbols and &amp;ldquo;alt-history&amp;rdquo; also began to reappear. A year later, at the Unite the Right Rally, organised by Richard Spencer, protestors could be seen carrying Thor&amp;rsquo;s hammer as they marched through the streets of Charlottesville &amp;ndash; an event that led to the murder of Heather Heyer, after a participant deliberately drove their car into a crowd of counter-protestors. The Viking helmets seen in the Capitol riots in 2021 were also part of the far right&amp;rsquo;s perversion of Norse folklore and paganism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Around this time, extremism researchers were also becoming concerned with the gaming community, which seemed to be increasingly overrun by violent, extremist imagery and propaganda. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t incidental. When the former Trump strategist Steve Bannon took over US far-right outlet Breitbart, he used his position to encourage Gamergate: an organised, misogynistic online harassment campaign directed against feminist gamers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Recent research from the Global Network of Extremism and Technology (GNET) looks at the weaponisation by the far right of two video games in particular: &lt;em&gt;Assassins Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;. Both are based on an alt-history in which gamers can play out their white supremacist fantasies. &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt; is rooted in Greek and Norse mythology and has been frequently criticised for graphic scenes of violence and portrayals of toxic masculinity. Artwork from &lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; has also been adopted by recognised white supremacist groups and shared online. The study shows how these hyper-real, reconstructed versions of history were adopted by fascists and scattered across the digital space.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Even before the release of &lt;em&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed [Valhalla]&lt;/em&gt;, the game&amp;rsquo;s developers knew it would be used by white supremacists. There was a tonne of pre-warning press saying that they were trying to avoid the game being manipulated by Nazis. The argument you could make, though, is that they have still created this extremely sensationalised version of Vikings which isn&amp;rsquo;t accurate,&amp;rdquo; Dr Ashton Kingdon, a teaching fellow in criminology at the University of Southampton, who authored the report, tells me.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Historical fantasies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; was launched in 2020 as the 12th instalment of the Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed series. It had the biggest launch to date, selling most of its copy within its first week. It is games developer Ubisoft&amp;rsquo;s second most profitable venture, gaining over $1 billion in revenue in 2022. Santa Monica Studio&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt; is a franchise that was originally based on Greek mythology. However, with its 2018 series, the developers decided to incorporate Norse mythology. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to overestimate the popularity of both games. Despite &lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s mixed reviews, the game built up a fan base of 20 million players in just two years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The story of &lt;em&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; centres on Eivor, whom the player can cast as male or female, and their brother Sigurd. It&amp;rsquo;s 873 CE. The siblings&amp;rsquo; backstory is told at the start of the game, over speeding visuals of a luminous, misty forest, as they recount witnessing their parents&amp;rsquo; murder before their eyes. From there, they take to England &amp;ndash; a land already populated with Danes and Norse after years of battle. The task is to gather allies and recruit new soldiers to defend the &amp;ldquo;homeland&amp;rdquo; against England&amp;rsquo;s begrudged four kingdoms: Mercia, East Anglia, Northumbria and Wessex. Players siege castles, set thatched huts alight and generally raid and massacre their way to glory.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an immersive, cinematic game, full of expansive scenes of rolling green hills in Dark Age England. You can also wander through the mountainous terrains of Vinland, an area first discovered by Leif Erikson in 1000 CE, five centuries before Columbus. It&amp;rsquo;s not all killing and pillaging, either. The game throws you into some emotionally testing scenarios. You find yourself ushered into making swift, life-ending decisions over suspected traitors, or unearthing the motivations behind a man who is haunted by the spirit of his dead wife. For some relief, you can sing songs or partake in a drinking game or two.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The attention to detail and artistry are impressive, and the romanticisation might not seem immediately harmful. But when it falls into the wrong hands, an intricate, highly realistic rendition of Viking mythology sends a worrying message. One of the main gripes for historians is the overarching use of the term &amp;ldquo;Viking&amp;rdquo; itself. The idea of the blue-eyed, blonde-haired warrior conquering Europe just isn&amp;rsquo;t true. Viking, Kingdon explains, is actually a verb, alluding to the group&amp;rsquo;s activities. The seafarers settled across the Mediterranean, Caspian, Black, Arctic and North Atlantic seas. They could be distinguishable from Celts or Saxons not because of their ethnicity, but because of their skill in sailing. It was only in the 19th century, when Europe was becoming increasingly nationalistic, that the myth that the Vikings were a superior race &amp;ndash; descended from a genetically pure bloodline &amp;ndash; began to take hold of the popular psyche.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The imaginary locations shown in &lt;em&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; tap into the insidious idea of &amp;ldquo;the hyperborea.&amp;rdquo; As Abbie Richards, an extremism researcher, succinctly puts it in a video explainer: &amp;ldquo;Hyperborea was this ancient, high civilisation where the Aryan race &amp;ndash; white people &amp;ndash; lived in paradise before they were forced to mix with other races. It&amp;rsquo;s a racist fairytale used to perpetuate white supremacy and to justify racist violence. This stuff is racist and antisemitic but also coded enough that people just engage with it like it&amp;rsquo;s just a story.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The term is rooted in esoteric Nazism, what Richards describes as &amp;ldquo;white supremacy disguised as a web of metaphysical and mystical nonsense. This flavour of Nazism is obsessed with the mythical Aryan race and restoring it [even though] it was never a thing.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Violence and video games&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, should we worry about these games and others like them? Not necessarily, but it&amp;rsquo;s a difficult line to toe. Researchers have emphasised that it&amp;rsquo;s not about the games themselves as much as how they are used. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing that&amp;rsquo;s inherent in video games that leads people towards extremist views or actions, nor is it the case that the violence within gaming &amp;ndash; or any other medium, like horror films or music &amp;ndash; will act as a form of radicalisation. In 2020, reanalysis of often-cited 2008 research from the American Psychological Association rebuffed claims that video games lead to an increase in aggressive behaviour. On the contrary, after reviewing 28 papers, the Royal Society for Open Science proposed that video games could have a positive impact on cognition and self-regulation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Moral panics surrounding video games do not help to answer the complex question of why some people commit unthinkable acts. It&amp;rsquo;s a kind of pseudo-psychology that sweeps aside structural issues, like regulation in technology and mental health care. By robbing people of their agency, it fails to hold the powerful to account. The National Rifle Association regularly blames video games for mass shootings to deflect from conversations on gun control. Following the shooting in Parkland, Florida in 2018, Trump said that &amp;ldquo;we have to do something ... I&amp;rsquo;m hearing more and more people say the level of violence on video games is really shaping young people&amp;rsquo;s thoughts.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Would it be possible for an ordinary person without any particularly strong political leanings to spend hours playing &lt;em&gt;Assassins Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; and emerge as a neo-Nazi? Kingdon doesn&amp;rsquo;t think so. &amp;ldquo;No, I think it&amp;rsquo;s ridiculous to blame the games themselves for radicalisation. Video games themselves don&amp;rsquo;t create terrorists because the narratives in these games are not extreme. It&amp;rsquo;s more about the way they&amp;rsquo;ve been manipulated and weaponised as propaganda,&amp;rdquo; she says.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Meme wars&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;To really understand radicalisation in technology, we need to understand online subcultures and communities. Gaming has historically been seen as a space for men; games are marketed towards men, and have a history of casual misogyny. Female gamers, journalists and developers are often seen as intruders in this space and are targeted accordingly. At the start of Gamergate in 2014, feminists in gaming seeking better representation in storylines and the industry itself faced an onslaught of online abuse and threats. It is now widely acknowledged that this wasn&amp;rsquo;t just organic. White supremacist groups used Gamergate as a political recruiting tool. Steve Bannon described how he was able to identify gamers as &amp;ldquo;These guys, these rootless white males [who] had monster power.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As alt-right figures used Gamergate to drum up support for Trump in online, misogynistic spaces, the neo-pagan, hypermasculine figures in alternative history video games have captured the same fan base. While there are plenty of women playing video games they are often still seen as unserious consumers of more violent games marketed to men. In 2022, the Bryter annual gamers study found that an increasing number of women were playing video games, but that 72 per cent of them had experienced some form of harassment, with 36 per cent of them experiencing it regularly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It might seem impossible to understand why anyone in society today would be drawn to the same Aryan race myths deployed in propaganda nearly a century ago. But many right-wing groups are adept at understanding and manipulating the language and imagery that young people, or at least some young people, can relate to. &amp;ldquo;The alt right knows that it won&amp;rsquo;t ever be able to get power in the ballot box. The only way they can attempt to gain influence is by shifting things culturally. They use images and symbols not just in games, but in meme culture too,&amp;rdquo; says Kingdon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In her book &lt;em&gt;Meme Wars: The Untold Story of the Online Battles&lt;/em&gt;, Joan Donovan describes how the right were able to capture audiences by offering simple, emotive images and slogans designed to be repeated and reshared across the internet: &amp;ldquo;Meme wars are culture wars, accelerated and intensified because of the infrastructure and incentives of the internet, which trades outrage and extremity as currency, rewards speed and scale, and flattens the experience of the world into a never-ending scroll of images and words, a morass capable of swallowing patience, kindness and understanding.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;, too, went through what researchers would describe as a form of memification. By taking screenshots and images from games like these and reposting them online as memes, extremists are able to instruct recruits on how they should be consumed and interpreted. GNET&amp;rsquo;s research points out that in 2018, an Italian far-right activist, Luca Triani, carried out a drive-by shooting in Marceta, where he injured five men and one woman of African origin. Triani was draped in an Italian flag and shouting &amp;ldquo;Viva l&amp;rsquo;Italia.&amp;rdquo; The shooting is thought to have acted as a motivation for the Christchurch attacks in 2019. Triani may have been acting alone, but he was not a &amp;ldquo;lone wolf&amp;rdquo;. The attack came a month before Italy&amp;rsquo;s general election, with parties of almost all political stripes blaming immigrants for frictions in society and a weakened economy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;His actions also had repercussions in a section of the gaming community, where he became a symbol around which the far right could rally. On Gab, a tech platform popular with social media users on the far right, a widely circulated meme shows Triani portrayed as the leading character in &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;, known as Kratos. It was first posted shortly after the attack.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;'Not Viking enough'&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fortunately, it&amp;rsquo;s only a small number of people operating in gaming that are locked into these highly distorted views of society. But when these views do appear, they are as deliberately grotesque as possible. A cursory look on Reddit, which I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend for anyone&amp;rsquo;s sanity, reveals users complaining that &lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rsquo;s developers Ubisoft have caved in to external pressure and become &amp;ldquo;too woke&amp;rdquo;. The most pressing concern on the thread is that there is no opportunity to rape anyone in the game, which didn&amp;rsquo;t make it &amp;ldquo;Viking&amp;rdquo; enough &amp;ndash; a complaint that&amp;rsquo;s been repeated on several forums. (It&amp;rsquo;s worth mentioning that no popular video game, including &lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt;, offers this function.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to police some of the behaviour in online gaming communities as so much of it is steeped in irony and humour. There&amp;rsquo;s no way of being able to tell if someone sharing a meme or even stating something vulgar or offensive is planning a terrorist act, or even if they believe in what they&amp;rsquo;re saying in any sense. Sometimes, a meme with deeply hidden connotations with the far right has been repeated so many times that it is stripped of its meaning and appears as a simple joke. Even the most advanced of analysts are usually unable to pinpoint someone&amp;rsquo;s motivations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean nothing can be done. TikTok banned the term &amp;ldquo;hyperborea&amp;rdquo; from its search function after fake videos claiming to show forgotten, hidden snow civilisations received millions of views. That won&amp;rsquo;t stop TikTok users who are so inclined to find alternative ways of posting esoteric Nazi content through using similar hashtags, but it at least shows that those holding the reins in big tech are aware of these far-right dog whistles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There have been attempts within the gaming community to tackle toxic attitudes through broader representation in storylines. &lt;em&gt;Valhalla&lt;/em&gt;, for example, includes a female protagonist, while &lt;em&gt;God of War: Ragnar&amp;ouml;k&lt;/em&gt;, launched in 2021, has also included Black, female characters. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell, however, how cynical these inclusions may turn out to be.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While developers may protest that no one can know how any fictional work will be used and adapted, this can also be argued as a reason to be more cautious. The GNET research showed that the developers of &lt;em&gt;Assassin&amp;rsquo;s Creed: Valhalla&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;God of War&lt;/em&gt; were aware that the games risked indulging the far right. And yet they still gave their players storylines that recycled dangerous prejudices. Meanwhile, Ubisoft made over $2 billion in revenue in 2022 alone. In an increasingly right-wing political landscape, games developers and technology companies making extortionate profits can afford to tell a different story.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here for access to the full magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6137/how-neo-nazis-are-radicalising-gamers#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-07-06T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-06T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Church in crisis</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6142/the-church-in-crisis#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="St Lawrence's church in Castle Rising, Norfolk. Credit: Alamy" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/rodell1.jpg" height="913" alt="St Lawrence's church in Castle Rising, Norfolk" width="1368"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By all accounts, Philip North is a very nice man. In fact, the Church of England, which appointed him as Bishop of Blackburn in January 2022, contains a lot of decent, well-meaning people. Unfortunately many of them are rather upset, because Philip North is opposed to the ordination of women priests.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Apparently he does not object to women having authority over men, and has no problem working with women priests. But he does not think the Church of England should unilaterally take decisions which should be made together with the Roman Catholic, Orthodox and other Anglican churches. This is 30 years after the Church first accepted women priests, and seven years after it appointed its first female bishop.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Just after North&amp;rsquo;s appointment came the recommendations from a five-year study by Church of England bishops, supported by its General Synod after an emotional debate, that the Church should continue to deny church marriages to same-sex couples, but instead &amp;ldquo;lament and repent of the failure&amp;hellip; to be welcoming to LGBTQI+ people&amp;rdquo; and provide &amp;ldquo;prayers of thanksgiving, dedication and for God&amp;rsquo;s blessing&amp;rdquo; for same-sex couples married in civil ceremonies. At the same time, they voted to reaffirm the doctrine that marriage is only between a man and a woman.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Archbishop of Canterbury, Justin Welby, also leads the global Anglican Communion, where &amp;ldquo;The average Anglican is a woman in sub-Saharan Africa in her thirties&amp;rdquo;. Anglican churches in the global south are vehemently opposed to same-sex marriage. He avoided a schism at the Communion&amp;rsquo;s 2022 Lambeth Conference by persuading delegates to agree to disagree, while reaffirming a 1998 statement &amp;ldquo;rejecting homosexual practice as incompatible with Scripture&amp;rdquo;. After the Synod&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;blessings&amp;rdquo; decision, he said he would not be giving any personally, and made emollient remarks to African bishops.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was not enough. The Global South Fellowship of Anglican Churches, which represents 10 of the 42 provinces in the Anglican Communion, responded by withdrawing its recognition of Justin Welby as the Communion&amp;rsquo;s leader, stating that the Church of England was &amp;ldquo;disqualified&amp;rdquo; as their historic &amp;ldquo;Mother Church&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And the problem will not go away within the Church of England itself. &amp;ldquo;We love and bless you, but your relationships are second class&amp;rdquo; is not a sustainable message.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These are not the only ethical challenges facing the Church. The Independent Inquiry into Child Sex Abuse reported in 2020 that it had failed to protect children. More abuse revelations surfaced in 2022. It also has an ethnic issue. According to Mike Royal, the Pentecostal head of Churches Together in England: &amp;ldquo;Urban Anglican Churches depend on black membership for their backbone.&amp;rdquo; Yet a report on the General Synod early in 2022 was headed: &amp;ldquo;Lord Boateng holds Synod&amp;rsquo;s feet to the fire over Church&amp;rsquo;s racism record.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A cliff edge&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;You may think, &amp;ldquo;So what if the Church ties itself in knots?&amp;rdquo; But these are symptoms of a bigger underlying issue which affects us all. To understand it, we need to look behind the &amp;ldquo;Less than half of England and Wales population identifies as Christian&amp;rdquo; headlines which accompanied the 2021 Census results. The Census is unrivalled when it comes to local detail, but provides no analysis of &amp;ldquo;Christian&amp;rdquo;. Fortunately we have the British Social Attitudes Survey (BSAS), which asks a more refined question about religious belonging, and provides a denominational breakdown.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What it tells us is that Anglican identity is falling off a cliff. In the mid-1980s, around two in five British adults considered themselves Anglican. Now, half of British adults have no religious identity. Of the 40 per cent identifying as Christian, only a third are Anglicans. Around a fifth are Catholics, with the rest a mix of declining Nonconformist churches, and growing Orthodox, Pentecostal and smaller denominations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On the face of it, the Church has massive potential influence over the country&amp;rsquo;s young people. It controls a quarter of England&amp;rsquo;s state-funded primary schools, and some secondaries. Often they have faith-based admission criteria, and in many places the Church primary school is the only practical option for parents. A few years ago, the then chair of the Church&amp;rsquo;s board of education, John Pritchard, called for clergy to be trained to use its schools to extend the Church&amp;rsquo;s mission: &amp;ldquo;The clergy ought to have a camp bed in there.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it is not working. The main driver of decline is not Anglicans leaving, but children of Anglicans not carrying on with the faith. While a third of people aged 75 and over identify with the Church, only one in a hundred under-25s do. One per cent. English Anglicanism is literally dying.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Looking at practice rather than identity, the mathematician John Hayward applied the &amp;ldquo;R number&amp;rdquo; methodology familiar from Covid-19 to church attendance data, and concluded that the Church of England would become extinct around 2060. The response from Stephen Cottrell, the Archbishop of York, was that &amp;ldquo;the church of Jesus Christ is not an organisation that lives or dies by graphs going up and down&amp;rdquo;. This is the man who, in 2021, proposed a new growth strategy involving the establishment of 10,000 new lay-led churches over 10 years &amp;ndash; around three a day &amp;ndash; a plan which led Canon Angela Tilby to wonder whether &amp;ldquo;in a desperate attempt to avoid facing&amp;hellip; reality, we have entered a state of corporate psychosis: a leap into false consciousness&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Speaking in tongues&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;As well as shrinking, the Church is changing. For some time, it has been moving in an evangelical, and especially &amp;ldquo;charismatic&amp;rdquo; direction: the form of Christianity featuring personal experiences of the Holy Spirt, healing miracles, and speaking in tongues, a practice which Justin Welby says he began aged 19.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A key vehicle has been the Alpha Course, which began at the &amp;ndash; very posh &amp;ndash; Holy Trinity Brompton (HTB) Anglican Church in Kensington. It spread rapidly in the 1990s across the Church of England, and to other denominations and other countries, promising &amp;ldquo;an opportunity to explore the meaning of life&amp;rdquo;. HTB is now a major force in the Church, with nearly 100 churches in its network. But it has not stemmed the Church&amp;rsquo;s overall decline.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To understand this decline, it&amp;rsquo;s useful to make a distinction between &amp;ldquo;societal&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;congregational&amp;rdquo; religion. In the past, the Church of England was &amp;ldquo;societal&amp;rdquo;: some people went to services, others just on special occasions. But most people felt they somehow belonged. That no longer applies. Evangelical Anglicanism is &amp;ldquo;congregational&amp;rdquo;. Its members are aware that many others think some of their practices bizarre, or their views strange. But they&amp;rsquo;ve come to Jesus, and face a sinful world together.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet, as we shall see, there are reasons why this smaller, increasingly evangelical, less &amp;ldquo;white&amp;rdquo; and more female entity will not simply take its place among others as it sinks into our diverse religion and belief landscape. The Church&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;established&amp;rdquo; status is under increasing pressure, both because of its decline and because of its position on same-sex marriage. Yet Justin Welby still wants to keep the privileges that establishment brings, including 26 bishops in the House of Lords.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He is not alone in wanting the Church to remain a part of the state. According to Bristol University&amp;rsquo;s Tariq Modood, minority faiths also like this arrangement, in the belief that it provides a &amp;ldquo;canopy&amp;rdquo; of respect for all people of religious faith. It may go further than respect. There was some discussion, after Queen Elizabeth II&amp;rsquo;s death, as to whether our new monarch should retain the role of Supreme Governor of the Church of England (see Andrew Copson in the Winter 2022 issue of New Humanist). Among the minority voices who spoke in favour of King Charles III&amp;rsquo;s taking on the &amp;ldquo;Defender of the Faith&amp;rdquo; title was (Lord) Daniel Finkelstein, who expressed his belief that the role did more than protect the Anglican community. &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;as a Jew I feel I cannot be fully secure in respect for my own religion unless assurance is given by someone secure in what they themselves believe.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In a recent survey for the think-tank Theos, a third of all non-religious people in the UK agreed that &amp;ldquo;Religion is comparable to the smallpox virus, but harder to eradicate&amp;rdquo; (it&amp;rsquo;s important to note that this doesn&amp;rsquo;t account for a third of all humanists.) That sounds like &amp;ldquo;contempt for all religion&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; although, importantly, it does not mean &amp;ldquo;contempt for all religious people&amp;rdquo;. Meanwhile, there is no evidence that the established Church does anything to protect against antisemitism, or anti-Muslim prejudice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Clearly we must be careful not to allow an uncomprehending religious/non-religious divide to damage the country. The end of establishment for the Church of England, when it comes, might usefully be accompanied by a reassurance that human rights, including freedom of religion or belief, remain protected.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Financial atonement&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are also the finances to consider. We still have 16,000 Anglican church buildings, nearly 80 per cent of them &amp;ldquo;listed&amp;rdquo; by Historic England, many with small congregations.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Operating and maintaining old buildings takes a lot of money. Fortunately, the Church has plenty of it. Unlike a company, with a Chief Executive and an annual report, the Church&amp;rsquo;s finances are complex. In 2016, Ed Moore, then Treasurer of the National Secular Society, attempted to estimate its total wealth. He came up with over &amp;pound;22 billion. Today, Church Commissioners manage &amp;pound;10 billion in assets, in addition to the &amp;pound;5 billion or so held by the 42 dioceses. Over the past 30 years, the Commissioners claim their average return has been an impressive 10 per cent. All of this is tax free (see Emma Park on page 42).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;From a purely financial viewpoint, then, the Church Commissioners could carry on indefinitely. Meanwhile, its diminishing band of parishioners manage to raise &amp;pound;1 billion each year, but say they are desperately starved of funds. Although the Commissioners have recently increased their funding for the Church&amp;rsquo;s operations, Justin Welby says the purpose is to provide &amp;ldquo;support for mission so every person might hear the Good News of Jesus Christ&amp;hellip; [and] support our aims to double the number of children and young disciples by 2030&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The reaction from parish level was therefore predictable when the Church announced it would spend &amp;pound;100 million to atone for the fact that some of its wealth &amp;ndash; equivalent to &amp;pound;1.4 billion in today&amp;rsquo;s money according to one calculation &amp;ndash; can be traced back to investments in slavery in the 18th century. The money would go on a &amp;ldquo;programme of investment, research and engagement&amp;rdquo; including funding to support &amp;ldquo;communities affected by historic slavery&amp;rdquo;. Nothing wrong with that, of course. But Rev Marcus Walker, chairman of Save The Parish, was understandably upset: &amp;ldquo;After decades of telling us that there is no money to fund the churches and priests who keep the church alive on the front line, suddenly they&amp;rsquo;ve found &amp;pound;100 million behind the back of the sofa.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are no easy solutions to the problem of large numbers of listed buildings little used for their original purpose as places of worship. But a diminished Church cannot expect to protect a legacy of enormous wealth and tax-exempt investments, while at the same time starving its parishes and relying on charities, with a bit of government support, to conserve its estate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One beneficial use is as a base for local social action, of which the Church is rightly proud. Yes, plenty of non-religious people make important contributions here, as do non-Christian faith groups. But the Church has a physical presence in a lot more places, providing the infrastructure for foodbanks, playgroups and places to go in emergencies. As the traditional model of churches and vicars becomes increasingly unsustainable, new solutions will be needed to keep the social action baby while the Anglican bathwater flows away.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Hollowed out&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the time being at least, the Church retains a carapace of a great national institution: massive wealth; still-significant power; a substantial bureaucracy, both centrally and duplicated across 42 dioceses (with more senior clergy now than 20 years ago); buildings in virtually every city, town and village, many of cultural importance; the Head of State as its Supreme Governor, reflecting its established status; and control over a quarter of the country&amp;rsquo;s state-funded primary schools.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But inside the carapace, it is hollowed out. While many appreciate its social work, musical tradition, buildings and people, a rapidly diminishing number identify with it, share its metaphysical beliefs, subscribe to its positions on LGBTQI+ equality &amp;ndash; and still, in some places, gender equality &amp;ndash; or attend its services.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You would not know that by reading its strategy. Its vision is still to be &amp;ldquo;A Church for the whole nation which is Jesus Christ centred, and shaped by, the five marks of mission&amp;rdquo;, the first two of which are all about evangelism and proselytisation. As well as becoming &amp;ldquo;younger and more diverse&amp;rdquo;, its strategic priorities are to become a church of &amp;ldquo;missionary disciples&amp;rdquo;, where &amp;ldquo;every person in England has access to an enriching and compelling community of faith by adding new churches and new forms of Church.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is the &amp;ldquo;corporate psychosis&amp;rdquo; speaking. Sooner or later, reality must strike, and the carapace adapt to its contents. The question is how this major transition will take place, over what period, and what sort of creature will emerge at the end. We all have an interest in the answer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whatever happens, there is no case for a diminished Church to have a privileged status in the constitution of a plural, and increasingly non-&lt;br&gt;religious, country. Establishment, and with it bishops in the House of Lords, needs to go. And an institution with an evangelical agenda overtly targeting young people should not be in control of state-funded schools.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Aside from that, maybe a values-based approach offers a way forward. Many people would agree with the other &amp;ldquo;Marks of Mission&amp;rsquo;&amp;rsquo;, which are about social justice, violence reduction, peace and reconciliation, and the environment. Instead of faith-based structures accommodating people with a range of values, could there be values-based structures accommodating people with a range of beliefs?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Maybe a new values-based body, or local community trusts, should take ownership of many of the buildings, and most of the wealth, with the Church becoming one of many users of its spaces. Perhaps such a body could find a way, without erasing the history, to provide a community focus without the religious baggage, where everyone locally could feel at home, irrespective of their beliefs, ethnicity, education or income &amp;ndash; an increasingly important need in a fractured society.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But conversations about a realistic future are hard to envisage while Church leaders continue in their &amp;ldquo;state of false consciousness&amp;rdquo;. Accepting and managing decline is hard, especially when you think your mission is God-given. But at some stage, something has to give.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6142/the-church-in-crisis#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-07-04T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-04T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JULY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/07/open-discussion-july-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978562</id>
    <published>2023-07-01T08:00:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-07-01T08:00:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A history of women's desire</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6135/a-history-of-womens-desire#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="'The Circle of Love' (1917) by Gerda Wegener. Credit: Bridgeman Images" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/bal_79151.jpg" height="782" alt="'The Circle of Love' by Gerda Wegener is a painting from 1917 depicting an erotic relationship between two women" width="800"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A recent YouGov poll asked Britons about their &amp;ldquo;love language&amp;rdquo;. The survey referred to US author Gary Chapman&amp;rsquo;s concept of the &amp;ldquo;five love languages,&amp;rdquo; which are summarised as quality time, words of affirmation, gifts, acts of service and touch. To most British men and women, praise and time together were the preferred ways to feel loved by their partners. But some of the results were strikingly gendered. Over 20 per cent of men placed utmost importance on physical touch, while only 7 per cent of women cared about it. The figures were practically flipped when it came to acts of service, considered to be &amp;ldquo;helping&amp;rdquo; or doing those little things that make someone&amp;rsquo;s life easier.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The poll, while not straightforwardly pernicious, is nonetheless problematic. The idea of &amp;ldquo;love languages&amp;rdquo; is a piece of pop psychology, rather than a scientific phenomenon. The results reinforce the idea that, when it comes to love, men value sex, while women value atonement.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Historian Eleanor Janega is concerned about the way concepts such as &amp;ldquo;love languages&amp;rdquo; are being co-opted. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re seeing a lot of reactionary ideas come to the forefront and a real pushing of the idea that women are first and foremost baby machines, and that we exist in this biological capacity where we are always and for ever at a kind of disadvantage to men,&amp;rdquo; Janega said at the 2 March launch of her latest book, &lt;em&gt;The Once and Future Sex&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Misogynist propagandists like Jordan Peterson and Andrew Tate often push this notion that women are naturally nurturing and subdued beings, corrupted by feminist ideology. Men, in turn, are instinctive, corporeal creatures. In response, Janega decided to do a &amp;ldquo;real deep-dive, historical look at gender&amp;rdquo;, reminding us all that its perceived natures and assigned duties are blatantly socially constructed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For this, she turned to a historic period that is relatively unexamined when it comes to the female perspective, let alone when related to sex and desire. &lt;em&gt;The Once and Future Sex&lt;/em&gt; explores the ways in which women were seen in the course of the roughly 1,000 years we call the Middle Ages. Between the fifth and 15th century, the book shows, women weren&amp;rsquo;t seen as inherently frigid homebodies or delusional romantics. As Janega puts it, &amp;ldquo;the majority of recorded European history thinks that women are innately sex-crazed.&amp;rdquo; Similarly, her research shows how the great majority of women in the Middle Ages worked outside the home, in the fields, as shop- or innkeepers, as midwives or maids, or in the many industries and crafts of the period.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Women were also not seen as exceptional when holding jobs, even when married with children. In fact, those who could proficiently run household or business accounts and manage staff were understood as assets and better wives. The &lt;em&gt;Once and Future Sex&lt;/em&gt; is peppered with such examples and anecdotes, helping us not only humanise our foremothers, but also remember how profoundly historically contextual our ideas of women are. With stories like that of the 15th-century London wool merchant Rose of Burford, who upon her husband&amp;rsquo;s death continued running the business and even settled fiscal arrangements with the crown, or of her French contemporary Christine de Pizan, the court author who wrote the &amp;ldquo;equivalent of a medieval best seller&amp;rdquo;, &lt;em&gt;The Book of the City of Ladies&lt;/em&gt;, Janega spurs you on until the final page.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Her conclusion is that, while those 1,000 years are indeed the pillars upon which western societies are built, medieval people and their thoughts are not transposable to our times, nor can they possibly serve as illustration to contemporary sexist tropes. On the contrary, as Janega writes, &amp;ldquo;seeing the past and rejecting it allows us to imagine new futures and make the changes that are necessary to create a more equitable world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is in the spirit of creating a more equitable world that journalist Sophie K. Rosa&amp;rsquo;s debut book &lt;em&gt;Radical Intimacy&lt;/em&gt; is written. With great diligence, Rosa goes about exploring the ways in which our socioeconomic system robs us of authentic and liberatory intimacy. The book explores alternative narratives for love and intimacy, reporting on the communities who have over the last century proven that there is life beyond the mainstream norms &amp;ndash; not only when it comes to romance and family, but also wider issues like death and home ownership, friendship, care and solidarity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an ambitious book by a great reporter, and the research is exhaustive: from the Gay Liberation Front London communes of the 1970s to today&amp;rsquo;s Campaign for Psych Abolition, fighting against the incarcerating and often punitive nature of psychiatric care. But one keeps wanting to hear Rosa&amp;rsquo;s voice through the beautifully woven stats and quotes. While the introduction feels like a rousing call to arms, the rest of the book reads like a collection of journalistic pieces.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Despite their very different topics, Janega and Rosa&amp;rsquo;s books work well in tandem. Where one confronts misinformed tropes with the real lives of women living 500 years ago, the other shows us that there is nothing inevitable about patriarchal or heteronormative relations: we are living side by side with the alternatives.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Both prove vital reading in a world struggling for palliative answers and often resorting to regressive ideologies. Both provide hope. And both prove how women do not uniformly fit into the boxes provided by pseudo-scientific theories like the five love languages. Women have been sex workers, sole landowners, squatters, carers, artists, asexual, bisexual, queer or not identifying as women at all. And all these people, past and present, have experienced moments of authenticity and moments of intimacy &amp;ndash; not just in spite of, but often because of, their idiosyncrasies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Eleanor Janega's "The Once and Future Sex" is published by W. W. Norton &amp;amp; Company&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sophie K. Rosa's "Radical Intimacy" is published by Pluto Press&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here for access to the full magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6135/a-history-of-womens-desire#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-29T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-29T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>We are back!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/06/28/we-are-back/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

<div class="wp-block-image">
<figure class="alignleft is-resized"><img data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" class="wp-image-13712" width="488" height="488" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=488&amp;h=488 488w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=976&amp;h=976 976w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=300 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=768 768w" sizes="(max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px"/></figure></div>


<p>I am delighted to say that the second series of our On Your Mind podcast has launched today!!</p>



<p>Each week, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will explore aspects of the human psyche, including astrology, how the clothes we wear influence our thoughts, attraction, friendship, dreaming, mind control and much much more.  We will also be joined by some special guests as we attempt to answer all of your questions about psychology. The first series reached No.1 in Apple Podcast’s Science charts, and so we hope that you can join us. </p>



<p>Our first episode looks at creativity and explores how to have good ideas and whether children are more creative than adults. You can listen <a href="https://open.spotify.com/show/2txmeCf9U2rj4aAdMLoczK">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to say that the second series of our On Your Mind podcast has launched today!! Each week,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/06/28/we-are-back/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">We are back!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13884</id>
    <published>2023-06-28T16:36:48Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-28T16:36:48Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Protect Itself. It Needs Our Help.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/06/science-cannot-protect-itself-it-needs-our-help/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It can be easy to take science for granted, to mistakenly believe there is a universal understanding of its importance and agreement about its value and function. Of course, we know that isn’t true. In the new issue of Skeptical Inquirer, Jerry Coyne and Luana Maroja deliver …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978555</id>
    <published>2023-06-27T18:41:11Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-27T18:41:11Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Mussolini in Myth and Memory</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6134/book-review-mussolini-in-myth-and-memory#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img title="Mussolini in 1935. Credit: Alamy Stock Photo" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Mussolini.jpg" height="1007" alt="Benito Mussolini stands on a podium in 1935" width="1368"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mussolini in Myth and Memory: The First Totalitarian Dictator&lt;/strong&gt; (Oxford University Press) by Paul Corner&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The United States is not the only democracy flirting with the idea of destroying itself. Russians, Romanians, Italians &amp;ndash; people from all over the world are falling back in love with dictators and dictatorships they fervently rejected not too long ago. Joseph Stalin, declared a criminal by his successors, is now being depicted alongside Vladimir Putin as a strong, feared leader. Nicolae Ceaușescu, who upon his arrest was executed as quickly as possible so he wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be lynched by his own followers, was remembered favourably by 65 per cent of Romanians, according to a 2018 survey. Even Benito Mussolini, whose mutilated body was hung upside down at the Piazzale Loreto in Milan, somehow managed to gain the sympathy of the children and grandchildren of the Italians who celebrated his death.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;How did we get here? Using Italy as a case study, Paul Corner&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Mussolini in Myth and Memory &lt;/em&gt;argues it all comes down to collective memory, the way it forms and is manipulated. Faced with problems like economic recession, political instability and changing social norms, people seek refuge in &amp;ldquo;phantom utopias&amp;rdquo;: augmented versions of the past in which memories of violence and suppression are themselves suppressed. Corner builds on ideas introduced by Russian sociologist Lev Gudkov (&amp;ldquo;Soviet ideological slogans get reborn in the mass consciousness, but are mistaken for a reality &amp;ndash; a phantom utopia &amp;ndash; that never existed&amp;rdquo;) and filmmaker Pier Paolo Pasolini (&amp;ldquo;We are a country without memory, which is like saying without history. Italy removes its recent past&amp;hellip; keeping only those memories, those fragments that might be useful for its contortions, its conversions&amp;rdquo;) to create an original, insightful study of the 20th century and its aftermath.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Each chapter identifies a popular misconception about Mussolini&amp;rsquo;s rule, discerns the purpose it serves in present-day Italy and gathers historical evidence to show why it is incorrect. Examples include: Mussolini made the trains run on time; Mussolini destroyed the mafia; siding with Nazi Germany was Mussolini&amp;rsquo;s one key mistake; and Mussolini alone bears responsibility for Italy&amp;rsquo;s actions before and during the Second World War. The notion that Mussolini reduced crime betrays frustration with the slow-moving administration of justice in bureaucratic democracies, just as the belief that Mussolini introduced pensions is rooted in financial insecurity. In truth, writes Corner, there is no evidence to suggest he made Italy less criminal, and while his regime did extend pensions, the foundations of those systems were put in place long before he rose to power. The misconception that Mussolini is responsible for Italy&amp;rsquo;s actions is a double-edged sword. On the one hand, it absolves Italians from the guilt of the war crimes they committed. On the other, it reinforces the image of Mussolini as all-powerful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Corner admittedly focuses more on the past than the present &amp;ndash; a bit disappointing considering the book&amp;rsquo;s title promises readers they will learn how the former is contained in the latter. Instead of merely reframing the work of other historians, it would have been fitting to see him devote a bit more time and energy to those aspects that make&lt;em&gt; Mussolini in Myth and Memory&lt;/em&gt; unique. But popular opinion on Mussolini &amp;ndash; or any other subject &amp;ndash; is difficult to pin down without resorting to surveys and statistical research, which would have slowed the book&amp;rsquo;s arresting pace.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If you want to get a better understanding of the rise, fall and persistence of fascism, this is a good book to start with. Corner&amp;rsquo;s central theme of collective memory and phantom utopias gives the reader a theoretical framework through which to organise information provided by other, more conventional studies. Corner, who served as the director of the Centre for the Study of Totalitarian Regimes in Siena, is doing more than fact-checking fake news. His is a study of how fake news &amp;ndash; for lack of a better term &amp;ndash; enters the world and warps it accordingly.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here for access to the full magazine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6134/book-review-mussolini-in-myth-and-memory#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-27T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-27T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What supporting my father through Alzheimer's taught me</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6133/what-supporting-my-father-through-alzheimers-taught-me#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="'Old Man in Sorrow' by Vincent van Gogh. Credit: Alamy" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/CRKX0E.jpg" height="1890" alt="'Old Man in Sorrow' by Vincent van Gogh" width="1519"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In November 1901 a woman named Auguste Deter was admitted to the Municipal Asylum for Epileptics and Lunatics in Frankfurt. She was 51 years old. Paranoid delusions about her husband&amp;rsquo;s fidelity had given way to amnesia and disorientation; she failed to recognise old friends and forgot life&amp;rsquo;s daily occurrences the moment they were past. Soon she was unable to look after herself entirely. &amp;ldquo;I have lost myself,&amp;rdquo; she told her 36-year-old physician. His name was Dr Alois Alzheimer.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alzheimer was that rare thing at the turn of the 20th century, a doctor with an interest in both psychiatry, the workings of the mind, and histology, the study of cell tissue and structure. When he examined Deter&amp;rsquo;s brain after her eventual death in 1906, he found it alarmingly atrophied, abnormally light. Then, looking at it under the microscope, he saw two things he had never seen before. First, the buildup of a brain protein named beta-amyloid into what are known as &amp;ldquo;senile plaques&amp;rdquo;; second, dense tangles of fibrils within the brain&amp;rsquo;s cells that had gone rogue, as it were, choking and ultimately destroying the cells themselves. The damage was greatest where the tangles and the plaques coincided. As many as a third of the cells in Deter&amp;rsquo;s cerebral cortex were destroyed or damaged.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If it seems paradoxical that one of the definitive diseases of old age should have been first identified in someone much younger, Alzheimer himself regarded his discovery as a disease of middle age and entirely distinct from senile dementia. It was a view that held until the 1970s, when it became clear that they were essentially the same phenomenon; the neurologist Robert Katzman showed that Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s was one of the leading causes of death in the US, its presence in the deceased elided by a wide range of more immediately catastrophic health events recorded on the death certificate.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Somehow it seems apt for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s to be hiding in plain sight like that. It is after all a disease of deception, its presence masked in the patient by the general cognitive decline that we all experience once we pass the age of 50 or so. This can be compounded by the patient&amp;rsquo;s own unwillingness or inability to recognise or acknowledge the disease as it encroaches, and by the person&amp;rsquo;s stubborn, desperate retention of routine and behaviour &amp;ndash; even while memory and, arguably, identity crumble around them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;My father died of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s three days after his 90th birthday in May 2016. He had been admitted with sepsis four days earlier, but his renal functions had been failing, resulting in repeated spells in hospital, since the previous autumn. There was one long spell of about a month in the spring from which he never really rallied. All semblance of independent life ended. There were four 15-minute visits from health workers spread across the empty plain of the day, and then soon a nurse staying overnight in case he accidentally pulled his catheter out &amp;ndash; and, more generally, to comfort a newfound panic that overwhelmed him when he was alone, particularly at night.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It can&amp;rsquo;t have been much more than a week into this new restricted life that he stopped coming downstairs, or even getting out of bed. He ate less and less. By this time he was incontinent as well as cathetered and had lost any sense of the indignity of the experience, lost his sense of privacy, of decency, of inhibition. He would have been appalled, had he known. He was, I would have said, a proud man; he wanted to live in his home of 50 years on his own terms. The change was disorienting. A few weeks earlier, in hospital, he had to be physically restrained by two security guards to stop him discharging himself against medical advice. Deprivation of Liberty Safeguards were invoked. He was sedated. Most of that fight seemed to have drained away. It&amp;rsquo;s tempting to say that he gave up the ghost: it implies a degree of agency and choice on his part, and the dignity that goes with a sense of volition. It&amp;rsquo;s impossible to know if that is actually true; but it is comforting, in a small way, to think it might be.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The role of loneliness&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Memory plays tricks on all of us. Or rather, we conspire with it in a process that psychologists call &amp;ldquo;coherence&amp;rdquo;, shaping memories to fit narratives we find more comfortable, or that accommodate our present sense of self better. My recollection is that Dad&amp;rsquo;s difficulties date to the last couple of years of his life, but going back through the emails between myself and my three siblings to research this piece, I see that we had serious concerns about his memory at least as far back as 2011. Perhaps I want to avoid thinking about ways in which those last years might have been better for him. Perhaps we should have pushed him harder to recognise his predicament. But would the emotional distress, never mind the potential of ruptured familial relationships, have been worth the cost? It is not as if it is a disease with a cure. Perhaps he was already, in some senses, unreachable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Our mother had died of esophageal cancer early in 2009, and grief, loneliness and depression weighed heavily on my father. I don&amp;rsquo;t think it was a sorrow he ever had the wherewithal to adapt to, never mind overcome. He was prescribed citalopram, an anti-depressant, but we were never sure how reliably he took it. We were never sure how reliably he took any medication in those years. He bristled at the intrusion whenever we enquired; the irritation, touched with defensiveness, was entirely in character, but I wonder now how much that kind of sensitivity, possibly extending to resentment, was related to the Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s. The hippocampus nestles beside the amygdala in the brain, and the amygdala regulates the great primal emotions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was a function of the disease too, then, that he seemed to be more emotional about Mum&amp;rsquo;s loss the longer it receded into the past. When we all met on the anniversary of Mum&amp;rsquo;s death, or on her birthday, on the hillside where we had scattered her ashes, Dad took to throwing himself to the ground and kissing the earth where the ashes had fallen. Hitherto, he had been among the most reserved of people; the only time I ever saw him express intense physical affection for Mum was at her death, when he showered her cold face with kisses and sobbed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Looking back now, I can see that Dad&amp;rsquo;s situation was fertile ground for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s to take root in.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sandeep Jauhar&amp;rsquo;s new book, &lt;em&gt;My Father&amp;rsquo;s Brain&lt;/em&gt;, is a moving account of his father&amp;rsquo;s illness and eventual death. Like my own father, Jauhar&amp;rsquo;s had lost his wife a few years earlier; like Dad, too, he had a successful career in which intellect played a key role. He cites a 2007 study which suggests there is a strong correlation between loneliness and the development of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s; and another, from 2020, which found that the recently widowed decline mentally three times as quickly as those who have not experienced such wrenching, disabling griefs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I wish I had known about that correlation. But I don&amp;rsquo;t know how easy it would have been to make use of it. It&amp;rsquo;s sometimes said that Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s destroys the self. Ultimately, perhaps, it does, if the patient lives long enough to reach the final stage where the disease attacks not just memory but motor function, the ability to undertake such fundamental tasks as swallowing. Dad died before he reached that extremity. I think we must be grateful for that. In one moment of clarity in those last weeks, he described the disease to me as a kind of hollowing out; he said he looked inside himself and found a blackness, as if what remained of memory and the self clung vertiginously to the outer limits of his identity. I think it terrified him. Looking back, though, what feels remarkable is not the loss of self, but its persistence.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Memory and the self&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The relationship between memory and the self has long been argued over. Jauhar notes the 18th-century philosopher David Hume&amp;rsquo;s observation in his &lt;em&gt;A Treatise of Human Nature&lt;/em&gt; that &amp;ldquo;Had we no memory, we never should have any notion of causation, nor consequently of that chain of causes and effects, which constitute our self or person.&amp;rdquo; Late in life the surrealist film maker Luis Bu&amp;ntilde;uel wrote poignantly in his memoir &lt;em&gt;My Last Breath&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;You have to begin to lose your memory, if only in bits and pieces, to realise that memory is what makes our lives. Life without memory is no life&amp;hellip; Our memory is our coherence, our reason, our feeling, even our action. Without it, we are nothing.&amp;rdquo; But are we only the sum of our own memories? Does the self only have meaning in terms of the interior life? &amp;ldquo;The conventional paradigm about what constitutes a person does not give adequate import to the richness of a human being outside of his cognitive capacities,&amp;rdquo; Jauhar writes. &amp;ldquo;Human beings exist not only in an inner world but also in a public space. It is that space that continues to give meaning to the lives of people living with severe dementia.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s an idea also explored in another new book on the subject, Dasha Kiper&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Travellers to Unimaginable Lands&lt;/em&gt;, a psychologically acute and compelling series of case studies exploring the relationship between the carer and the dementia patient. &amp;ldquo;The notion that there is a part of ourselves that is entirely separate from others is most likely a fiction,&amp;rdquo; she writes. There is no &amp;ldquo;us&amp;rdquo; that is distinct from &amp;ldquo;how people see us&amp;rdquo;. &amp;ldquo;Neurologically speaking, there is no special place in the brain that is hermetically sealed from the influence of other people. Quite the contrary: the self is porous.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A related theme in Kiper&amp;rsquo;s book resonated powerfully with me: the idea that Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s is emotionally and mentally disabling for the carer, as well as the patient. &amp;ldquo;We simply have no cognitive framework that allows for [memory&amp;rsquo;s] absence in others,&amp;rdquo; she writes. &amp;ldquo;Human beings did not evolve to function in isolation, and in fact each person&amp;rsquo;s cognition is dependent on the cognitive faculties of those around them. So when one person&amp;rsquo;s memory is impaired, those close to him or her also become disoriented.&amp;rdquo; That is, Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s bends the world to its rhythms and processes. It&amp;rsquo;s quite totalitarian in this regard. Alternate realities &amp;ndash; narratives, perspectives, points of view &amp;ndash; are not viable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Extraordinary intimacies&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;To accompany a loved one into the horror of Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s is to negotiate extraordinary intimacies at the limit of human experience to which you are the only witness. You have to keep privately reminding yourself what is occurring, what has occurred. Your memory of events becomes a kind of private resistance to the disease. But in the public space between you and the patient, Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s obliterates you too. Faced, say, with endlessly repeated questions or statements, you can tell the truth and say, &amp;ldquo;We just talked about that&amp;rdquo;. But it won&amp;rsquo;t change the sequence of events. Or you can acquiesce, play the game as it were, and respond to each moment as if it is new to you too. Either way, Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s wins. Its reality trumps your reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;In the end,&amp;rdquo; a neurologist tells Jauhar, &amp;ldquo;all dementias look alike. The whole brain is affected. Patients generally can&amp;rsquo;t speak.&amp;rdquo; But the journey to that end is surely unique &amp;ndash; or as unique as the person for whom you are caring, as unique as your relationship with them. In the same way as my relationship with my dad was not the same as his with each of my siblings, however much common ground we shared, I am sure my experience of his Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s was different, because it was grounded in the deep memory of our prior history. Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s strips away almost everything that is individual. But even when language and memory failed Dad the most, there were still the bare, non-verbal, human things of touch and companionship, comfort and care which we gave him, each as we could: a kind of somatic continuity to counterbalance the strobing discontinuous struggle of surviving as each brief moment of existence flashed past unremarked to make way for the next. I don&amp;rsquo;t know if it mattered to him; it felt very much like it did. What does it matter if he didn&amp;rsquo;t remember afterwards?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s, writes David Shenk in his classic study &lt;em&gt;The Forgetting&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;is not only a disease, but also a prism through which we can view life in a way not normally available to us&amp;hellip; it forces us to experience death in a way it is rarely otherwise experienced&amp;hellip; It is more painful than many people can even imagine, but it is also perhaps the most poignant of all reminders of why and how human life is so extraordinary. It is our best lens on the meaning of loss.&amp;rdquo; We are social animals. We need community, even if that is a community of two people. We need reciprocity, a sense of the shared moment. But reciprocity requires a mutual understanding. What happens then if there is only one person to understand, to remember?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As a historian, as a writer, I think a lot about memory and erasure, memory and loss. Absences in the record. The value of testimony. The sense of my father&amp;rsquo;s life &amp;ndash; all those unshared, unwritten memories flaking away, falling into oblivion in those last months, perhaps years &amp;ndash; was almost palpable. But if the self is not limited to the individual memory, if it is in some senses a shared construct, a shared endeavour, then it is important to rescue what can still be rescued, and not to write off the ends of life, to compound one erasure with another.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Towards the end of the 20th century there was a sometimes vituperative debate about the historiography of the Holocaust. Put very crudely, the argument was about whether it is possible even to write history about such a subject: narrative history is inevitably selective, cohering to an argument, and ultimately a kind of falsification, the thinking runs. Critics of this position saw it as an attack on the status of survivor testimony that opened the door to Holocaust revisionism and denial. The Italian historian Carlo Ginzburg&amp;rsquo;s contribution was an essay titled &amp;ldquo;Just One Witness&amp;rdquo;. He begins by citing the extermination of the entire Jewish community in a village in Provence in 1348, in the wake of the Black Death, for which the only evidence now is the written memory of a single survivor. We cannot, as historians, disregard such testimony, he argues, even if there is nothing reciprocal in the record to confirm it. It exists; we must make sense of it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That essay, or its core sentiment, has been rattling around my head writing this. For all the grinding bewilderment and exhaustion of those months, there is a kind of privilege to care for someone in these straits. A privilege to travel with someone into such a bleak, strange part of human existence. To travel with them, and bring the last of them back with you. Two people, one supporting the other. One community of two. One witness. One love.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6133/what-supporting-my-father-through-alzheimers-taught-me#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-22T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-22T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JUNE 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/06/open-discussion-june-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978548</id>
    <published>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/05/open-discussion-may-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978543</id>
    <published>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Agree to Disagree</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/agree-to-disagree/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! As Steven Pinker wrote recently in the Boston Globe, “The very concept of freedom of expression is anything but intuitively obvious.” He’s right, of course. When we are confronted with ideas we find disagreeable, dangerous, or downright abhorrent, our first instinct is likely to want to silence …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978537</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
