<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2022-12-11T18:31:48Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>These are the kinds of Christmas gifts popular with the kids today?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/11/these-are-the-kinds-of-christmas-gifts-popular-with-the-kids-today/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;It&amp;#8217;s cute, but sorry grandchildren, this isn&amp;#8217;t what you&amp;#8217;re getting from us this year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/OdA5K0J2rjQ" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It’s cute, but sorry grandchildren, this isn’t what you’re getting from us this year.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68723</id>
    <published>2022-12-11T14:05:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-11T14:05:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I’ve got this</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/10/ive-got-this/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free-150x112.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="112" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-68721" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free-150x112.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free-500x375.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-free.jpeg 667w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Classes over! All grading to date completed! Freedom is in sight!</p>
<p>OK, I have to compose two final exams by Monday, and grade them next weekend. This won’t be too intimidating, though — my plan is to make the final machine-gradeable, mostly multiple choice and math problems, so with a little preparation I can just log in next Saturday, see all the scores waiting for me, and then I plug them into a spreadsheet that spits out letter grades.</p>
<p>So, next weekend…margaritas and tacos and lounging about, playing with spiders and data. Until then, one last push.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Classes over! All grading to date completed! Freedom is in sight! OK, I have to compose two final exams by Monday, and grade them next weekend. This won’t be too intimidating, though — my plan is to make the final machine-gradeable, mostly multiple choice and math problems, so with a little preparation I can just […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68720</id>
    <published>2022-12-10T14:31:10Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-10T14:31:10Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Now I’m feeling old</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/09/now-im-feeling-old-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">My wife was tidying up old papers, and found this letter. My daughter had written it to her grandparents to thank them for some Christmas presents (and also to share the family excitement, that her older brother had gotten a ball python). Grandma had put the date on it, and we got it back after they died.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol-500x352.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="352" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-68718" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol-500x352.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol-150x106.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol-300x211.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol-768x540.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/skatjeletter-smol.jpeg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Written when my daughter was about the same age as my granddaughter is now, 26 years ago. Jebus, but time flies by, and leaves me all old and sentimental. I may need to mope for a bit.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">My wife was tidying up old papers, and found this letter. My daughter had written it to her grandparents to thank them for some Christmas presents (and also to share the family excitement, that her older brother had gotten a ball python). Grandma had put the date on it, and we got it back after […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68717</id>
    <published>2022-12-09T21:31:25Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-09T21:31:25Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why we need a radical approach to the countryside</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6053/why-we-need-a-radical-approach-to-the-countryside#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;img title="Flatford Mill (&amp;lsquo;Scene on a Navigable River&amp;rsquo;) by John Constable, 1816" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Constab_e.jpeg" height="817" alt="Flatford Mill by John Constable, 1816" width="1024"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p1"&gt;It is the strangest doublethink. As I write, one third of Pakistan is underwater. Recently in &lt;em&gt;Science&lt;/em&gt;, a team led by David Armstrong McKay published findings that indicate global warming has already passed the threshold for triggering five disastrous tipping points, from ice-sheet collapse to permafrost thaw. Even in temperate Britain, summer 2022 brought widespread drought and the highest temperatures the country has ever recorded. We &amp;ndash; at least, &amp;ldquo;we progressives&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; know this. Yet our default, when it comes to the natural environment, seems to be a long comfortable yawn. That stuff &amp;ldquo;out there&amp;rdquo;, the barely differentiated bird and plant life blurring beyond the car windows, isn&amp;rsquo;t really worth getting to know, is it? We seem to assume it is a cultural and political dead zone, where nothing interesting could possibly happen.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Yet we make an exception for big-scale nature. Shades of imperial heroics haunt TV expeditions to film rare, faraway species, or beautifully judged literary works in which middle-class white men go off alone to explore mountains, woods or rivers &amp;ndash; othering even the natural environment. Of course, something is better than nothing. No one would deny that David Attenborough, or writers like Richard Deakin or Robert MacFarlane, have made a difference not only to the popularity of the natural world as entertainment, but to what we know about it. But still, this strikes a somewhat post-colonial note.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not to make some insulting equivalence between the human suffering Britain and other countries have already inflicted, and the suffering being inflicted on our neighbour species today. But, while unchecked climate change will eventually destroy us all, the people who will suffer first and worst will be in the global south. And in both the recent imperial past and the near future, this damage results from a culture of othering. It is a dangerous nonsense to turn the world around us &amp;ndash; like the people of that world &amp;ndash; into something we don&amp;rsquo;t need to bother with because it is both, in the immortal words of Father Ted, &amp;ldquo;small: far away&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re not from London,&amp;rdquo; cry the hopelessly metropolitan protagonists of&lt;em&gt; Withnail and I&lt;/em&gt; (1987), out of their depth in the rain-soaked Lake District. But of course they are: and the satire, rounded like all the best writing, shows their agreeable heedlessness, as they leave field gates open wide, solicit a poacher in public and prove unable even to feed themselves. The natural environment is neither tiny nor distant. Today&amp;rsquo;s intellectual and, increasingly, popular cultures take the collapse of the global biosphere seriously. But not so the fact that the quotidian, vaguely apprehended British countryside is &amp;ndash; for all of us here on these islands, right now, in every moment &amp;ndash; our local natural environment. The countryside is what our urban areas sit within; and it&amp;rsquo;s what sustains them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-converted-space"&gt;The countryside is anything but a-political&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also an increasingly radicalised space, at the forefront of our collective attempts to manage the climate emergency. The Johnson administration was close to advocates of rewilding. Farming communities &amp;ndash; particularly in the less wealthy parts of the country often selected for such projects, because land there costs less &amp;ndash; see rewilding as a rich man&amp;rsquo;s hobby which is pricing them out of existence. Some explicitly cite parallels with the paralegal process of enclosure, which culminated in the 18th century. This saw productive agriculture, and the livelihoods of ordinary people in rural communities, cleared away to make room for the hobby parks and model farms of the wealthy. As today&amp;rsquo;s farmers point out, food comes ultimately from land, not factories; food security is an important part of biosecurity; and farming where we live slashes carbon-heavy food miles.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;The connection between land and food, though, often seems to be missing from rewilders&amp;rsquo; thinking: perhaps because the reality, which is that we need to find ways to farm sustainably, is so complex. Connected thought is also missing from the commercial strategy of buying up productive farmland for carbon offset sinks. Changing ownership of a green space does not create more of it. Meanwhile, amid political chaos at Westminster, the environment appears to be low on the agenda. The short-lived Truss government was not interested even in greenwashing; her September mini-budget was seen by environmentalists as a clear &amp;ldquo;attack on nature&amp;rdquo;. Sunak&amp;rsquo;s government reversed many of these measures &amp;ndash; reinstating the ban on fracking and pledging more offshore wind &amp;ndash; but ministers have repeatedly framed environmental issues as a sideshow. The early days of Sunak&amp;rsquo;s premiership were dogged by controversy over his reluctance to attend the COP27 climate summit.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;So what&amp;rsquo;s gone wrong? Why can we not fix our attention on the British countryside for long enough to think and act rationally in relation to it? More than we surely realise &amp;ndash; and leaving aside the particular shamelessness of this new governmental asset-stripping &amp;ndash; this has to do with our culture. If we think of our natural environment as remote, it&amp;rsquo;s because it&amp;rsquo;s so often presented that way. When William Morris designed his wallpapers and fabrics, in which vines and roses become a repeating frieze, he was developing what he understood as good socialist practice. In his workshops, craftsmen and women could earn their living in ways that allowed them to further their skills, and to take ownership of the (improved) results.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Yet it was adoption in the nation&amp;rsquo;s gift shops that finally made these designs ubiquitous &amp;ndash; as symbols, ironically, of middle-class Britain. We no longer hear, in their handmade origins, the echo of earlier movements seeking to afford workers self-sufficiency, such as Chartism. Instead, we fall back on thinking of workers and their rights as necessarily urban. That we do so is another consequence of enclosure because the ordinary people it displaced into cities became cheap labour for the industrial revolution&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;dark Satanic mills.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;That famous phrase comes from the Romantic poet William Blake (in &amp;ldquo;Jerusalem&amp;rdquo;). It&amp;rsquo;s something of an irony that, at the very time these upheavals were taking place, Romanticism was advancing ideas of human rights centering on the inalienable status of the self as a human. We take for granted the ideas of liberty and equality, if not fraternity, that were first linked by Fran&amp;ccedil;ois F&amp;eacute;nelon at the dawn of the Enlightenment; they took their first steps onto the political stage with the Romantic-era French Revolution. On this side of the Channel, political philosophers including William Godwin and Mary Wollstonecraft, politicised intellectuals Thomas Jefferson Hogg and James Leigh Hunt, and writers and activists including Percy Bysshe and Mary Shelley, were arguing for a person-centred dismantling of traditional institutions, including monarchy and marriage, and a recourse to personal judgment rather than social and religious obedience.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2 class="p3"&gt;Let's learn from the Romantics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;So the fine-tuned Romantic &amp;ldquo;sensibility&amp;rdquo; the more conservative Jane Austen mocked in &lt;em&gt;Sense and Sensibility &lt;/em&gt;(1811) and &lt;em&gt;Northanger Abbey &lt;/em&gt;(1817) was more than self-indulgence. It was a form of heightened awareness underpinned by political philosophy. The Tory governments of the early 19th century effectively stamped out revolutionary thought, not least by repeated suspensions of habeas corpus and the right to a fair trial. This posed a threat for those it deemed subversives: many, including the Leigh Hunts and the Shelleys, went into political exile in Europe. And it&amp;rsquo;s this, rather than mere emotion or artistic expression, that&amp;rsquo;s actually going on in those Romantic representations of the natural environment which are so often, paradoxically, co-opted to present the British countryside as picturesque, old-fashioned and unchanging. In fact, these representations were urgently new: and they were created in response to an era of rapid change.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Look again and the evidence is everywhere, as I rediscovered recently in writing and thinking about the Romantic encounter with the countryside. William Wordsworth &amp;ldquo;wandered lonely as a cloud&amp;rdquo; because the countryside was newly depopulated, and the sense you get when you&amp;rsquo;re alone in the high fells is vertiginous &amp;ndash; like looking up into a nearly cloudless sky and wondering why you don&amp;rsquo;t fall up into it. John Constable&amp;rsquo;s Dedham Vale, away from the worker community at Flatford Mill, is empty for the same reason, as the solitary observer becomes newly aware of every rustle or squeak. J. M. W. Turner&amp;rsquo;s wide horizons record this too, as up to date in their way as his brilliant portrayal of speed on Maidenhead viaduct in &lt;em&gt;Wind, Steam, Speed&lt;/em&gt;. Percy Bysshe Shelley&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Ode to the West Wind&amp;rdquo; takes a high wind in Florence as an occasion to evoke the human &amp;ndash; and ecological &amp;ndash; potential for change and revolution.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;m saying, then, is that in a time of crisis we need to pay attention to everything surrounding us. Not only our natural environment, but our culture. We should keep a particular eye on ideas so familiar we think they&amp;rsquo;re our own. Our assumptions about the countryside have held us back from paying attention to catastrophes unfolding there in plain sight. Such assumptions emerge from historical and cultural circumstance. They are the reason we shouldn&amp;rsquo;t ignore historical moments like Romanticism, which have shaped our relationship with rural life, and which therefore cannot be &amp;ldquo;over and done&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;Close up, Samuel Taylor Coleridge and the Wordsworths in Somerset &amp;ndash; or Lord Byron and the Shelleys in Switzerland &amp;ndash; probably splashed about in country mud just as helplessly as Bruce Robinson&amp;rsquo;s Withnail. But the lesson of Romanticism itself &amp;ndash; rather than our reception of it as decorative clich&amp;eacute; &amp;ndash; must be its fearlessness in taking the rural environment as a site of and for radical rethinking. We too need to become unafraid of the proximity of the countryside: as the series of lived realities with which, even in town, we all relate. And if an increasingly authoritarian government claims that paying attention to such things is both uneconomic and impractical &amp;ndash; arts and humanities, anyone? &amp;ndash; perhaps we need to ask ourselves whose version of the natural environment, as of things in general, we are meant unquestioningly to accept.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fiona Sampson&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Starlight Wood: Walking Back to the Romantic Countryside&amp;rdquo; is published by Hachette&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p2"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6053/why-we-need-a-radical-approach-to-the-countryside#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-12-09T14:34:29Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-09T14:34:29Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Holiday? No thanks</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6052/holiday-no-thanks#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/NewHUmanistLaurieheadstand.jpg" height="589" alt="Laurie Taylor hates holidays" width="410"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As I sidle out of bed every morning I am increasingly put in mind of the Lewis Carroll poem: &amp;ldquo;&amp;lsquo;You are old, Father William,&amp;rsquo; the young man said, / &amp;lsquo;And your hair has become very white; / And yet you incessantly stand on your head&amp;ndash; / Do you think, at your age, it is right?&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In truth, I don&amp;rsquo;t exactly emulate Father William&amp;rsquo;s headstand, but I do embark on a series of rather bizarre physical exercises. Before I risk a trip to the bathroom, I check that my surgically replaced ankle is in good working order by standing on one leg for several seconds. Then I need a few minutes of running on the spot to prove that my newly fitted pacemaker is ticking over nicely.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;These are only the more dramatic signs. They sit alongside more mundane evidence of physical deterioration: an anxiety about biting into apples, a refusal to run for buses, a declining capacity to throw up both arms in any sort of exultation, and a distinct unreadiness to bend down in a public place and tie up my shoelaces. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But all these corporeal concerns count for little when set against my new existential discovery. It can be simply stated: I never, ever, never, ever want to go on holiday again. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to spend so much as a single night in a small hotel in Paris, or a fat villa in Antibes. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to travel several thousand miles in order to look at tropical birds and a basking hippopotamus. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to sit on a yacht, walk the Pilgrims&amp;rsquo; Way or be sculled through Venice by a singing gondolier. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This new-found reluctance to leave home has nothing to do with any anxiety about the customary hassles of travelling. It is entirely prompted by a recent aversion to nearly every one of the delights that are so regularly reported by friends who have returned from holiday. The more they tell me about their vacation, the more my resolution is stiffened.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here, for example, on my writing desk, is a recently received picture of Michael and Janet lounging on white plastic sun-beds beside a blue swimming pool somewhere in the south of France. &amp;ldquo;We are really away from it all at last,&amp;rdquo; runs the self-congratulatory message. The photo is in perfectly focused glossy Technicolor, but all I can see is an encroaching greyness: the perceptual deprivation induced by having nothing to stare at for hour after hour apart from a stretch of flat chlorinated water and the constant fear of losing your lounger when you depart to grab some buffet lunch.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But far more relevant to my new resolution is this report from Charlotte and James. They&amp;rsquo;re an acerbic couple, always alert to hypocrisy and double standards. But still they can&amp;rsquo;t wait to tell me in an email that &amp;ldquo;Yesterday we visited the magnificent cathedral. Such a solemn and holy place, with crowds of worshippers before the renowned statue of the Virgin Mary. An unforgettable experience!&amp;rdquo; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And Charlotte and James are hardly alone. Over the years, dozens of my agnostic and atheist friends who would normally no more visit a holy building than volunteer to tour the local abattoir have reported in rapturous tone on their &amp;ldquo;delightful&amp;rdquo; visits to foreign churches and abbeys and monasteries. But more than that. They&amp;rsquo;ve told me in detail about the wonders of attending religious processions and parades. &amp;ldquo;Laurie. If you look closely at the head of the procession you can see the casket that is said to contain a splinter from the Holy Cross.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But I suspect that none of these factors contribute so much to my abhorrence of holidays as my loss of a critical cognitive faculty. To put it simply, I no longer have the mental capacity to pretend that matters are really better than they actually are, to simulate my delight at a merely average French seaside restaurant, or a garish Italian sunset, or an over-extended Portuguese fado, or the discovery that my hotel room bears only a parodic reference to the one featured in the brochure. I can only recall Robert Robinson&amp;rsquo;s astute observation that wherever you stay on holiday will always be less comfortable than your home.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All in all, I have far more sensible and reasonable matters to attend to than a holiday. Tomorrow, for example, I intend to practise standing on my head.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;article class="a2-a8 t2-t7 m-all m-padinfull"&gt; &lt;div class="text-body a-all a-padinfull t-all t-padinfull m-all"&gt; &lt;div class="main-content a3-a7 a-clear t-all t-clear m-all"&gt; &lt;p class="p6"&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;2022 &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/div&gt; &lt;/article&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6052/holiday-no-thanks#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-12-09T14:34:15Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-09T14:34:15Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>…last day…must crawl…just a little further</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/09/last-daymust-crawljust-a-little-further/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Almost there.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-300x197.jpeg" alt="" width="300" height="197" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-68715" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-300x197.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-150x98.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank-500x328.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/shawshank.jpeg 615w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p>I have to finish grading this stack of lab finals this morning, then compose an exam for intro biology, and finally stagger into bed.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Almost there. I have to finish grading this stack of lab finals this morning, then compose an exam for intro biology, and finally stagger into bed.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68714</id>
    <published>2022-12-09T13:32:01Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-09T13:32:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The students do know how to have fun</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2022/12/08/the-students-do-know-how-to-have-fun/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">To celebrate the end of classes, we have two big events this weekend at UMM.</p>
<p>First up, park your butt in an auditorium (haven’t they had enough of that?), and watch a Marvel Movie Marathon. I’m not sufficiently interested in the Marvel universe to do that, but sure, soak in it for the weekend.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel-500x667.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="667" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-68711" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel-500x667.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel-113x150.jpg 113w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel-225x300.jpg 225w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/marvel.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>And then, top off Saturday night with the Yule Ball. This is a photo of a decorative pile of tchotchkes that were on a table. I like the sentiment on the button.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball-500x667.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="667" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-68712" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball-500x667.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball-113x150.jpg 113w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball-225x300.jpg 225w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball-768x1024.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/12/yuleball.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Party hard, young’uns! For the professoriate will deliver unto you a week of pain immediately afterwards!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To celebrate the end of classes, we have two big events this weekend at UMM. First up, park your butt in an auditorium (haven’t they had enough of that?), and watch a Marvel Movie Marathon. I’m not sufficiently interested in the Marvel universe to do that, but sure, soak in it for the weekend. And […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=68710</id>
    <published>2022-12-08T19:49:02Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-08T19:49:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Rethinking the origins of life</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6051/rethinking-the-origins-of-life#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/rowsonsmall.jpg" height="1663" alt="Martin Rowson cartoon on the origins of life in deep sea vents" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The origin of life is such a fabled event (more than 4 billion years ago) that searching for clues on the Earth today might seem a fool&amp;rsquo;s errand. But, piece by piece, a wonderfully interlocking skein of evidence is emerging. It began with a chance encounter in the deep ocean.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 1977, the deep-sea submersible research vessel Alvin discovered hot upwelling mineral vents &amp;ndash; black smokers &amp;ndash; in the deep Pacific Ocean, off the coast of California. Such upwellings occur near the boundaries of the Earth&amp;rsquo;s tectonic plates where there is volcanic activity. The streams that pour out are hot water laced with minerals that then accumulate and grow into rocky towers. The interest of biologists and biochemists was piqued by the constant flow of hot, chemically rich effluents, which suggested that this might be life&amp;rsquo;s birthplace. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The energetic chemistry discovered in the black smokers bore some resemblance to the energy metabolism of modern cells, especially in the presence of iron-sulphur clusters. These clusters lie at the heart of many of life&amp;rsquo;s nanomachines &amp;ndash; large protein complexes, often with moving parts &amp;ndash; that perform life&amp;rsquo;s key functions (see my article &amp;ldquo;Nature&amp;rsquo;s Nanomachines&amp;rdquo; in the Spring 2021 edition of &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt;). &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Black smokers proved to be a dead end: they were too hot and unstable to have been a source of early life. However, the idea that deep sea vents might point to the secret of the origin of life was taken up by other researchers. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 1988, the geochemist Mike Russell, at Glasgow University, predicted the existence of another kind of hydrothermal vent: alkaline, and much cooler. This vent, he hypothesised, could have used hydrogen spewing from the effluents to react with dissolved carbon dioxide (CO2) in the ocean waters, creating the precursor chemicals of life. In fact, Russell made the claim: &amp;ldquo;The purpose of life is to hydrogenate carbon dioxide&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This may sound grandiose &amp;ndash; but as it turned out, Russell was correct. In December 2000, mysterious white chimney structures, now dubbed the Lost City, were found by chance by the same submersible vessel on the mid-Atlantic seafloor. (The very best science is done like this: a prediction &amp;ndash; often seemingly improbable &amp;ndash; followed by the clinching discovery.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The most exciting revelation of the calcium carbonate chimneys, which are up to 60m tall, was their porous structure. Each has many tiny holes like a mineralised sponge, through which, as Russell predicted, alkaline fluids rich in hydrogen and minerals really do pour into an acidic ocean which contains dissolved CO2 (the ocean is mildly acidic now, but it was much more so 4 billion years ago). In primeval conditions, these vents could have spawned and harboured the necessary ingredients and the right conditions to promote the growth of biomass. It seems that we might have finally found the birthplace of life on Earth.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;"Life is a river that never stalls"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over the last two decades, much work has been done on deep-sea vents. There is a striking similarity between their chemistry and the biochemistry of primitive bacteria which still exist today and can live on purely chemical substances. As a result, we now have a detailed and highly plausible account of how life probably arose. These are exciting times, but the science is complex and difficult to explain to the general public. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thankfully, one of the researchers working on the origin of life is also an excellent communicator. Nick Lane, professor of evolutionary biochemistry at University College London, has been working on the question of what life is, and how it began, for more than a decade. Most biologists see life in terms of information encoded by DNA, but Lane focuses on the flow of energy through living things. In his latest book, &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt;, which came out in May 2022, he writes that his aim is to &amp;ldquo;explain how the flow of energy and matter structures the evolution of life and even genetic information. I want to turn the standard view upside down.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An analogy for Lane&amp;rsquo;s view of life can be found in rivers. A river is only a river if it is in motion, and that motion requires energy. Rivers are not only water, just as living things are not only the chemicals that comprise them. In every living cell, chemical matter is incessantly in motion to a frantic degree. Humans die very quickly if oxygen is withdrawn, but what kills us is not suffocation but a collapse of the energy flow through every cell. &lt;br&gt;Living things need fuel to power the metabolism of life. They get this by trading gases with the environment: for plants in today&amp;rsquo;s world, that means CO2 in, oxygen out, and the reverse for animals. Life is reproduced through DNA. But the puzzle has always been to discover how primitive chemistry could have led to intricate biochemistry in the first place. Darwin memorably mused on the subject of the origin of life:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;But if (and oh what a big if) we could conceive in some warm little pond with all sorts of ammonia and phosphoric salts, light, heat, electricity etcetera present, that a protein compound was chemically formed, ready to undergo still more complex changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;This seemed unlikely, because in open water any interesting chemistry would quickly be dispersed &amp;ndash; a drop in the ocean is more than a metaphor here. However, we can now hypothesise that this is where the deep-sea vents came into play. They could have provided a shelter in their pores in which useful molecules could accumulate in the unceasing flow. Over millions of years, the constancy of the same upwellings satisfies the &amp;ldquo;life is a river that never stalls&amp;rdquo; requirement. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But what on the primeval Earth could have enabled the vital reaction between CO2 and hydrogen? This is the problem that Lane&amp;rsquo;s lab and others have been working on. In 2020, a research team led by Lane&amp;rsquo;s former student Victor Sojo, with Reuben Hudson, managed to mimic conditions in the primordial vents. They demonstrated that an energy gradient that exists in the vents between the alkaline effluents and the acid ocean was indeed capable of hydrogenating CO2. Other labs are producing similar results, confirming what was long suspected but difficult to prove. Lane says: &amp;ldquo;I take my hat off to them&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The beginning of natural selection&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;If the first requirement of life is the hydrogenation of CO2, what is needed next? All life today is composed of cells and new life can now only come into being through the division of living cells. Cells are cells because they are bounded by a membrane &amp;ndash; a barrier between the non-living outside world and the living interior (or between one cell and another). &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Cell membranes are made from fatty acids which behave like detergents in that one end of the molecule is water repellent and one end is water loving. In the reactions that occur in the vents, long-chain fatty acids would have formed easily. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple lab demonstration to show that these fatty acids will self-assemble into bilayer spheres in water, with the fatty ends butting together, separating the watery world inside from the watery world outside. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So the idea is that the pores in the chimneys were a template for protocells with this bilayer structure. This was the beginning of the metabolism that powers all cells today. The minerals that pour out of the vents have catalytic properties and would have created a positive feedback loop in which the protocells that could fix more carbon would come to dominate the vents. This was the beginning of natural selection.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt;, Lane demonstrates the centrality of this metabolism to all life in a suite of reactions that goes by the name of the Krebs Cycle, after the great biochemist Hans Krebs (1900-1981). The textbook Krebs Cycle describes oxygen &amp;ldquo;burning&amp;rdquo; glucose to provide energy and to create the basic biomass of life, whilst emitting CO2 in the process. It is at the heart of the way that animals like us live and move and exist. Ironically, Lane&amp;rsquo;s first encounter with learning about the cycle was unpropitious. &amp;ldquo;I did biology and chemistry at school and loved them both and thought that combination was perfect but I did biochemistry at university and hated it,&amp;rdquo; he told me, &amp;ldquo;hated it because I was told to memorise pathways off by heart.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It turned out that this rote learning was not only tedious and unhelpful. It also sold the Krebs Cycle short. The cycle had already been revealed, back in 1966, to be more complicated than the textbook version. It was capable of working backwards, starting with CO2 and creating biomass from the products of that first reaction with hydrogen. As is often the way, however, this concept was resisted by the research community for more than 20 years. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The reverse Krebs Cycle is now fully recognised and is vital to the hypothesis that life may have emerged from the deep-sea vents, long before the existence of DNA or its cousin RNA. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is highly promising, but as Lane himself admits in &lt;em&gt;Transformer&lt;/em&gt;, &amp;ldquo;many a beautiful idea has been killed by ugly facts&amp;rdquo;. The search for life&amp;rsquo;s greatest prizes has always been tortuous, but many teams of researchers are working to confirm Lane&amp;rsquo;s ideas experimentally. He makes sure, in the book, to fully acknowledge the work of his PhD students and post-doctoral researchers. Great strides are being made, but more hard evidence is needed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The overriding idea of the vent hypothesis is that the chemistry that existed in the pores of the vents was eventually interiorised by the protocells that nestled within them. In a thrilling recent experiment in Lane&amp;rsquo;s lab, Sean Jordan and Hanadi Rammu discovered that protocells form particularly readily in simulated vent conditions. The amino acid cysteine, mixed with iron and sulphides found in the vents, produced exactly the kind of iron-sulphur clusters at the heart of modern protein enzymes.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Did the origins of life involve DNA?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;One area of research is revealing how the deep-sea vents might have produced the molecule ATP (adenosine triphosphate), the universal fuel of life, powering every move we make and every internal process in all living things. Lane&amp;rsquo;s PhD researcher Silvana Pinna is investigating how this vital molecule might have originated in the hydrothermal vents. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the very early stages of the vents, the chemicals formed would have been tiny molecules with only a handful of atoms. Life in its developed form uses giant molecules &amp;ndash; long chains wound into a double helix in DNA or folded into intricate structures in proteins. Pinna has shown that the simple molecule acetyl phosphate can catalyse the formation of ATP from ADP (adenosine diphosphate) and that this reaction is chemically favoured under hydrothermal conditions. The paper by Pinna and her colleagues, recently published by the journal PLOS Biology, concludes:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;This implies that ATP could have become the universal energy currency of life not as the endpoint of genetic selection or as a frozen accident, but for fundamental chemical reasons.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;p&gt;Other researchers, such as Markus Ralser, the Einstein professor of biochemistry at the Einstein Foundation in Berlin, are producing similar results in finding purely chemical routes to the basic building blocks of life. Lane told me: &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s great about Markus&amp;rsquo;s work is that he&amp;rsquo;s brought attention to something that he calls the &amp;lsquo;end product problem&amp;rsquo;.&amp;rdquo; This poses the apparently awkward fact that the intermediate stages of the Krebs cycle only make sense when they are all in place. Both Ralser&amp;rsquo;s and Lane&amp;rsquo;s labs have found that Krebs and other key intermediates occur in sequence by simple chemistry alone, as opposed to the chemistry that can only be performed in living things today by the complex protein enzymes in every living cell. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Such chemistry, with that river metaphor in mind, is as natural as water flowing downstream. It&amp;rsquo;s the chemistry of reactions that happen by necessity, as when hydrogen reacts with oxygen to form water, or sodium with chlorine to form sodium chloride. The success of work like this leads Lane to suggest: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m coming to believe that the whole of biochemistry up to nucleotide synthesis just happens spontaneously . . . It&amp;rsquo;s just built into the chemistry of CO2&amp;rdquo;. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is a remarkable conclusion, overturning the generally held assumption that the origin of life must have had something to do with DNA or its cousin RNA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;"Tornado in the junkyard"&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Life originating by purely chemical means was once considered so far-fetched that the astronomer Fred Hoyle compared it, in 1983, to &amp;ldquo;the chance that a tornado sweeping through a junkyard might assemble a Boeing 747&amp;rdquo;. But it seems that the currents that flow though the hydrothermal vents really are the &amp;ldquo;tornado in the junkyard&amp;rdquo;, able to create some of life&amp;rsquo;s early metabolism.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This theory could also solve the problem of how DNA originated. Today, new life is produced by coding from DNA, but a code can&amp;rsquo;t predate the thing coded for. How did it emerge in the first place? The genetic code by which DNA spells out the composition of proteins is regarded by some as a frozen accident &amp;ndash; there seems no rhyme or reason to it, like the Morse code, which could just as well have a completely different pattern of dots and dashes. But a recent paper published in the journal Biochimica et Biophysica Acta &amp;ndash; Bioenergetics by Lane&amp;rsquo;s PhD students &amp;ndash; Stuart Harrison, Raquel Nunes Palmeira and Aaron Halpern &amp;ndash; shows how the genetic code most likely evolved.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;They have discovered that the nucleotide bases that form DNA and its more primordial cousin RNA actually have a direct chemical affinity for particular amino acids, the building blocks of proteins. The early little strings of nucleotides &amp;ndash; forerunners of the great chains of RNA and DNA &amp;ndash; had no coding function: in the first instance, they were catalysts, just like the iron-sulphur clusters before them and the protein enzymes that succeeded them. But then, depending on their position in the reverse Krebs cycle, particular amino acids became associated with one or other of the four RNA bases. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The authors of the paper conclude by noting that coding &amp;ndash; biological information encoded in genes &amp;ndash; thus emerged by chemical necessity. The genetic code wasn&amp;rsquo;t imposed on life, but evolved alongside it. The theory &amp;ldquo;offers a framework that enables the transition from deterministic chemistry to genetic information at the origin of life&amp;rdquo; [my italics]. This is a conclusion as dramatic as that of Watson and Crick&amp;rsquo;s iconic 1953 paper, in which they posited that DNA was the means through which life was reproduced.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Since the discovery of DNA, inquiries into the origin of life have tended to focus on how DNA replication and the genetic code originated. How could complex life have begun to develop without such a code? We may now be opening a new chapter in biology that turns our assumptions upside down. The work of Lane and his colleagues shows that the complex lifeforms that exist on Earth today may have evolved from simple beginnings. The systems that power these lifeforms may seem bafflingly sophisticated, but they could have evolved by purely chemical means. Now, we see how, from the ever-pulsing currents on the primeval ocean floor, life could have booted itself up.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6051/rethinking-the-origins-of-life#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-12-02T11:08:45Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-02T11:08:45Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Sri Lanka’s dream village</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6049/sri-lankas-dream-village#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="GotaGoGama protest site, Colombo" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/srilankamedium.jpg" height="1080" alt="GotaGoGama protest site, Sri Lanka" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 9 April, people from across Sri Lanka converged on Galle Face, a 12-acre seafront stretch of green in front of the Presidential Secretariat in Colombo. They set up a tented protest site called GotaGoGama, or Gota Go Village. The protesters called for the resignation of President Gotabaya Rajapaksa and for a wider system change in Sri Lanka &amp;ndash; an end to the culture of impunity, nepotism, racism and injustice. They did so in a remarkably peaceful and creative way, for three long months, and successfully toppled one of Asia&amp;rsquo;s most powerful strongmen. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The protests were driven by an unprecedented economic crisis caused by a perfect storm of economic mismanagement, corruption and the impact of both the Ukraine war and the global pandemic. When Sri Lanka reneged on its foreign exchange debt of $51 billion, the crisis assumed devastating proportions: daily power cuts, businesses and schools closed, inflation at 60 per cent, food inflation at 90 per cent. People died of heat exhaustion while queuing for fuel, or quietly at home, in the absence of essential drugs. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Opposition to the government grew, especially to the president and his clan. The Rajapaksa family had dominated politics in Sri Lanka for 20 years and the people decided they&amp;rsquo;d had enough. GotaGoGama became the epicentre of the resistance, an imaginative expression of a growing hope for constructive and meaningful change. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The village drew thousands of people: medics and lawyers, students and teachers, journalists and artists, trade unionists and Indigenous people of the forest, bus drivers and businessmen, environmentalists and engineers, Catholic nuns and Buddhist clergy. Under the gusts of monsoon rain, the village not only provided food, water, medical and legal aid, with the support of 50 organisations, it also hosted lectures and musical performances, street theatre and art shows, under banners that called in loud letters to the president, &amp;ldquo;Gota Go Home&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Give Our Stolen Money Back&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Then on 9 May, the site was broken into by government-backed thugs. Tear gas and water cannon added to the force of an attack that injured over 100 protesters. In retaliation for that evening, dozens of houses belonging to MPs were burned down across the island, including the ancestral home of the Rajapaksas. Although the arsonists may have acted in support of GotaGoGama, no direct link has been made between the fires and the protest village. Indeed, some of the protesters left the GotaGoGama village as a result. Soon afterwards, the prime minister Mahinda Rajapaksa, who allegedly instigated the attack on the village, resigned.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Although diminished, the GotaGoGama protests carried on, ebbing and swelling in waves, until 9 July when they rose dramatically. State buildings were occupied by hundreds of protesters and members of the public. The president fled to the Maldives and on to Singapore where he resigned. The photos of ordinary people swimming in the president&amp;rsquo;s pool or taking selfies on his bed made headlines around the world. The protesters had achieved one of their main objectives: Gota was gone. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet there was little time for celebration. Later that month, a new president and prime minister were installed &amp;ndash; both linked to the political old guard &amp;ndash; and a state of emergency declared. It would be easy to conclude that the protests had failed. But the GotaGoGama village achieved what no government had ever done. It united the country, crossing barriers of ethnicity and religion, culture and class.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I first visited the village in April when it was, in the words of the Indian journalist Rohini Mohan, &amp;ldquo;a carnival of hope&amp;rdquo;, and went there regularly till late May. My hotel room directly overlooked the site. I have decided to write of the village as I found it, in the present tense, to call back a time that needs to be remembered if the values the protesters stood for &amp;ndash; unity, democracy, justice and human rights &amp;ndash; are ever to take hold in Sri Lanka. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A carnival of hope&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the midst of a row of large tents by the bustling thoroughfare, I find a white tent covered with signs that call for justice in three tongues. It is occupied by the Families for the Disappeared. Inside, Jennifer Weerasinghe sits quietly with her husband and a friend. Jennifer has taken her case to the press many times to no avail. But here, in GotaGoGama, she feels she has finally been heard. Above the din of electricity generators, she tells me it is the first time she has been able to talk about the abduction of her son in such a large public space.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;ldquo;I have been lucky, I know what happened to my son,&amp;rdquo; she says. He disappeared, she tells me, after attending a farewell party for a friend who was heading to study medicine in the UK. She thinks she knows the identity of one of the people responsible for kidnapping her son and his five friends; the students&amp;rsquo; vehicle was later found with false numberplates in the possession of a former Navy captain. The abduction appears to have been part of a series of kidnaps carried out by Navy personnel, a case known as the &amp;ldquo;Navy 11&amp;rdquo;. While it happened during the civil war, the motive seems to have been purely the extraction of money from the families. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Tens of thousands of people were disappeared during the civil war in Sri Lanka between the state and the separatist Tamil Tigers. It lasted almost 30 years, ending brutally in May 2009 after the intensification of military conflict led by Gotabaya Rajapaksa, who was then defence secretary. After the war ended, the families of the disappeared urgently needed answers. Gotabaya&amp;rsquo;s reponse was cruel and dismissive. He simply told them that their missing loved ones were &amp;ldquo;actually dead&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet Jennifer&amp;rsquo;s quest for justice continues, emboldened by GotaGoGama. &amp;ldquo;There are many people who are scared to speak out,&amp;rdquo; she says. &amp;ldquo;I used to feel afraid but I am without fear now because of the strength of the youth. We speak out, letting our blood boil, while our throats turn dry. The government has to listen.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The village is a communal space of mixed voices &amp;ndash; punctuated by the blare of music, the drill of generators and the sound of electronically amplified calls and chants. Stepping from the tent, I come across Andi Schubert, a language lecturer, and Harinda, founder of a social enterprise focused on community service, speaking animatedly in English. They tell me that the site has generated new conversations across communities and class. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Andi has just given a talk on ethnic identity at the People&amp;rsquo;s University that his friends set up on the site. The People&amp;rsquo;s University is &amp;ldquo;a great place&amp;rdquo;, he says, for &amp;ldquo;rethinking what a university can be at a time when the university itself is becoming a more repressive and conservative space &amp;ndash; not just in Sri Lanka but globally&amp;rdquo;. Harinda describes a scene of open contestation where those from a lower socio-economic background felt free to challenge those higher up. It was a scene, he says, &amp;ldquo;that melted my heart&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When I return to the site after the government&amp;rsquo;s attack on 9 May, the mood has changed and conversations are more focused. Plainclothes police are moving through the crowds to collect witness reports. Some protesters are not sure if they should assist with this. People are climbing the steps to a platform where lawyers dispense advice on their rights.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Close by, I find Priyantha Vishvajith, a filmmaker, who sports the flowing locks and beard common to many of the young men here. &amp;ldquo;We are in an economic, social and political crisis which is creating a struggle for all communities, so we want unity to fight the government to create a new society,&amp;rdquo; he tells me. &amp;ldquo;Even newborn babies are bearing the burden of the country&amp;rsquo;s debt . . . We are like refugees in our native country. We are suffering like them.&amp;rdquo; &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Like so many of the protesters, Priyantha tells me he has no party-political line and no personal grudges, but simply wants a country free from corruption. &amp;ldquo;They are robbing us and filling up their stomachs,&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;One or two families are doing this, including eight members of the Rajapaksa family.&amp;rdquo; As we talk, someone comes up and embraces him. It is only now that he tells me that he was one of those assaulted by government-backed thugs in the attack on 9 May. They beat him over the head and back, and dragged him through the streets. He was carrying his phone and managed to film the assault. The film went viral and was picked up globally. &amp;ldquo;How are you now?&amp;rdquo; I ask. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t answer, just lifts his white T-shirt and shows me the wounds that still blotch his body six days later. No action has been taken against those who assaulted him. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Later, I meet a painter, Malinda Bulathsinhala, working on a five-foot-high canvas depicting the Buddha seated in a grove surrounded by a circle of saffron-robed monks: a wash of sunset colours. He tells me it is a satirical take on a scene depicted in a mural at the Kelaniya temple.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;ldquo;My painting depicts extremist monks who divide people up. Those who are corrupt and have worked with politicians,&amp;rdquo; he says. &amp;ldquo;Politics corrupts Buddhism as politicians are only interested in power and money and use Buddhism for their own gain.&amp;rdquo; He emphasises that the protest is non-violent and began &amp;ldquo;through art and music&amp;rdquo;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Nevertheless, the protesters were confronted with state violence. I meet Rakshida, a 17-year-old who was being trained in first aid when the tear gas came rolling in on 9 May. &amp;ldquo;Mobs came and broke all of the tents but did not touch the Red Cross tent, which is clearly marked,&amp;rdquo; she tells me. &amp;ldquo;If I saw what was happening outside, I would have been scared. I was too busy. One of the victims had a dislocated jaw and cried a lot. Another person had his head cracked open into two pieces.&amp;rdquo;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;She recalls that they helped a pregnant Rajapaksa supporter who had come with the mob and been injured. &amp;ldquo;The nurse who treated her said if she wasn&amp;rsquo;t pregnant, she would have slapped her,&amp;rdquo; she laughs. &amp;ldquo;We gave help to all the people who came in.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The 9 May attack was only the first wave of violence against the protesters at GotaGoGama. Within 24 hours of the appointment of the new president on 21 July, masked military came under cover of darkness. Protesters were beaten, phones and film confiscated, several journalists attacked. And the site that had drawn so many for over 100 days was dismantled, leaving a smattering of tents behind.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Transforming Sri Lanka&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Today, there is no physical trace of the protest village at Galle Face. Meanwhile, the ousted president, Gotabaya Rajapaksa, has returned to Sri Lanka. Protesters are being abducted in broad daylight; more than 4,000 have been arrested to date. Unidentified bodies wash up on the beach. The struggle is being criminalised. Protesters are &amp;ldquo;fascists&amp;rdquo;, according to the president, &amp;ldquo;terrorists&amp;rdquo; according to the prime minister, and &amp;ldquo;drug addicts&amp;rdquo; according to the chief whip. And some commentators who once praised the protesters have started to echo this line. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet it is hard to imagine that the energy unleashed by the protest will simply disappear. All popular protests are underscored by idealism. GotaGoGama enacted its vision of Sri Lanka as a united community of equals. This quest to change society has a particular urgency now. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sri Lanka today is a country where survival is at risk: survival of body and being, of democracy and rights, as the economic crisis deepens with no end in sight. Without the foreign exchange for essential imports, food costs have spiralled and a third of the population is now food insecure. Medicine continues to be restricted to the point where life-saving drugs are scarce; pregnant women and children are most at risk. And while International Monetary Fund aid may be brought in, the anticipated fiscal reforms and the likely terms of debt restructuring, combined with the ongoing crackdown on dissent, mean a deepening of divisions that will likely fracture the nation along new lines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sri Lanka&amp;rsquo;s peaceful protests invented a new space of unity: a utopian site born out of &amp;ldquo;the pure urge for survival&amp;rdquo;, in the words of the Slovenian philosopher Slavoj Žižek. They drew attention to the precarity that lies at the heart of human rights, in the injunction to protect &amp;ldquo;life, liberty and security of person&amp;rdquo; and the intimate connection between survival, bodily integrity and social values. The significance of the protests lies in both the way they embodied their political objectives and the way they exposed this link between political and human needs. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The village also matters, not only because of what protesters fought for, but because it marks a place and time when once-terrorised people lost their fear. The physical site may now be gone, but the dream village where people dared to unite and build a community of care &amp;ndash; a village of diverse voices arguing, debating, interjecting and calling out &amp;ndash; cannot be dismantled as easily. The myth of the invincibility of the government has been shattered in Sri Lanka. The dream village, meanwhile, remains &amp;ndash; marking the potentiality of a people&amp;rsquo;s power.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist winter 2022 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6049/sri-lankas-dream-village#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-12-02T11:07:37Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-02T11:07:37Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION DECEMBER 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/12/open-discussion-december-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978465</id>
    <published>2022-12-01T09:59:32Z</published>
    <updated>2022-12-01T09:59:32Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Highs, Lows, and the Cosmic Perspective</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/11/highs-lows-and-the-cosmic-perspective/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It’s been an eventful few weeks since our last update; weeks that have seen both remarkable highs and terrible lows. It’s been, to paraphrase Charles Dickens, both the best and worst of times. We closed October with CSICon 2022, which returned to being in-person for the first …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978460</id>
    <published>2022-11-30T16:38:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-11-30T16:38:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Q&amp;A: Victoria Amelina</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6060/qa-victoria-amelina#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="p1"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Victoria Amelina is a writer from Lviv, Ukraine. She is the author of the novels &amp;ldquo;Fall Syndrome&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Dom&amp;rsquo;s Dream Kingdom&amp;rdquo;. The latter book, published in 2017, won the Best Book of the Year award at the Zaporizhzhya Book Fair, and was shortlisted for numerous awards, including: LitAkcent Book of the Year, Lviv City of UNESCO Literary Award and the European Union Prize for Literature. &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is Russia aiming to destroy Ukrainian culture?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Everyone was shocked when the Russians at the beginning of this war bombed the museum in Ivankiv, an urban settlement in the Kyiv Oblast. It contained the paintings of many famous artists, including the work of Maria Prymachenko. This is one of our worst fears. It&amp;rsquo;s very painful to lose people in war, of course. But losing culture and history is a tragedy too. Russians keep trying to punish us for having this history, and for being Europeans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;There was a poignant photo that emerged in the media after Russian troops left the town of Bucha, near Kyiv, back in late March. It showed a dead woman&amp;rsquo;s hand, with a key chain next to it, which displayed a symbol of the European Union . . . She thought that the European Union was her home. But Europe did not save her.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is behind the efforts to undermine a distinct Ukrainian identity?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;The Russian Federation hates Ukraine because the country has managed to become democratic. We have true elections. We are, you could say, obsessed about our freedom, and we&amp;rsquo;re ready to die for it. Russians cannot forgive us for that.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;We now have a very black joke here in Ukraine that if we don&amp;rsquo;t like some building, we should just write the word &amp;ldquo;children&amp;rdquo; on the building, because we know the Russians will destroy it. They act like terrorists. Russian officials keep warning Ukrainians that cities that do not surrender, like Kyiv and Lviv, will be completely destroyed, like Mariupol was. I&amp;rsquo;m sure Russia will attempt to keep bombing our historical and cultural sites.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there a historic precedent for this? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;In the 1920s there was a renaissance of Ukrainian culture, which for some time the Soviet regime allowed to flourish. Ukrainians were able to publish texts, and plays were allowed to run in theatres. There was an apartment building where some of the best writers in Ukraine all lived: the Slovo building in Kharkiv. Most of its inhabitants have since become known as &amp;ldquo;the Executed Renaissance&amp;rdquo;. They were arrested by [the Soviet secret police] and executed. That wiped out about 90 per cent of the best writers in Ukraine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has the Russian government acknowledged these past abuses? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;[After the fall of the Soviet Union] there was no attempt to understand what went wrong in their history. On the contrary, the Russian government has prosecuted the few individuals who were brave enough to talk about shameful episodes of their history. Take, for example, the graves [of the executed Ukrainian writers]. A historian named Yury Dmitriev, who took care of these graves, was arrested. He is, I believe, currently still in prison in Russia.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do so many Russians appear to believe the government&amp;rsquo;s propaganda on Ukraine and its past?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;The propaganda the Russian government uses is not even consistent. But Russians want to believe these lies. Unfortunately, the roots of it are very deep. They have an imperial mindset. This insinuates that it could not possibly be true that Ukrainians could have built a democratic state, or that they could have visa-free travel to Europe, or that Ukrainians are flourishing, and they are ready to be with Europe. It just doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit into the picture of the world the Russians have. This is cognitive dissonance. They want to keep believing that they are saving the world. They believed they saved Georgia, after the 2008 invasion. &lt;br&gt;They did the same in Chechnya [with two wars there from 1994 to 2000], where Russia committed a genocide. Russians are proud of that. They cannot see what is wrong with &lt;br&gt;this history.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ukraine became part of the USSR in 1922 and independent in 1991. Meanwhile, its borders changed multiple times during Soviet rule. How do Ukrainians deal with that complicated history? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Under any [totalitarian] regime you get used to it, and you more than cooperate. You become part of this regime. In my novel &lt;em&gt;Dom&amp;rsquo;s Dream Kingdom,&lt;/em&gt; I used the story of my grandfather. He was a Soviet military pilot. He became part of the Soviet regime. But he was from the east of Ukraine, where the &lt;em&gt;Holodomor&lt;/em&gt; [now recognised in Ukraine as an act of genocide] occurred. His family were victims of the that man-made famine, and he had terrible memories about that. I also remember my grandfather explaining to me the fear he felt if the Soviet army could potentially send him to Czechoslovakia in 1968.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;But regimes force people to do terrible things. As a Ukrainian I felt there was something wrong with that, and I should be somehow even ashamed. This is not what is happening in Russia today. There is no shame. They are proud of their victories, and they believe they&amp;rsquo;re the &lt;br&gt;saviours of Europe.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Dom&amp;rsquo;s Dream Kingdom&amp;rdquo; is set in Lviv, in the childhood home of science-fiction writer Stanislaw Lem. Why did you choose this setting?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s important to talk first about the history of Lviv, after the Second World War, when the population changed drastically. In 1939 we had more than [150,000] Jews living in Lviv [then known by its Polish name, Lw&amp;oacute;w]. After the war less than [one percent] of Jews survived. Stanislav Lem was a Polish author of Jewish origin. He suffered under Nazi occupation [and later went to Krakow in Poland]. He had survivor&amp;rsquo;s guilt there for all his life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;Researchers in Poland and Ukraine now point out that novels like &lt;em&gt;Solaris&lt;/em&gt;, and other books written by Lem, were not just random fictional stories. They were, in a way, his attempt to understand what happened to him during those years of occupations. Because the Lviv Lem lived under had three occupations. The Soviet Union occupied Lviv in 1939. Then the Nazis occupied the city in [June 1941]. Then the Soviets once again [in 1944].&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The 2014 Euromaidan revolution was a turning point for Ukraine, and your novel &amp;ldquo;Fall Syndrome&amp;rdquo; explores the lead-up to it. What changed?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;In 2014 we stopped having doubts about ourselves as Ukrainians. I was born in 1986, the year Chernobyl happened. As a child I witnessed the collapse of the Soviet Union. It was one thing in 1991, when the majority of Ukrainians voted for being independent. But it was drastically different when we were ready to fight for it in 2014. When Russia then started a war immediately after that [in eastern Ukraine] we showed that we would not support a puppet government in Kyiv.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;But what&amp;rsquo;s happening now is the Russians showing their true face. They show they are ready to kill women and children, and then pretend afterwards that it didn&amp;rsquo;t happen. It&amp;rsquo;s yet another level. I don&amp;rsquo;t know what will happen tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p3"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You work closely with PEN Ukraine. What does your work involve? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p4"&gt;Right now, PEN Ukraine is helping to evacuate writers from certain parts of Ukraine, where their lives are in danger. I am part of the so-called PEN security initiative that is helping with this. I have been reiterating the same point since the war began, when talking to an international &lt;br&gt;audience:&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p class="p5"&gt;I know you support us in Ukraine now, but please, stay with us &amp;ndash; not for a day, not for a week, not for a month, stay with us until victory, or until we are all dead, because this is what is at stake, I&amp;rsquo;m afraid.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6060/qa-victoria-amelina#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2022-11-29T12:32:05Z</published>
    <updated>2022-11-29T12:32:05Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>CFI: Last Chance to Stick Up For Science</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/11/cfi-last-chance-to-stick-up-for-science/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dear friend, When we look at how far we’ve come in bettering human health, lengthening lifespans, and increasing prosperity, one thing stands out: science saves.  Lifespans have doubled, modern medicine makes us healthier, and most of us have the food and basic comforts we need to do better than survive—to thrive. And it’s all due …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978453</id>
    <published>2022-11-23T12:09:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-11-23T12:09:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Featured"/>
    <category term="Original"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION NOVEMBER 2022</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/11/open-discussion-november-2022/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978443</id>
    <published>2022-11-01T09:48:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-11-01T09:48:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Misinformation Masquerading as Truth</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2022/10/misinformation-masquerading-as-truth/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! This is the time of year when many people are getting ready for Halloween. You may be getting ready for a costume party or stocking up on candy in anticipation of trick-or-treaters at your door. Most of our team is currently in Las Vegas getting ready for …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978437</id>
    <published>2022-10-18T17:15:06Z</published>
    <updated>2022-10-18T17:15:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The results are in!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint?&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;I recently invited people to take an online survey about sustainable lifestyle changes and over 800 people kindly responded. The work was conducted with Prof Mike Page from the University of Hertfordshire and Edinburgh Science, and the results are now in!&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Everyone were asked to estimate how many kilograms of carbon dioxide would be saved by taking a range of actions. Many of the ratings were hugely inaccurate, with people generally overestimating the effects of less impactful changes, such as unplugging appliances, but underestimating the contribution of larger lifestyle changes such as following a vegetarian diet. For example&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….unplugging a mobile phone charger saves around 2kg of CO2 emissions per year; yet one third of respondents thought that it saved five times that (100kg or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….leaving a television on standby emits around 15kg of CO2 per year, but a third of respondents estimated that it was far more significant (125 kg&amp;nbsp;or more).&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;….becoming a vegetarian can save over 600kg, yet half of the respondents thought that it only saved 300kg or less.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;…buying a blue jumper rather than a red one has no impact at all, but, on average, people thought that it would save 37kg.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;The good news is that other estimates about, for example, the impact of flying, were more accurate. Every little helps, and people should consider doing whatever they can to cut emissions. However, these results suggest that there are many widely believed myths about sustainable behaviour. There’s a real appetite to make changes, which is great, but many of us may need clearer information on how make the biggest impact.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who was kind enough to take part.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you know how best to cut your carbon footprint? I recently invited people to take an online survey about… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/04/26/the-results-are-in/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">The results are in!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13415</id>
    <published>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</published>
    <updated>2022-04-26T10:31:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>NEW SURVEY</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<p>I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability. It only takes a few minutes and it would be lovely if you could take part. All you need to do is click <a href="https://herts.eu.qualtrics.com/jfe/form/SV_7OjwGKXfXw80IM6" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. Thank you! </p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have teamed up with Edinburgh Science to conduct a short survey into your thoughts about climate change and sustainability.… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/03/30/new-survey/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">NEW SURVEY</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13379</id>
    <published>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</published>
    <updated>2022-03-30T19:29:19Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Real magic</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13231" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1433/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" data-orig-size="507,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520957&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;125&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1433" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=507" class="wp-image-13231 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg" alt="IMG_1433" width="268" height="338" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=268&amp;h=338 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=119&amp;h=150 119w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg?w=238&amp;h=300 238w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1433.jpg 507w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history of this strange performing art, and when I was 13 years old I wrote a school project entitled ‘The Art And History Of Conjuring’.</span></p>
<p>One section of this 34-page extravaganza was devoted to contemporary magicians and included the cover of a magic magazine featuring the legendary David Copperfield.</p>
<p><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">A few years ago, I was in Las Vegas with my friend and fellow magician, Massimo Polidoro. We went to see David Copperfield’s amazing show and he kindly invited us to his secret museum of magic. This stunning collection is housed is a large building on the outskirts of Vegas and contains a jaw dropping collection of apparatus, posters and books. It is the Smithsonian of magic and explores how magic shapes society, inspires technology, and creates a sense of wonder.</span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13232" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1435/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" data-orig-size="459,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635520987&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;50&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.02&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1435" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=459" class="wp-image-13232 alignright" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg" alt="IMG_1435" width="253" height="352" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=253&amp;h=352 253w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg?w=215&amp;h=300 215w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1435.jpg 459w" sizes="(max-width: 253px) 100vw, 253px"/>Due to the nature of the exhibits, David is only able to show a few people around the museum at any one time. Afterwards, David and I spoke about producing a book that provides readers with a personal tour of this magical space. Excited by the idea, we enlisted the help of brilliant magician David Britland and amazing photographer (and co-director of David Copperfield’s shows) Homer Liwag. Together, we put together a pitch document and were delighted when Simon and Schuster agreed to publish the book. Not only that, but the wonderful Priscilla Painton agreed to act as our editor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13233" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/img_1409/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" data-orig-size="480,640" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;1.8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;iPhone SE (2nd generation)&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1635263313&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;3.99&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;320&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="IMG_1409" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=480" class="wp-image-13233 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg" alt="IMG_1409" width="268" height="357" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=268&amp;h=357 268w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=113&amp;h=150 113w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg?w=225&amp;h=300 225w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/img_1409.jpg 480w" sizes="(max-width: 268px) 100vw, 268px"/><span style="color:var(--th-color-primary-base);font-family:var(--th-site-font-body);font-size:revert;">Three years on and our vision has become a reality. This 270-page glossy book is our love letter to magic. Filled with Homer’s stunning photographs, it celebrates a group of outsiders who bring a much-needed sense of magic into the world, including the man who fooled Houdini, the woman who caught bullets in her bare hands, and the illusionist who made himself vanish. Along the way we encounter a sixteenth-century manual on sleight of hand, stunning French automata, and even some coins that are said to have magically passed through the hands of Abraham Lincoln.</span></p>
<p>Over forty years ago, 13 year-old Wiseman write a school project on magic and referenced David Copperfield. Today, I am honoured to have worked with this legendary performer and co-authored a beautiful book on the topic. To me, that feels like real magic.</p>
<p>For information on how to purchase in the USA, click <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/David-Copperfields-History-of-Magic/David-Copperfield/9781982112912">here</a> and for the UK, click <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/David-Copperfields-History-Magic-Copperfield/dp/1982112913">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13235" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/71k22hd8aql/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" data-orig-size="2156,1400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="71K22hD8AqL" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=750" class="size-full wp-image-13235 aligncenter" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg" alt="71K22hD8AqL" width="2156" height="1400" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg 2156w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=150&amp;h=97 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=300&amp;h=195 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=768&amp;h=499 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2021/11/71k22hd8aql.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=665 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 2156px) 100vw, 2156px"/></p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I have been interested in magic since I was 8 years old.  Early on, I became fascinated with the history… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2021/11/01/real-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Real magic</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13225</id>
    <published>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</published>
    <updated>2021-11-01T15:01:20Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Evidence to House of Commons Sci Tech Select Committee on Research Integrity</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/12/evidence-to-house-of-commons-sci-tech-select-committee-on-research-integrity/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sorry not to be in regular blogging mode at the moment. Here’s a video of our evidence session to parliament, where they are running an inquiry into research integrity. I think clinical trials are the best possible way to approach this issue. Lots of things in “research integrity” are hard to capture in hard logical […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3498</id>
    <published>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</published>
    <updated>2017-12-05T11:42:17Z</updated>
    <category term="alltrials campaign"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How do the world’s biggest drug companies compare, in their transparency commitments?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/how-do-the-worlds-biggest-drug-companies-compare-in-their-transparency-commitments/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hereâ€™s a paper, and associated website, that we launch today: we have assessed, and then ranked, all the biggest drug companies in the world, to compare their public commitments on trials transparency. Regular readers will be familiar with this ongoing battle. In medicine we use the results of clinical trials to make informed treatments about […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3485</id>
    <published>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-27T06:33:23Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Meaningful Transparency Commitments: the WHO Joint Statement from Trial Funders</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/07/meaningful-transparency-commitments-the-who-joint-statement-from-trial-funders/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By now I hope you all know about the ongoing global scandal of clinical trial results being left unpublished, and of course our AllTrials campaign. Doctors, researchers, and patients cannot make truly informed choices about which treatments work best if they don’t have access to all the trial results. Earlier this year, I helped out […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3481</id>
    <published>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</published>
    <updated>2017-07-26T16:17:06Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
    <category term="publication bias"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2017/02/how-many-epidemiologists-does-it-take-to-change-a-lightbulb/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robin Ince just asked if I know any epidemiologist lightbulb jokes. I wrote this for him. How many epidemiologists does it take to change a lightbulb? Weâ€™ve found 12,000 switches hidden around the house. Some of them turn this lightbulb on, some of them donâ€™t; some of them only work sometimes; and some of them […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3472</id>
    <published>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</published>
    <updated>2017-02-01T12:49:44Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>“Transparency, Beyond Publication Bias”. A video of my super-speedy talk at IJE.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://www.badscience.net/2016/10/transparency-beyond-publication-bias-a-video-of-my-super-speedy-talk-at-ije/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">People oftenÂ talk about “trials transparency” as if this means “all trials must be published in an academic journal”. In reality, true transparency goes much further than this. We need Clinical Study Reports, and individual patient data, of course. But we also need the consent forms, so we can see what patients were told. We need […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Ben Goldacre</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://www.badscience.net/?p=3463</id>
    <published>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</published>
    <updated>2016-10-11T08:01:43Z</updated>
    <category term="bad science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
