<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-06-08T06:05:43Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>The AI hype machine might be in trouble</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/07/the-ai-hype-machine-might-be-in-trouble/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/theyre-the-same-picture.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/theyre-the-same-picture-150x83.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="83" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70344" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/theyre-the-same-picture-150x83.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/theyre-the-same-picture-300x166.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/theyre-the-same-picture.jpeg 320w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="lead"&gt;David Gerard brings up an interesting association: the crypto grifters, as their scam begins to disintegrate, have &lt;a href="https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2023/06/03/crypto-collapse-get-in-loser-were-pivoting-to-ai/"&gt;jumped ship to become AI grifters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ll be delighted to hear that blockchain is out and AI is in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li aria-level="1"&gt;Sequoia Capital, who wrote a now-deleted &lt;a href="https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2022/11/13/ftx-files-for-bankruptcy-and-the-fallout-begins-whos-next/"&gt;glowing profile of FTX founder Sam Bankman-Fried&lt;/a&gt;, has gone full AI. See their home page. [&lt;a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Sequoia&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;, &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href="https://archive.ph/7de7b"&gt;&lt;i&gt;archive&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt; of June 3&lt;/i&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li aria-level="1"&gt;Crypto VC firm Paradigm has broadened its focus to include AI. [&lt;a href="https://www.theblock.co/post/232247/crypto-vc-paradigm-ai"&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Block&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li aria-level="1"&gt;Circle’s Jeremy Allaire: “AI and blockchains are made for each other.” [&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/jerallaire/status/1661735753108570115"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Twitter&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li aria-level="1"&gt;IBM: “The convergence of AI and blockchain brings new value to business.” IBM previously folded its &lt;a href="https://davidgerard.co.uk/blockchain/2021/03/05/news-india-crypto-ban-north-korea-bitmex-execs-to-appear-ibm-blockchain-dead-more-mcafee-charges/"&gt;failed blockchain unit&lt;/a&gt; into the unit for its failed Watson AI. [&lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/blockchain-ai"&gt;&lt;i&gt;IBM&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not clear if the VCs actually buy their own pitch for ChatGPT’s spicy autocomplete as the harbinger of the robot apocalypse. Though if you replaced VC Twitter with ChatGPT, you would see a significant increase in quality.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huh. Interesting. I never trusted crypto, because everyone behind it was so slimy, but now they&amp;#8217;re going to slime the AI industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also interesting, though, is who &lt;em&gt;isn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/em&gt; falling for it. Apple had a recent shindig in which they announced all the cool shiny new toys for the next year, and they are actively incorporating &lt;em&gt;machine learning&lt;/em&gt; into them, but &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ChatGPT/comments/142zxgt/apple_avoids_ai_hype_at_wwdc_keynote_by_baking_ml/"&gt;they are definitely not calling it AI&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you had watched &lt;a href="https://developer.apple.com/wwdc23/"&gt;Apple&amp;#8217;s WWDC keynote&lt;/a&gt;, you might have realized the lack of mention of the term &amp;#8220;AI&amp;#8221;. This is in complete contrast to what happened recently at events of other Big Tech companies, such as Google I/O.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out that there wasn&amp;#8217;t even a single mention of the term &amp;#8220;AI&amp;#8221;. No, not even once.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The technology was referred to, of course, but always in the form of “machine learning” — a more sedate and technically accurate description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apple took a different route and instead of highlighting AI as the omnipotent force, they pointed to the features that they&amp;#8217;ve developed using the technology. Here&amp;#8217;s a list of the ML/AI features that Apple unveiled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improved Autocorrect on iOS 17: Apple introduced an enhanced autocorrect feature, powered by a transformer language model. This on-device machine learning model improves autocorrection and sentence completion as users type.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Personalized Volume Feature for AirPods: Apple announced this feature that uses machine learning to adapt to environmental conditions and user listening preferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enhanced Smart Stack on watchOS: Apple upgraded its Smart Stack feature to use machine learning to display relevant information to users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Journal App: Apple unveiled this new app that employs on-device machine learning to intelligently curate prompts for users.
&lt;p&gt;3D Avatars for Video Calls on Vision Pro: Apple showcased advanced ML techniques for generating 3D avatars for video calls on the newly launched Vision Pro.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transformer-Based Speech Recognition: Apple announced a new transformer-based speech recognition model that improves dictation accuracy using the Neural Engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Apple M2 Ultra Chip: Apple unveiled this chip with a 32-core Neural Engine, which is capable of performing 31.6 trillion operations per second and supports up to 192GB of unified memory. This chip can train large transformer models, demonstrating a significant leap in AI applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike its rivals, who are building bigger models with server farms, supercomputers, and terabytes of data, Apple wants AI models on its devices. On-device AI bypasses a lot of the data privacy issues that cloud-based AI faces. When the model can be run on a phone, then Apple needs to collect less data in order to run it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also ties in closely with Apple’s control of its hardware stack, down to its own silicon chips. Apple packs new AI circuits and GPUs into its chips every year, and its control of the overall architecture allows it to adapt to changes and new techniques.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Say what you think of Apple as a company, but one thing they know how to do is make money. Lots of money. They also have first-rate engineers. Apparently they are smart enough to not fall for the hype.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">David Gerard brings up an interesting association: the crypto grifters, as their scam begins to disintegrate, have jumped ship to become AI grifters. You’ll be delighted to hear that blockchain is out and AI is in: Sequoia Capital, who wrote a now-deleted glowing profile of FTX founder Sam Bankman-Fried, has gone full AI. See their […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70343</id>
    <published>2023-06-07T13:32:41Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-07T13:32:41Z</updated>
    <category term="Technology"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Quick update on Chris Licht</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/07/quick-update-on-chris-licht/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">Mr <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/06/there-are-consequences/">Licht</a> is <a href="https://www.rawstory.com/chris-licht-cnn-2661084160/">OUT</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Byers notes that the CNN Trump town hall combined with a less-than-flattering profile of Licht in The Atlantic led to “the near-total decimation of staff morale” and left Licht with few defenders at the network.</p></blockquote>
<p>Pay heed, media people: sucking up to Trump can kill your career.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mr Licht is OUT. Byers notes that the CNN Trump town hall combined with a less-than-flattering profile of Licht in The Atlantic led to “the near-total decimation of staff morale” and left Licht with few defenders at the network. Pay heed, media people: sucking up to Trump can kill your career.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70341</id>
    <published>2023-06-07T13:05:30Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-07T13:05:30Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don’t make Zinnia angry</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/07/dont-make-zinnia-angry/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class="lead"&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve been a fan of Zinnia Jones for a long time, starting way back in the day when she was doing a lot of atheist content. She was always calm and dispassionate, and put out well-scripted videos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You want to see her when she gets angry? Easy. She lives in Florida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center"&gt;&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lm07oKXIfFE" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Righteous.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I’ve been a fan of Zinnia Jones for a long time, starting way back in the day when she was doing a lot of atheist content. She was always calm and dispassionate, and put out well-scripted videos. You want to see her when she gets angry? Easy. She lives in Florida. Righteous.</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70339</id>
    <published>2023-06-07T12:53:09Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-07T12:53:09Z</updated>
    <category term="Feminism, Gender, and Equality"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>There are consequences?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/06/there-are-consequences/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/licht.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/licht-134x150.jpeg" alt="" width="134" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-70336" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/licht-134x150.jpeg 134w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/licht-268x300.jpeg 268w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/06/licht.jpeg 328w" sizes="(max-width: 134px) 100vw, 134px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Chris Licht, the former head of CNN who pushed that disastrous, mismanaged Trump town hall on us, seems to have faced some kind of rebuke from the men who control the pursestrings. He has undergone some ambiguous lateral transfer or downgrade — <a href="https://www.dailykos.com/stories/2023/6/2/2173015/-Chris-Licht-architect-of-CNN-s-Trump-town-hall-steps-aside">he’s not in charge anymore</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>Anyway, the guy made no friends with his “let Republicans lie” brand of journalism because, really, that’s not what journalism is supposed to be. It’s supposed to inform people of the truth. CNN’s staff hated what Licht was trying to do. The viewers hated it, and left in droves. Freaking Newsmax started beating CNN in ratings. And the business suits hated it, because if money isn’t being made, what’s the point? In short, he shit the bed.</p></blockquote>
<p>It’s not much of a consequence, but it’s something. If nothing else, all his rich friends know that he is in disgrace, which is probably what hurts him most. Being outright fired would hurt him better, though.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chris Licht, the former head of CNN who pushed that disastrous, mismanaged Trump town hall on us, seems to have faced some kind of rebuke from the men who control the pursestrings. He has undergone some ambiguous lateral transfer or downgrade — he’s not in charge anymore. Anyway, the guy made no friends with his […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70335</id>
    <published>2023-06-06T12:38:55Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-06T12:38:55Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Are you middle class?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/06/06/are-you-middle-class/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/02/dollarsign.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/02/dollarsign-121x150.jpeg" alt="" width="121" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-65477" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/02/dollarsign-121x150.jpeg 121w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/02/dollarsign-242x300.jpeg 242w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2022/02/dollarsign.jpeg 289w" sizes="(max-width: 121px) 100vw, 121px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I took this little <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/interactive/2023/middle-class-income/?itid=hp-top-table-main_p001_f003">survey in the Washington Post</a> that takes into account your income, number of dependents, and region of the country you live in, and it tells me that I am officially and totally middle class. I’m right smack in the center of the arbitrarily defined boundaries that delimit “middle class” — and that the way I got to this point was by getting rid of those pesky kids who were holding me back. Fifteen years ago, I discovered, I was way down deep in <em>lower</em> middle class territory.</p>
<blockquote><p>Your household has a middle-class income, and you have the financial security associated with the middle class. Your income is similar to others in your Zip code above the median for rural Minnesota. Rural Minnesota is an inexpensive place to live, and you would still be considered middle income anywhere in the country.</p></blockquote>
<p>It’s a comfortable place to be, but there is no hope that I will ever be wealthy. That’s good enough.</p>
<p>I won’t ask you what class you fall into, because only a grifter cares about that sort of thing.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I took this little survey in the Washington Post that takes into account your income, number of dependents, and region of the country you live in, and it tells me that I am officially and totally middle class. I’m right smack in the center of the arbitrarily defined boundaries that delimit “middle class” — and […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=70333</id>
    <published>2023-06-06T12:13:26Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-06T12:13:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How taxpayers subsidise evangelism</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6127/how-taxpayers-subsidise-evangelism#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="'The current state of the law means that religious organisations are given government-backed support to promote their views'" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/NewHumanist_.jpg" height="1414" alt="An illustration shows the Archbishop of Canterbury, King Charles III and Prime Minister Rishi Sunak as painted figures on stained glass windows" width="1920" is=""&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The charity sector in England and Wales is enormous. Over 180,000 organisations today benefit from tax relief, better access to grant funding and the reputational cachet of being a registered charity. The justification for this special treatment is that charities are supposed to act for the public benefit. It might surprise you, though, to discover just how many of these charities are religious in nature. In a search I recently made of the charity register, the term &amp;ldquo;religious&amp;rdquo; was included in the &amp;ldquo;objects and activities&amp;rdquo; section of nearly 20,000 organisations. Of these, a significant proportion specifically included the &amp;ldquo;advancement&amp;rdquo; of Christianity or other religions as one of their purposes &amp;ndash; by which they claim their right to charitable status.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In other words, everyone who pays taxes or votes in England and Wales today is helping to subsidise the advancement of religion by thousands of organisations, and to support its approval by the state. This is despite the fact that the country itself is less and less religious. The results of the 2021 census have revealed that less than half of the population (46.2 per cent) are &amp;ldquo;Christian&amp;rdquo;, while 10.6 per cent follow minority religions, and 37.2 per cent have &amp;ldquo;no religion&amp;rdquo;. Christianity has decreased significantly from the last census in 2011, while non-religion has increased.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Despite this, charity law continues to consider the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; as in itself a purpose which qualifies an organisation to be a charity &amp;ndash; quite separately from any other charitable aims such as advancing education or relieving poverty. In theory, such an organisation must demonstrate that its advancement of religion is publicly, and wholly, beneficial. But in practice, the Charity Commission, especially in the last decade, seems to have put little effort into requiring organisations to produce evidence to prove this. The current state of the law means that religious organisations &amp;ndash; particularly those associated, however loosely, with a mainstream faith &amp;ndash; are given government-backed support to promote their views. Why is merely &amp;ldquo;advancing religion&amp;rdquo; enough to qualify an organisation for the privileges of a charity?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The idea of charity, in Europe at least, has its roots deep in Christianity. &amp;ldquo;Now abideth faith, hope, and charity,&amp;rdquo; wrote St Paul, as translated in the King James Bible, &amp;ldquo;but the greatest of these is charity.&amp;rdquo; But while the Church encourages the practice of giving alms to the poor and other worthy causes, it has also long taught that one of the worthiest causes is giving to itself. This was already a target for satire in Chaucer&amp;rsquo;s Canterbury Tales. &amp;ldquo;Therfore in stede of wepynge and preyeres / Men moote yeve silver to the povre freres,&amp;rdquo; he wrote ironically of the rapacious Friar.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The first modern law about charity in England, the &amp;ldquo;Statute of Charitable Uses&amp;rdquo; of 1601, contained in its preamble a list of purposes, donations for which were to be protected from misappropriation. Some &amp;ldquo;charitable uses&amp;rdquo;, such as &amp;lsquo;&amp;ldquo;Releife of aged impotent and poore people&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Schooles of Learninge&amp;rdquo;, are still familiar. &amp;ldquo;Religion&amp;rdquo; itself was not on the list, although the &amp;ldquo;Repaire&amp;rdquo; of &amp;ldquo;Churches&amp;rdquo; was, among other public works. In 1891, however, the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; was definitively established by the House of Lords as a distinct &amp;ldquo;head&amp;rdquo; (or &amp;ldquo;purpose&amp;rdquo;) of charity, along with the advancement of education, the relief of poverty and &amp;ldquo;other purposes beneficial to the community&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;'Any religion is better than none'&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the 20th century, there was a legal presumption that the first three heads &amp;ndash; on religion, education and relief of poverty &amp;ndash; were inherently of &amp;ldquo;public benefit&amp;rdquo;. Thus there was usually no need for religious organisations to provide any evidence that advancing their faith would benefit wider society. As the High Court put it in the case of Neville vs Madden (1962), which concerned a synagogue trust, &amp;ldquo;As between different religions the law stands neutral, but it assumes that any religion is at least likely to be better than none.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the early 2000s, the Charity Commission &amp;ndash; the government organisation responsible for regulating charities &amp;ndash; seemed willing to judge for itself whether advancing a particular religion was in fact solely &amp;ldquo;religious&amp;rdquo;, or beneficial. In 1999, it held that the Church of Scientology could not rely on the presumption of public benefit, because it was relatively new. It had also failed to demonstrate that its activities were of public benefit. Finally, the Commission held that Scientology was not a religion in the first place: although its faith did involve a &amp;ldquo;supreme being&amp;rdquo;, its practices did not count as &amp;ldquo;reverence or veneration&amp;rdquo; of that being. (Which leads, of course, to the knotty question of how a secular body like the Commission is supposed to determine what is or is not a religion.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 2004, the Commission rejected the application of Good News for Israel to register as a charity, because one of its objects was to promote Aliyah, &amp;ldquo;the return of Jewish people to the land promised to them by God&amp;rdquo;. This, the Commission concluded, had &amp;ldquo;implications&amp;hellip; beyond the religious and spiritual&amp;rdquo;, raising &amp;ldquo;political, economical, social and civil order issues&amp;rdquo;. This disqualified GNI from registering, because, as is still the case now, the purposes or &amp;ldquo;charitable objects&amp;rdquo; of a charity, as set out in its governing document, must all be charitable.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It was only in the Charities Act of 2006 that the &amp;ldquo;presumption of benefit&amp;rdquo; for religious (and other) charities was finally removed. The new state of affairs, as the Commission put it, was that &amp;ldquo;advancing religion can be seen as a public good if such advancement can be demonstrated to be in relation to a system having a benign and positive content which is being advanced for the benefit of the public&amp;rdquo;. Parliament had belatedly recognised that the benefits of advancing a particular religion could not be taken for granted.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Charitable advantages&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;At least, that was the theory. There were, however, warning signs that the presumption of benefit for religions might not be displaced so easily. One of these was the Labour government&amp;rsquo;s refusal to insert &amp;ldquo;or belief&amp;rdquo; into the relevant clause that confirmed the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; as a charitable purpose. Adding &amp;ldquo;or belief&amp;rdquo; would have brought the clause into line with other legislation, like the Equality Act 2010, which recognised &amp;ldquo;religion or belief&amp;rdquo;, including lack of belief, as a protected characteristic under Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights, taken together with the prohibition on discrimination under Article 14.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There seems to have been a feeling that there were enough charitable purposes already, and any deserving non-religious-belief organisations would be covered by a clause allowing stated purposes to be extended by analogy, or else they could be considered educational charities. This had been the case for the South Place Ethical Society (SPES), now Conway Hall, which won a court battle in 1980 to give it recognition as a charity under the &amp;ldquo;advancement of education&amp;rdquo; head &amp;ndash; specifically, &amp;ldquo;education in humanist ethical principles&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Today, the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; remains in the Charities Act 2011, which replaced the 2006 Act. Now is the time for this clause to be repealed. Above all, because it perpetuates a systemic favouritism towards religious organisations which is not justified in modern Britain.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Register a charity and your organisation will receive a host of benefits. Gift Aid and other tax advantages, like on income tax and stamp duty, business rates relief and better access to grant funding are only some of these perks. Add to that improved public trust and confidence in your organisation, including from having a registered charity number and information being shown on the public register.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In other words, registering as a charity enables an organisation to be subsidised by the taxpayer, to obtain additional funding more easily and to benefit from the reputational cachet of being a charity on the official Register of Charities, with an appearance of oversight by a government body. These are significant advantages.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Who benefits?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The very concept of &amp;ldquo;advancing religion for the public benefit&amp;rdquo; is riddled with problems. Some of these emerge from the Commission&amp;rsquo;s own guidance on the issue, first published in 2008 (it has been marked as &amp;ldquo;under review&amp;rdquo; since at least 2018).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;According to the guidance, to &amp;ldquo;advance religion&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;to promote or maintain or practise it and increase belief in the supreme being or entity that is the object or focus of the religion&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; for example by &amp;ldquo;seeking new followers&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;promoting particular tenets&amp;rdquo;. As an example of &amp;ldquo;promoting tenets&amp;rdquo;, it posits an Islamic charity that could help Muslims in hospital to &amp;ldquo;observe the requirements of the Islamic Halal practice&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is no explanation of how this practice &amp;ndash; involving the consumption of ritually slaughtered animals &amp;ndash; might benefit anyone beyond those individuals concerned.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Or take a real example: the Christian Science Society, Oxted, which first registered in 1965. The sole purpose of this registered charity is &amp;ldquo;to maintain and spread the truth as set forth in the Bible and interpreted in &amp;lsquo;Science and Health with Key to the Scriptures&amp;rsquo; by Mary Baker Eddy&amp;rdquo;. In Chapter XII of this curious text, first published in 1875, Eddy proclaims that &amp;ldquo;If you believe in inflamed and weak nerves, you are liable to an attack from that source. You will call it neuralgia, but we call it a belief&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; Whatever this means, it is hard to see how promoting such a tenet would be for the public benefit &amp;ndash; or, indeed, what basis the organisation has for characterising their unprovable beliefs as &amp;ldquo;the truth&amp;rdquo; in a public secular document.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Seeking new followers&amp;rdquo; certainly benefits the religions themselves. As the Evangelical Alliance, a Christian charity, put it in 2008, &amp;ldquo;religious organisations need to be able to sustain themselves into the future, something that has always been done through the medium of evangelism&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; and through the extraction of funds that inevitably follows.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the ability of religious organisations to fund themselves cannot be of public benefit, unless the practice of the religion itself is. Most of the examples the guidance offers of the benefits of a religion, such as &amp;ldquo;the spiritual and moral education of children&amp;rdquo;, primarily concern its adherents rather than the public, or else would qualify under other heads of charity, such as the relief of poverty.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Advancing religion could, the guidance says, &amp;ldquo;contribut[e] towards a better society, for example by promoting social cohesion and social capital&amp;rdquo;. On the other hand &amp;ndash; a point which the guidance does not consider &amp;ndash; advancing one religion at the expense of others, or other non-religious beliefs, could also sow mutual distrust. Altogether, the guidance is nebulous and weak on what should be the crucial section, namely why advancing religion &amp;ndash; whatever the content of its teachings &amp;ndash; should qualify an organisation to receive public money.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A fourth, practical difficulty concerns how the Charity Commission is supposed to determine whether the views and practices of thousands of religious charities are of public benefit &amp;ndash; or whether they might be positively harmful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Examples of types of harm associated with religious charities include conversion therapy, circumcision, political extremism and discriminatory religious &amp;ldquo;courts&amp;rdquo;. These were discussed in &amp;ldquo;For the Public Benefit?&amp;rdquo;, a 2019 report by the National Secular Society. More examples keep coming to light. Take the Moray Coast Baptist Church, which registered as a charity in August 2022. Its pastor, Donald Clough, posted a sermon on its website in which he said that &amp;ldquo;society would be a lot better if women would submit to their husbands and tend to their children and take care of their home.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The conclusion drawn by the NSS report still holds: the Commission is &amp;ldquo;not regulating the sector as rigorously as it should&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;5 reasons to change the system&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Another question concerns equal treatment between religious and non-religious organisations. Not more than a handful of organisations advocating non-religious views have applied to register as charities via the &amp;ldquo;analogy&amp;rdquo; clause. The biggest one that has is Humanists UK (HUK), whose first charitable object (out of four) is &amp;ldquo;the advancement of Humanism, namely a non-religious ethical lifestance the essential elements of which are a commitment to human wellbeing and a reliance on reason, experience and a naturalistic view of the world.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 2011, after an extensive campaign by HUK, the Commission accepted &amp;ldquo;the advancement of Humanism&amp;rdquo; as a charitable object in its own right. This seemed tacitly to admit that the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; could be extended to non-religious beliefs by analogy, thereby avoiding claims for discrimination under the ECHR.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Religion, however, remains the paradigm. Indeed, the Commission&amp;rsquo;s acceptance of humanism, according to Richy Thompson of HUK, was &amp;ldquo;without prejudice as to whether the advancement of other beliefs might be considered charitable&amp;rdquo;. In other words, it seems to have been a decision on the particular merits of humanism (as defined by HUK), not on the general desirability of non-religious views.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In fact, one of the prejudices that non-believers have always faced in Britain, and continue to face today in some quarters, is that without the guidance of a religion, they have no moral code by which to orient themselves. HUK&amp;rsquo;s characterisation of humanism as an &amp;ldquo;ethical lifestance&amp;rdquo; seems to have been partly shaped in response to this perception; the motto on its website, &amp;ldquo;think for yourself, act for everyone&amp;rdquo;, illustrates the explicitly moral outlook adopted by this organisation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet no one seems to have considered whether a non-religious approach might be beneficial, not because it is still moral despite not being religious, but rather because it does something that is not analogous to religion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For instance, the purpose of Atheism UK (which is not a charity) is to &amp;ldquo;challenge religious claims and the propagation of religious faith&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; not to present a moral code. My own magazine, the &lt;em&gt;Freethinker&lt;/em&gt;, is funded by Secular Society Ltd, which is also not a charity, even though it is a non-profit whose objects include promoting the &amp;ldquo;utmost freedom of enquiry&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Apparently criticising belief systems is less beneficial to society than simply propagating them. The only charity that came up on the Register under &amp;ldquo;atheism&amp;rdquo; was Genexis, an organisation run by an evangelical church in Leamington Spa. Its sole object is, &amp;ldquo;for the public benefit, the advancement of the Christian faith worldwide with a particular emphasis on cultures and geographical areas which are facing a rise in secularism, humanism and atheism, in particular by advancing the case for theism (as opposed to atheism) based on scientific, philosophical and historical evidence.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In other words, an organisation whose explicit aim is to oppose atheism can be charitable, but not one designed to promote it. This is not to argue that every association of unbelievers ought to be a charity. Equally, organisations from Humanists UK to the Church of England can, and do, still qualify as charities under other perfectly legitimate heads, such as the &amp;ldquo;promotion of religious harmony&amp;rdquo; or the &amp;ldquo;advancement of education&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; one of the purposes of the Rationalist Association, which publishes &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt;. My objection is simply to the specific provision of &amp;ldquo;advancing religion&amp;rdquo;, or even humanism, as a separate head of charity, for a number of reasons.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;1. Because this provision is unfairly biased in favour of established religions, as opposed to either new religions or many non-religious approaches to life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;2. It assumes that propagating a belief system or ideology is better than criticising it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;3. The Charity Commission is either reluctant or does not have the resources to question the public benefit of many charities whose only purpose is to &amp;ldquo;advance religion&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;4. The provision adds a superfluous head of charity to an already inflated list.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;5. Charities that qualify as such purely for &amp;ldquo;advancing religion&amp;rdquo; are often undeserving of public support. (Even Humanists UK, as Richy Thompson said, &amp;ldquo;would be happy to see the advancement of religion removed as a head of charity&amp;rdquo; and would be prepared to dispense with the &amp;ldquo;advancement of humanism&amp;rdquo; by the same token.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;When religion meets politics&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is also a final reason why &amp;ldquo;advancing religion&amp;rdquo; should be removed as a head of charity: because religious ideologies are so often closely entwined with politics. According to the Commission&amp;rsquo;s current guidance on &amp;ldquo;Campaigning and political activity&amp;rdquo;, charities &amp;ldquo;can campaign to achieve their purposes. But a charity can&amp;rsquo;t have a political purpose, or undertake political activity that is not relevant to the charity&amp;rsquo;s charitable purposes.&amp;rdquo; The reason for this is that, &amp;ldquo;constitutionally, it is not possible for the Commission or the Courts to make decisions about whether a change in the law or government policy would be for the public benefit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;However, despite the prohibition on political purposes, the Charity Commission&amp;rsquo;s own guidance recognises that &amp;ldquo;campaigning and political activity can be legitimate and valuable activities for charities to undertake&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; provided that such activity be undertaken by a charity &amp;ldquo;only in the context of supporting the delivery of its charitable purposes&amp;rdquo; and does not become &amp;ldquo;the reason for the charity&amp;rsquo;s existence&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You might wonder if there were a certain equivocation here. Moreover, in its most recent update to its guidance on political campaigning, published in November 2022, the Commission emphasised that &amp;ldquo;campaigning, advocacy and political activity are all legitimate and valuable activities for charities to undertake.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Such guidance is hardly likely to strengthen the already thin line between religious and political beliefs. Moreover, religious charities frequently run campaigns for or against legislation &amp;ndash; such as on assisted dying, abortion, same-sex marriage or hate speech laws. In contrast, organisations which, like the National Secular Society, do not invoke any sort of belief system cannot benefit from government subsidies when campaigning, usually against religious groups, on the same issues.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The subsidies also continue. In July 2022, the Department for Levelling Up, Housing and Communities announced grants for 16 religious charities to work in partnership with secular authorities on community projects, under a pilot &amp;ldquo;Faith New Deal Fund&amp;rdquo;. Among these was the (Anglican) Church Revitalisation Trust (CRT), whose charitable object is &amp;ldquo;the advancement of the Christian religion&amp;rdquo;, and one of whose aims on its website is &amp;ldquo;the evangelisation of the nation&amp;rdquo;. CRT received a grant of &amp;pound;200,000 to help &amp;ldquo;plant&amp;hellip; churches in key cities across England and Wales&amp;rdquo;, as well as to &amp;ldquo;recruit and train clergy&amp;rdquo;. In other words, more government money is being used to prop up the Church of England.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the last resort, the decision whether to lend support to an organisation promoting Paganism, Pastafarianism, Christianity, atheism or none of the above, should be a matter for the individual conscience. Retaining a clause like the &amp;ldquo;advancement of religion&amp;rdquo; effectively gives some religious beliefs and practices a free pass to subsidies and status on a preferential basis, regardless of whether they offer any real benefit to the public.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The only just way forward would be to repeal the clause. This prospect seems distant, however, given the current religious influences on both the Conservative and Labour parties. This is unfortunate, because the longer religious organisations are allowed to cling on to their privileges, the harder it will be to take them away.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6127/how-taxpayers-subsidise-evangelism#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-06T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-06T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A glimpse into the history of parenthood</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6121/a-glimpse-into-the-history-of-parenthood#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Image credit: Ilya Pavlov" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/ilya-pavlov-XPT-OtA0E-8-unsplash-_1_.jpg" height="1282" alt="A stock image of a man and a woman with two children" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It would not be a surprise to anyone that men in the UK become fathers, on average, roughly three years later than women. Indeed, anthropologists have observed such discrepancies in parental age, or &amp;ldquo;generation times&amp;rdquo;, in over 99 per cent of contemporary cultures. But has this always been the case?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A study published in &lt;em&gt;Science Advances&lt;/em&gt; in January provides the first evidence that these sex differences have been a feature across all 250,000 years of human history. Improving the precision of these sorts of estimates helps evolutionary geneticists to better date major population events, such as mass migrations or interbreeding events between early humans and extinct hominins such as the Neanderthals.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The researchers at Indiana University first studied a large genetic dataset of Icelandic families, which had data on parental age. This allowed them to model how parental age and sex relates to the types of new DNA mutations that arise between generations. The model was then applied to a dataset of genomes from across the world, allowing the researchers to estimate both when in human history a mutation was likely to have arisen, and also the likely age and sex of the parents who preceded it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The results found that the average generation time for humans across history was 26.9 years, with more than seven years difference between the typical age at conception for men (30.7 years) compared to women (23.2 years).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Whilst reaching puberty at basically the same age as women, men can typically reproduce for an additional 20 years, which likely explains some of the difference. However, the researchers suggest that social factors could also play a role, such as expectations to accrue assets or status before starting a family.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Some have raised valid concerns that the model does not sufficiently account for factors other than parental age affecting the pattern of mutations, such as the impact of environmental exposures. However, the work takes us one step closer to understanding the biology, demography and social structures of our ancient ancestors.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6121/a-glimpse-into-the-history-of-parenthood#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-05T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-05T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION JUNE 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/06/open-discussion-june-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978548</id>
    <published>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-01T08:02:31Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Victory City by Salman Rushdie</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6126/book-review-victory-city-by-salman-rushdie#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img title="Salman Rushdie. Credit: Alamy" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/T67N9Y.jpg" height="1279" alt="A photo portrait of Salman Rushdie" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Victory City&lt;/strong&gt; (Penguin Books) by Salman Rushdie&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 1989, Iran&amp;rsquo;s Ayatollah Khomeini issued a fatwa on Salman Rushdie and his publishers for his novel &lt;em&gt;The Satanic Verses&lt;/em&gt;, claiming his depiction of a Muhammad-like figure was blasphemous. The international writers&amp;rsquo; organisation PEN was instrumental in the campaign calling for Rushdie&amp;rsquo;s protection and for his inalienable right to free expression to be recognised.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Later, I became director of English PEN&amp;rsquo;s Writers in Prison Committee and witnessed for myself Rushdie&amp;rsquo;s dedication to persecuted writers worldwide. He was always a signatory on our petitions and served as president of American PEN from 2004 to 2006. Today, he is a patron of Humanists UK and a laureate of the International Academy of Humanism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Last summer, Rushdie was brutally attacked at a literary event in New York state, leaving him blinded in one eye. Months later &lt;em&gt;Victory City&lt;/em&gt;, his latest novel, was published. Words endure. The pen is indeed mightier than the sword.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Victory City&lt;/em&gt; is an epic tale with a feminist slant. The novel&amp;rsquo;s protagonist is Pampa Kampana, a fictitious poet and prophetess who creates an empire, and then writes about its rise and fall in a narrative poem called the Jayaparajaya. The poem is buried in a clay pot sealed with wax and unearthed four and a half centuries later. Rushdie cleverly frames &lt;em&gt;Victory City&lt;/em&gt; as a version of her-story, rather than his-story, retold in plainer language by &amp;ldquo;a spinner of yarns&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The novel opens in 14th-century southern India. Nine-year-old Pampa witnesses her mother burning to death as part of a mass suicide after their kingdom is defeated. Orphaned, she is blessed by the goddess Parvati and later reaches a monk&amp;rsquo;s cave dwelling, where she lives for nine years with a scholar, Vidyasagar, who abuses her: &amp;ldquo;He did not do it often, because scholarship usually left him too tired to do much about his lusts, but he did it often enough.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When she comes of age Pampa sows a city, Vijayanagar (Sanskrit for victory city), using a bag of magical seeds, and whispers its people into existence. It becomes known as Bisnaga. During her lifetime &amp;ndash; she dies aged 240 &amp;ndash; Pampa attempts to give women equal rights in a patriarchal world. She promotes education for all and religious tolerance. The arts are seen as essential and female warriors are as much to be feared as their male counterparts.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Pampa gives birth to three daughters with her lover, a dashing Portuguese trader, whom she prioritises over the three arrogant sons she has with the second king of Bisnaga. She insists their &amp;ldquo;barbarian&amp;rdquo; sons are sent away. War is waged against neighbours, battles are won and lost. After the king&amp;rsquo;s death, Pampa is herself exiled and lives in an enchanted forest with her three daughters and two loyal servants.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Fantastical elements are woven throughout the narrative. As well as magic seeds, there are talking birds, a forest goddess and troublesome pink monkeys. Pampa bides her time and returns to Bisnaga 132 years later, becoming Queen Regent. The kingdom flourishes under her rule. Later her despotic husband has her blinded with red-hot irons &amp;ndash; particularly chilling, given Rushdie&amp;rsquo;s own fate. Inevitably, with Pampa weakened, the empire declines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Rushdie is finely tuned to the political manoeuvrings that allow tyranny to flourish: &amp;ldquo;the blurring between the worship of the god and the devotion felt for the king&amp;rdquo;, the repression of fundamental human rights, the renaming of streets, and using religion as &amp;ldquo;a tool for the maintenance of social control.&amp;rdquo; The rulers come from a mixed stock, including cowherds and soldiers, and dynasties can change overnight. Rushdie also plays with different registers of tone and language. Passages of lyrical prose are followed by modern idiom &amp;ndash; one character might say &amp;ldquo;fuck&amp;rdquo;, another punctuates their sentences with &amp;ldquo;isn&amp;rsquo;t it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I imagine &lt;em&gt;Victory City&lt;/em&gt; will divide readers, as it has critics. It&amp;rsquo;s a challenging read, but one that celebrates the power of storytelling. Pampa&amp;rsquo;s conclusion echoes Rushdie&amp;rsquo;s lifelong belief: &amp;ldquo;Words are the only victors.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6126/book-review-victory-city-by-salman-rushdie#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-06-01T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-06-01T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Robotic poetry</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6125/robotic-poetry#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="An AI-generated image from Boris Eldagsen's controversial ongoing series, 'Pseudomnesia'" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/boris_eldagsen_THETIE_s-copy.jpg" height="600" alt="An AI-generated image from Boris Eldagsen's controversial ongoing series, 'Pseudomnesia', which shows a black and white, hyper-realistic image of a man and a woman with their arms around each other" width="508"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The recent release to the public of a wave of new art and writing tools, such as DALL-E and ChatGPT, has been greeted with an outpouring of alarmist rhetoric. The software, based on artificial intelligence, responds to prompts like &amp;ldquo;create a picture of a woman eating salad and laughing&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;write a poem in the style of Lewis Carroll&amp;rdquo; by searching the web for examples and building on these to create an approximation: an image (though often disturbingly mangled) or something like a poem (at least in the sense that it rhymes). Sometimes the prompt works well and the production can seem magical.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Sceptics have been horrified. &amp;ldquo;AI in art&amp;rdquo; is &amp;ldquo;a creditless, thankless, and soulless alternative to the real thing,&amp;rdquo; Jade King complains in the &lt;em&gt;Gamer&lt;/em&gt; magazine. Writing in the &lt;em&gt;Washington Post&lt;/em&gt;, musician and producer T-Bone Burnett and author Jonathan Taplin worry that AI threatens &amp;ldquo;the core creative act&amp;rdquo; which if &amp;ldquo;radically diminished, or replaced&amp;hellip; will stop culture in its tracks.&amp;rdquo; The underlying fear here is that artificial intelligence will rise up, exploit and replace us. Art &amp;ndash; real art &amp;ndash; is deeply human. These new tools, which scrape the web for content, simply remix and remash without any personal, individual spark.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are real concerns about the way AI picks up source material without payment, just as there were reasonable concerns about the way that early hip-hop artists lifted source tracks without recompensing the original creators. Art under capitalism, like most labour under capitalism, is monetised in ways that benefit those at the top and grind down those at the bottom, and new tech is quickly subverted to that purpose.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Exploitation, though, isn&amp;rsquo;t new. Nor is it inhuman. On the contrary, the exploitation of artists is often rationalised by the pretence of art as unquenchable and unbindable individualism. Our most famous music artists may sing about being rebellious and free, but are often trapped in contracts involving financial exploitation, or worse (the latest case being pop star Kesha, accusing her producer of physical and sexual abuse.) If art is your soul, then the business of art is selling your soul, which has some obvious downsides.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Why not, instead, embrace the mechanism? Forget originality and the divine afflatus. If the AI is going to control us all, shouldn&amp;rsquo;t we be working to become the AI? Let us seize the means of production of ourselves!&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s the essential argument of the wonderful &lt;em&gt;Against Expression&lt;/em&gt;, a 590-page anthology of &amp;ldquo;uncreative writing&amp;rdquo; edited by poets Craig Dworkin and Kenneth Goldsmith. Published more than a decade ago, in 2011, it holds some valuable insights for our own fraught cultural moment. The writing in the book is &amp;ldquo;uncreative&amp;rdquo; for the same reason that AI art is often labeled as such. The 100-odd authors in the book create their poems by cutting up or lifting text from other sources: literature, internet detritus, grammar books, psychological testing instruments.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anthology demonstrates the long and rich tradition of such practices. The &amp;ldquo;writers&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; including William Burroughs, Kathy Acker, Marcel Duchamp, Andy Warhol and Claudia Rankine &amp;ndash; find text and then remix and recontextualise. They are less like Byron (&amp;ldquo;Yet, Freedom! yet thy banner, torn, but flying,/streams like the thunderstorm against the wind&amp;rdquo;) and more like, say, ChatGPT, trawling the internet for content to slice up, rewrite and misinterpret.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One of my favorite poems from the anthology is an excerpt from Rory Macbeth&amp;rsquo;s 2007 book &lt;em&gt;The Bible (alphabetized)&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s exactly what the title says: a list of every word in the Bible in alphabetical order, including eight pages of: &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be be&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The different authors in the volume aren&amp;rsquo;t different because they have different identities and unique voices. They&amp;rsquo;re different because they draw from different data sets. Macbeth uses the Bible. Nada Gordon&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Abnormal Discharge&amp;rdquo; (first published in the anthology itself) reproduces post titles from the Women&amp;rsquo;s Health Forum message board (&amp;ldquo;possible pregnancy/vaginal discharge Jessica/Abnormal Pap Smear Jennifer/Abnormal Pap&amp;rdquo;). H. L. Hix&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;God Bless&lt;/em&gt; (2007) is a book of poems entirely composed of phrases from the speeches of George W. Bush and the public statements of Osama bin Laden. Claude Cosky&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;The First Thousand Numbers Classified in Alphabetical Order&amp;rdquo; begins with &amp;ldquo;Eight, eight-hundred, eight hundred and eight&amp;rdquo; and ends with &amp;ldquo;two-hundred and two.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I personally find this impersonal approach to writing exhilarating. I laughed out loud at all those &amp;ldquo;be&amp;rdquo;s. I thought to myself, &amp;ldquo;I never realised that eight was the first number in the alphabetical order.&amp;rdquo; But if you are not, like me, a neurodivergent oddball, you may well be less convinced. Why would anyone read this? Why would anyone write it?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Co-editor Goldsmith is most famous for &amp;ldquo;Day&amp;rdquo;, a 2003 poem in which he wrote out the entirety of the &lt;em&gt;New York Times&lt;/em&gt; from 1 September 2000. He argues in the preface to &lt;em&gt;After Expression&lt;/em&gt; that the rise of uncreative writing is in part a reaction to the increasing manipulability and algorithmicisation of text made possible by the internet. &amp;ldquo;Never before has language had so much materiality &amp;ndash; fluidity, plasticity, malleability &amp;ndash; begging to be actively managed by the writer.&amp;rdquo; T-Bone Burnett sees AI as eating away at originality as it hoovers up old art and spews out garbled and rearranged (but still old) art. Goldsmith, in contrast, thinks the ease of hoovering and spewing is itself a new kind of creation and a new kind of creativity. Which is really more creative: writing (yet another) lyric poem about lost love, or listing every word in the Bible alphabetically?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The poetry compiled in &lt;em&gt;Against Expression&lt;/em&gt; is a system or a process. When Robert Fitterman rewrites Ernest Hemingway&amp;rsquo;s 1926 novel &lt;em&gt;The Sun Also Rises&lt;/em&gt; by removing all sentences except for those that begin with the pronoun &amp;ldquo;I,&amp;rdquo; he is both removing the self from literature and centering the self in literature. Is he mocking Hemingway&amp;rsquo;s self-absorption? Enjoying it? Replacing it with his own? It&amp;rsquo;s all of those, I would argue, and also just a joke that makes you laugh &amp;ndash; at once an intimate and universal, and therefore impersonal, response.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Similarly, when Dan Farrell turns a psychological diagnostic tool into a series of &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo; statements (&amp;ldquo;I do things that keep me from becoming physically unhealthy. I feel angry. I am pretty angry about things these days&amp;rdquo;), the voice is an eerie mirror of self and soul. There is an &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;, but it&amp;rsquo;s not an &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;. It&amp;rsquo;s just an algorithm, a grammatical convenience. The effect is poignant, repulsive, beautiful, uncanny, hard to categorise &amp;ndash; like poetry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To dismiss AI art as &amp;ldquo;soulless&amp;rdquo; is to assume that the purpose of art is to demonstrate soul, to validate a romantic personhood at the centre of culture and existence. But, as &lt;em&gt;Against Expression&lt;/em&gt; shows by its inclusion of works by figures like Samuel Beckett and W. B. Yeats, the presence of the soul in art has long been an object of scepticism.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a call for tech utopianism. Algorithmic art, with or without AI assistance, can be moving or tedious, fun or irritating, just like any other kind of creative endeavour. But when we assume we can produce originality via a conventional chord change or rhyming couplet, we may be just another cog in the culture industry&amp;rsquo;s endless grinding soulless reiteration of soul.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Artificial intelligence won&amp;rsquo;t free us from this dynamic. But if we listen, it might speak back our own thoughts, or their absence, in words meaningless enough to make some new sense of a tired idea, from &amp;ldquo;be&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;eight&amp;rdquo; to &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6125/robotic-poetry#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-05-30T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-30T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A breakthrough in the hunt for chemical weapons</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6120/a-breakthrough-in-the-hunt-for-chemical-weapons#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Image credit: James Wainscoat" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/james-wainscoat-gthfMEtd7A8-unsplash-_1_.jpg" height="1279" alt="A stock image of thick vegetation" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;On 22 April 1915, a cloud of noxious gas drifted from German lines towards the Allied troops entrenched on the Ypres battlefield. The soldiers were wholly unprepared, with no masks to protect them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Not wanting to be caught offguard again, the Allies dispatched a chemist to the battlefield, to shed light on this devestating new weapon. Of course, by the time John Scott Haldane and his team arrived the gas had long since dispersed. But subtle clues were left. They noticed a discolouration of the brass buttons on the unfortunate soldiers&amp;rsquo; uniforms. Something had reacted with the zinc and copper in the brass, and the culprit was chlorine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Over 100 years later, inspectors at sites of chemical weapon attacks face a similar problem. The chemical agents are reactive, volatile and frequently work at very low concentrations, all of which make them difficult to detect. Often autopsies are used, but this can be complicated as human remains need careful and considerate collection and transportation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Plants, however, are much easier to work with. This approach has been recently pioneered by a group from TNO Defence in the Netherlands. They exposed plants to mustard gas, sarin (a nerve agent deployed by Syrian President Bashar al-Assad in 2013), chlorine and Novichok (used in the 2018 Salisbury attacks). Vegetation survives the exposure, but is not totally unaffected. Each of these agents reacts with proteins within the plants. These modified proteins can be easily extracted and detected using highly sensitive mass spectrometry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The method was tested on basil, stinging nettles and bay laurels, suggesting the approach will likely work for a wide variety of species. The only issue was that exposure to common household bleach generated the same response as chlorine gas. Meaning, in the absence of brass buttons, there is more work to be done to rule out this source of false positives.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Nevertheless, the methodology shows strong promise and now just requires some samples from real-world incidents to validate the approach. Let&amp;rsquo;s hope TNO Defence don&amp;rsquo;t get these samples any time soon.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist summer 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6120/a-breakthrough-in-the-hunt-for-chemical-weapons#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-05-29T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-29T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MAY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/05/open-discussion-may-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978543</id>
    <published>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</published>
    <updated>2023-05-01T10:11:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Agree to Disagree</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/agree-to-disagree/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! As Steven Pinker wrote recently in the Boston Globe, “The very concept of freedom of expression is anything but intuitively obvious.” He’s right, of course. When we are confronted with ideas we find disagreeable, dangerous, or downright abhorrent, our first instinct is likely to want to silence …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978537</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/open-discussion-april-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978526</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Be Tongue-Tied</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/science-cannot-be-tongue-tied/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It might be funny, if it weren’t so worrisome. Recent weeks have seen some absurd new instances of science beset by would-be censors operating under the banner of “inclusion.” Examples are many, and they come from all over the globe. We’ll look at an ongoing controversy in …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978517</id>
    <published>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
