<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-04-25T21:28:55Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Another Supreme Court justice bought &amp; paid for</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/25/another-supreme-court-justice-bought-paid-for/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch-144x150.jpeg" alt="" width="144" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69949" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch-144x150.jpeg 144w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch-288x300.jpeg 288w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch-500x520.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/gorsuch.jpeg 694w" sizes="(max-width: 144px) 100vw, 144px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">We have the receipts: <a href="https://www.politico.com/news/2023/04/25/neil-gorsuch-colorado-property-sale-00093579">Neil Gorsuch has a great big conflict of interest</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>For nearly two years beginning in 2015, Supreme Court Justice Neil Gorsuch sought a buyer for a 40-acre tract of property he co-owned in rural Granby, Colo.</p>
<p>Nine days after he was confirmed by the Senate for a lifetime appointment on the Supreme Court, the then-circuit court judge got one: The chief executive of Greenberg Traurig, one of the nation’s biggest law firms with a robust practice before the high court. Gorsuch owned the property with two other individuals.</p>
<p>On April 16 of 2017, Greenberg’s Brian Duffy put under contract the 3,000-square foot log home on the Colorado River and nestled in the mountains northwest of Denver, according to real estate records.</p></blockquote>
<p>It’s not as if this was an attempt to curry favor with a judge presiding over big cases…</p>
<blockquote><p>Since then, Greenberg Traurig has been involved in at least 22 cases before or presented to the court</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh.</p>
<p>I guess when the process for appointing him was corrupt, you can’t expect a mere Supreme Court justice to behave ethically.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have the receipts: Neil Gorsuch has a great big conflict of interest. For nearly two years beginning in 2015, Supreme Court Justice Neil Gorsuch sought a buyer for a 40-acre tract of property he co-owned in rural Granby, Colo. Nine days after he was confirmed by the Senate for a lifetime appointment on the […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69948</id>
    <published>2023-04-25T17:02:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-25T17:02:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Crime"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The sheep look up</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/25/the-sheep-look-up/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/UM-regents.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/UM-regents-147x150.png" alt="" width="147" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69946" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/UM-regents-147x150.png 147w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/UM-regents.png 200w" sizes="(max-width: 147px) 100vw, 147px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">I teach. I’ve been at this university for 23 years, and I try to avoid the management side of things — I stay away from the administration building, I don’t even care who is the university president as long as they leave me alone. This may have been a very bad idea.</p>
<p>I got a notice from the administration that they are accepting applications for interim president of the university, because the last one is abandoning us after a short 5 years of employment (that’s not surprising, U presidents seem to flit hither and yon, another reason to ignore them.) But it meant I had to take a minute to figure out what’s going on.</p>
<p>Our outgoing president, Joan Gabel, is paid <strong>over $700,000/year</strong>. I don’t know that she is worth that much. Now I learn that she’s being offered an <a href="https://kstp.com/kstp-news/top-news/u-of-m-president-gabel-could-get-additional-260k-if-she-stays-through-june/">additional $260,000 if she stays through June</a>. All right, that’s a pretty sweet deal she’s had. What is she being offered by the University of Pittsburgh?</p>
<p>She’s had a few scandals — the biggest being that she took a position on the board of Securian, a financial company that does a lot of money management for the university. This was a serious conflict of interest, not to mention that she’s getting paid a buttload of money to be the U president, and should be devoting full time to her job. The Board of Regents said it was OK, though, although our governor said it was not. She resigned eventually. Maybe she’s mad at us because we wouldn’t let her rake in more money with a side gig?</p>
<p>And then, the Board of Regents…every time I hear about them, the less impressed I am. These are a bunch of politicians and business people who don’t understand the purpose of an educational system. I’ve mentioned Sviggum before — the bozo who thought UMM was “too diverse”. Now I learn that the chair of the board, Ken Powell, was the disgustingly rich <a href="https://www.startribune.com/pay-watch-general-mills-ken-powell-made-24-4-million-in-last-year-as-ceo/440548233/?refresh=true">CEO of General Mills</a> who made $24 million in the year before he retired. He is, supposedly, retired, but is now appointed to the chair of the Board of Regents — he’s the guy who thought is was no problem for her to work with Securian, who approved her exorbitant salary. The Regents main purpose seems to be to dip into the university till and give money to each other.</p>
<p>All I can say is that if I got paid tens of millions in my last year here, I would definitely definitively absolutely retire. I’d be done. I’d go relax with my grandchildren, and wouldn’t come back to plague my university for years to come, and I certainly wouldn’t be working hard to transfer money from hardworking faculty and staff salaries to serve the leeches appointed to administrative positions.</p>
<p>There’s no hope that I’ll get paid that much — that’s like more than my lifetime income — but here’s the deal. Appoint me to the interim presidency, pay me like a half million for my services, and I’ll try to keep the money going to the people who really deserve it, and then quietly disappear when my term is done. You can trust me on that. I was such a good boy when the regents visited my university in March, not confronting them at all and turning around and walking away when I saw them coming. I promise to ignore all of their blandishments in the future, as well.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I teach. I’ve been at this university for 23 years, and I try to avoid the management side of things — I stay away from the administration building, I don’t even care who is the university president as long as they leave me alone. This may have been a very bad idea. I got a […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69945</id>
    <published>2023-04-25T14:00:11Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-25T14:00:11Z</updated>
    <category term="Academics"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The most punchable face in America is back!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/25/the-most-punchable-face-in-america-is-back/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">And he’s giving us <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/martin-shkrelis-dr-gupta-ai-chatbot-is-a-medical-and-legal-nightmare">even more reason to punch him</a>!</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/shkreli.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/shkreli.jpeg" alt="" width="256" height="144" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-69943" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/shkreli.jpeg 256w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/shkreli-150x84.jpeg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px"/></a></p>
<blockquote><p>Infamous “Pharma Bro” Martin Shkreli announced his newest venture yesterday, and it’s about as awful as you’d expect. In a Substack post and on Twitter, he unveiled DrGupta.ai, a “virtual healthcare assistant” that (predictably) Shkreli believes will disrupt medicine—in spite of some very real and worrying legal and ethical gray areas.</p>
<p>“My central thesis is: Healthcare is more expensive than we’d like mostly because of the artificially constrained supply of healthcare professionals,” he wrote on Substack. “I envision a future where our children ask what physicians were like and why society ever needed them.”</p>
<p>“Dr. Gupta” is just Shkreli’s latest health venture since being released from prison last May. Last year, he founded Druglike, a drug discovery software platform being investigated by the Federal Trade Commission. The FTC is looking into whether Shkreli is violating a court-ordered lifetime ban on working in the pharmaceutical industry by running Druglike.</p></blockquote>
<p>Madness. If you replace all the healthcare professionals who generate the data that is leeched off by a glorified chatbot with said chatbot, where is the information that they parrot going to come from? All you’re going to have left is a feedback loop that is disconnected from any reality checks, it’s going to get progressively worse, and we’re not going to get any new medical knowledge.</p>
<p>It’s quite rich that he’s blaming the high expenses of medical care on scarce skilled medical labor and knowledge, when he’s the guy who artificially elevated the cost of life-saving drugs. Blame the greedy pharmaceutical executives instead.</p>
<p>Hey, people like Shkreli are the ones who could be replaced by a mindless software program!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">And he’s giving us even more reason to punch him! Infamous “Pharma Bro” Martin Shkreli announced his newest venture yesterday, and it’s about as awful as you’d expect. In a Substack post and on Twitter, he unveiled DrGupta.ai, a “virtual healthcare assistant” that (predictably) Shkreli believes will disrupt medicine—in spite of some very real and […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69942</id>
    <published>2023-04-25T12:56:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-25T12:56:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Medicine"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I know what kind of houseplant I want to get this summer</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/25/i-know-what-kind-of-houseplant-i-want-to-get-this-summer/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana-300x199.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="199" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-69940" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana-300x199.jpg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana-150x100.jpg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana-768x510.jpg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana-500x332.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/marijuana.jpg 1000w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Back in the long gone days of my youth, when I was working long hours as a nurseryman at a wholesale nursery in Kent, Washington, there were certain plants I admired greatly. This place had a small greenhouse just for bonsai that the owners tended carefully just about every day (mere laborers like me couldn’t touch those.) They sold lace maples, which were probably my favorite tree at that time — I bought one for my parents. But by far the most beautiful plants in the whole place were these big, gloriously bushy, vividly green plants raised out back, secretly, by a couple of the workers. These were the healthiest plants I’ve ever seen, lovingly tended by the crew on breaks, initially raised illicitly under the benches in a hothouse and then transplanted to a sunny spot in an empty field.</p>
<p>You can guess what kind of plant they were. Unfortunately, just as they were reaching peak growth, the owner discovered them and took a machete to them.</p>
<p>There will be <a href="https://www.mprnews.org/story/2023/04/24/mn-house-puts-marijuana-bill-to-a-vote-with-senate-on-deck">no machetes in Minnesota this summer</a>!</p>
<blockquote><p>Minnesota’s foray into legal marijuana reached the first major decision point as the state House considered a bill Monday that establishes a seed-to-sale program and streamlines a process for clearing prior criminal offenses off records.</p>
<p>The vote – along with one set for Friday in the Senate – won’t end the debate. Differences in the two versions would have to be reconciled before anything reaches Gov. Tim Walz, who supports permitting adults over 21 to buy, possess and use cannabis.</p>
<p>But if a bill passes before May 22, Minnesota’s marijuana landscape would change starting this summer.</p>
<p>“Cannabis will be no longer illegal this summer,” said the bill’s lead sponsor, Rep. Zack Stephenson, DFL-Coon Rapids. “The regulation, rulemaking and licensing process will take many more months. Beyond that you will of course also be able to home grow starting this summer so it will be a while before Minnesotans can expect to see a dispensary open up.”</p></blockquote>
<p>I should mention my least favorite plant: kinnikinik. They had acres of that potted stuff that I had to shuffle around and weed and load on trucks — it’s a popular, low growing ground cover that may have been the bread and butter of the nursery, but I just found it boring.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Back in the long gone days of my youth, when I was working long hours as a nurseryman at a wholesale nursery in Kent, Washington, there were certain plants I admired greatly. This place had a small greenhouse just for bonsai that the owners tended carefully just about every day (mere laborers like me couldn’t […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69939</id>
    <published>2023-04-25T12:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-25T12:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>When voters get it wrong</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6107/when-voters-get-it-wrong#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/NewHumanistFalseConsciousness2.jpg" height="1486" alt="A cartoon shows a sneering man smothering a voter as they cast their ballot" width="1920"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If real life was a Hollywood movie, a great many world leaders &amp;ndash; from Putin to Orb&amp;aacute;n to Bolsonaro &amp;ndash; would be classic, almost cheesy villains. Yet according to a curious modern orthodoxy, we are led to believe that politicians who are elected must be taken seriously, lest we insult those who voted them in. Even as elected politicians across the world commit acts as outrageous as razing the Amazon, inciting a gun-wielding mob or deporting asylum seekers to Rwanda, their actions are normalised. The bad guys are winning everywhere, but any desire to stop them is perversely constrained.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the field of economics, it is commonplace to observe that people make bad decisions. We neglect our pensions, stick with our overpriced insurance plans and scoff mediocre takeaways on the sofa. In fact, an entire sub-field, behavioural economics, is devoted to anatomising different varieties of poor decisions &amp;ndash; from bias (systematic errors that skew everyone&amp;rsquo;s choices in a single direction) to noise (random mistakes caused by the vagaries of individual circumstance). Bestselling books have brought these insights to a global audience: &lt;em&gt;Thinking, Fast and Slow&lt;/em&gt; by Nobel Prize winner Daniel Kahnemann lays bare the cognitive flaws that &amp;ldquo;consistently violate&amp;rdquo; the &amp;ldquo;rules of rational choice&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Two other behavioural economists, Richard Thaler and Cass Sunstein, developed nudge theory as a policy response: if we can&amp;rsquo;t be trusted to make good decisions, then corporations and governments should design better &amp;ldquo;choice architecture&amp;rdquo; to help us improve our lives by default. Rates of organ donation are increased by switching from opt-in to opt-out; school cafeterias encourage healthier diets by placing salad rather than chips at eye level. The &amp;ldquo;science of choice&amp;rdquo;, Thaler and Sunstein wrote in their highly influential book &lt;em&gt;Nudge: Improving Decisions About Health, Wealth and Happiness&lt;/em&gt;, has &amp;ldquo;raised serious questions about the rationality of many judgements and decisions that people make&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet if we are quite happy to admit we are irrational in the realm of economics, when it comes to politics, the very notion that people tick the &amp;ldquo;wrong&amp;rdquo; boxes is taboo &amp;ndash; even if doing so adversely affects their lives. Indeed, the more wrong-headed the decision, the harder it is to criticise, as &amp;ldquo;remoaners&amp;rdquo; have found to their cost. In 2017, Conservative MP Robert Goodwill defended the ongoing disaster of Brexit by rejecting the idea that &amp;ldquo;the British people who voted for Brexit were stupid and didn&amp;rsquo;t understand&amp;rdquo;; on the contrary, he insisted, &amp;ldquo;they knew exactly what they were voting for&amp;rdquo;. That phrase &amp;ldquo;the will of the people&amp;rdquo; implies, in itself, conscious self-determination; utilitarian action designed to produce good consequences.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the supermarket, therefore, humans are frail and erring, but as soon as they step into the voting booth they become discerning and perspicacious. Voters&amp;rsquo; views are truths to be divined by pollsters; politicians endlessly refer to the need to &amp;ldquo;listen&amp;rdquo;; media pundits refer to opinions they hear &amp;ldquo;on the doorstep&amp;rdquo; as if they are inherently original, rather than noting the resemblance to yesterday&amp;rsquo;s headlines.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The more democracy is hollowed out, corrupted and degraded, the more naively we take voting at face value. As Trump ransacked constitutional rules and norms, liberals tied themselves in knots; they were desperate to critique a figure clearly outside the boundary of democratic acceptability, yet felt they had to respect his place within it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So if homo economicus was knocked off his pedestal decades ago, homo politicus is still very much intact. We are well aware of the depressingly effective commercial forces shaping consumer behaviour &amp;ndash; Percy Pigs at the till, byzantine energy tariffs &amp;ndash; yet the dark arts of political persuasion are far less widely discussed. Raise the possibility that, in 2023, we are under the spell of propaganda, and you run the risk of being accused of a kind of student-y, out-dated scaremongering.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;The return of false consciousness&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There used to be a name for voting against your best interests: false consciousness. But the term has fallen out of fashion amongst academics and commentators. For political scientist Colin Hay, it &amp;ldquo;conjures up a deeply condescending conception of the social subject as an ideological dupe&amp;rdquo;. High up above the &amp;ldquo;ideological mists which tame the masses&amp;rdquo; is the &amp;ldquo;enlightened academic&amp;rdquo; who may &amp;ldquo;look down to discern the genuine interests of those not similarly blessed&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet our reluctance to interrogate manifestly poor electoral choices means that it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to acknowledge the reality of malign political persuasion at the worst possible time. In the UK and elsewhere, we are more influenced than ever by ministerial message discipline, continual polling and spin on an industrial scale. Reports of the death of the traditional media are in an important sense premature: newspaper circulation may be in free-fall, but these mostly billionaire-owned outlets still have a surprisingly strong hold over public conversation. The reaction of the &lt;em&gt;Mail&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sun&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Times&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Telegraph&lt;/em&gt; to the latest skulduggery of the British government sets the tone: the question of &amp;ldquo;cut through&amp;rdquo;, how things are &amp;ldquo;playing&amp;rdquo; with the public, is the only test that matters. Scandals like &amp;ldquo;Partygate&amp;rdquo; have been largely contained by tabloids selecting only the tamest photographs of Boris Johnson celebrating his birthday during lockdown, accompanied by forgiving headlines such as &amp;ldquo;Is that it?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Power is not now simply imposed. It&amp;rsquo;s exerted insidiously through the aggressively ascendant illusion that ordinary working people are finally having their say. Contemporary autocrats are masters of the humility topos, deploying winning hubris to defuse any challenge. Posh and rich as they are, these faux friends of the grassroots constantly cite the wisdom of the voter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Just when we need it most, the critique of manipulation has been depoliticised and transposed to a technocratic realm, defused by popular science facts and consumer finance tips, and recruited to the self-help project of life optimisation. Interestingly, Cass Sunstein published a book in 2021 promisingly titled &lt;em&gt;Liars: Falsehoods and Free Speech in an Age of Deception&lt;/em&gt;, but it&amp;rsquo;s concerned with myths such as those spread by anti-vaxxers, rather than political persuasion. It&amp;rsquo;s a firmly apolitical book, in fact, which displays an uncritical belief in governments&amp;rsquo; ability to regulate misinformation; never mind the mendacious behaviour of many democratically elected governments themselves.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;According to the Britannica definition, &amp;ldquo;false consciousness&amp;rdquo; denotes &amp;ldquo;people&amp;rsquo;s inability to recognise inequality, oppression, and exploitation in a capitalist society because of the prevalence within it of views that naturalise and legitimise the existence of social classes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There was a time when this concept animated academic seminars and Labour party meetings. It&amp;rsquo;s usually attributed to Karl Marx, but the phrase was coined by Friedrich Engels, in a letter to the Communist scholar Franz Mehring in 1893. In any case, both Marx and Engels argued that capitalism operates not only by oppressing the workers, but also by persuading them to conspire in their oppression by subscribing to the myth of social mobility. Later, Marxists used the concept to account for the apparent puzzle of why workers didn&amp;rsquo;t revolt. Theorists such as Antonio Gramsci and Louis Althusser described how the ruling classes cultivate shared forms of &amp;ldquo;common sense&amp;rdquo; that disguise and sustain inequality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A version of this idea originated much earlier: the 16th-century poet, magistrate and friend of Michel de Montaigne, &amp;Eacute;tienne de La Bo&amp;eacute;tie, wrote that there are three possible reasons why people submit to tyranny: the force of custom; distraction by &amp;ldquo;bread and circuses&amp;rdquo;; and the fact that tyrants surround themselves with expanding circles of loyal dependents: in other words, as the sociologist Steven Lukes summarises, &amp;ldquo;inertia, manufactured consent, and patronage&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thomas Frank updated the idea with scathing verve in his classic 2004 book &lt;em&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the Matter with Kansas?&lt;/em&gt;, which exposes the paradox &amp;ldquo;of working-class guys in mid-western cities cheering as they deliver up a landslide for a candidate whose policies will end their way of life, will transform their region into a &amp;lsquo;rustbelt&amp;rsquo;, will strike people like them blows from which they will never recover&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;More recent still is the popular &amp;ldquo;Leopards Ate My Face&amp;rdquo; parody thread on the Reddit website, satirising people who regret their predictably disastrous electoral choices: &amp;ldquo;Leopards Ate My Face When I Voted For The Leopards Eating People&amp;rsquo;s Faces Party&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Systematic falsehoods&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But these articulations of false consciousness are the rare exceptions. Left-wing theorists abandoned the territory just as prominent right-wingers began to co-opt their ideas: the British Conservative politician Michael Gove cites Gramsci as a strategic, if not ideological, influence. Progressives, meanwhile, have become diffident and tongue-tied, stricken with the fear of associating delusion with class.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So it is that we find ourselves in a toxic spiral. As nudge theorists are fond of pointing out (presumably in order to not appear paternalistic), smart people can be duped too. They may be, in some cases, more susceptible &amp;ndash; as David Robson claims to show in his 2020 book &lt;em&gt;The Intelligence Trap: Why Smart People Make Dumb Mistakes&lt;/em&gt;. But making good decisions is not just about being smart; it&amp;rsquo;s also about having access to good information. It&amp;rsquo;s therefore a problem that we live in a culture that demonises the intellectual &amp;ldquo;elite&amp;rdquo;: being well-informed has itself come to be regarded as a marker of being out of touch.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The association between rationality, condescension and well-meaning but patronising progressives erodes our ability to call out right-wing administrations when voters are misled. Perverse decisions are validated against supposedly &amp;ldquo;elitist&amp;rdquo; reason. As one American voter told Buzzfeed during the 2016 election: &amp;ldquo;Hillary Clinton isn&amp;rsquo;t alone in saying 25 per cent of Americans are deplorable. That is a sentiment that is rampant upon the American left. . . . And I think the American people aren&amp;rsquo;t stupid. And that&amp;rsquo;s the problem with Hillary Clinton. She thinks we&amp;rsquo;re all stupid.&amp;rdquo; Clinton was wrong to blame the sinner rather than the sin, but her mistake has led to almost universal liberal anxiety about questioning voters&amp;rsquo; choices.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Progressives collude, therefore, in the conservative framing of this scepticism as the left not having faith in voters. &amp;ldquo;The Conservatives,&amp;rdquo; Jacob Rees-Mogg commented about the 2019 election that handed Boris Johnson an 80-seat majority, &amp;ldquo;trust the British people &amp;ndash; the opposition benches do not.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;ldquo;people aren&amp;rsquo;t stupid&amp;rdquo; sounds egalitarian, but it actually perpetuates inequality. As the sociologist Steve Hanson has commented: &amp;ldquo;False consciousness doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the working classes are idiots, but it does mean that they have been systematically fed untruth.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Whose interests?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But what if people know they&amp;rsquo;re being lied to, but choose to vote against their interests anyway? And who gets to define what &amp;ldquo;best interests&amp;rdquo; really means? Affluent progressives, for their part, arguably exhibit economic false consciousness every time they vote for left-wing parties that would tax more of their income.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As the philosopher Slavoj Žižek notes, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to have a very clear idea of what the reality is and still act in self-destructive ways. &amp;ldquo;One knows the falsehood very well,&amp;rdquo; he writes, showing the limitations of the Britannica definition of false consciousness, &amp;ldquo;and still one does not denounce it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When it comes to the working class in Britain, some voters may be ideologically right-wing, while others may feel &amp;ndash; even after decades of austerity, low wages and measly benefits under successive Conservative governments &amp;ndash; that the other side is not much better. In some countries, the left have now been out of office so long they&amp;rsquo;re considered almost &amp;ldquo;unelectable&amp;rdquo;: they&amp;rsquo;ve effectively lost their clout.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Another explanation is that put-upon voters favour right-wing parties that appear to confer on them some dignity, as opposed to liberals who seem to pity them. Around the world, shabbily corrupt populists have done a pretty good job of convincing ordinary people that they are themselves reassuringly ordinary, in the sense of vividly exemplifying the crooked timber of humanity.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;And populists have also convinced many blue-collar voters that, despite their offshore wealth and private jets, they share those voters&amp;rsquo; values. The very politicians who promote the financialisation of everything piously point out that not everything is about money, you know.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The culture wars have turbocharged this process. Republicans in the US have used social policies &amp;ndash; on abortion, or immigration &amp;ndash; to encourage poor white voters to betray their economic interests. Here in the UK, confected debates about patriotism and &amp;ldquo;wokeness&amp;rdquo; are shifting the political fault-line ever further away from the gaping socio-economic divide and towards a split based on social attitudes, level of education and whether you live in a city or a seaside town.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Time for an update&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is some evidence that working-class support for parties that will harm them economically is overstated. The authors of a 2016 journal article entitled &amp;ldquo;There Is Nothing Wrong with Kansas&amp;rdquo; found that poor white voters in America actually tend to vote for Democrats around 75 per cent of the time. They found that the small remaining group of poor whites who vote Republican didn&amp;rsquo;t vote against their interests more often than other groups. So it&amp;rsquo;s complicated. The result of the next general election will be influenced by a number of factors, including rationality, compassion, self-interest and cynicism. But voters will also be influenced by ideology, still energetically propagated by old and new media.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In recent years, left-leaning think tanks have focused much of their energies on extending and enhancing voter &amp;ldquo;engagement&amp;rdquo;: developing digital democracy platforms, or participatory budgeting initiatives. It&amp;rsquo;s right to give more people more of a say. But we should also examine why they say what they do, and acknowledge that simply having a voice (on social media or in a citizens&amp;rsquo; assembly) doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily diminish the powerful factors influencing people&amp;rsquo;s views and allegiances.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;If the original Marxist meaning of false consciousness is now ill-suited to today&amp;rsquo;s complex, diverse society, it is high time we updated it. Otherwise, the monopolies and magnates wrecking the world will continue to be bolstered by the widespread notion that they do so with authentic grassroots consent.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Since the political earthquakes of 2016, there&amp;rsquo;s been a surfeit of commentary about &amp;ldquo;post-truth&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;fake news&amp;rdquo;. Yet while we may accept we are living in this environment, there is still a widespread nervousness about accepting that &amp;ndash; individually and collectively &amp;ndash; we are being managed. As plutocrats prosper and the planet burns, we must channel our energies into understanding how public opinion is shaped. Those who regard themselves as progressive are letting the bad guys get away with it. We think we are doing the right thing, but we are getting it all wrong.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6107/when-voters-get-it-wrong#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-25T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-25T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Tucker Carlson is OUT</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/24/tucker-carlson-is-out/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson.jpg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson-100x150.jpg" alt="" width="100" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-57285" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson-100x150.jpg 100w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson-200x300.jpg 200w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson-500x749.jpg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/12/tuckercarlson.jpg 672w" sizes="(max-width: 100px) 100vw, 100px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Well, I’m surprised. As an aftershock of the Dominion lawsuit and the embarrassment of Fox News, <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/media/2023/04/24/tucker-carlson-leaves-fox-news/">Tucker Carlson is out on his ass</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>In a shocking announcement, Fox News announced Monday that its controversial yet top-rated prime-time host Tucker Carlson is leaving the network.</p>
<p>“Fox News Media and Tucker Carlson have agreed to part ways,” the network said in a statement. “We thank him for his service to the network as a host and prior to that as a contributor.”</p>
<p>The apparently hasty parting — Carlson gave no indication he was leaving in his last nightly appearance Friday, and the network was still running promos for his show Monday morning — came less than a week after Fox settled a defamation lawsuit from Dominion Voting Systems, which had sued the network for false claims about the 2020 election. Carlson was among several on-air personalities expected to testify.</p></blockquote>
<p>You might be wondering…was it because of his racism? Because of his lies? Because of his lack of qualifications? No, of course not. Those things are prerequisites for working at Fox News.</p>
<p>It was because he told the truth and chewed out Fox management for promoting lies about the election.</p>
<blockquote><p>But it was Carlson’s comments about Fox management, as revealed in the Dominion case, that played a role in his departure from Fox, a person familiar with the company’s thinking told The Post.</p>
<p>“Do the executives understand how much credibility and trust we’ve lost with our audience?” Carlson wrote to a colleague in a message a day after Fox, like other media outlets, called the election for Joe Biden. It was a sentiment echoed by others at Fox in the fall of 2020, as even network officials who disbelieved Trump’s election-fraud conspiracy theories fretted that countering them strongly would alienate their conservative viewers.</p>
<p>In another message, Carlson referred to management with an expletive: “Those f—–s are destroying our credibility.” He later wrote: “A combination of incompetent liberals and top leadership with too much pride to back down is what’s happening.”</p></blockquote>
<p>This termination is sending a message to all the other “journalists” at Fox News: you can lie all you want, be as biased as you want, as long as you are supporting the particular lies and bigotry of Rupert Murdoch and other executives.</p>
<p>It must be scary being a highly paid apparatchik at a propaganda organ, but he’ll get no sympathy for me. Maybe he can land a new job with a North Korean news agency?</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Well, I’m surprised. As an aftershock of the Dominion lawsuit and the embarrassment of Fox News, Tucker Carlson is out on his ass. In a shocking announcement, Fox News announced Monday that its controversial yet top-rated prime-time host Tucker Carlson is leaving the network. “Fox News Media and Tucker Carlson have agreed to part ways,” […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69935</id>
    <published>2023-04-24T17:34:05Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-24T17:34:05Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Agree to Disagree</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/agree-to-disagree/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! As Steven Pinker wrote recently in the Boston Globe, “The very concept of freedom of expression is anything but intuitively obvious.” He’s right, of course. When we are confronted with ideas we find disagreeable, dangerous, or downright abhorrent, our first instinct is likely to want to silence …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978537</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-20T20:08:01Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Reality is dead, long live reason</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6109/reality-is-dead-long-live-reason#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Hilary Lawson is a philosopher and founder of the Institute of Art and Ideas" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/hilary-lawsonsquare02.jpg" height="571" alt="Hilary Lawson" width="700"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is 1882, 140 years ago. Bismarck is chancellor in Germany, Gladstone is Prime Minister in Britain, and memories of the Civil War are still fresh in the United States. A relatively unknown academic, Frederick Nietzsche, publishes what is now known as &lt;em&gt;The Gay Science&lt;/em&gt;, originally translated as &amp;ldquo;The Joyful Wisdom&amp;rdquo;. His academic career has foundered. He has given up his academic post, and almost no one is buying his work. Yet this particular book will be a major influence on all subsequent western thought.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the third section of &lt;em&gt;The Gay Science&lt;/em&gt;, Nietzsche makes his most controversial claim: God is dead, and goes on to say that we killed him. While he sometimes has Christianity in his sights, the case he is making is broader than the demise of a Christian God. Nietzsche is pointing to the demise of an authority higher or above the human and making the case that belief in the divine had been killed by the gradual unfurling of the Enlightenment and the progress of human knowledge.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The book and the claim had no immediate impact for there was, initially, no discernible audience. Yet the claim was prophetic. Religious belief in the West has been in gradual but continuous decline ever since. In Nietzsche&amp;rsquo;s time, almost all children were baptized. Today, in England, only six per cent of the population regularly attend church.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;So, what replaced God? Reality. A reality uncovered by observation, understanding and science. For those who have now taken leave of the notion of God, reality has a straight-forward, down to earth quality. It is the opposite of superstition. It may not have the magic and mystery of religious belief, but it enables in its place a calm, measured assessment of the world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yet strangely, reality, our replacement for God, turns out to share some of the key characteristics that have traditionally been applied to God. For example, God is understood to be everywhere and everything, but at the same time unknowable, elusive, unattainable. And so, it turns out, is reality.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;A universe of fields and energy&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Most will accept that reality is everywhere and everything. Less obvious is that it is unknowable, elusive and unattainable. I&amp;rsquo;m a longstanding critic of philosophical realism and the notion that our language and theories are capable of describing reality. So you might expect me to claim that reality is elusive and unattainable. However, over the last few years, many leading neuroscientists working on human perception and cognition have come to similar conclusions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A few years ago, Beau Lotto, professor of neuroscience at the University of London, used optical illusions to demonstrate that &amp;ldquo;Our brains did not evolve to sense reality; they evolved to give us what is useful for our survival.&amp;rdquo; Donald Hoffman, professor of cognitive science at the University of California Irvine, argues that what we take to be reality is akin to icons on a desktop. &amp;ldquo;Whatever reality is, it is not what you see. What you see is just an adaptive fiction.&amp;rdquo; While David Eagleman, a Stanford neuroscientist and leading researcher into brain plasticity concludes &amp;ldquo;reality is an illusion &amp;ndash; perpetuated by our brains&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not just several prominent neuroscientists. The framework of contemporary physics has also uncovered the elusive nature of reality. Once we imagined reality was ultimately made of indivisible minute particles we called atoms. Now we have a series of Chinese boxes each with smaller particles, protons, neutrons, quarks, leptons, bosons. As we examine them closer their material quality itself evaporates. Instead, we have a universe of fields and energy. It is as if we have lost the stuff of the world altogether. Niels Bohr, one of the founders of contemporary physics, concluded "Everything we call real is made of things that cannot be regarded as real.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Heisenberg, one of the most influential scientists of the 20th century, who won a Nobel prize for the creation of quantum mechanics, abandoned the notion that science was capable of uncovering reality altogether, &amp;ldquo;objective reality has evaporated&amp;rdquo;. More recently, Stephen Hawking, who in &lt;em&gt;A Brief History of Time&lt;/em&gt; had thought a theory of everything was in our grasp, abandoned this view in 2010 and concluded that science was only capable of providing models and the ultimate character of the world was beyond us. &amp;ldquo;There is no model-independent test of reality&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The last century has also seen the relentless uncovery of the inability of human thought to break free from the limitation of its particular perspective. Our narratives and theories, our histories and most fundamental beliefs, have been identified as the outcome of a particular language, history and culture, and the product of particular brain chemistry and physiology. There is no human access to a God&amp;rsquo;s eye view of the world that can somehow see the world as it &amp;lsquo;really&amp;rsquo; is. Sociologists, historians and philosophers have all played their part in uncovering the profoundly limited and human character of thought and perception. So, from all sides, the idea that we have access to reality is under attack.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Peering behind the veil?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the puzzle over reality is even trickier than it first appears. For it initially encourages the notion that we might be able to peer behind the veil and discover the truth. Confronted with the impossibility of this task, there is a temptation to search instead for an alternative underlying hidden or non-material version of reality, as if behind the illusion we can find the real thing. This has led some to propose that reality is consciousness, or material things are also conscious. Thinkers like Donald Hoffman and Iain McGilchrist have rightly identified the extent to which our account of the world is a product of our particular brain physiology. But they then go on to toy with these idealist or panpsychist 'solutions'.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But this is a wild goose chase. The new non-material 'reality' is going to be just as illusory as the materialist account. If what we take to be reality is an illusion, we are not going to be able to frame a metaphysical story that describes how it really is. Any account we give of this underlying 'reality' will itself be from a limited human perspective, and limited also by the constraints of a given language, culture, and context. &lt;a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the 18th century, the hugely influential philosopher Immanuel Kant reframed the history of thought by posing the question: how must thought be structured in order for us to have knowledge? Instead, we now have to address the central question about reality by beginning from the opposite starting point &amp;ndash; that we have no knowledge and no means of reaching through to describe the ultimate character of reality. The contemporary philosophical challenge is to explain how it is possible for us to intervene with such precision and accuracy in the world, even though we cannot know how things are. How is that we are able to share and talk about a seemingly fixed and known reality? How is that you can make your way home using your previous experience or by consulting Google maps? How is it that we can invent successful vaccines or send satellites into space if our theories are not precise descriptions of an objective reality and ultimate knowledge is not possible?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is not going to be one definitive answer to this question. As if we might give a final explanation of the nature of the human condition. For to do so would at once be a description of an ultimate reality. But that does not mean that there is nothing to say. We have to attempt to provide a means to make sense of our circumstances, even while knowing that it cannot be a final account.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Responding to the world&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The framework I have used to help escape from this deep puzzle, initially outlined in the book &lt;em&gt;Closure: a story of everything&lt;/em&gt;, proposes that reality should not be taken to be a thing or combination of things that we might describe. Instead it proposes that we close the openness of the world with our sensations, thoughts and language. Through this process of closure, we hold the world as things, objects and actions. People and objects, the sea and the sky, atoms and histories are not found in the world, they are instead ways by which we close the openness of the world. Language does not describe the world, instead it holds the world &lt;em&gt;as&lt;/em&gt; something. Language provides us with metaphors for the world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;You might think this is a very unlikely starting point. After all, if the world is nothing in particular, how is it that we all agree on so much? If our language and thought have nothing in common with reality, how is it that we can intervene so precisely?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;While the question first appears baffling, the starting point of an explanation is straight-forward. We make sense of reality not by describing it but by reacting to its consequences. Our senses do not observe the world, they respond to the world, and we hold those responses as things and characteristics through the process of closure.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What the framework of openness and closure demonstrates is that we can give a detailed account of the success of our theories and beliefs without proposing that they describe how reality ultimately is. In providing this demonstration, the theory also accounts for why it is itself possible without at the same time claiming to have definitively described the nature of the human condition.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In abandoning the notion that our accounts of the world describe reality, we have to rethink the nature of all belief. Our theories and beliefs, our accounts of the world, are not only no longer absolute, they cannot be an attempt to be absolute. Our theories are not, to use a phrase that Hawking used when he believed in a theory of everything, a glimpse into &amp;ldquo;the mind of God&amp;rdquo;. They are instead human frameworks, created at a given point in cultural history, set in a certain language, that help us to achieve things that we would not be able to do otherwise.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Doubling down on reason&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;The passing of reality is not something to regret, but something to lift our spirits.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We can feel confident of the value and strength of our current theories and accounts of the world, while at the same time recognising that they will in due course be modified and eventually abandoned in favour of alternatives that will be thought to be more effective, or more powerful, or more desirable. Millenia of exploration and testing of our temporary metaphors have enabled us to refine them and create versions that allow us to have lives that those in the past could hardly imagine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This ability to improve our circumstances and address our desires and goals does not need to come at the cost of limiting the world to the stories we have adopted or to imagining that there are no alternatives, or that we might have arrived at a final answer, or that there is a truth of the matter.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Observation and reason led us to imagine that we were uncovering the ultimate character of the world, that reality was being laid bare. It was no such thing. Instead, we were refining our closures to enable them to be more successful at predicting what would happen and helping us to intervene to achieve outcomes we could not achieve otherwise.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In contemporary culture, partly as a result of an awareness of the importance of perspective, many have become critical of observation and reason. Instead, we need to double down on observation and reason; not to uncover the truth, but to test our closures, our metaphors, our ways of holding the world. For it is only by observing where they work and where they fail that we are able to refine them &amp;ndash; or, if need be, abandon them in favour of others. Instead of being critical of observation and reason, it is the idea that we are uncovering reality that we need to abandon. The idea that there is a correct way to think. An endpoint where we can rest our account of the world. Our closures provide us with what we take to be reality but they have nothing in common with openness, and their success is not dependent on describing the world.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Reality, it turns out, is a theological notion. An ultimate that cannot be reached. And it is time we rid ourselves of its superstition. It is not only God that is dead, but reality itself.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;By giving up the idea of uncovering reality we can instead seek to realise the unlimited potential of openness, enabling us to achieve things we do not think currently possible. We can improve the circumstances in which we operate, and counter prejudice and injustice, but we should not imagine that we are right, or that we have said how the world is. Instead, we have offered a way of thinking that enables change, and that helps create new, different, and hopefully better futures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Postscript: The approach I have advocated here is but one way to respond to the uncovery of our inability to describe reality. There will, of course, be others. At the same time, any such account offers a means of holding the world, which has the appearance of holding fast that which in the end cannot be held at all.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hilary Lawson is founder of HowTheLightGetsIn festival. As a festival partner, &lt;em&gt;New Humanist&lt;/em&gt; is offering a 20 per cent discount on tickets to all of our readers, with the code NEWHUMANIST23. Don't miss out on tickets &lt;a href="https://howthelightgetsin.org/festivals/hay/festival-passes?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; And for those of you who can't be with us in person, all the debates and talks from the festival will gradually be released online, on the Institute of Art and Ideas platform, &lt;a href="https://iai.tv/?utm_source=New+Humanist&amp;amp;utm_medium=Preview&amp;amp;utm_campaign=HTLGI+Hay+2023&amp;amp;utm_id=Media+Partner"&gt;IAI.TV.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6109/reality-is-dead-long-live-reason#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T11:53:08Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-20T11:53:08Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The female scientists written out of history</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6106/the-female-scientists-written-out-of-history#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Rosalind Franklin" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/HRKT1E.jpg" height="1121" alt="A black and white photo of Rosalind Franklin" width="1368"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the last day of February in 1953. An odd pair &amp;ndash; one a tall, lanky 25-year-old American microbiologist, the other a 37-year-old British physicist &amp;ndash; burst into the Eagle pub in Cambridge. Interrupting the lunchtime chatter of the patrons at the bar, the elder announces, without the slightest hint of irony, that they &amp;ldquo;had found the secret of life!&amp;rdquo;. That morning, 70 years ago, James Watson and Francis Crick finally cracked the double helical structure of deoxyribonucleic acid: DNA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This tale is recounted in James Watson&amp;rsquo;s 1968 account of the discovery of the structure of DNA, &lt;em&gt;The Double Helix&lt;/em&gt;. I first read the book in the 1990s, after it was recommended by one of my biochemistry lecturers. I remember being quite enthralled by the personal account of Watson&amp;rsquo;s chaotic approach to his science. It broke a stereotype I had subscribed to, that scientific endeavours have to take a linear, methodical approach. It resonated with me and my own way of working.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Many years later and it was my turn to stand behind the lectern and face a theatre full of young minds. As I clicked through my slides I remembered how deeply &lt;em&gt;The Double Helix&lt;/em&gt; had influenced me and considered whether to add it to my own course&amp;rsquo;s reading list. Back in my office I dusted off my old copy of Watson&amp;rsquo;s book.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This time round the book had a very different effect. Watson came across as ambitious and brilliant, but also arrogant and happy to openly voice prejudices (a characteristic he displayed throughout his life). Early on in the book, he introduces his collaborators at King's College London, dedicating several pages to denigrating Rosalind Franklin &amp;ndash; whose invaluable contribution to the DNA story is now well known. He persistently calls her Rosy, a diminutive that he knew she disliked, describing how her colleague Maurice Wilkins treated her as an assistant. He finishes the chapter by saying &amp;ldquo;The thought could not be avoided that the best home for a feminist was in another person&amp;rsquo;s lab.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Photo 51&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Among her other achievements, Rosalind Franklin and her PhD student Raymond Gosling produced one of the most famous images in science: Photograph 51, a diffraction pattern created by shining X-rays through a crystal of DNA. The photo shows a blurry, spotty cross. To those initiated in crystallography, it positively screamed &amp;ldquo;helix&amp;rdquo;. But, more subtly, locked within the shape of the cross, and eventually deciphered by Franklin and Gosling, were the precise dimensions of the DNA&amp;rsquo;s form.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Photo 51 and the detailed structural information it contained became crucial to Watson and Crick&amp;rsquo;s endeavours. The pair never once conducted an experiment on DNA themselves. Instead, they took a more theoretical approach, gathering all available information and using these data to inform the building of physical, often cardboard, models. The crucial, keystone, piece of data was contained in Photo 51. This they obtained, not from Franklin, but instead from her colleague Wilkins, who shared the photo without Franklin&amp;rsquo;s permission or knowledge. The importance of the spotty cross was immediately apparent to Watson, who describes his first glimpse of it in &lt;em&gt;The Double Helix&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;ldquo;The instant I saw the picture my mouth fell open and my heart began to race.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The photo was the framework into which the rest of the DNA puzzle pieces fit. It provided the three-dimensional constraints for those pieces, which when slotted into place revealed the details of the double helix.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Almost a century of research informed this revelation. First, a clear understanding of DNA&amp;rsquo;s chemistry was required. This gave Watson and Crick the shape of their puzzle pieces and how they interacted with their neighbours. Second, the biological role of DNA needed to be understood. When Watson and Crick started their work, it was not at all clear that DNA carried genetic information. Instead, it was generally suspected that proteins were responsible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The concept of genetic inheritance begins with Gregor Mendel and his famous work on peas. Over the course of eight years he systematically cultivated, crossed and observed almost 30,000 plants. Eventually, he noticed patterns and arrived at some basic rules of inheritance, including the concepts of recessive and dominant genes. He published his work in 1865, but of course at the time the molecules and mechanisms that underpinned these rules were entirely unknown.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Those that came before&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;To find the very beginning of the thread that ties DNA with inheritance and culminates in Crick&amp;rsquo;s lunchtime proclamation in the Eagle pub, we have to go back a little earlier, and travel to T&amp;uuml;bingen, Germany. There, a laboratory led by Felix Hoppe-Seyler was busy establishing itself as the first research group in Europe dedicated to understanding the chemistry of life. At the time, this largely meant focusing on proteins, a relatively recently discovered class of biological molecule.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Hoppe-Seyler was a prestigious and inspiring character, who frequently changed the course of careers of aspiring scientists. Johann Friedrich Miescher had already graduated as a medical doctor but was persuaded by Hoppe-Seyler to turn from medicine towards research and join his lab (which was actually a converted kitchen) to work on physiological chemistry, as it was then known. The young Miescher was tasked with extracting proteins from leukocytes, or white blood cells. This was a rather unenviable project given that the most viable source of leukocytes was pus-soaked bandages picked out of the buckets in surgical wards. Nevertheless, Miescher diligently toiled, isolating several proteins and also something else.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Something that had a quite different chemical composition, lacking in sulfur and plentiful in phosphorous. Something that was only found in the nucleus of cells. In reference to its source, he named the material &amp;ldquo;nuclein&amp;rdquo;. Some years later, one of Miescher&amp;rsquo;s students demonstrated that nuclein was acidic and so renamed it nucleic acid: the NA in DNA.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the ever-energetic Hoppe-Seyler had upped sticks and established himself as a professor of chemistry in Strasbourg. There, he turned the head of yet another medic. The task for the convert, Albrecht Kossel, was to better understand the chemistry of Miescher&amp;rsquo;s molecule. Kossel soon worked out a formula for nuclein: C₂₉N₄₉N₉O₂₂P₃. This didn&amp;rsquo;t reveal much about the molecule&amp;rsquo;s structure. Nevertheless, Kossel&amp;rsquo;s interest was piqued. Over the course of 16 years he set about isolating the chemical components that came together to form nuclein.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;One component had already been isolated from bird guano, or excrement, and had been given the name &amp;ldquo;guanine&amp;rdquo;. For the rest, Kossel needed thousands of kilos of animal organs rich in nuclein. So, he formed a relationship with a local slaughterhouse which provided him with a steady stream of pancreas and thymus. From these organs, Kossel eventually isolated &amp;ldquo;adenine&amp;rdquo;: a name derived from the Greek &amp;ldquo;adenas&amp;rdquo; meaning &amp;ldquo;gland&amp;rdquo; (in reference to the pancreas) and &amp;ldquo;ine&amp;rdquo; meaning &amp;ldquo;contains nitrogen&amp;rdquo;. From calf thymus he extracted two more compounds which he named &amp;ldquo;thymine&amp;rdquo; (after &amp;ldquo;thymus&amp;rdquo;) and &amp;ldquo;cytosine&amp;rdquo; (from &amp;ldquo;cyto&amp;rdquo; meaning cell). This nomenclature is the names of the four fundamental bases that make up DNA. And so, Kossel gave us the DNA alphabet; the letters ATGC, now so familiar to us.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Having isolated the building blocks of DNA, it fell to a prolific chemist, Phoebus Levene, to work out the chemistry linking them together. Over a period of two decades at the beginning of the 20th century, Levene investigated the building blocks of nucleic acids and revealed that they are composed of just three distinct chemical components. A phosphate group, a five carbon sugar, and one of the four bases (guanine, adenine, cytosine and thymine). Just as importantly, Levene also worked out how the components were linked together to form what he called &amp;ldquo;nucleotides&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Despite DNA being under their noses (and up them too, given the prevalence of bird poo and offal), none of the big players &amp;ndash; including Kossel, Miescher and Levene &amp;ndash; understood its true significance. They were still convinced that only proteins were large and complicated enough to carry genetic information. Their research on DNA, therefore, was a sideline. Many believed it to be a storage molecule for phosphorous, or maybe a structural molecule.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Paving the way&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Others very nearly uncovered DNA&amp;rsquo;s true role. As early as 1927, the great Russian biologist Nikolai Koltsov came uncannily close to the truth in his description of the mechanism by which DNA replicates and stores information. He predicted that inheritance would occur via a &amp;ldquo;giant hereditary molecule&amp;rdquo; consisting of &amp;ldquo;two mirror strands that would replicate in a semi-conservative fashion using each strand as a template&amp;rdquo;. But despite his extraordinary insight into the mechanisms of inheritance, Koltsov was not able to go against the dominant scientific thinking of the time, and like everyone else presumed that proteins were the agents that stored genetic information.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But the dogma was slowly shifting. The idea that DNA might have a role in inheritance was beginning to be expressed. One frequently overlooked voice was that of Florence Bell. In 1939, she was a PhD student in the lab of William Astbury, a professor in Leeds with a prestigious reputation for his work on the structure of fibres. In Bell&amp;rsquo;s doctoral thesis, which was focused on the X-ray diffraction of nucleic acids, she wrote: &amp;ldquo;Possibly the most pregnant development in molecular biology is the realisation that the beginnings of life are closely associated with the interaction of proteins and nucleic acids.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bell&amp;rsquo;s work paved the way for Rosalind Franklin and Raymond Gosling. She produced the first X-ray images of DNA. The images are blurry because, unbeknownst to Bell and Astbury (and everyone else), DNA could take two subtly different structures, and their sample contained a mixture of both. Nevertheless the image revealed that DNA adopted a regular structure and allowed them to determine some key dimensions of the molecule, specifically the distances between the As, Ts, Gs and Cs, in each step of the DNA ladder.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Bell and Astbury&amp;rsquo;s Nature paper in 1938 described these DNA nucleotides as being stacked like &amp;ldquo;a pile of pennies&amp;rdquo;. This information fed directly into Watson and Crick&amp;rsquo;s models. Unfortunately, Bell&amp;rsquo;s work was curtailed by the outbreak of the Second World War. She joined the Women&amp;rsquo;s Auxiliary Air Force as a radio operator, later married a US serviceman, emigrated and worked as an industrial chemist in Texas.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There is a strange footnote to the history of the Astbury lab. Following the war and having lost valued researchers such as Bell (whom he had tried his best to retain), Astbury rebuilt his group and in 1951 received fresh samples of DNA. He directed another PhD student, Elwyn Beighton, to shine X-rays through them, just as Bell had done over a decade before. This new sample contained just one form of DNA, and so it was much sharper than Bell&amp;rsquo;s images. Beighton&amp;rsquo;s photograph is near enough identical to Photo 51, but precedes it by a year. Bizarrely, however, Astbury showed very little interest in the photo and so never published or even presented it at a meeting. Had he done so, the Nobel prizes and familiar names associated with the structure of DNA might have been quite different.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Too little, too late&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;A breakthrough was needed. It came in 1944 when Oswald Avery, Colin Macleod and Maclyn McCarty carried out a meticulous study showing that the characteristics of a bacterium could be altered by &amp;ldquo;transforming&amp;rdquo; it with DNA and only DNA. The final nail in the coffin was the theory of protein-based inheritance, hammered home by Martha Chase and Alfred Hershey with their famous &amp;ldquo;blender experiment&amp;rdquo; in the early 1950s.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At the time it was known that bacteriophages (viruses that infect bacteria) are comprised of a protein shell encapsulating DNA. Chase and Hershey &amp;ldquo;tagged&amp;rdquo; the protein and DNA, by introducing radioactive isotopes of sulfur to the protein, and radioactive phosphorous to the DNA. This labelling system allowed them to follow the whereabouts of the different molecules. They then infected bacteria with their radioactive phages.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The phage rapidly proliferated inside the infected bacteria, indicating some form of genetic material had been transmitted to the bacteria. Traces of radioactivity could only be detected in bacteria that had been infected with labelled DNA, and not the labelled protein, clearly indicating that DNA and only DNA had been injected into the bacteria. The pair went on to categorically prove that DNA originated from the phage by whizzing the broth of newly infected bacteria in a modified kitchen blender. This knocked the phage off the surface of the bacteria. When they then looked for the location of the labelled protein, it was in solution, along with the now empty phage capsules, whilst the labelled DNA had been injected into the bacteria.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Thus, Chase and Hershey conclusively showed that DNA was the molecule of inheritance. Hershey went on to win a Nobel Prize in 1969. Sadly, in yet another story of women losing out, Martha Chase went on to lose her job and leave science, at the age of 37. Little more of her life is on record, apart from a few obituaries when she passed away in 2003.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Without Chase and Hershey&amp;rsquo;s insights into the secrets of life, it is doubtful that James Watson and Frances Crick would have put so much effort into DNA. When Hershey died in 1997, Watson said in a memorial article that &amp;ldquo;the Hershey-Chase experiment . . . made me ever more certain that finding the three-dimensional structure of DNA was biology&amp;rsquo;s next important objective.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In recent times, more light has been thrown on the contribution of women scientists to the story of DNA. However, it can feel like too little, too late. It took the best part of 70 years for Rosalind Franklin&amp;rsquo;s contributions to be fully appreciated. Often described as the &amp;ldquo;Dark Lady of DNA&amp;rdquo;, Franklin has now been the subject of multiple biographies. In 2015, Nicole Kidman played her in a West End show named &amp;ldquo;Photograph 51&amp;rdquo; after Franklin&amp;rsquo;s famous image.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It is a shame that Martha Chase and Florence Bell, who provided equally important insights and influence, are not as widely recognised. The pivotal blender experiment does bear Chase&amp;rsquo;s name, but most people who are familiar with the experiment are unaware that Chase was a woman. Meanwhile, Florence Bell remains almost entirely unknown.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;The Double Helix&lt;/em&gt;, Watson claims it was Crick who rushed into a nearby pub and blurted out that they had found the &amp;ldquo;secret of life&amp;rdquo;. The announcement in the Eagle pub has since gone down in scientific history. According to Gosling, when Rosalind Franklin heard about it a few days later, she commented, &amp;ldquo;We all stand on each other&amp;rsquo;s shoulders.&amp;rdquo; Quite whose shoulders she meant we cannot know, but I like to think she was paying tribute to the likes of Bell, Chase, Gosling, Miescher, Kossel, Levene and many more besides.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6106/the-female-scientists-written-out-of-history#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-20T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>In a word: Memoir</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6105/in-a-word-memoir#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/clay-banks-pNEmlb1CMZM-unsplash.jpg" height="912" alt="An empty notebook with a pen, ready to write" width="1368"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;memoir&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;, early 15th century: from Anglo-French memorie &amp;ldquo;something written to be kept in mind&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;When a member of the British monarchy recently published a memoir, it set off a feeding frenzy. We have an alternative word that is used in a similar way: &amp;ldquo;autobiography&amp;rdquo;. But &amp;ldquo;memoir&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;memoirs&amp;rdquo;, used interchangeably, seem to have become more popular. Perhaps there&amp;rsquo;s an echo of &amp;ldquo;memory&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;remember&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;reminisce&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;memento&amp;rdquo; in the word &amp;ldquo;memoir&amp;rdquo;. We often forget that the meaning of words is not really like a bar of chocolate with the word &amp;ldquo;chocolate&amp;rdquo; on the label. Words work in our minds (or we do the work on words) through connotations, connected to our experiences of life and of other words.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This cluster of &amp;ldquo;mem&amp;rdquo; words owes its origins to the Ancient Greek goddess of memory, Mnemosyne, and to an even more ancient word in Proto-Indo-European &amp;ndash; &amp;ldquo;men&amp;rdquo; meaning &amp;ldquo;to think&amp;rdquo;. More recently than this, &amp;ldquo;memoir&amp;rdquo; came to us via 12th-century French. It was first used in English (Middle English as it was then) to mean a memorandum &amp;ndash; as with diplomats passing notes to each other.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Its use to describe a life story, or an account of events, starts a little later. According to the Oxford English Dictionary, in 1659 one J. Pearson wrote that &amp;ldquo;Pontius Pilate kept the Memoirs of Jewish affairs&amp;rdquo;. By 1762, we have Lawrence Sterne writing in the inimitable and ground-breaking novel Tristram Shandy about the &amp;ldquo;memoirs of my uncle Toby&amp;rsquo;s courtship&amp;rdquo;. Leap forward another century to 1818 and Samuel Smith comments, &amp;ldquo;Any one who provides good dinners for clever people, and remembers what they say, cannot fail to write entertaining memoirs.&amp;rdquo; Scientists found a parallel use for the word, to refer to the proceedings of a learned society, and so we find memoirs on a &amp;ldquo;petrifaction mixed with shells&amp;rdquo;, &amp;ldquo;a Michigan mud-hole&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;the weather of Scotland&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A wisecrack credited to, of all people, Marshal P&amp;eacute;tain (the head of Vichy France 1940-44) appeared in the Observer in 1946: &amp;ldquo;To write one&amp;rsquo;s memoirs is to speak ill of everybody except oneself.&amp;rdquo; Reluctant as people might be to quote P&amp;eacute;tain as an authority, this thought seems to have survived the test of time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6105/in-a-word-memoir#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-18T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-18T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How have the protests changed Iran?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6103/how-have-the-protests-changed-iran#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img title="Protests in solidarity with Mahsa Amini in Ottawa, Canada (September 25, 2022). Credit: Taymaz Valley" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Iran_Protests__52382844957_.jpeg" height="564" alt="Protests in solidarity with Mahsa Amini in Ottawa (September 25, 2022). Credit: Taymaz Valley" width="966"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soraya Lennie is a journalist, analyst and author of "Crooked Alleys: Deliverance and Despair in Iran".&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The protests in Iran began in September of last year, sparked by the death of a young woman in police custody. What did they grow to encompass? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The protests were about issues much larger than compulsory hijab, or dislike of the morality police. The death in custody of Mahsa Amini was of course the spark, but arguably the protests represent the continuing decline in public perception vis a vis the legitimacy of the state and those who hold power.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Widespread protests largely fizzled out after a couple of months but quickly evolved into a campaign for change. Ultimately, in a leaderless movement, the motivations and desires of individuals differ, but generally speaking, the demands from those who took to the streets in Iran are similar: end morality policing, impunity and the compulsory hijab &amp;ndash; and overhaul, if not end, the current system of the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The overall campaign is now one of civil disobedience, where many supporters chant sporadic slogans against the Supreme Leader and state and no longer wear hijab in public. The number of activists inside Iran who are speaking out and risking arrest and prison, has also grown. There is also significant support for a referendum on a new constitution &amp;ndash; which is the legal avenue to dismantle the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In your book &amp;ldquo;Crooked Alleys&amp;rdquo; you paint a picture of an Islamic Republic that is a prisoner of its past. Are the protests the sign of a younger generation demanding a better future? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Iran is a prisoner of the past due to US foreign policy since the hostage crisis [in 1979], and its own belligerent and caustic reaction. It is a complex issue, but generational change in Iran means less people have a personal stake in maintaining the debilitating status quo. They are less inclined to cling to the rationales and ideologies of the past which have helped paralyse Iran&amp;rsquo;s progress, both internally and externally. Less and less people care about yesterday&amp;rsquo;s revolutionaries, or even the Iran-Iraq war mythology, and thus are much more focused on the present, and on their own futures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Generational change is an exceptional driver of new ideas anywhere, but in Iran, it is absolutely crucial in advancing the pro-democracy movement. They have injected new life into a movement for change that has gone nowhere the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How extensive has the government crackdown been, and have women faced the brunt of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Iran&amp;rsquo;s own Judiciary Chief suggests more than 22,000 people were arrested in the crackdown. Human rights groups say more than 500 people, including dozens of security forces, were killed. The crackdown doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear to be focused on one gender or another, as both men and women protested &amp;ndash; and faced arrest and prison &amp;ndash; together. Further, dozens of photographers and journalists have also been jailed &amp;ndash; both men and women. The difference is, in many cases it is generally easier to identify a woman involved in an act of civil disobedience by virtue of appearance [including whether or not she wears the hijab], than it is a man.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special rapporteur Javaid Rehman has told the UN Human Rights Council that the violations since the protests began amount to &amp;ldquo;crimes against humanity&amp;rdquo;. Does this seem justified?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Rome Statute is rather generalised. In Iran&amp;rsquo;s case, there is evidence of torture and specifically, of security forces intentionally committing inhumane acts &amp;ndash; a crime against humanity. Specifically blinding protesters with bird shot, beating civilians and subjecting thousands to arbitrary arrest. Further, many people, including journalists, were convicted of crimes in sham trials void of transparency or due process.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some Iranians have rallied around Reza Pahlavi, the son of the Shah, to lead a transitional government from clerical to secular rule. Why do others argue that this would be bad for democracy? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several issues here; first, this is a diaspora project, not an indigenous Iranian one and I&amp;rsquo;ve not seen much support for it inside the country. Iran&amp;rsquo;s most legitimate civil rights activists are in jail or under house arrest, not in the United States. Second, detractors argue that Mr Pahlavi has never held elected office so doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the political credentials. Third, millions of Iranians already lament replacing one dictatorship with another (the crown for the turban) and therefore argue another unelected group or individual is the antithesis of progress.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lastly, many people assume &amp;ndash; as does the charter that Mr Pahlavi and other diaspora have issued &amp;ndash; that Iranians want a &amp;lsquo;secular-democratic system.&amp;rsquo; Although the absence of evidence is not evidence of absence, there is no data that proves this is what an overwhelming majority of Iranians want. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t think his participation as an elected official in any future Iranian system &amp;ndash; based on consensus of the Iranian people &amp;ndash; is bad for democracy, so long as he is elected in a free and fair vote, like anyone else.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The role of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC) was originally around security and &amp;ldquo;religious discipline&amp;rdquo;. What is their current role in society?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The role of the IRGC is to protect the revolution, which is embodied by the Supreme Leader, and protect the revolution&amp;rsquo;s ideals &amp;ndash; independence, freedom and Islamic Republic. However, its role changed when Ruhollah Khomeini died in 1989, and Ali Khamenei replaced him as Supreme Leader. Although the constitution forbids active IRGC members from political activity or groups, IRGC figures are involved in every key branch of the Islamic Republic system, from the judiciary and parliament to intelligence. Further, the IRGC has morphed into an economic cartel with outsized power and leverage, even over pillars of the revolution and the clergy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it possible to tackle their power, without reforming the state? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In short, no. Constitutional amendments in 1982 have ensured that. Certain articles gave the IRGC outsized power with no real checks and balances. Further, the Corps reports to the Supreme Leader, not the Ministry of Defence. It also operates its own intelligence wing, often in competition with the state&amp;rsquo;s Ministry of Intelligence. Further, it&amp;rsquo;s full budget is not subject to public parliamentary scrutiny, stripping away another layer of accountability, while increasing its already formidable role.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February was the 44th anniversary of the 1979 revolution. The government used it as a show of might and to send the message that they had won, and the protests are now a spent force. How true is that? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anniversary of the revolution in theory, is a celebration of freedom and independence from foreign domination &amp;ndash; widely supported concepts. But it is also a propaganda tool used by the state and its supporters to cling to legitimacy and a long dead revolutionary mythology. The most telling element at these events, is the absence of the many millions of Iranians who fought for the revolution, who are now disillusioned, if not repulsed by the system they helped create.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As for the protests, they were not as large nor as widespread as those seen, for example, in 2009. Any significant showing ended about two months after the death of Mahsa Amini &amp;ndash; aside from in Zahedan. In essence, the protests are over, and did not lead to systematic change. But the Islamic Republic of Iran cannot claim it has won anything &amp;ndash; in fact the opposite. The number of Iranians who view the country&amp;rsquo;s circle of elite as illegitimate has grown exponentially and this rift between the people and the state is arguably, beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are reports that thousands of women are now openly breaking the law and refusing to wear the hijab. What impact have the protests had on the general population in Iran? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Millions of Iranian women weren&amp;rsquo;t abiding by the letter of the law for decades and in the past ten years, it was common to see unveiled women at cafes, art galleries, and even walking down the street. Despite arrests, threats and even attacks from members of the public, the protests have emboldened more women to follow suit. The protests broke another layer of fear in the Islamic Republic and the importance of that cannot be understated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soraya Lennie is the author of &lt;a href="https://www.hurstpublishers.com/book/crooked-alleys/"&gt;Crooked Alleys: Deliverance and Despair in Iran&lt;/a&gt; (Hurst Publishers). &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6103/how-have-the-protests-changed-iran#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-13T16:36:37Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-13T16:36:37Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/open-discussion-april-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978526</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Be Tongue-Tied</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/science-cannot-be-tongue-tied/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It might be funny, if it weren’t so worrisome. Recent weeks have seen some absurd new instances of science beset by would-be censors operating under the banner of “inclusion.” Examples are many, and they come from all over the globe. We’ll look at an ongoing controversy in …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978517</id>
    <published>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MARCH 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/open-discussion-march-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978514</id>
    <published>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
