<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Planet Skeptic</title>
  <link rel="alternate" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="text/html"/>
  <subtitle>Question Everything</subtitle>
  <author>
    <name>Dave Cross</name>
    <email>dave@theplanetarium.org</email>
  </author>
  <updated>2023-04-15T21:28:41Z</updated>
  <link rel="self" href="https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/" type="application/atom+xml"/>
  <id>https://skeptic.theplanetarium.org/</id>
  <entry>
    <title>Maybe social media shouldn’t be for profit?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/15/maybe-social-media-shouldnt-be-for-profit/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/lastwords.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/lastwords-135x150.jpeg" alt="" width="135" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69852" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/lastwords-135x150.jpeg 135w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/lastwords.jpeg 270w" sizes="(max-width: 135px) 100vw, 135px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">Here’s a radical idea: social media and capitalism are not a good match. Everyone is trying to force-fit human social interactions into a pay-to-play capitalist box, and it’s just not working.</p>
<p>Parler — remember Parler? One of those Twitter-substitutes fueled by conservative billionaires, promising no content moderation at all, used to plan the January 6 insurrection? That Parler? — <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/04/parler-shuts-down-as-new-owner-says-conservative-platform-needs-big-revamp/">just died</a>. It will not be missed.</p>
<blockquote><p>Parler, the self-described “uncancelable free speech platform,” has been sold and shut down while its new owner conducts a “strategic assessment.” The platform will be back eventually, new owner Starboard says.</p>
<p>The Parler website is now a simple page containing only today’s press release announcing the acquisition, which was completed without financial terms being disclosed. “No reasonable person believes that a Twitter clone just for conservatives is a viable business any more,” the acquisition announcement said, promising a revamp.</p>
<p>“While the Parler app as it is currently constituted will be pulled down from operation to undergo a strategic assessment, we at Starboard see tremendous opportunities across multiple sectors to continue to serve marginalized or even outright censored communities—even extending beyond domestic politics,” the press release said. No timing for a return was mentioned.</p></blockquote>
<p>Yeah. The uncancelable has been canceled by market forces, as a luxury that wasn’t a “viable business.” It wasn’t. It takes a real shock to get conservatives to recognize reality.</p>
<p>Then there’s Facebook. Facebook makes money, although the amount is declining, but it relies on selling people’s personal information to marketers — it’s less a social media company than a colossal siphon for collecting data that it can manipulate and sell to those who want to take advantage of users. What it offers as an inducement to draw in those users is the worst of human nature, giving grifters and attention-seeking fools free reign. Facebook is great if you want to sell trash to the gullible and demolish democracy as you go, but Facebook is what you get when you fully meld social media and capitalism. It’s not a good example.</p>
<p>Ah, Twitter. Poor Twitter. It was fun while it lasted, but now it’s been taken over by egomaniac and incompetent businessman, and is being run into the ground by a bad man whose “focus appears to be on cutting costs and making Twitter profitable.” On the one hand, I feel like we should kill it while the Nazis are lying on the ground, helpless and twitching, but on the other…it turns out that <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/ideas/archive/2023/02/elon-musk-twitter-blue-natural-disaster-crisis-emergency-response/673209/">Twitter has been integrated into the world-wide disaster response network</a>.</p>
<blockquote><p>For years, Twitter was at its best when bad things happened. Before Elon Musk bought it last fall, before it was overrun with scammy ads, before it amplified fake personas, and before its engineers were told to get more eyeballs on the owner’s tweets, Twitter was useful in saving lives during natural disasters and man-made crises. Emergency-management officials have used the platform to relate timely information to the public—when to evacuate during Hurricane Ian, in 2022; when to hide from a gunman during the Michigan State University shootings earlier this month—while simultaneously allowing members of the public to transmit real-time data. The platform didn’t just provide a valuable communications service; it changed the way emergency management functions.</p></blockquote>
<p>We started taking it for granted, that buried in the noise was a genuine public good that could be used to help people. That wasn’t a side of the service that made money, though. At least, not until some soulless clever dicks decided that maybe they could exploit that capability for their profit, unaware that the utility vanishes when you start demanding cash to save people’s lives.</p>
<blockquote><p>Unfortunately, the platform is becoming less useful as a way of monitoring chatter about developing events. Twitter announced on February 2 that it would end free access for researchers to its application programming interface—a mechanism that allows people outside the company to gather and analyze large quantities of data from the social-media platform. Relief workers have frequently used API access to determine where supplies and other resources are needed most.</p>
<p>Four days after the company’s API announcement, a massive earthquake hit Turkey and Syria, killing at least 46,000 people. In an enormous geographic area, API data can help narrow down who is saying what, who is stuck where, and where limited supplies should be delivered first. Amid complaints about what abandoning free API access would mean in that crisis, Twitter postponed the restriction. Still, its long-term intentions are uncertain, and some public-spirited deployments of the API by outside researchers—such as a ProPublica bot tracking politicians’ deleted tweets—appear to be breaking down.</p></blockquote>
<p>Social media can be a valuable tool for a society, but not when some capitalist or autocrat somewhere is monitoring it to milk every drop of advantage from it so they can actively harm its users. That’s the fatal flaw: the free flow of information is a strong social good, but when people exploit it for profit it’s no longer free.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here’s a radical idea: social media and capitalism are not a good match. Everyone is trying to force-fit human social interactions into a pay-to-play capitalist box, and it’s just not working. Parler — remember Parler? One of those Twitter-substitutes fueled by conservative billionaires, promising no content moderation at all, used to plan the January 6 […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69851</id>
    <published>2023-04-15T11:44:43Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-15T11:44:43Z</updated>
    <category term="Miscellaneous and Meta"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>What beast emerges from the dark depths?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/14/what-beast-emerges-from-the-dark-depths/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost-150x113.jpeg" alt="" width="150" height="113" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-56232" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost-150x113.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost-300x225.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost-768x576.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2019/10/atkinsoncompost-500x375.jpeg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">This is exciting. I’ve written about my compost bin before, which has been a rich source of spider lore — a partially closed habitat, the domain of some large dark spiders that build their cobwebs in a place rife with buzzing insects.<br/>
The bin has been inaccessible for months, buried under snow. Today the snow had retreated enough that we could hobble over slick, crunchy ice to get to it and throw back the lid. What did I see?<br/>
First, fresh silk, new cobwebs laid across the corners. Somebody had been working hard. Then, suddenly, at one side, a massive spider loomed out of the darkness — a fully grown, adult male <i>Steatoda borealis</i>.  His presence tells me something: he’s much too large to be a recent hatchling, so he must have overwintered down in the dark, sheltered from the storms, huddled in the fermenting warmth of the compost.<br/>
We closed the lid and let him be. I’m sure there are more down there who will creep out in the next few weeks to rebuild a thriving colony.
</p>
<p>If you want to see this massive unit of a tough Minnesota spider, you can go to <a href="https://www.patreon.com/posts/what-beast-from-81522962">Patreon</a> or <a href="https://www.instagram.com/p/CrBzoVlPXVn/">Instagram</a>. He’s big and dark in shades of red and black with thick strong limbs and glowing eyes.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is exciting. I’ve written about my compost bin before, which has been a rich source of spider lore — a partially closed habitat, the domain of some large dark spiders that build their cobwebs in a place rife with buzzing insects. The bin has been inaccessible for months, buried under snow. Today the snow […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69849</id>
    <published>2023-04-14T19:49:02Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-14T19:49:02Z</updated>
    <category term="Spiders"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The only reason to pay attention to the haters is to shame them</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/14/the-only-reason-to-pay-attention-to-the-haters-is-to-shame-them/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p class="lead">A borough in the UK posted an innocuous tweet, suggesting that <a href="https://twitter.com/Calderdale/status/1646166929583775753">people should go in for cervical screening</a>. They had to take it down because a small minority of haters complained that the words “anyone with a cervix” was offensive to women.</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen-500x273.png" alt="" width="500" height="273" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69845" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen-500x273.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen-150x82.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen-300x164.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/cervical-screen.png 583w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>The wording was just fine! It was inclusive and was a message to an appropriate audience. In fact, if you look at the thread, there’s a deluge of support for it, with swarms of people, cis and trans, chiming in to see that the message was good and they appreciated it. There were also, of course, a few indignant assholes whining that only women have cervices, and they were the ones they had to listen to, because Calderdale deleted the tweet.</p>
<p>Those few vicious, mocking tweets are the modern equivalent of this, an ugliness that will stain us all for years to come:</p>
<p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights-500x240.jpeg" alt="" width="500" height="240" class="aligncenter size-large wp-image-69846" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights-500x240.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights-150x72.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights-300x144.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights-768x369.jpeg 768w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/resistance-civil-rights.jpeg 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px"/></a></p>
<p>Meanwhile, in the science world, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-00973-7">the journal <i>Nature</i> is updating their policies</a>. Language matters.</p>
<blockquote><p>It is regrettable but true that researchers have used and abused science to justify racist beliefs and practices. As previous editorials have acknowledged, Nature has played its part in perpetuating racism — and has now pledged to play its part in tackling it, together with colleagues in the research community.</p>
<p>As part of this pledge, Nature and the Nature Portfolio journals are updating our advice to authors on reporting research that involves race, ethnicity and other socially constructed characteristics. Specifically, we’re asking that authors exercise care and consideration so that the highest standards of rigour are applied where these attributes are found to be an explanation for an outcome or conclusion. This is part of our ongoing updates to guidance asking authors to describe how demographic characteristics, including sex and gender, are considered in the design of studies — and, more broadly, to consider the research’s potential to cause harm.</p></blockquote>
<p>They aren’t asking a lot. This is what <i>Nature</i> expects now, and I was a little surprised…shouldn’t this have been standing, routine policy all along?</p>
<blockquote><p>So, what are we asking authors to do, if their research describes people according to race, ethnicity or other socially constructed categories? Essentially, three things. First, specify the categories used and explain why such classification is needed. Second, explain the methods used to describe people in this way — for example, did study participants self-report, or did the information come from a census, social media or administrative data? Third, we would like authors to describe how they controlled for confounding variables, such as socio-economic status. These requests will be added to a paper’s reporting checklist so it is a part of the usual editorial and publishing workflow.</p></blockquote>
<p>I’m not going to publish in <i>Nature</i>, and the kind of work I do isn’t going to touch on issues of race and sex (although some will <a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/03/01/spider-sex-is-more-complex-than-the-binary-paradigm/">try to force it</a>!), but I would have thought that if you were doing work in those areas of sufficient prestige that it would be published in top-tier journals, those rules would have been already incorporated. You can never underestimate the devious efforts of bigots, though!</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A borough in the UK posted an innocuous tweet, suggesting that people should go in for cervical screening. They had to take it down because a small minority of haters complained that the words “anyone with a cervix” was offensive to women. The wording was just fine! It was inclusive and was a message to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69844</id>
    <published>2023-04-14T12:39:04Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-14T12:39:04Z</updated>
    <category term="Feminism, Gender, and Equality"/>
    <category term="Race, Society, and Social Justice"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Naked corruption</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/14/naked-corruption/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption.jpeg"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption-300x233.jpeg" alt="" width="300" height="233" class="alignright size-medium wp-image-69840" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption-300x233.jpeg 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption-150x117.jpeg 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption-500x389.jpeg 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/clarence-corruption.jpeg 700w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">It’s all just hanging out there, exposed, flapping rudely in the wind, and we’re supposed to pretend that Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas <em>isn’t</em> selling out the country. The story is simple and transparent.</p>
<p>Thomas’s mother lived on some property owned by Thomas. <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/clarence-thomas-harlan-crow-real-estate-scotus">Harlan Crow paid Thomas $133,363 for that property</a>, and then allowed his mother to continue to live there rent-free afterwards, and in fact renovated the house, put on a new roof, a nice fence, etc.</p>
<p>Crow was the best landlord of all time!</p>
<p>Of course, what it all was was a pretext to put a whole lot of money in a judge’s pocket and curry favor with him. Thomas knew this; he rather obviously avoided reporting the whole money shuffle to the government, and tried to hide the source of this sudden largesse.</p>
<blockquote><p>“He needed to report his interest in the sale,” said Virginia Canter, a former government ethics lawyer now at the watchdog group CREW. “Given the role Crow has played in subsidizing the lifestyle of Thomas and his wife, you have to wonder if this was an effort to put cash in their pockets.”</p></blockquote>
<p>Oh, really? You think? I’m not wondering at all. Hint to ethics lawyers everywhere: the time for understatement is over. This is time to suspend him from the bench while impeachment proceedings are begun. I’d go so far as to suggest it’s time for handcuffs, except we all know that white collar crime by high-ranking federal officials is going to be treated with kid gloves, instead.</p>
<p>See also <a href="https://www.laprogressive.com/law-and-the-justice-system/clarence-and-giclarence-and-ginninni">Robert Reich’s take on this situation</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It’s all just hanging out there, exposed, flapping rudely in the wind, and we’re supposed to pretend that Supreme Court Justice Clarence Thomas isn’t selling out the country. The story is simple and transparent. Thomas’s mother lived on some property owned by Thomas. Harlan Crow paid Thomas $133,363 for that property, and then allowed his […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69839</id>
    <published>2023-04-14T11:56:54Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-14T11:56:54Z</updated>
    <category term="Politics, History, and Law"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I went back to high school for a day</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/2023/04/14/i-went-back-to-high-school-for-a-day/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><a href="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class.png"><img src="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class-150x150.png" alt="" width="150" height="150" class="alignright size-thumbnail wp-image-69837" srcset="https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class-150x150.png 150w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class-300x300.png 300w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class-500x500.png 500w, https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/files/2023/04/count-dooku-teaching-a-high-school-class.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"/></a></p>
<p class="lead">On Wednesday, I’d had a little private pity party, moaning to myself how I really disliked my teaching schedule and would never do this again. You see, this semester, thanks to a sudden schedule change, I was teaching two very different classes back to back — I’d finish lecturing in genetics, and immediately have to swivel and scuttle off to teach introductory biology. I like to have a little break between my classes, a time to reorient myself, review the material, put my feet up, sip a little wine (OK, I don’t do the last bit, but I can dream.) I have been spoiled.</p>
<p>Thursday I was a guest at the local high school. Yikes. One class after the other, all day long. You get your lesson plan all mapped out well ahead of time, because once that first class launches at 8:25, you are on a fixed trajectory all day long, with only a few minutes between classes. Forget moments of reflection, don’t even think about the imaginary glass of wine, because a succession of students are going to march in and occupy your classroom.</p>
<p>I don’t think I could cope with teaching high school. Much respect to those who do — you are all overworked and underpaid.</p>
<p>On the positive side, though, it was a pleasant experience…for a day. Just a day at a time. The big difference between college and high school is that college students are generally so damned serious. They’re paying out big bucks and accumulating a substantial debt to be here, and classes are their <em>job</em>, while professors are the bosses armed with the scourges of exams. At the 7th and 10th grade classes, I started talking about spiders, hands were raised, students would spontaneously offer wild accounts of their spider experiences, they’d ask question after question, it would sometimes get a bit raucous. Their enthusiasm was wonderful.</p>
<p>Now how to get the college students that fired up…I think I’ll have to kill all the exams. Abolishing tuition would help, too. I’ll get right on that for next year.</p>
<p>By the way, I also got to peruse their textbooks, briefly. There’s been a change there: they weren’t using Miller &amp; Levine anymore! They’d switch to something called <i>Inspire Biology</i>, which looked fine, but different: lots of short, choppy segments with exercises to make the students think, less of a narrative, more for short attention spans. That isn’t bad, I could see how you could use textbooks like that to customize how you teach.</p>
<p>They did still use the familiar Miller &amp; Levine lab manual and praised it highly.</p>
<p>For those who don’t know, Miller &amp; Levine’s <i>Biology</i> was, for many years, the ubiquitous text I’d see in every high school student’s backpack. It was kind of like Campbell <i>Biology</i> at the college level. I’m seeing a lot more textbook diversity in the last decade or two as publishers seem to have realized that owning the rights to a popular textbook is a cash cow. For them, not the authors.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Wednesday, I’d had a little private pity party, moaning to myself how I really disliked my teaching schedule and would never do this again. You see, this semester, thanks to a sudden schedule change, I was teaching two very different classes back to back — I’d finish lecturing in genetics, and immediately have to […]</div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>PZ Myers</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://freethoughtblogs.com/pharyngula/?p=69836</id>
    <published>2023-04-14T11:29:44Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-14T11:29:44Z</updated>
    <category term="My classes"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>How have the protests changed Iran?</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6103/how-have-the-protests-changed-iran#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img title="Protests in solidarity with Mahsa Amini in Ottawa, Canada (September 25, 2022). Credit: Taymaz Valley" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Iran_Protests__52382844957_.jpeg" height="564" alt="Protests in solidarity with Mahsa Amini in Ottawa (September 25, 2022). Credit: Taymaz Valley" width="966"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soraya Lennie is a journalist, analyst and author of "Crooked Alleys: Deliverance and Despair in Iran".&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The protests in Iran began in September of last year, sparked by the death of a young woman in police custody. What did they grow to encompass? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;The protests were about issues much larger than compulsory hijab, or dislike of the morality police. The death in custody of Mahsa Amini was of course the spark, but arguably the protests represent the continuing decline in public perception vis a vis the legitimacy of the state and those who hold power.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Widespread protests largely fizzled out after a couple of months but quickly evolved into a campaign for change. Ultimately, in a leaderless movement, the motivations and desires of individuals differ, but generally speaking, the demands from those who took to the streets in Iran are similar: end morality policing, impunity and the compulsory hijab &amp;ndash; and overhaul, if not end, the current system of the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The overall campaign is now one of civil disobedience, where many supporters chant sporadic slogans against the Supreme Leader and state and no longer wear hijab in public. The number of activists inside Iran who are speaking out and risking arrest and prison, has also grown. There is also significant support for a referendum on a new constitution &amp;ndash; which is the legal avenue to dismantle the Islamic Republic.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In your book &amp;ldquo;Crooked Alleys&amp;rdquo; you paint a picture of an Islamic Republic that is a prisoner of its past. Are the protests the sign of a younger generation demanding a better future? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Iran is a prisoner of the past due to US foreign policy since the hostage crisis [in 1979], and its own belligerent and caustic reaction. It is a complex issue, but generational change in Iran means less people have a personal stake in maintaining the debilitating status quo. They are less inclined to cling to the rationales and ideologies of the past which have helped paralyse Iran&amp;rsquo;s progress, both internally and externally. Less and less people care about yesterday&amp;rsquo;s revolutionaries, or even the Iran-Iraq war mythology, and thus are much more focused on the present, and on their own futures.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Generational change is an exceptional driver of new ideas anywhere, but in Iran, it is absolutely crucial in advancing the pro-democracy movement. They have injected new life into a movement for change that has gone nowhere the last 15 years.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How extensive has the government crackdown been, and have women faced the brunt of it?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Iran&amp;rsquo;s own Judiciary Chief suggests more than 22,000 people were arrested in the crackdown. Human rights groups say more than 500 people, including dozens of security forces, were killed. The crackdown doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear to be focused on one gender or another, as both men and women protested &amp;ndash; and faced arrest and prison &amp;ndash; together. Further, dozens of photographers and journalists have also been jailed &amp;ndash; both men and women. The difference is, in many cases it is generally easier to identify a woman involved in an act of civil disobedience by virtue of appearance [including whether or not she wears the hijab], than it is a man.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special rapporteur Javaid Rehman has told the UN Human Rights Council that the violations since the protests began amount to &amp;ldquo;crimes against humanity&amp;rdquo;. Does this seem justified?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The Rome Statute is rather generalised. In Iran&amp;rsquo;s case, there is evidence of torture and specifically, of security forces intentionally committing inhumane acts &amp;ndash; a crime against humanity. Specifically blinding protesters with bird shot, beating civilians and subjecting thousands to arbitrary arrest. Further, many people, including journalists, were convicted of crimes in sham trials void of transparency or due process.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Some Iranians have rallied around Reza Pahlavi, the son of the Shah, to lead a transitional government from clerical to secular rule. Why do others argue that this would be bad for democracy? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There are several issues here; first, this is a diaspora project, not an indigenous Iranian one and I&amp;rsquo;ve not seen much support for it inside the country. Iran&amp;rsquo;s most legitimate civil rights activists are in jail or under house arrest, not in the United States. Second, detractors argue that Mr Pahlavi has never held elected office so doesn&amp;rsquo;t have the political credentials. Third, millions of Iranians already lament replacing one dictatorship with another (the crown for the turban) and therefore argue another unelected group or individual is the antithesis of progress.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Lastly, many people assume &amp;ndash; as does the charter that Mr Pahlavi and other diaspora have issued &amp;ndash; that Iranians want a &amp;lsquo;secular-democratic system.&amp;rsquo; Although the absence of evidence is not evidence of absence, there is no data that proves this is what an overwhelming majority of Iranians want. However, I don&amp;rsquo;t think his participation as an elected official in any future Iranian system &amp;ndash; based on consensus of the Iranian people &amp;ndash; is bad for democracy, so long as he is elected in a free and fair vote, like anyone else.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The role of the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps (IRGC) was originally around security and &amp;ldquo;religious discipline&amp;rdquo;. What is their current role in society?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The role of the IRGC is to protect the revolution, which is embodied by the Supreme Leader, and protect the revolution&amp;rsquo;s ideals &amp;ndash; independence, freedom and Islamic Republic. However, its role changed when Ruhollah Khomeini died in 1989, and Ali Khamenei replaced him as Supreme Leader. Although the constitution forbids active IRGC members from political activity or groups, IRGC figures are involved in every key branch of the Islamic Republic system, from the judiciary and parliament to intelligence. Further, the IRGC has morphed into an economic cartel with outsized power and leverage, even over pillars of the revolution and the clergy.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is it possible to tackle their power, without reforming the state? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In short, no. Constitutional amendments in 1982 have ensured that. Certain articles gave the IRGC outsized power with no real checks and balances. Further, the Corps reports to the Supreme Leader, not the Ministry of Defence. It also operates its own intelligence wing, often in competition with the state&amp;rsquo;s Ministry of Intelligence. Further, it&amp;rsquo;s full budget is not subject to public parliamentary scrutiny, stripping away another layer of accountability, while increasing its already formidable role.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;February was the 44th anniversary of the 1979 revolution. The government used it as a show of might and to send the message that they had won, and the protests are now a spent force. How true is that? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The anniversary of the revolution in theory, is a celebration of freedom and independence from foreign domination &amp;ndash; widely supported concepts. But it is also a propaganda tool used by the state and its supporters to cling to legitimacy and a long dead revolutionary mythology. The most telling element at these events, is the absence of the many millions of Iranians who fought for the revolution, who are now disillusioned, if not repulsed by the system they helped create.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;As for the protests, they were not as large nor as widespread as those seen, for example, in 2009. Any significant showing ended about two months after the death of Mahsa Amini &amp;ndash; aside from in Zahedan. In essence, the protests are over, and did not lead to systematic change. But the Islamic Republic of Iran cannot claim it has won anything &amp;ndash; in fact the opposite. The number of Iranians who view the country&amp;rsquo;s circle of elite as illegitimate has grown exponentially and this rift between the people and the state is arguably, beyond repair.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are reports that thousands of women are now openly breaking the law and refusing to wear the hijab. What impact have the protests had on the general population in Iran? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Millions of Iranian women weren&amp;rsquo;t abiding by the letter of the law for decades and in the past ten years, it was common to see unveiled women at cafes, art galleries, and even walking down the street. Despite arrests, threats and even attacks from members of the public, the protests have emboldened more women to follow suit. The protests broke another layer of fear in the Islamic Republic and the importance of that cannot be understated.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Soraya Lennie is the author of &lt;a href="https://www.hurstpublishers.com/book/crooked-alleys/"&gt;Crooked Alleys: Deliverance and Despair in Iran&lt;/a&gt; (Hurst Publishers). &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6103/how-have-the-protests-changed-iran#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-13T16:36:37Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-13T16:36:37Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Book review: Britain's Jews</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6104/book-review-britains-jews#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;img title="Floor tiles at Garnethill Synagogue" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/2K1GF26.jpg" height="863" alt="Floor tiles inside Garnethill Synagogue, Glasgow" width="1300"&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Britain&amp;rsquo;s Jews: Confidence, Maturity, Anxiety&lt;/strong&gt; (Bloomsbury) by Harry Freedman&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The recent release of the 2021 England and Wales census figures for religion and ethnicity led to the usual debates about who &amp;ldquo;we&amp;rdquo; are now. While particular findings attracted attention &amp;ndash; most notably, that self-identifying Christians are now in the minority &amp;ndash; the census holds a deeper allure. By describing the population as a series of coherent, easily identifiable groups, it holds out the comforting promise that we might be able to understand the messy diversity of this nation (or nations).&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This desire to &amp;ldquo;fix&amp;rdquo; the population, to pin the butterfly, conceals much harder questions as to how we might come to comprehend the collective identities that people actually hold. The case of British Jews &amp;ndash; the ethno-religious group I both belong to and write about &amp;ndash; is particularly illuminating. The contrast between what people think they know about Jews and what they actually know is often perilously stark.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a paradox in how Jews are made visible in contemporary Britain. On the one hand, we have never been more present in national debates than in the last decade or so, largely due to debates about antisemitism. Individual British Jews &amp;ndash; from comedian David Baddiel to historian Simon Schama &amp;ndash; are more visible and more talkative about their Jewish identities. Yet this visibility conceals much of who British Jews actually are. Jews are visible if they are strictly Orthodox men in black hats, if they are defiantly secular media personalities, or if they are campaigning about antisemitism. Beyond that, the great mass of Jewish life is usually invisible.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Harry Freedman&amp;rsquo;s new book &lt;em&gt;Britain&amp;rsquo;s Jews: Confidence, Maturity, Anxiety&lt;/em&gt; helps to fill in the picture. Volumes that take an overview of contemporary British Jewish life as a whole are surprisingly few (&lt;em&gt;Turbulent Times: The British Jewish Community Today&lt;/em&gt;, which I wrote with Ben Gidley, came out in 2010 and was the first book-length sociological study of the community in decades). That means that Freedman can&amp;rsquo;t take anything for granted about the background knowledge of his non-Jewish readers. He writes clearly and knows the community inside and out, but the book is full of detail that readers may find engrossing, but which they might equally find dull or simply odd.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The British Jewish community contains a bewildering alphabet soup of organisations. Explaining the difference between the Liberal and Reform movements is a challenge even for their rabbinic leaders. Given that organisations like the Board of Deputies or the Chief Rabbi are often the targets of non-Jewish (and sometimes Jewish) suspicion, it&amp;rsquo;s essential to go into some detail as to whom they do or do not represent. But I felt a nagging anxiety that Freedman&amp;rsquo;s guide to the community&amp;rsquo;s structures might tax the patience of the reader.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Perhaps the confusion inherent in conveying this array of organisations and their arcane politics is the point &amp;ndash; maybe that is actually what being Jewish is. But to convey that reality in a compelling style may be a challenge too far. At the same time, as someone who has worked in the British Jewish community for many years, I inevitably noted which individuals and Jewish organisations Freedman doesn&amp;rsquo;t mention.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In fairness, &lt;em&gt;Britain&amp;rsquo;s Jews&lt;/em&gt; is not intended as a comprehensive guidebook. Freedman has a larger theme that he wishes to explore: the seeming paradox that Jewish life in Britain seems to be thriving, at the same time as British Jews are increasingly speaking publicly about antisemitism. The struggles with the Labour Party during the Corbyn years saw an unprecedented institutional effort across the Jewish community to articulate its concerns in vehement terms (with, of course, a significant proportion of Jews dissenting). This was the action of a self-confident and well-organised community. The duality has bewildered and sometimes angered many non-Jews, particularly on the left.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;This is an exceptionally sensitive issue and Freedman&amp;rsquo;s overall positivity about Jewish life in Britain has been received with some murmurs of disquiet within the community (both about downplaying the threat of antisemitism and about not giving enough attention to the more problematic aspects of the community). There are old fears at work here: that a complex picture of Jewish reality will undermine the unified messaging that Jews require to survive.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no way around it, though. Some aspects of British Jewish life do seem odd to outsiders. Freedman demonstrates the common (if slowly declining) tendency of British Jews to belong to synagogues whose values they do not actually share. Most members of the United Synagogue &amp;ndash; the largest Orthodox body, whose spiritual head is the Chief Rabbi &amp;ndash; are not themselves Orthodox. It is as if secular liberals chose to affiliate to the evangelical branch of the Church of England.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In his attempt to capture what everyday Jewish life actually feels like, Freedman quotes his interviewees at length. But the book was written during the pandemic and the Zoom interviews don&amp;rsquo;t compensate for the lack of portraits of the spaces in which Jewish life is lived. This is important, as the aspects of that life that may seem bizarre to outsiders make much more sense when you see them &amp;ldquo;in action&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Reading &lt;em&gt;Britain&amp;rsquo;s Jews&lt;/em&gt; made me wonder whether my own understanding of other ethnic and religious minorities might be shaped by accounts that leave out the texture of everyday life. While reading books can provide a starting point for understanding what it is to be Muslim, Sikh or Afro-Caribbean in Britain today, they are no substitute for the experiential knowledge that we need to understand the other more deeply. Without the texture of everyday life, all we are left with is a much more detailed version of the kind of knowledge that the census provides.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6104/book-review-britains-jews#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-13T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-13T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The pursuit of immortality</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6102/the-pursuit-of-immortality#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img title="Is there any value to this unregulated research?" src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/coverFilleCOLORINGREWORK-1-222.jpg" height="646" alt="Illustration shows someone inserting a swab" width="678"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Humanity&amp;rsquo;s pursuit of longevity has yielded impressive results over the last century. Life expectancy is up dramatically in most parts of the world, and new medical breakthroughs are tackling the most prolific of killers &amp;ndash; cancer and heart disease. But the mission to radically extend life has hit something of a ceiling, as we realise that healthy living and exercise will only take us so far.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a reason the oldest human on record, Jeanne Calment, reached 122 years old despite being a heavy smoker and eating a poor diet: her genes. We can make incremental changes to our health through smart lifestyle choices, but ultimately we&amp;rsquo;re all at the mercy of the genetic code which determines our vulnerability to disease and ultimately our deaths. However, our destiny may not be foretold in our genes for much longer. Gene therapy, which genetically modifies cells to fix problems in our bodies, has already been used to cure significant diseases. The rapid advancement of the field has led some to speculate it could hold the key to unlocking longer life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Among those keenly observing gene therapy&amp;rsquo;s potential are immortalists, a global offshoot of the transhumanist movement who believe they can live for ever. Longevity enthusiasts, a much more populous group of people who chase extended life through science, also have their eye on the medical technology.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Both groups place a great deal of hope in gene therapies to radically extend the average human lifespan. But they&amp;rsquo;re already tired of waiting for access to the technology. Frustrated that the science is moving too slowly, some have started doing their own research into the field. In some cases, this has involved self-administering treatments, outside legal jurisdictions, using treatments not yet approved by any trusted medical bodies.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Are they falling for humanity&amp;rsquo;s oldest vice, and hopelessly pursuing a modern version of the fountain of youth? Or are they doing the world a favour by ushering in a new therapy with the potential to increase humanity&amp;rsquo;s lifespan and tackle the many problems associated with age?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Scientific breakthroughs&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Many consider gene therapy to be one of the most exciting areas of medicine. The last 30 years have seen a series of significant breakthroughs, often in cases of disease that would otherwise be untreatable. In 2021, gene therapy partially restored a man&amp;rsquo;s eyesight. The man, who hasn&amp;rsquo;t been named, suffered from retinitis pigmentosa &amp;ndash; where light-sensing cells on the surface of the retina die &amp;ndash; and was completely blind. The treatment first utilised the genes of algae. Genetic instructions for making proteins called rhodopsins were taken from the algae and given to cells deep in the retina at the back of the patient&amp;rsquo;s eye. When light hit these new proteins, it sent an electrical signal to the brain, but not one that could be deciphered &amp;ndash; at least not yet.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The proteins only respond to amber light, so the man had to wear goggles with a video camera on the front. This captured what was happening in the world and fired a version onto the back of the eye in the right wavelength. The patient then waited several months for the levels of rhodopsins to build up in the eye, and for the brain to learn a new way of interpreting sight. He first realised the treatment was working when he went out on a walk with the goggles and saw the white stripes of a pedestrian crossing. He has since been able to grab and count objects on a table in front of him.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;These kinds of breakthroughs have given hope to many others who suffer from diseases born out of faulty genes. Gene therapy appears to be entering into a new age of progress, but there are still worries about the pace of change &amp;ndash; concerns that have been voiced since the practice was first developed.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Relative to the history of medicine, gene therapy is still fairly new. In 1972, Theodore Friedmann and Richard Roblin published a paper titled &amp;ldquo;Gene Therapy for Human Genetic Disease?&amp;rdquo; in the journal Science. The two American scientists outlined the potential of inserting DNA sequences into a patient&amp;rsquo;s cells to treat genetic disorders. Each of our cells contains thousands of genes that provide the information needed for the production of proteins and enzymes that make our bones, blood and muscles. Issues arise when a whole or part of a gene is defective or missing. This can occur before birth, or a gene can mutate later on, disrupting how proteins are made and causing major health problems or diseases.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Genetic diseases were seen as completely incurable until the 1972 paper proposed a solution. However, the two authors urged caution on the development of the technology and opposed any attempts at gene therapy in human patients, due to inadequate understanding of the concept and its potential side effects. The scientific community took note and waited 18 years, conducting a lot of research before launching the first gene therapy trial in 1990. Ashanthi DeSilva, a four-year-old girl suffering from a rare genetic disease known as severe combined immunodeficiency, underwent a 12-day treatment involving gene therapy. Her condition meant she lacked an enzyme called adenosine deaminase (ADA), rendering her immune system almost completely useless. This put her at risk of dying from infection and forced her to live in isolation.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;To boost DeSilva&amp;rsquo;s ADA levels, doctors introduced a functional copy of the gene that encodes the enzyme into the immune system. As you might imagine, it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to insert a gene directly into a person&amp;rsquo;s cells. It has to be delivered via a carrier, known as a vector. The most common gene therapy vectors &amp;ndash; used on DeSilva &amp;ndash; are viruses, because they can identify certain cells and carry genetic material into the genes of that cell. In order to make it safe, researchers remove the disease-causing genes from the virus and replace them with the helpful genes. When the viral vector containing the gene therapy was introduced, DeSilva&amp;rsquo;s immune system improved, and she was able to live a normal life.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The case was celebrated around the world, kicking off numerous other trials in the field during the 1990s. But just nine years later, that progress was brought to a sudden halt when a clinical trial went tragically wrong.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Approach with caution&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 1999, Jesse Gelsinger, an 18-year-old suffering from the genetic condition ornithine transcarbamylase deficiency, signed up for an experimental gene therapy trial at the University of Pennsylvania. The disease, which was caused by a genetic mutation, stopped his liver&amp;rsquo;s ability to break down ammonia, causing the toxic substance to accumulate in the blood. The trial introduced a functional copy of the missing gene to Gelsinger&amp;rsquo;s liver cells, using a modified common cold virus as a vector.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But four days after the treatment, Gelsinger suffered a catastrophic immune reaction and died. His death shocked scientists in the field and received widespread media attention. The FDA criticised the design of the trial and suspended the University of Pennsylvania&amp;rsquo;s entire gene therapy program, which was one of the largest in the world. The regulator also launched investigations into 69 other gene therapy trials underway in the US. In the fallout, gene therapy was accused of moving too fast, and viral vectors in particular were called into question. Progress slowed considerably.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Research has rebounded since, but the comeback has been gradual. In 2003, China approved its first gene therapy, called Gendicine, which treated head and neck cancer. Russia gave the green light to Neovasculgen, a therapy for peripheral artery disease, in 2011. But even when a treatment is approved it may not be commercially viable. The year after the breakthrough in Russia, the European Commission approved Glybera, a gene therapy treating lipoprotein lipase deficiency, an ultra-rare disease. But while it was heralded at the time as a great success for Europe, Glybera was a commercial failure. The therapy came with a &amp;euro;1 million price tag, making it the most expensive treatment in the world. [See Peter Forbes&amp;rsquo; report in the Winter 2019 edition of New Humanist.] By the time it was withdrawn in 2017, the treatment had been prescribed to just one patient.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where the immortalists and longevity fanatics come in. Frustrated that the science is moving too slowly, some have taken matters into their own hands. And one anti-ageing entrepreneur has taken drastic steps to ensure gene therapies to reverse ageing are at least being tested on humans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Patient zero&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Liz Parrish, then a housewife and part-time advocate for stem cell therapies, first became interested in gene therapy after learning that her nine-year-old son had been diagnosed with type one diabetes. She was outraged by the amount of time and money it took for experimental treatments to reach patients. She began to travel to medical conferences, badgering experts in the hallways, looking for potential cures for diseases like that which afflicted her son. In her frantic pursuit of treatments, she eventually convinced herself that by curing ageing, everyone &amp;ndash; including children &amp;ndash; would suffer less.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In 2015, at the age of 44, Parrish flew to Bogot&amp;aacute;, Columbia, to receive dozens of experimental gene therapy injections, with the goal of turning back her biological clock. By that time, she had founded her own company, BioViva. For her first public appearance as CEO, she had chosen to address the immortalist group People Unlimited, where she told a receptive crowd that she wanted to cure ageing, and do it fast enough that they could all benefit. That year, she raised enough cash to fund the Bogot&amp;aacute; experiment. The plan was to become patient zero.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;A video of Parrish&amp;rsquo;s procedure is available online. Prior to the treatment, she made jokes to the doctors. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m supposed to go in the corner, grab my face and shake around, and turn around and be young, right?&amp;rdquo; she laughed. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not going to happen like that.&amp;rdquo; Wearing a white medical gown, she sat back for hours while a doctor and nurse administered more than 100 injections in her triceps, thighs, buttocks, face, and below her kneecaps. By the time she was done, past midnight, she had created medical history as the person to receive the most potent dose of gene therapy ever, all in the quest to fight ageing.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;In the aftermath, Parrish and BioViva were bombarded with attention, some good, some bad. A reporter contacted the company for a story about the ethical issues of the treatment, claiming nobody could really know the risks and give informed consent. There was a lot of pressure, Parrish told me in a video call in 2021. &amp;ldquo;People are constantly looking at me and saying, &amp;lsquo;Do you look younger? Do you feel younger?&amp;rsquo; I&amp;rsquo;m a guinea pig.&amp;rdquo; The criticism didn&amp;rsquo;t just come from the press. George Martin, a gerontologist and member of BioViva&amp;rsquo;s scientific advisory board, resigned soon after.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Among the longevity and immortalist crowds, however, Parrish was an instant hero. Finally, someone was taking the initiative in the mission to beat ageing. A year after the treatment, BioViva issued a press release with the results. The company compared blood drawn from Parrish before and after the procedure and found her white blood cells&amp;rsquo; telomeres had increased in length by nine per cent. Telomeres are often compared to the plastic tips on the end of shoelaces. If telomeres shorten too much over time, the cells, like a shoelace, become exposed and begin to fray and are damaged. By lengthening the telomeres, Parrish was theoretically improving the health of her cells.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But this was just one person&amp;rsquo;s results, and no study was published. There was not enough data to measure. The news was dismissed as inconsequential by the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Regulatory battles&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Parrish, however, has not given up. She is now focused on battling against the current system of regulation, which she believes is holding back crucial medical technologies. When we spoke in 2021, she was writing her thesis for an MBA on a new regulatory system she is proposing called Best Choice Medicine. She wants to make it easier for gene therapies and other regenerative medicines to enter human testing trials.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;These gene therapies are already performing better, hitting more points of metabolic disorder and dysfunction that happens with ageing in animal models, and yet we continue to do animal models, and no humans get access to this?&amp;rdquo; she said. &amp;ldquo;That&amp;rsquo;s what we were saying when I took the gene therapies in 2015. We were saying no, we have to jump, at some point you have to jump, and if you don&amp;rsquo;t jump you die of the same predictable diseases.&amp;rdquo; She believes that while animal testing is important to gauge the effectiveness of a treatment, it can never really replicate human interaction. She wants treatments to be tested on humans much sooner, at the cost of the caution that regulates the medical industry.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But Parrish is not a scientist. I wanted to talk to someone respected in the gene therapy space, who also had an opinion on what entrepreneurs like Parrish were trying to achieve. So I contacted George Church, an adviser to BioViva. Church teaches genetics at Harvard Medical School and MIT and is also director of the US Department of Energy Technology Center, as well as the NIH Centers of Excellence in Genomic Science. His list of achievements is just as impressive as his job titles. He developed the first direct genomic sequencing method in 1984 and helped initiate the Human Genome Project that same year. In 2005, he helped launch the Personal Genome Project.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, given his r&amp;eacute;sum&amp;eacute;, Church is well connected. He has founded and advised numerous biotech startups and is seen as a major contributor to Crispr technology, which edits genes. On our video call, Church, who sports a bushy beard and glasses, told me Parrish was not the only person he knew who had conducted self-experimentation attempting to advance science. He thinks there is some value in the work that she and others are doing as pioneers.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If you have enough resources, it&amp;rsquo;s totally obvious what you should do &amp;ndash; a full-fledged clinical trial. But it helps to do these little things because at a minimum it shows it&amp;rsquo;s not toxic. And if it&amp;rsquo;s nontoxic, a whole variety of people will want to try it out, and then you&amp;rsquo;ll find out if it&amp;rsquo;s toxic in a wide variety of people,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to show efficacy, that&amp;rsquo;s the other thing you have to do, you have to very carefully do baseline. And if you know you&amp;rsquo;re getting the experimental over the control there are going to be all types of placebo effects . . . it&amp;rsquo;s much better if you don&amp;rsquo;t know which treatment you&amp;rsquo;re getting.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He encourages anyone doing self-experimentation to use a double-blind placebo crossover trial, where there are two samples, one a placebo and one the real thing. The researcher then injects themselves, not knowing if it&amp;rsquo;s the real thing or not, and a few days or months later injects the other sample. That means at some point they get both the placebo and the real thing, but they don&amp;rsquo;t know what order they had them in. Church described this as a cheap and easy way to make self-experimentation results more useful.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Church doesn&amp;rsquo;t see much hope in record-breaking humans like Jeanne Calment. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;ve sequenced them, and we hoped we would learn something, but it&amp;rsquo;s very challenging because there are 3 million differences between each of them, and each other, and us as well. It&amp;rsquo;s underpowered statistically. We were hoping something would jump out at us, it might still . . . I don&amp;rsquo;t think we&amp;rsquo;ve learned that much from supercentenarians yet.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;h2&gt;Heroic or reckless?&lt;/h2&gt; &lt;p&gt;Instead, he is looking in other directions. In 2017, he co-founded the gene therapy company Rejuvenate Bio, launched from Church&amp;rsquo;s lab at Harvard Medical School and the Wyss Institute for Biologically Inspired Engineering. The company wants to reverse ageing in dogs through treatments that have shown promise in worms, flies and mice. Church believes any treatment that would make dogs live longer would be hugely popular and fund the next stage: clinical trials in humans.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;For the immortalists and longevity fanatics, that day can&amp;rsquo;t come soon enough. In the meantime, they will continue to lobby for earlier access to experimental medicines that could extend their lives. The question remains, however: are they putting themselves at unnecessary risk chasing an unobtainable goal or are their actions heroic?&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Medical technology has never been more exciting. Some of the breakthroughs we read about appear to be straight out of science fiction, and groups like the immortalists follow them with the fervour of sports fans. But the gap between research and implementation is large for a reason: safety. The libertarian, anti-regulation leanings of those pursuing extended life may result in fraudsters and conmen queuing up to exploit them.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Gene therapy, despite recent high-profile breakthroughs, is still a young scientific field. The potential is so huge that it&amp;rsquo;s easy to see why people are enthusiastic about the technology, including those seeking to extend their lifespan. But there is much to be done, and the risks associated are not to be underestimated. Whether or not pioneers like Liz Parrish continue to conduct their experiments independently, we are at the beginning of this scientific journey. Meanwhile, failed or reckless experiments may set us back. The potential is exciting, but our deaths may be written in our genes for many decades to come.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is an edited extract from Peter Ward&amp;rsquo;s book "The Price of Immortality" (Penguin Random House), from the spring 2023 edition of New Humanist. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe now&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6102/the-pursuit-of-immortality#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-11T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-11T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everybody’s Magic!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13806" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-1/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" data-orig-size="7360,4140" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;8&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665658121&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=750" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13806" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-1" width="7360" height="4140" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg 7360w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=768&amp;h=432 768w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;h=576 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 7360px) 100vw, 7360px"/>I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing <a href="https://www.collegeofmagic.com/">College of Magic</a> in South Africa. The College is a non-profit community youth development organisation that uses magic to offer hope to young people in and around Cape Town.  They do incredible work and for the past two years I have been working with them and Vanishing Inc (the largest magic retailer in the world ) to produce a unique  magic booklet and custom deck of cards for budding magicians. </p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13808" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-11/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" data-orig-size="6589,3706" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;16&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660769&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-11" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13808 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-11" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-11.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>This gorgeous full-colour booklet involves students from the College teaching magical illusions, and tells inspirational stories of diverse historical magicians. Both the booklet and cards showcase great artwork by South African illustrator, Ndumiso Nyoni, and readers have special access to videos of the students teaching the tricks and offering top tips.<br/><br/></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13807" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/everybodys-magic-4/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" data-orig-size="6006,3379" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;11&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;Canon EOS 5D Mark IV&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1665660400&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;100&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;800&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.04&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="everybodys-magic-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=750" class=" wp-image-13807 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg" alt="everybodys-magic-4" width="374" height="211" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=374&amp;h=211 374w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=748&amp;h=422 748w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=84 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/04/everybodys-magic-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=169 300w" sizes="(max-width: 374px) 100vw, 374px"/>All the profits raised from the sale of the booklet and deck of cards will go towards furthering the important and wonderful work of the College. It’s a lovely gift for friends and family and it would be great if you can support the project.</p>
<p>To find out more, please click <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/everybodys-magic/">here</a>. </p>


<p/>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am excited to launch a new fund raising initiative for the amazing College of Magic in South Africa. The… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/04/07/everybodys-magic/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Everybody’s Magic!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13799</id>
    <published>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-07T10:47:06Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Q&amp;A: Anna Lembke on the power of dopamine</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6099/qa-anna-lembke-on-the-power-of-dopamine#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/Anna_Lembke_office_112-copy.jpg" height="1181" alt="Anna Lembke" width="1771"&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anna Lembke is a professor of psychiatry and program director for the Stanford Addiction Medicine Fellowship. Her latest book is &amp;ldquo;Dopamine Nation&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dopamine is an important neurotransmitter when it comes to motivation, pleasure and reward. What makes it so special? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s the final common pathway for all reinforcing substances and behaviours. So, for example, the use of alcohol, and other stimulants, lead directly to the release of dopamine. The more dopamine that&amp;rsquo;s released, and the faster it&amp;rsquo;s released, in this specific circuit [in the brain] called the reward pathway, means it can lead to more addictive behaviour, when it comes to certain substances or activities.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But we need it, don&amp;rsquo;t we? Isn&amp;rsquo;t it also involved in memory, attention and the regulation of our body movements? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. It&amp;rsquo;s no coincidence that over many years of evolution the same neurotransmitter that&amp;rsquo;s important for motivation, pleasure and reward is also important for movement, because for most organisms, this has always been linked. In order to get your reward, you have to do the physical work to get there. Even the most primitive worm will release dopamine in response to food in its environment, which allows it to move toward that food. Part of the problem today in modern society is that we humans don&amp;rsquo;t really have to do any work to get our rewards.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You write about the &amp;ldquo;dopamine economy&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;limbic capitalism&amp;rdquo;. Can you explain these terms?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m talking here about how the natural end result of successful capitalism is to turn us all into good consumers and addicts. The ultimate consumer, after all, invests all their energy, creativity and resources into getting and consuming their drug of choice.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Has the internet made us addicted to information? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. In fact, digital media itself is a drug. The smartphone is a modern-day hypodermic syringe. Take, for example, a 10-second TikTok video. As soon as you view it, you&amp;rsquo;re already craving the next clip, because as soon as it ends, you&amp;rsquo;re feeling that comedown. And that drive to want to restore that physiological state is overwhelming.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How can we achieve a healthy balance of pleasure and pain?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;The best way to stay in balance is to use intoxicants in extreme moderation. And to avoid intoxicants that are super potent. It&amp;rsquo;s also helpful to leave sufficient time in between intoxicants to allow the pleasure-pain balance to restore equilibrium. Exposing our bodies and minds to things that are painful and difficult is also a useful way to regulate our own dopamine production and tilt the balance toward the side of pleasure. Because for every pleasure, we pay a price, and that price is the comedown. Getting our dopamine indirectly, through painful effortful engagement, like, say, taking a cold shower, is helpful, because we pay for our dopamine up front &amp;ndash; as opposed to getting a quick fix of it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You define addiction as &amp;ldquo;the continued and compulsive consumption of a substance or behaviour, despite its harm to self and/or others&amp;rdquo;. How would I know if I&amp;rsquo;m addicted to something?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Addiction is very hard to define because it&amp;rsquo;s a bio-psychosocial disease that is very contextualised, depending upon the time, the place and the culture. It&amp;rsquo;s also a spectrum disorder. It&amp;rsquo;s not a single moment in time, where you cross the line, and now you&amp;rsquo;re addicted. It&amp;rsquo;s a gradual process, characterised by these brain changes, where, over time, the drug essentially stops working. This means the user needs more of it, and more potent forms to get the same effect.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Is there any way to end this spiral of addiction? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;What I recommend is a dopamine fast. This involves abstinence from the particular substance or behaviour. This helps reset reward pathways in the brain. I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t recommend this for somebody who was at risk of life-threatening alcohol, benzo or opioid withdrawal. Or for someone who had tried repeatedly to stop activities related to addiction on their own, but were unable to because the compulsions were so overwhelming. But for most individuals I treat, it&amp;rsquo;s a good first pass. Typically, during the first 10 to 14 days, they feel worse, because they&amp;rsquo;re experiencing withdrawal when they are in that dopamine-deficit state. But if they can just go long enough, and get over that hump, they find their pleasure-pain balance starts to reregulate itself, and they start to upregulate dopamine and other endogenous feel-good neurotransmitters that have been suppressed. Then by week three or four, they&amp;rsquo;ll report feeling better than they have in a very long time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you make of Gabor Mate&amp;rsquo;s theory that all addiction stems from trauma?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t agree. Trauma can certainly be one of many gateways into addiction. But another reason is simple exposure to the drug, which changes our brain. We can get addicted to things when our lives seem to be perfect. The main point of Dopamine Nation is to show that we&amp;rsquo;re now living in a world that&amp;rsquo;s so saturated with pleasure goods that we&amp;rsquo;re all more vulnerable to the problem of compulsive overuse.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;But you note that the poor and undereducated, especially those living in rich nations, are more susceptible?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;People living in poverty don&amp;rsquo;t have access to the healthier forms of dopamine, which wealthy people do. For example, exposure to being in nature, or gyms, where you can get your dopamine indirectly. People who are unemployed, for instance, have enormous amounts of unstructured time.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You argue that we have created &amp;ldquo;oversanitised children&amp;rdquo;. Would tough love from parents better serve their mental health in the long run? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Yes. What I have seen over two decades of clinical work is parents who have assiduously insulated their children not just from painful experiences, but really any kind of challenging experiences. This means that children haven&amp;rsquo;t had the opportunity to build up the mental strength they need to live in the real world. A more effective strategy is to set limits, and boundaries, and give our children real feedback about their strengths and weaknesses, which in the long term will enforce real consequences for transgression.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Might these &amp;ldquo;sanitised children&amp;rdquo; become more predisposed to addiction? &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Definitely. If you&amp;rsquo;re not having the experience of your own self efficacy, and your ability to rely on your own fortitude to overcome challenges, that really undermines a sense of competence, and fosters an avoidant coping style, which is really at the heart of many addictions.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The use of antidepressants is rising all over the world. Is this a problem?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;We are definitely insulating ourselves from challenging, painful experiences that we need in order to be resilient in the world. One way we are doing that is by overprescribing psychotropics, antidepressants, anxiolytics and hypnotics. That said, I&amp;rsquo;m a psychiatrist. And I regularly prescribe these medicines. In many instances, they are life-saving for people with severe mental illness. But I&amp;rsquo;m concerned about the indiscriminate prescribing of [drugs] like Xanax, which is a highly potent and addictive benzodiazepine. When we take a pill to manage anxiety, we deprive ourselves of the opportunity to learn from that experience, or to conceptualise anxiety as a form of energy. If the anxiety is so overwhelming that it&amp;rsquo;s paralysing, well, that&amp;rsquo;s different. But in many instances, anxiety is energy. And we need to figure out how to manage it.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6099/qa-anna-lembke-on-the-power-of-dopamine#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-06T06:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-06T06:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>That don't impress me much</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6098/that-dont-impress-me-much#utm_source=rss" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://newhumanist.org.uk/images/NewHumanistLaurieJesusMagician.jpg" height="678" alt="A cartoon depicts Jesus performing a card trick" width="402"&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;At my Roman Catholic boarding school, it was a requirement to get down on one&amp;rsquo;s knees at bedtime and pray for miracles. There was a good reason for this injunction. Every pupil had been repeatedly told that firm evidence of miracles was the only way in which the school&amp;rsquo;s patron, the Blessed Michael Garico&amp;iuml;ts, could be raised from mere Blessedness into full-blown Sainthood. Three miraculous happenings were required before the Pope could confer such spiritual promotion. The Blessed Michael had so far only managed two such fundamental violations of the natural law. (As I remember, these involved the miraculous restoration to health of an elderly nun, and the transformation of a cauliflower into a bunch of grapes.)&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Alongside these official calls for miracles, there were the numerous miraculous requests made by the school&amp;rsquo;s boarders. Some were purely selfish. Boys routinely prayed for God to intervene in the calculation of their examination marks or in the promotion of their favourite football team. But I also remember regularly going down on my knees to invoke God&amp;rsquo;s help in the reincarnation of a third-former&amp;rsquo;s mother and the furtherance of world peace.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d like to be able to say that my faith in miracles withered with time, but even at the age of 18 I was still asking my patron saint (Saint Lawrence, who was burned to death over a gridiron in 258 AD) if he would do his level best to bring on Maureen Dobson&amp;rsquo;s period. Thankfully, I was spared the strain of fatherhood at such a tender age.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d also like to be able to say that my current scepticism about miracles was based on some firm philosophical ground, perhaps upon John Stuart Mill&amp;rsquo;s powerful argument that &amp;ldquo;We cannot admit a proposition as a law of nature, and yet believe a fact (a cited miracle) in real contradiction to it. We must disbelieve the alleged fact, or believe that we are mistaken in admitting the supposed law.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But it was not Mill &amp;ndash; or such other philosophic sceptics as Auguste Comte, David Hume or Ludwig Feuerbach &amp;ndash; who finally applied the coup de grace to my lingering belief that there might just be &amp;ldquo;more things in heaven and earth&amp;rdquo; than Horatio had dreamt of in his philosophy. It was none other than the American magician David Blaine.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Even before I&amp;rsquo;d encountered Blaine and his awesome feats of magic, I&amp;rsquo;d come to regard Jesus&amp;rsquo;s miracles as somewhat lacking &amp;ndash; not only in credibility, but also in invention. Quite frankly, turning water into wine was poor stuff, as was catching a bumper load of fish on the Lake of Gennesaret. Neither could one be unduly impressed by the news that he had turned a group of demons into a herd of pigs.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;Indeed, when compared to David Blaine&amp;rsquo;s achievements, it has to be said that Christ&amp;rsquo;s inventory of miracles is decidedly second-rate. I don&amp;rsquo;t wish to labour the point, but was Jesus able to hold his breath for 17 minutes, submit to electrocution while standing on top of a pole, or levitate a foot in the air in front of a crowd of New Yorkers? Blaine was buried alive for seven days; Jesus only managed three. Not only did Blaine triumphantly accomplish all these miraculous feats, but they also usually took place in front of passers-by in the streets, people who &amp;ndash; in these irreligious times &amp;ndash; were likely to be far more sceptical than the multitude of God-botherers who inhabited Jerusalem in 27 AD.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;But although Blaine&amp;rsquo;s magic can startle and fool entire modern-day audiences, there are several websites devoted, with varying degrees of success, to unmasking his deceptions. As far as I am aware, there is no similar site devoted to unmasking the claims of the divine magician. This fact is no doubt indicative of the peculiar manner in which our world allows the truths of science to happily intermingle with the deceits of religion.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I recently asked an elderly and rather reclusive philosopher about this apparent paradox. He was reluctant to comment.&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;I pressed him. &amp;ldquo;If you had to choose&amp;rdquo;, I persisted, &amp;ldquo;which of Christ&amp;rsquo;s miracles would you select as the most amazing?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;He closed his eyes and thought for a several minutes. &amp;ldquo;Quite simple, really&amp;rdquo;, he said. &amp;ldquo;It was having as many as 12 friends after the age of 30.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This piece is from the New Humanist spring 2023 edition. &lt;a href="/subscribe"&gt;Subscribe here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
    <id>https://newhumanist.org.uk/articles/6098/that-dont-impress-me-much#utm_source=rss</id>
    <published>2023-04-04T07:00:00Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-04T07:00:00Z</updated>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION APRIL 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/04/open-discussion-april-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978526</id>
    <published>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-04-01T11:51:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
    <category term="Featured"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Science Cannot Be Tongue-Tied</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/science-cannot-be-tongue-tied/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! It might be funny, if it weren’t so worrisome. Recent weeks have seen some absurd new instances of science beset by would-be censors operating under the banner of “inclusion.” Examples are many, and they come from all over the globe. We’ll look at an ongoing controversy in …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978517</id>
    <published>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-08T19:06:35Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION MARCH 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/03/open-discussion-march-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978514</id>
    <published>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</published>
    <updated>2023-03-01T09:44:26Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>My new podcast!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13712" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1080,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080×1080" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=750" class="wp-image-13712 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg" alt="Richard-Wisemans-On-Your-Mind-1080x1080" width="299" height="299" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=299&amp;h=299 299w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=598&amp;h=598 598w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/02/richard-wisemans-on-your-mind-1080x1080-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w" sizes="(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px"/>I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! </p>
<p>Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and I will be exploring one of my favourite psychological topics, such as happiness, lying, laughter, and luck. We will be taking a deep dive into the research and revealing simple ideas that could help to improve your life. </p>
<p>We launched yesterday and have already reached the Number 2 slot on the Apple Science Chart! Thank you so much to everyone who has listened so far. During the episodes we will be answering 1000 questions about the mind, so feel free to post your questions on my blog. </p>
<p>It’s called Richard Wiseman’s On Your Mind and the link to the podcast is <a href="https://linktr.ee/richardwisemanonyourmind">here</a>.</p>
<p>My thanks to Podimo and TellTale studios for supporting and producing the podcast.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am very excited to announce that I have a new podcast out! Each episode, science journalist Marnie Chesterton and… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/02/09/my-new-podcast-2/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">My new podcast!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13706</id>
    <published>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-09T12:06:36Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demanding the Ability to Live and Think Freely</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/demanding-the-ability-to-live-and-think-freely/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the Richard Dawkins Foundation Newsletter. Subscribe here. Hello! The rights, beliefs, and freedoms of nonbelievers are just as important as those of the religious faithful. We should strive for—we should demand—a world where the ability to live and think freely is available to everyone. It’s a remarkably straightforward premise, but it seems like there’s a …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Jeff Dellinger</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978497</id>
    <published>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-02T19:52:18Z</updated>
    <category term="Original"/>
    <category term="Politics"/>
    <category term="Religion"/>
    <category term="Science"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>OPEN DISCUSSION FEBRUARY 2023</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richarddawkins.net/2023/02/open-discussion-february-2023/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This thread has been created for thoughtful, rational discussion on subjects for which there are not currently any dedicated threads. Please note that our Comment Policy applies as usual. There is a link to this at the foot of the page. If you would like to refer back to previous open discussion threads, the most …</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Moderator</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://richarddawkins.net/?p=978493</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</published>
    <updated>2023-02-01T09:46:27Z</updated>
    <category term="Discussion"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hocus Pocus: New book!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13692" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16-53-58/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" data-orig-size="920,910" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=750" class="wp-image-13692 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png" alt="Screenshot 2023-01-28 at 16.53.58" width="335" height="332" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=335&amp;h=332 335w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=670&amp;h=664 670w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=150&amp;h=148 150w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2023/01/screenshot-2023-01-28-at-16.53.58.png?w=300&amp;h=297 300w" sizes="(max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px"/>A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic, psychology and the paranormal. I teamed up with ace comic book artist Jordan Cullver, writer Rik Worth and colourist Owen Watts, and together we created 5 issues of Hocus Pocus.</p>
<p>Each issue introduces true stories of amazing feats, describes astounding psychic investigations, celebrates the history of magic, and examines the psychology of the paranormal. Not only that, but we included lots of interactive elements, including tests of your paranormal abilities, magical illusions,  psychic readings and much more. The comics were well received and even ended up being nominated for a prestigious Eisner award! As a result, many of the issues sold out and are now unavailable.</p>
<p>This week, those nice folks at Vanishing Inc have kindly put all five issues into a lovely, full colour, hard backed book.  Not only that but it contains some extra material for HOCUS POCUS fans:</p>
<p>A new introduction by me<br/>
A beautiful Cover Gallery showcasing Jordan’s fantastic artwork from all five issues<br/>
“How we made HOCUS POCUS: The Secrets Revealed!” — Rik spills the beans all our deceptions.<br/>
The complete live HOCUS POCUS issue used as an interactive element from Lawrence Leung’s The Davenport Séance reprinted here for the first time.<br/>
PLUS, pick up your copy from Vanishing Inc and you’ll also receive a copy of the exclusive, one-of-a-kind “Hiding the Elephant Puzzle” comic. Not only will you learn the history of one of Houdini’s greatest illusions, you’ll make an elephant vanish as you do so. While stock lasts.</p>
<p><iframe class="youtube-player" width="750" height="422" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bdZ2YE-dk18?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" style="border:0;" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"/></p>
<p>I hope that you enjoy it, and the book is available <a href="https://www.vanishingincmagic.com/magic-books/hocus-pocus-book/">here</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few years ago I had the idea of making a comic devoted to three of my favourite topics: Magic,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2023/01/30/hocus-pocus-new-book/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">Hocus Pocus: New book!</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13685</id>
    <published>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</published>
    <updated>2023-01-30T16:46:29Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Book: Why Psychology Matters</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


<p/>


<p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13493" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/mattersweb/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" data-orig-size="600,840" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="mattersweb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=600" class="wp-image-13493 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg" alt="mattersweb" width="285" height="398" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=285&amp;h=398 285w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=570&amp;h=796 570w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=107&amp;h=150 107w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/mattersweb.jpg?w=214&amp;h=300 214w" sizes="(max-width: 285px) 100vw, 285px"/>I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students, and is the book that I wished I had read when I was an undergraduate. It examines why psychologists do what they do and aims to inspire the next generation of researchers.  It’s a personal journey into my favourite aspects of psychology, exploring how research can reveal the hidden workings of the mind, boost critical thinking, debunk myths, and improve lives. Along the way, I explain how to think like a psychologist, spot a liar, uncover the truth about happiness, and much more.  Several colleagues have been very kind about it and I hope that you enjoy it too!</p>
<p>“This engaging yet scrupulous introduction is ideal for those who wonder what psychology is really about.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Uta Frith,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> University College London</span></strong></p>
<p>“Reading this one-of-a-kind book, you feel as if you’re in a personal conversation with Richard Wiseman, one of the world’s most creative psychologists. He beautifully explains how psychologists gain insight into the human mind, expertly regales you with findings that are fascinating and surprising, and uncovers some of the many ways in which psychology improves lives. Perfect for students and professionals alike.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Elizabeth Loftus, Past President, </span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic">Association for Psychological Science</span></strong></p>
<p>“A fantastic book. No one is better than Richard Wiseman to write about what psychology does and doesn’t offer. The quality of the writing and research reported is excellent.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Cara Flanagan,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> top-selling author of A level psychology textbooks</span></strong></p>
<p>“This wonderfully entertaining book celebrates why psychology really matters, calls for even more meaningful research, and presents a manifesto for change. A thought-provoking text that is deserving of serious consideration by both students and professional psychologists.”<br/><strong><span class="a-text-bold">Adrian Owen, OBE, neuroscientist and author</span><span class="a-text-italic">,</span><span class="a-text-bold a-text-italic"> Western University</span></strong></p>
<p>The book is available in the UK <a href="https://www.amazon.co.uk/Psychology-Why-Matters-Richard-Wiseman/dp/1509550437">here</a>. </p></div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I am delighted to announce that I have a new book out! This one is written for psychologists and students,… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/09/14/new-book-why-psychology-matters/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">New Book: Why Psychology Matters</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13562</id>
    <published>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</published>
    <updated>2022-09-14T14:27:39Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>More magic &amp; mystery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"><p><img loading="lazy" data-attachment-id="13506" data-permalink="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/coverlev/" data-orig-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" data-orig-size="750,1037" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="coverlev" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217" data-large-file="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=741" class="wp-image-13506 alignleft" src="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg" alt="coverlev" width="449" height="620" srcset="https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=449&amp;h=620 449w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=108&amp;h=150 108w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg?w=217&amp;h=300 217w, https://richardwiseman.files.wordpress.com/2022/07/coverlev.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 449px) 100vw, 449px"/>Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared!</p>
<p>First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt) an article in PeerJ about the psychology of the impossible. It takes a look at research into impossible experiences across many different areas (including magic, dreaming, children’s play, and science fiction), examining how these experiences inspire creativity and have changed the world. It is free and can be be seen by clicking <a href="https://peerj.com/articles/13755/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>.</p>
<p>Second, the fifth and final issue of our Hocus Pocus comic has landed! This comic celebrates magic, mystery and the mind, and this issue is all about levitation. It has stories about stage magic, the Indian rope trick and seance room trickery. It has been enormous fun working with the creative team of Jordan Collver, Rik Worth and Owen Watts. The comic has been selling out fast and this issue is available now at <a href="https://www.propdog.co.uk/hocus-pocus-levitation">Propdog</a>.</p>
</div>
    </content>
    <summary type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hi, a quick update about two projects that have just magically appeared! First, I have co-authored (with Prof Caroline Watt)… <p class="more-link-container th-text-xs th-links-inherit th-uppercase"><a href="https://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/2022/07/21/more-magic-mystery/" class="more-link">Read More <span class="screen-reader-text">More magic &amp; mystery</span></a></p></div>
    </summary>
    <author>
      <name>Richard Wiseman</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://richardwiseman.wordpress.com/?p=13500</id>
    <published>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</published>
    <updated>2022-07-21T14:40:03Z</updated>
    <category term="Quirky stuff"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>For any teen atheists who want to be on TV</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/14/for-any-teen-atheists-who-want-to-be-on-tv/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Someone contacted me hoping to find young atheists who might be interested in being part of a new series. I’m not particularly interested in having my mug on TV, but I would love to have some great personalities represent atheism on the show, so I offered to repost his email on my blog: My name […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=185</id>
    <published>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-15T01:01:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Getting older</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2013/03/09/getting-older/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All throughout my youth, I dreamed of becoming a writer. I wrote all the time, about everything. I watched TV shows and ranted along with the curmudgeons on Television Without Pity about what each show did wrong, convincing myself that I could do a better job. I flew to America with a dream in my […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=180</id>
    <published>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</published>
    <updated>2013-03-09T16:17:12Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="friends"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It gets better</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/11/01/it-gets-better/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A friend linked me to this. I was a sobbing mess within the first minute. I sometimes wonder why I feel such a strong kinship to the LGBT community, and I think it’s because I’ve been through the same thing that many of them have. So I watched this video and I cried, because, as […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=143</id>
    <published>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</published>
    <updated>2010-11-01T13:35:53Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>I have always depended on the kindness of strangers.</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/10/27/i-have-always-depended-on-the-kindness-of-strangers/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UPDATE #1: I got my domain back! Many thanks to Kurtis for the pleasant surprise: So I stumbled upon your blog, really liked what I saw, read that you had drama with the domain name owner, bought it, and forwarded it here. It should work again in a matter of seconds. I am an atheist […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=141</id>
    <published>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</published>
    <updated>2010-10-27T06:36:40Z</updated>
    <category term="Uncategorized"/>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Ask Teen Atheist #6</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://teenatheist.wordpress.com/2010/09/04/ask-teen-atheist-6/" type="text/html"/>
    <content type="xhtml">
      <div xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chadwell writes: I’m a 16 year old in highschool and I guess my natural cynicism lead me to question the dogma and ignorance of religion. I was a christian but I just figured that why would god send the only salvation to man kind to a single area and practically turn his all-mighty back on […]</div>
    </content>
    <author>
      <name>Teen Atheist</name>
    </author>
    <id>http://teenatheist.wordpress.com/?p=137</id>
    <published>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</published>
    <updated>2010-09-04T11:56:24Z</updated>
    <category term="Ask Teen Atheist"/>
    <category term="family"/>
    <category term="issues"/>
  </entry>
</feed>
